<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Philosophiæ Logica Empirismus Principia Informatica</title>
  <para>Philosophiæ Naturalis Principia Mathematica (pron. /fɪləˈsɒfi.iː nætʃərˈɑːlɪs prɪnˈsɪpi.ə
    mæθəˈmætɪkə/, Latin for Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy),[1] often referred to as
    simply the Principia, is a work in three books by Isaac Newton, in Latin, first published 5 July
    1687.</para>
  <para> mission: reliable data feeding a reliable model producing knowledge which drives quality
    healthcare delivery? </para>
  <para><emphasis>Logical Empirismus</emphasis>: A pursuit of knowledge purely through experience,
    especially by means of observation and sometimes by experimentation. (philosophy) A doctrine
    which holds that the only or, at least, the most reliable source of human knowledge is
    experience, especially perception by means of the physical senses. (Often contrasted with
    rationalism.) </para>
  <para> https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/rationalism-empiricism/ </para>
  <para> The disagreement between rationalists and empiricists primarily concerns the question: How
    can we gain knowledge? </para>
  <para> [empiricists] What held the group together was a common concern for scientific methodology
    and the important role that science could play in reshaping society. Within that scientific
    methodology the logical empiricists wanted to find a natural and important role for logic and
    mathematics and to find an understanding of philosophy according to which it was part of the
    scientific enterprise. </para>
  <para> https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/science-theory-observation/ </para>
  <para> https://docs.oracle.com/javaee/7/tutorial/websocket.htm </para>
  <para> Add a custom table of contents for principles: </para>
  <para> http://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.1/toc.html </para>
  <section>
    <title>Principles</title>
    <para/>
    <section>
      <title>Principle 1: Seperation of concerns</title>
      <para> </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Principle 2: Phenomenon</title>
      <para> Definition: Observation of Phenomenon<footnote>
          <para>wikipedia: In scientific usage, a phenomenon is any event that is observable,
            however common it might be, even if it requires the use of instrumentation to observe,
            record, or compile data concerning it. For example, in <link
              xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physics">physics</link>, a phenomenon may be
            described by a system of <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information"
              >information</link> related to <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matter"
              >matter</link>, <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Energy">energy</link>,
            or <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spacetime">spacetime</link>, such as
              <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaac_Newton">Isaac Newton</link>'s
            observations of the <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moon">moon</link>'s
            orbit and of <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_gravitation"
              >gravity</link>, or <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galileo_Galilei"
              >Galileo Galilei</link>'s observations of the motion of a <link
              xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pendulum">pendulum</link>.</para>
        </footnote> is the active acquisition of information from a primary source. In living
        beings, observation employs the senses. In science, observation can also involve the
        recording of data via the use of instruments. The term may also refer to any data collected
        during the scientific activity. The human mind, and modern scientific instruments can
        extensively process "observations" before they are consciously surfaced to the observer.
        This unconscious or automated pre-processing of data makes answering the question as to
        where in the data processing chain "observing" ends and "drawing conclusions” begins
        difficult. For our purposes, we do not try to draw a line between “observing” and “drawing
        conclusions” because for our analysis purposes, the distinction is immaterial.  </para>
      <para>
        <link
          xlink:href="https://www.revolvy.com/main/index.php?s=Qualitative%20property&amp;item_type=topic"
        /></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Principle 3: Measurement</title>
      <para> Definition: Standard… </para>
      <para> Definition: Measurement consists of using observation to compare the phenomenon being
        observed to a standard [not a normal range]. Measurement asserts something. These standards
        can be qualitative, that is, only the absence or presence of a property is noted, or
        quantitative if a numerical value is attached to the
        observed phenomenon by counting or measuring. The standard of comparison can be an artifact,
        process, or definition which can be duplicated or shared by all observers, if not by direct
        measurement then by counting the number of aspects or properties of the object that are
        comparable to the standard. Measurement reduces an observation to a number which can be
        recorded, and two observations which result in the same number are equal within
        the resolution of the process. </para>
      <para>Units of measure: Units of measure can include relative measures... Relative to
        effective time, Relative to Unix Epoch, Relative to freezing point of water, relative to
        absolute zero. Others have a concern that there should be no units of measure for Ratio...
        It is dimensionless. What is wrong with saying that the units are dimensionless? What use
        cases cannot be met? We can call it something other than units of measure if that is the
        underlying problem... <link
          xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Level_of_measurement#Nominal_scale">Level of
          measurement or scale of measure</link> may provide a basis for what we are looking for.</para>
      <blockquote><para><emphasis role="bold">Level of measurement</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">scale of
            measure</emphasis> is a classification that describes the nature of information within
          the values assigned to <link
            xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependent_and_independent_variables"
            >variables</link>.</para></blockquote>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_8f62f599-4897-4afc-9fc1-c6c7588b97d3">
      <title>Concern 1: Phenomenon Measurement</title>
      <para> We need a simple, and universally applicable way to represent  </para>
      <para> Technique 1.1: A quantitative approach </para>
      <para> As we’ve discussed:  </para>
      <para> [0,0] absent </para>
      <para> [0,3] possibly present, but no more than 3 </para>
      <para> [0,∞] unknown </para>
      <para> [1,∞] present </para>
      <para> [4-6] 4-6 </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_35228d10-cd7c-432d-9bcd-e3c83b782889">
      <title>Concern 2: Identification of equivalent Observation Results</title>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_2cbcaaef-efcd-4fa3-8de1-78ab44577bb7">
      <title>Title</title>
      <para> </para>
      <para> Identification of equivalence is imperative to enable data analytics, decision support,
        and other  secondary uses of data. </para>
      <para> Technique 2.1 Inverse concepts Concepts which are considered opposites of another.
        Loosely based on the idea of a multiplicative inverse. Cooperative = 1/Uncooperative.
        Define Cooperative as the LEft Inverse Form (LEIF), and Uncooperative as the Right Inverse
        Form (RIF). We create editorial guidelines as to what constitutes a LEIF vs a RIF concept.
        We start out with a straw man rule that “Concepts that assert the positive are LEIF
        concepts, Concepts that are the inverse of a LEIF concept are RIF concepts.” By generically
        stating right and left hand sides of the inverse function Cooperative inverse Uncooperative
        -> LEIF inverse RIF, we have a semantically unburdened categorization, so RIF concepts are
        not required to negate something… And we are not bound specifically to our first straw-man
        rule of “asserting the positive” if we find better discriminators.  </para>
      <para> We then work to move RIF concepts to a set of RIF extensions. RIF concepts will be
        excluded from the normalized form, and must be converted to LEIF concepts as part of the
        normalization process.  </para>
      <para> The Inverse function will apply specifically to an Observation Result. We won’t try to
        apply it to an expression for the purposes of using that expression in classification.  </para>
      <para> Technique 2.2 OWL EL profile definitions and classification of normalized form </para>
      <para> OWL EL profile with concrete domains supports multiple sufficient sets, and necessary
        conditions, and an ability to include concrete domains, such as ingredient strength,
        Concepts which have provably equivalent definitions by an appropriate classifier are
        considered equivalent.  </para>
      <para> Technique 2.3 Equivalence by generalization and subsumption  </para>
      <para> Often, equivalence is most appropriately considered with regard to a generalization.
        For example, all patients with presence or absence of diabetes mellitus. The equivalence to
        diabetes mellitus is determined though the use of an is-a taxonomy computed as part of
        Technique 2.2... </para>
      <para> Technique 2.4 Equivalence among post-coordinated and pre-coordinated expressions   </para>
      <para> All post-coordinated expressions are converted to concepts with a single identifiers,
        and the equivalence of the post-coordinated and pre-coordinated expressions is determined
        through the classifier's computation of logical equality, and through use of the is-a
        taxonomy the classifier computes  </para>
      <para> Technique 2.4: Multiple sufficient sets, independent of the necessary sets </para>
      <para> Technique 2.5: Concrete domains </para>
      <para> Concern 3: Identification of logical inconsistencies </para>
      <para> Technique 3.1 Disjoint Concepts </para>
      <para> Identifying concepts as disjoint can be used to identify logical inconsistencies, at
        data entry time, or during other   </para>
      <para/>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="section_2d7ee8e3-4f7d-462c-bb0e-1bccfb48078d">
      <title>"Not elsewhere classified" revisited</title>
      <para>Each concept used as a [interpretation, qualifier, ?], within a value set, must be
        accompanied by sufficient information to reconstruct the value set, and the value set must
        provide a partial order such that the concept's "range" of meaning can be determined. </para>
      <para>For example, a concept representing a color selected from the value set {Red, Green,
        Blue} will have a different range than a color selected from the value set {Red, Orange,
        Green, Yellow, Blue (get a better example of a granular color set ordered properly by em
        spectrum)}.</para>
      <para>Create a set of "intrepretative concepts," or a similar construct, that is the
        intrepretation of that concept when constrainted by a value set...</para>
      <para>Same preferred name, fully specified name incorporates the identify of the refset that
        constrained the concept. </para>
      <para/>
      <section xml:id="section_9869b6ed-bff6-465c-a282-c5a642e53861">
        <title>values from constraints</title>
        <para>if an concept is used as an intrepretation, the values they where selected from must
          accompany somehown so that the value can be determined against a partial ordering. </para>
        <para>Interpretation concepts can have children just like the can have units of
          measure?</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
