<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Application Layout</title>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Knowledge Editor</title>
        <para>The Knowledge application is organized into 2 areas: Editor and Manager. The manager
            is only available to administrators, so we will lay out the Editor functionalities in
            this article.</para>
        <para>The Editor is an interactive application that allows you to search, view, edit, and
            create terminologies, reference sets, and search criteria. By default, it is divided
            into 2 sections: the <emphasis role="bold">task</emphasis> pane and the <emphasis
                role="bold">concept viewer</emphasis> pane. When you select a concept on the left
            task pane, its details can be viewed in the right details pane. <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor layout as described above.</alt>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="editor-layout.jpg" width="600px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>You can optionally open another <emphasis role="bold">concept
                viewer</emphasis> pane that will display on the far right side of the window. There
            are three ways to do so: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Right-click the concept you wish to review and select "<emphasis
                            role="bold">open in new concept viewer</emphasis>". </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Highlight the concept you want to see in a new viewer and press "
                            <emphasis role="bold">keyboard shortcut tbd, e.g. ctrl+alt+n</emphasis>
                        " to open a new concept viewer. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the top navigation pane, select <emphasis role="bold"
                            >"Authoring"</emphasis>, then <emphasis role="bold">"Launch Third
                            View"</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What can I do in the Editor?</title>
        <para>The Editor has tasks divided under 2 interfaces: Authoring and Export Management. You
            can access either of these interfaces in the top navigation anytime you are logged into
            the Editor.</para>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor navigation with the interfaces highlighted</alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="nav-editor-layout.jpg" width="750px"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para>The application indicates which area and interface you are working with on the upper
            left corner.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Authoring</title>
            <para>The Authoring interface provides information on concepts and
                terminologies, lists reference sets, queries, mapsets, enables user to run the
                classifier, and allows user to search for items in the database. Depending on your
                account permissions, there is also the ability to edit many of the previously mentioned
                items.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Export Management</title>
            <para>The Export Management interface is viewable by users who have Editing permissions.
                Tasks such as QA runs, content releases, metric reports, and conflict resolutions is
                done under this interface, but the Content Manager has permissions to create a
                release version in this area.</para>

        </section>
    </section>
    
    </section>
