<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"> 

<info>
     <title>About the Classifier</title>
    <abstract><para>The Article will focus on the Classifier capabilities in the 
        Mind Computing Knowledge Authoring functions. Specifically, this article will describe how to 
        run the classifier, view the results of the classifier, resolve equivalency and 
        cycle errorsin the terminology.</para></abstract>
</info> 
   
    
   <para>The Knowledge Editor integrates a high performance Classifier--SnoRocket <link
        xlink:href="https://aehrc.com/snorocket/">https://aehrc.com/snorocket/</link>--which
        supports OWL EL++ and Concrete Domains. The classifier evaluates the stated relationships
        based on <emphasis role="italic">Description Logics </emphasis>upon which the terminology is
        defined and generates the inferred relationships for each concept. The Knowledge Editor
        displays <emphasis role="italic">stated and inferred </emphasis>views of the concept in the
        <emphasis role="italic">concept viewer pane </emphasis>and the Taxonomy displays
        <emphasis role="italic">stated and inferred </emphasis>is-a relationships based on the
        Taxonomy display options.</para>
    <para>This article provides general information on what a classifier is, how to run the classifier, 
        view the results of the classifier, and resolve any issues the classification uncovers.</para>
 
      <!--  <bridgehead renderas="sect1">Classifier Questions</bridgehead> -->
        <qandaset defaultlabel='qanda'>
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>How Do I Run the Classifier?</para></question>
                <answer>
                    <para>There are 2 places in the Knowledge Editor interface to run the classifier: at the
                        main navigation menu under "Authoring" and in the "Classifier" tab on the left pane.                    
                        The initial run of the classifier after the start of the system will result in all
                        concepts being evaluated. Subsequent classifications will only evaluate modified
                        concepts, also known as incremental classification. Incremental classification will
                        continue so long as the classifier status cache is maintained. This number is only a
                        measure of how much work the classifier did. 
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>How Do I View Previous Classifier Results?</para></question>
                <answer>
                    <para>
                        When you open the Classifier tab under the Authoring interface, there is a table of
                        previously run classifications. You may view classifications  results selecting a
                        different classification run from the dropdown "Classifier runs". 
                    </para>
                    <para>To view the results of these runs, select one and it will display in a concept viewer on the
                        right.</para>
                    <para>A summary of the attributes and types are displayed including:
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Added "Is a" Types</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Inactived "Is a" Types</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>New Attributes</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Inactivated Attributes</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Cycles Detected</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Equivalents Detected</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>To review the concepts under each of these summaries, select the row. A
                        table listing the identificed concepts will display below the summary list. You also
                        have the option of adding concepts to your briefcase.</para>
                    <important><para>If cycles or equivalencies are detected, you must edit the concept in question
                        to resolve the equivalence or cycle. Refer to "How to Edit a Concept" for information
                        on modifying terminologies.</para></important>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry><question><para>What is an Equivalency Error?</para></question>
                        <answer>
                            <para>The Classifier will detect an equivalency error when the definition 
                                  of multiple concepts is the same or perceived the same by the Classifier.</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry><question><para>How Do I Resolve an Equivalency Error?</para></question>
                        <answer>
                            <para>The definition (axiom) of one of the concept(s) should be modified to remove the equivalency error 
                                or one or more of the concepts should be inactivated by the user.   
                            </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry><question><para>How Do I Resolve a Cycle?</para></question>
                <answer>
                    <para> A cycle is an error in the axiom (definition) of a concept. It is essentially a 
                        circular definition. Something in the concepts definition points back to the concept being defined. 
                        e.g. Concept A -> Concept B -> Concept C -> Concept D -> Concept A.
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry><question><para>How Long Does Classification Take?</para></question>
                <answer>
                    <para>
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry><question><para>Does?</para></question>
                <answer>
                    <para> 
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
        </qandaset>
</article> 