<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Creating and Editing Assets</title>
    <para>Description</para>
    <para>Assets include: Concepts, Axioms, Assemblages, and Mapsets</para>
    <para>Note: Assets created in your local environment do not immediately affect the master
        version. The content needs to be exported as a release version, which will upload your
        changes to the repository.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Creating and Editing Concepts</title>
        <para>Concepts, or terminologies, are the defining content of existing terminology systems.
            In order to view, modify, and create new ones, Knowledge provides a simple workflow for
            your local concept needs. This section will provide information on how to edit, create,
            and clone a concept.</para>
        <!-- Part 2 -->
        <section>
            <title>How to Edit a Concept</title>
            <para>If your account has editor permissions, you can edit a concept by viewing its
                concept details, then selecting "Edit" in the upper right corner of the
                viewer.</para>
            <para>In Edit Concept mode, the concept can be activated or inactivated and the
                descriptions and axioms may be modified. In order to save any changes, select the
                "Save" button at the bottom of the viewer.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>How do I inactivate a Concept?</title>
                <para>You need to be in Edit Concept mode in order to inactivate or activate any
                    concepts or descriptions. There is a dropdown menu on the page to select the
                    proper status for the terminology. Select the Save button to confirm your
                    changes.</para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <alt>The Edit Concept page displaying Save and Reset buttons, Concept name,
                            SCTID, publication status, and a dropdown for Active or Inactive
                            states.</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/inactive-concept.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
            </simplesect>
        </section>
        <!-- Part 3 -->
        <section>
            <title>How to Create a Concept</title>
            <para>Follow the steps below to create a new concept:</para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Select "New Concept" from the Authoring menu in the top
                            navigation.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Once you open the New Concept page, select the terminology's parent
                            (you may add additional parents as needed in this form as well). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Type in the name of the new concept and verify that it does not have
                            any duplicates.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Select "Create" to confirm the new addition. This will create the
                            concept and take you to the Edit Concept page to add additional
                            information such as multiple descriptions and link reference sets.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <!-- Part 4 -->
        <section>
            <title>How to Clone a Concept</title>
            <para>A terminology can be cloned and modified as needed by users with editing
                permissions. </para>
            <para>Clone a concept by viewing its concept details, then select "Clone" in the upper
                right corner of the viewer.</para>
            <para>In Clone Concept mode, everything in the concept is copied over to an editable
                form where the concept name, descriptions, and axioms may be modified. In order to
                save any changes, select the "Create" button at the bottom of the viewer.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Note: The Fully Qualified Name (FQN) and Names (NAM) must be unique as
                    duplicates are not allowed. The definition or axiom also needs to be different
                    or the classifier could flag it as an equivalent concept. </emphasis></para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- Section 2 -->
    <section>
        <title>Axioms</title>
        <para>Define Axiom TBD<orderedlist>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is an Axiom</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Creating an Axiom</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Modifying an Axiom</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </orderedlist></para>
    </section>
    <!-- Section 3 -->
    <section>
        <title>Creating
            <?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190618T164621-0700" comment="maybe we just create a referenced component refset so the section title would be Creating a Referenced Component Assemblage"?>Reference<?oxy_comment_end?>
            Sets</title>
        <para>There are several different types of Assemblages but currently Knowledge has
            implemented Simple Assemblages. A Simple Assemblage is a set of concepts. The set of
            concepts are defined by the user creating the Simple Assemblage. For example, a simple
            Assemblage may be created for values used to record the measurement site of a patients
            heart rate, where the values could be finger, ear lobe, and wrist.</para>
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190618T102147-0700" comment="Need to define refsets" id="jvk_k11_d3b" mid="4"?><?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190618T162756-0700" comment="There are several different types of refsets but we&apos;re going to use the word Assemblage since refsets/reference sets is very snomed specific. Assemblages are useful for including, excluding concepts.  Assemblages can also be used to &quot;collect&quot; certain content for a particular use case. e.g. values used to record the site of a measurement of a patients heart rate. in this case the values could be finger, ear lobe. This is a simple Assemblage and the most common Assemblage created by users of  Knowledge. A simple Assemblage is a set of concepts. The set of concepts are defined by the user creating the Simple Assemblage. For example, a simple Assemblage maybe created for values used to record the measurement site of a patients heart rate, where the set could be finger, ear lob, and wrist." parentID="jvk_k11_d3b"?>There<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="4"?>
            are two ways to create a new reference set, also referred to as a refset in the
            application: by selecting "Create Refset" under the Authoring navigation menu, and by
            selecting "New…" under the Sets tab in the Authoring viewing pane.</para>
        <para>On the Create New Refset page, fill out the information needed and select "Create".
            Once the refset is created, you will see the ability to add concept members on the left
            pane.</para>
        <section>
                <title>Adding Members to a Refset</title>
        <para>To add members to a refset, select the "Edit Members" button when viewing the refset
                details. This will take you into an edit view where you can find concepts by
                taxonomy, search, or import. Once you have found the concept(s) you want to add,
                select the plus icon next to it and the item will be added to the table on the left
                pane. </para>
        <para>When you are ready to save the members list, select "Compare &amp; Sync" to review
            your changes. If there are any conflicts, the table will display the information to help
            you decide how to sync the new data into the refset.</para>
        <para>On the Compare &amp; Sync page, the "Save Changes" button means that you wish to save
                the changes you just made (as displayed under the <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Draft</emphasis> column in the table). The "Cancel Changes" button means that
                you wish to discard the changes you made (save the changes under the <emphasis
                    role="bold">Published</emphasis> column in the table).</para>
        </section>
        <section>
                <title>Removing Refset Members</title>
        <para>To remove members from a refset, select the "Edit Members" button when viewing the
            refset details. This will take you to Edit Mode, where you can remove members from the
            table by selecting the "X" icon. You must select "Compare &amp; Sync" to review and
            confirm your changes. </para>
            <para>Refer to the "Adding Members to a Refset" section for additional information on
                what the "Save Changes" and "Cancel Changes" buttons do.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- Section 4 -->
    <section>
        <title>Creating Refset Queries</title>
        <para>Refset queries can be created by selecting the "New…" button under the Sets tab in the
            left panel of the Authoring interface. Click on "Create" after filling out the form, and
            the new query's details page will
            load.<?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190618T100459-0700" comment="Need to define refset queries" id="xcp_4c1_d3b"?><?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190618T164423-0700" comment="A query Assemblage --- lets leave out for now...there isn&apos;t a UI implemented for it." parentID="xcp_4c1_d3b" mid="6"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="6"?>
        <para>To add conditions to the new query, select "Options…" > "Edit Conditions", and the
            Edit Mode will load. In Edit mode, you can create conditions and search for specific
            concepts to drag-drop into the "Add Conditions" area.</para>
        <para>After filling out the "Add Condtion" area, select "Add This Condition" button to add
            it to the query list.</para>
        <para>To test your conditions, select the "Run Query" option.</para>
        <para>To save your changes, you must select "Compare &amp; Sync" to review the changes and
            save.</para>
        <para>The "Save Changes" button means that you wish to save the changes you just made (the
            changes are displayed under the <emphasis role="bold">Draft</emphasis> column in the
            table). The "Cancel Changes" button means that you wish to discard the changes you made
            (the items under the <emphasis role="bold">Published</emphasis> column in the table will
            stay as is).</para>
    </section>
    <!-- Section 5 -->
    <section>
        <title>Creating Mapsets</title>
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190618T102214-0700" comment="Need to define mapsets"?>There<?oxy_comment_end?>
            are two ways to create a new mapset: by selecting "Create Mapset" under the Authoring
            navigation menu or by selecting "New…" under the Sets tab in the Authoring viewing
            pane.</para>
        <para>On the new mapset form, fill out the required information and select "Save" to create
            the
            mapset.<?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190618T102431-0700" comment="The &quot;Creating Mapsets&quot; workflow needs to be confirmed later"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
    </section>
    <!-- Section 6 -->
    <section>
        <title>Creating, Modifying, and Viewing Assemblages</title>
        <para>Create an Assemblage Specification -- TBD</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
