<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Getting
        <?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190620T073832-0700" comment="Need to decide whether we use &quot;user&quot; or &quot;you&quot; in the documentation. What are your preferences? I have always used &quot;user&quot; but wondering your thoughts on this."?>Started<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
 
    <simplesect><title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Whether you are brand new to creating and modifying medical terminology, MindComputing's
        Knowledge is an intuitive web application to use. This article will show you the fastest way
        to get the most value out of Knowledge by using key features, such as search, creating a new
        concept, and running the classifier. The first section will describe the login process and
        the overall application layout.</para>     
   </simplesect>
    <section>
        <title>Logging In</title>

        <section>
            <title>Accessing Knowledge for the First Time</title>
            <para>To access Knowledge Editor, you need a username and temporary password assigned to
                you by the application administrator. The application administrator has the ability
                to manage project permissions, and user accounts. You should receive an email with
                login information (be sure to check your spam folder). If you do not receive an
                email, contact the Knowledge administrator.</para>
            <para>Once you log in, you will see one of two screens:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Generic Welcome Screen</emphasis></para>
                        <para>If the administrator has not assigned a project to your account, you
                            will only be able to edit your user profile, e-mail, and password.
                            Contact your administrator for project assignment.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Project-specific Welcome
                            Screen</emphasis></para>
                        <para>If a project has been assigned to you, Knowledge Editor will load,
                            providing you a view of the taxonomy and announcements panels.</para>
                        <para>
                            <inlinemediaobject>
                                <alt>Image of the Editor screen after login displays a taxonomy
                                    list, announcements, and assigned projects.</alt>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/editorlogin.png" width="800px"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </inlinemediaobject>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
    
        <section>
            <title>Related Login Questions</title>
            <simplesect>
                <title>What happens if I forget my username/login?</title>
                <para>There are links to request your username or a password reset on the login page
                    of the application. Select the information you need and provide the details
                    requested to be notified of next steps.
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190619T155609-0700" comment="add picture?"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
            </simplesect>
            
            <simplesect>
                <title>What are my account permissions?</title>
                <para>You can review your account permissions under Account Preferences. To access
                    this page, select your username in the top navigation menu, then select "Account
                    Preferences". The table will display the projects assigned to you and the
                    permissions you have in each project.
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190619T155641-0700" comment="add picture?"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
            </simplesect>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- Part 2-->
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>Application Layout</title>
        </info>
        <para>The Knowledge application is organized into 2 areas: Editor and Manager. The remainder
            of this article will describe the Editor functionality and the Manager functionality
            will be described in a separate article. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Editor</title>
            <para>The Editor is an interactive application that allows you to search, view, edit,
                create new content,  assemblages, and searches. By default, the Editor is divided
                into 2 sections: the <emphasis role="bold">task</emphasis> pane and the <emphasis
                    role="bold">concept viewer</emphasis> pane. When you select a concept on the
                left task pane, its details can be viewed in the right details pane. <informalfigure>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor layout as described above.</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/editor-layout.png" width="600px"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>Optionally another <emphasis role="bold">concept viewer</emphasis>
                pane can be opened and will display on the far right side of the window. There are
                three alternatives to open another concept viewer: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Right-click the concept you wish to review and select "<emphasis
                                role="bold">open in new concept viewer</emphasis>". </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Highlight the concept you want to see in a new viewer and press "
                                <emphasis role="bold">keyboard shortcut tbd, e.g.
                                ctrl+alt+n</emphasis> " to open a new concept viewer. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>In the top navigation pane, select <emphasis role="bold"
                                >"Authoring"</emphasis>, then <emphasis role="bold">"Launch Third
                                View"</emphasis>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What can I do in the Editor?</title>
            <para>The Editor enables a you to modify, and create content – Authoring and to also
                export content from the application. Access to these functions are found in the top
                navigation bar.</para>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor navigation with the interfaces highlighted</alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/nav-editor-layout.png" width="750px"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
            <para>The application indicates which area and function you are working with on the
                upper left corner.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Authoring</title>
                <para>The Authoring interface displays terminologies loaded into the environment
                    specifically – concepts, assemblages, and mapsets. Enables the creation of new
                    concepts, assemblages, and mapsets. User's can also run the classifier, and
                    perform searches. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Export Management</title>
                <para>The Export Management functions are accessable users who have Editing
                    permissions. Tasks such as running QA checks, content releases, QA reports, and
                    conflict resolutions are done in this area. Only Content Managers have
                    permissions to export content.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- Part 3-->
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>Searching and Viewing Terminologies</title>
        </info>
        <section>
            <title>How do I search for concepts?</title>
            <para>You can perform a search in the Authoring interface. On the left
                pane,<?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190620T075340-0700" comment="do you mean the &quot;search&quot; tab?" id="jl1_vhv_d3b"?><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190621T144250-0700" comment="Updated phrasing to say that there are 2 main ways to find a concept" parentID="jl1_vhv_d3b" mid="4"?>t<?oxy_comment_end mid="4"?>here
                are two options to find the concepts: under the taxonomy tab or by the search
                tab.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Taxonomy
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190620T081005-0700" comment="I would put taxonomy functionality under it&apos;s own section. HOw do I navigate the concept hiearchy?"?>Tree<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
                <para>One of the ways to navigate through the concept hiearchy is to traverse the
                    taxonomy tree located in the left pane. You can traverse the tree by selecting
                    the caret symbol on the left of the tree to display the selected concept's
                    children.</para>
                <section>
                    <title>What do the icons represent?</title>
                    <para>[Need list of icons and definitions for tree]</para>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Search</title>
                <para>Terminologies can be searched by keywords under the Search tab in the left
                    pane. Begin After the keywords are entered, select the button "Search" to
                    retrieve results. Knowledge supports Lucene search and FLWOR queries in this
                    area as well, for more information select the info icon next to the search
                    field. </para>
                <para>Knowledge has implemented Lucene as one of it's search engines. Lucene is an 
                    open-source full-text search library. Both Simple Search and Advanced Search described 
                    in the subsequent sections use Lucene. With the Lucene syntax you can easily perform
                    searchs for more details on the Lucene search syntax refer to the Lucene tutorial
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.lucenetutorial.com"> Lucene tutorial </link>
                </para>
                <section><title>Simple Search</title>
                <para>Simple search allows you to search for the keyword that you typed in the
                        search box without selecting and advanced search or SNOMED CT options.
                        Selecting the search button will return all descriptions that matches. </para>
                </section>
                <section><title>Advanced
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="susancastillo" timestamp="20190620T084126-0700" comment="FLWOR -- should have it&apos;s own section"?>Search<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
                    <para>There are several ways to refine the search criteria under  "Advanced
                        Search" and "SNOMED Filters" sections of the Search tab. Select the button
                        "Search" to retrieve results after any search criteria changes. Selecting
                        the "Reset" button will clear all fields in the Search tab. A figure of the
                        available filter criteria is shown below.</para>
                    <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <alt>Figure of the Search tab with additional filter criteria such as
                            Status, Path, STAMP date range, Author, Modules, and Description
                            type.</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/advanced-search.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
                </section>
                <section><title>Saved Searches</title>
                    <para>Search criteria can be saved for later user under the Search tab. To do so,
                        enter the search criteria and select the "Search" button. A results section
                        should appear below the search fields along with options to save the search and
                        to export the results to a CSV file. Select the "Save Search" link in order to
                        name and save the search.</para>
                    <para>Saved searches are retrieved under the "saved searches" section of the search
                        tab. This section is only visible if there are previously saved searches. Select
                        the desired search from a dropdown list and press the "Search" button to pull
                        results.</para>
                </section>
                
            </section>
            
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Viewing Terminologies/Concepts</title>
            <para>Once a concept is selected, its details is displayed on one of the Concept Viewer
                panes. The pane lists the general concept information such as STAMP (define STAMP), its
                descriptions which include additional names it may be known by in other languages and
                dialects, and the axiom history which illustrates its taxonomy relationship. Details
                such as the inferred information or inactive items can be toggled on by selecting
                "Display options" in the upper right corner, and its refset relationships and history
                can be found in tabs within the same panel.</para>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <alt>Figure of the Display Options modal from the concept viewer. Displays options
                    such as "Show authors, language, modules, filter STAMP date," and more.</alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/display-options.png" width="750px"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </section>    
    </section>
    <!-- Part 4 -->
    <section>
        <title>Using the Briefcase</title>
        <para>A briefcase is where you can temporarily hold concepts so that you can review them
            later. For example, if you run the classifier and it identifies multiple duplicates, you
            may want to add them to your briefcase so that you can access the list of concepts
            quickly to compare. Or if you're reviewing the concept's associated members, the table
            may have an option to add them to your briefcase.</para>
        <para>To add a terminology to your briefase from some lists such as classifier page, select
            the briefacse icon (not all tables have this feature). Simply click on the briefcase
            icon to add or remove it from your list. Your briefcase is viewable in the left pane
            navigation.</para>
    </section>
    <!-- Part 5 -->
    <section>
        <title>Selecting a Project Area</title>
        <para>The name of the project area you are currently working on is indicated on the top left
            corner of the application. If you are assigned to multiple projects, you may switch to a
            different area by selecting "Projects" in the top navigation menu.</para>
    </section>
    <!-- Part 6 --> 
    <section>
        <title>How do I link Taxonomy and Search to Concept Viewer?</title>
        <para>In the Knowledge Authoring application you can connect th concept selected in the
            search results and in the taxonomy to the Concept Viewer Panel. By default in connection
            or linkage is set. This means when you select a concept in the taxonomy the Concept
            Viewer will display the details of that concept. The same is true if select a result
            from a search. You can modify the linkage by toggling the linkage icon in the upper
            lefthand corner of the concept details panel.
        </para>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <alt>Linkage icon</alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/linkage-icon.png" width="250px" />
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
    </section>
</chapter>
