<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Getting Started with the Knowledge Editor</title>

    <section>
    <title>Logging In</title>
    <para>To access Knowledge Editor, you need a username and temporary password assigned to
        you by the application administrator. The application administrator has the ability
        to manage project permissions, and user accounts. You should receive an email with
        login information (be sure to check your spam folder). If you do not receive an
        email, contact the Knowledge administrator.</para>
    <para>Once you log in, you will see one of two screens:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Welcome Screen</emphasis></para>
            <para>If the administrator has not assigned a project to your account, you
                will only be able to edit your user profile, e-mail, and password.
                Contact your administrator for project assignment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Project-specific Welcome
                Screen</emphasis></para>
            <para>If a project has been assigned to you, Knowledge Editor will load,
                providing you a view of the taxonomy and announcements panels.</para>
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <alt>Image of the Editor screen after login displays a taxonomy
                        list, announcements, and assigned projects.</alt>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/editorlogin.png" width="800px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>
<section><title>Login Questions</title>
    <qandaset defaultlabel="none">
        <qandaentry>
            <question><para><emphasis role="bold">What happens if I forget my username/login?</emphasis></para></question>
            <answer>
                <para>There are links to request your username or a password reset on the login
                    page of the application. Select the information you need and provide the
                    details requested to be notified of next steps.</para>
            </answer> 
        </qandaentry> 
        <qandaentry>
            <question><para><emphasis role="bold">What are my account permissions?</emphasis></para></question>               
            <answer>
                <para>You can review your account permissions under Account Preferences. To
                    access this page, select your username in the top navigation menu, then
                    select "Account Preferences". The table will display the projects assigned
                    to you and the permissions you have in each project.</para>
            </answer>
        </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
</section>
</chapter>
