<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>QA</title>
        <section xml:id="qa-section">
        <title>Quality Assurance</title>
            <para>Quality Assurance (QA) rules flag terminologies that have broken concept rules,
            including domain attribute errors and description duplicates. These QA rules are
            executed in the QA tab or as part of creating a version. To execute QA rules, select
            "QA" from the Task panel tabs and click "Run QA Test".</para>
            <para>Once the QA test has completed its analysis details can be viewed by clicking on
            the test in the QA Run List. Refresh the list if necessary.</para>
            <para>
                <note><para>At this time, QA rules check for
                    "active concepts should not contain tabs, newlines, or characters @, $, #, \\." Additional
                    rules will be implemented at a later time.</para></note></para>
        <section>
            <title>Viewing the QA Results</title>
            <para>The QA Test results provide generic information such as the duration of the test
                and total failures detected. Below that, a list of rules and number of results are
                displayed. If you click on one of the rules, the second list below it called QA Run
                Details, will display the specific concepts that failed the test. Right-click to
                open the context menu and perform actions such as viewing the concept and copying
                the UUID.</para>
            <para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Quality Assurance Run Details</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>The details for a QA run includes the request time, complete time,
                            status, duration, total QA failure, QA rules, and the error
                            counts.</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%"
                                fileref="images/whitelist-qatests.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

</chapter>
