<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Navigation Bar</title>
<section xml:id="navigation-bar"><title>Navigation Bar</title>
    <para>The Editor allows the ability to modify,create content, view content, and
        export content. Access to these functions are found in the top navigation bar.
        Additional features may also be accessed by right-clicking the concepts within the
        taxonomy tab. The application also indicates which area and function you are working
        with on the upper left corner.</para>
    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor navigation displaying the Editor logo, and
            menu options for Projects, Export Management, Authoring, Manager, and User
            name Admin</alt>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/nav-editor-layout2.png" width="750px"/>
        </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject></para>
    <para>The navigation options are as described:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Projects - If your account has more than one project assigned, switch
                between them by selecting this menu item</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Release Management - Used for exporting classifications and
                dictionaries</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Authoring - Used for creating new concepts, running the classifier,
                and creating new map sets</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Manager - Visible only to administrators, this option takes you to the
                Manager section of Knowledge (refer to the Knowledge Manager
                chapter<link xlink:title="knowledge-manager.xml"/> for more
                details).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>User - The menu under the user's name provides the ability to update
                global settings, account settings, view the user guide, and to log
                out.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
    <section><title>Projects</title>
       <para></para></section>
    <section><title>Release Management</title>
        <para>The Export Management functions are accessable users who have Editing
            permissions. Tasks such as running QA checks, content releases, QA reports, and
            conflict resolutions are done in this area. Only Content Managers have
            permissions to export content.The Export Management interface contains information such as:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Content Releases Overview</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Release Content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Run QA</para>
                </listitem>
                
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Knowledge users with Content Manager permissions have access to these information. The
            primary purpose of Export Management is to run QA checks, export files and releases, and
            review release statistics.</para>
   
    <simplesect>
        <title>Creating an Export</title>
        <para>There are two types of exports that can be created: a local downloadable file, and a
            release version that is uploaded to the repository. Exports and releases created are
            specific to the module you are working on. Once a release is created, you have the
            option of downloading it onto your system.</para>
        <para>When an export is initiated, several steps happen in the background: the classifier is
            run, a QA check is performed, and then a file is packaged for download.</para>
        <para>To create an export, go to the Export Management interface and on the left pane there
            is a table of Exports and QA, filtered by Path. Select the "Actions…" dropdown and
            "Create an Export".</para>
        <para>A modal appears asking which path the release should be created under, the file type
            for export, and a few additional details. Select "Create" to confirm and execute the
            task.</para>
        
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190624T121747-0700" comment="Images are temporary, need new ones once features are developed."?>
            <alt>Create an Export Modal displays a form with the following information:
                Exporting Module, Path, Type of Export, Namespace, Create Release Version,
                Version number, and buttons Create and Cancel.</alt><?oxy_comment_end?>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/create-export-modal.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para>The content release will appear in the Content Releases table on the left pane. There
            is the ability to cancel the release creation if it has not been complete yet, located
            under the table's Status column. </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Creating a Release Version</title>
        <para>When a module is ready for a release, the content manager must go through the
            Export Management workflow in order to upload content to the repository.</para>
        <para>To create a version release, go to the Export Management interface and on the left
            pane there is a table of Exports and QA, filtered by Path. Select the "Actions…"
            dropdown and "Create an Export". </para>
        <para>A modal appears asking which path the release should be created under, the file
            type for export, and a dialogue for release version. Check the box for release
            version, modify the version number if needed, then select "Create" to confirm and
            execute the task. The version number is automatically set to your current date in
            year-month-date format.</para>
    </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Downloading files</title>
            <para>Conent releases and their statistics can be downloaded under the details panel. Select
                the release you are interested in and there will be a button on the right panel named
                "Download Release". Content releases download in a
                <?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190626T111231-0700" comment="needs file formats, including .txt and.xml (what is solor&apos;s native export?)"?>[format]<?oxy_comment_end?>.</para>
        </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>What are release statistics?</title>
                <para>Release statistics are a set of descriptive measures and statistics obtained
                    through automated queries with the objective of providing information on content
                    changes and temporal trends as a measurement of progress. You can download this
                    information by selecting "Download Statistics" under the export or release details
                    page.</para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                    <alt>Screenshot of the Content Export page titled, "Content Export 01/02/2019 12:09:05" with two buttons underneath "Download Export" and "Download Statistics".</alt>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/download-statistics.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></para>
            </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>QA Tests</title>
            <para>QA Tests flag terminologies that have broken concept rules in the requested
                release/export, including domain attribute errors and description duplicates. This check
                can be run individually or as part of an export request. To do so, select the desired
                action from the "Create…" dropdown on the Export Management interface.</para>
            <para>Once the QA test has completed its analysis, select the run you just requested from
                the Exports and QA table on the left to review the results on the right pane. There is a
                relationship tree categorizing the results for you to select from. When you select a
                category, its details will appear in the bottom half of the pane with the options to
                review the concept described and to whitelist the concept.</para></simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>What is whitelisting?</title>
                <para>Whitelisting a terminology in the QA Test Results pane means that the error the
                    system found is acceptable and no action needs to be done. You can choose to
                    whitelist a concept by clicking the "Whitelist" link in the table results.</para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                    <alt>The details for "All active stated relationships should be the same moduleID of the source concept" table displaying 3 concepts, a message associated with each describing QA problem, the concept ID, and a "Click to WHitelist" button.</alt>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/whitelist-qatests.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></para>
            </simplesect>
 
    </section>
    <section><title>Authoring</title>
       <para></para></section>
    <section><title>User Menu</title>
       <para></para></section>
    
</section>
</chapter>