<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xml:id="editor-chapter" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Knowledge Editor</title>
    
    <para>The Editor allows users to view, create concepts, modify concepts, classify, create
        versions, export versions, create value sets and modify value sets. This chapter provides an
        overview of the Editor layout and details of the editing functionality such as, creating new
        content, modifying content, and exporting content. All users in Knowledge are able to see
        changes made by other users in real-time. </para>    
 
    <para>The Knowledge Editor is divided into three sections: the <emphasis role="italic">Task
            Pane</emphasis>, the <emphasis role="italic">Concept Details</emphasis>, and the
            <emphasis>Navigation Bar</emphasis>, see <xref linkend="layout"/>: <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Task Pane</emphasis> – The Task Pane consists of several
                    tabs that contain the following functionality: <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Taxonomy – the Taxonomy tab displays the content in a hierarchical
                                view, and is the default view for the Task Pane.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Sets – create, edit and view value sets.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Search – the search function enables the user to search for
                                specific descriptions, IDs and other values.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Classifier – the user can run the classifier and view results of
                                classification.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>QA – data checks on content can be initiated and results can be
                                viewed.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Versions and Export – users with the appropriate permissions can
                                export content and/or create a version.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Briefcase – is similar to a list. Throughout the editor, there are
                                areas that allow users to add concepts to the Briefcase. Users can
                                then view or modify them in the Briefcase.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Concept Details</emphasis> – The Concept Details pane
                    displays details of the concept selected in the task pane.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Navigation Bar</emphasis> – The Navigation bar enables
                    fast access to functions e.g. New Concept, Run Classifier, Modify global display
                    options.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <figure xml:id="layout">
            <title>Knowledge Editor Layout</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                        fileref="images/Editor-layout2.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </para>
  
    <section xml:id="editor-functions"><title>Task Pane</title>
        <para/>
    <section><title>Taxonomy</title>
           <para>In the Taxonomy view, users can navigate through the concept hierarchy under the
            taxonomy tree. The Taxonomy also displays the concepts with their parents and their
            children. Users can traverse the tree by selecting the caret symbol on the left of the
            tree to display the selected concept's children.</para>
            <para>The tree-like structure of the Taxonomy View allows users to navigate content from
                a top-down view – users can navigate up or down the lineage of the content by
                selecting the <emphasis>caret</emphasis> symbol on the left. The user can also
                select to display the <emphasis role="italic">Inferred</emphasis> or <emphasis
                    role="italic">Stated</emphasis> view of the content (the <emphasis role="italic"
                    >Inferred</emphasis> view is displayed by default). The inferred view shows the
                parent-child lineage that is derived by inferences through a set of logical rules
                and related concepts; the <emphasis role="italic">Stated</emphasis> view shows the
                parent-child lineage that is set by the editor when creating the concept. </para>
            <para><figure xml:id="taxonomy-view">
                <title>Taxonomy</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" 
                            fileref="images/taxonomy-view.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
           
        <section><title>Status</title>
                  <para>The Taxonomy Tree can display <emphasis role="italic">Active</emphasis> only
                    concepts or both <emphasis role="italic">Active</emphasis> and <emphasis
                        role="italic">Inactive</emphasis> concepts. <emphasis>Inactive</emphasis>
                    concepts will display in <emphasis>italics</emphasis>. The default is set to
                    display only <emphasis>Active</emphasis> concepts. To see both status types,
                    change the settings under <emphasis>Display Options</emphasis> in the top right
                    hand corner of the <emphasis>Task Pane</emphasis>.</para>
        </section>
<!--   not currently easily changeble in UI will omit for now     <section><title>Display Type</title>
           <para>The user has an additional option to display concepts in the Taxonomy Tree by
                    their <emphasis role=italic>Fully Qualified Name</emphasis> (FQN) or their
                        <emphasis role=italic>Regular Name </emphasis>.</para>-->
        <!--</section>-->
        <section><title>Refresh the Taxonomy</title>
            <para>The user is also able to force a refresh of the taxonomy by selecting the
                    <emphasis>Refresh</emphasis> button. This is useful when multiple concepts are
                expanded and the user would like to collapse them all.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="concept-type"><title>Concept Type – Defined versus Primitive</title>
            <para>In Knowledge, concepts are created as either a <emphasis>Defined</emphasis> or
                        <emphasis>Primitive</emphasis>. <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                                    <imageobject>
                                        <imagedata format="SVG" fileref="images/green-circle.svg"/>
                                    </imageobject>
                                    <textobject>
                                        <phrase>Defined concept</phrase>
                                    </textobject>
                                </inlinemediaobject>Defined – A concept that is
                                    <emphasis>Defined</emphasis> is represented by a green circle. A
                                concept is considered defined by unique relationships between its
                                relatives (e.g. siblings and parents).</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <inlinemediaobject>
                                    <imageobject>
                                        <imagedata format="SVG" fileref="images/hexagon.svg"/>
                                    </imageobject>
                                </inlinemediaobject>Primitive – A concept that is
                                    <emphasis>Primitive</emphasis> is represented by an orange
                                hexagon and signifies that its attributes and parents composing the
                                concept are non-definitive characteristics. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para></section>
        <section xml:id="linking"><title>Linking the Taxonomy View with Concept Details</title>
            <para>In the Knowledge Editor, a user can connect/link the concept selected in the
                Taxonomy to the Concept Details Panel, by default the connection or linkage is
                set. The linkage can be modified by toggling the linkage icon in the upper
                left-hand corner of the concept details pane, refer to <xref linkend="taxonomy-linked-to-details"/> and <xref linkend="unlinked"/>.
                When the linkage is set selecting a concept in the Taxonomy View displays the 
                concept in the <emphasis>Concept Details Pane</emphasis>. 
                <figure xml:id="taxonomy-linked-to-details">
                        <title>Linked</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="75%" 
                                    fileref="images/linkage-icon.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="unlinked">
                        <title>Unlinked </title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="70%" fileref="images/unlinked-icon.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
        </section></section>
         
        <section><title>Sets</title>
              <para> The <emphasis>Sets</emphasis> tab allows a user to create, view, and modify
                both Value and Map sets. A <emphasis>Value Set</emphasis> is a collection of
                concepts used for a specific purpose (e.g. Wound Color Value Set would contain the
                concepts needed to describe the color of a wound). A <emphasis>Map Set
                </emphasis>provides link between one terminology and another (e.g. SNOMED CT to
                LOINC mapping). </para> 
                <section>
                <title>Creating a Value Set</title>
                    <para>A <emphasis>Value Set</emphasis>, also known as an assemblage or a
                    reference set (refset), contains a collection of concepts used for a particular
                    purpose determined by its author. <example>
                        <title>Value Set Usage</title>
                        <para>Lateralizable body structure reference set is a SNOMED CT refset that
                            can be used to specify which arm a blood pressure was taken.</para>
                    </example></para>
                    <para>There are two ways to create a new value set: selecting <emphasis>New
                        Value Set</emphasis> under the Shortcuts navigation menu, or by selecting
                    the <emphasis>New</emphasis> button under the <emphasis>Sets</emphasis> tab in
                    the <emphasis>Task Pane</emphasis>. </para>
                <para>To create a Value Set, select the Sets tab in the left panel, change the
                        <emphasis>View Group</emphasis> to <emphasis>Value Sets</emphasis> and
                    select <emphasis>New</emphasis> to create a concept for the Value Set, see 
                    <xref linkend="new-value-set"/>. On the create new value set page (which is 
                    the same as create new concept), fill out the information needed, check the box for
                        <emphasis>This concept is a Value Set</emphasis>, and select
                        <emphasis>Create</emphasis>. </para>
                    <para>
                        <figure xml:id="new-value-set">
                            <title>New Value Set</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%" 
                                        fileref="images/new-value-set.png"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </para>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Adding Members to a Value Set</title>
                    <para>To add members to a value set, select the value set in the list and then
                        select <emphasis>Edit</emphasis> when viewing the value set's details
                        (located on the top right corner). This will take you to the edit view where
                        concepts can be added to the value set, removed from the value set, or added
                        to the Briefcase, see <xref linkend="value-set-members"/>. If you do not see
                        the members, select the <emphasis>Members</emphasis> tab on the right panel
                        after opening the value set details.</para>
                    <para>Select <emphasis>Add Member</emphasis> to find concepts to add, select the
                        remove icon to remove them, and select the Add to Briefcase icon to add any
                        of them to your briefcase. </para>
                    <para>
                        <figure xml:id="value-set-members">
                            <title>Editing Value Set Members </title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%" 
                                        fileref="images/value-set-members.png"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </para>
                    <para>When you are ready to add the concepts in the <emphasis>Value Set
                            Membership Changes</emphasis> list to the <emphasis>Members of this
                            Value Set</emphasis> list, select <emphasis>Save</emphasis>. </para>
                    <para>If there are any conflicts, error notifications will display the
                        information to help you decide how to resolve them. </para>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Inactivating Value Set Members</title>
                    <para>To inactivate members from a refset, select the <emphasis>Edit
                            Members</emphasis> button when viewing the refset details. This will
                        take you to <emphasis>Edit Mode</emphasis>, where you can remove members
                        from the list by selecting the <emphasis>X</emphasis> icon. The system will
                        display your selection in the list <emphasis>Value Set Membership
                            Changes</emphasis> for review. Press <emphasis>Save</emphasis> to
                        confirm your updates.</para>
                    <para>Members cannot be removed from the list, only deactivated. A user can
                        reactivate the concept anytime.</para>
                </simplesect>
            </section>
                
                <section><title>Creating a Map Set</title>
                    <para> A map set associates codes that have the same or similar meaning in one
                    system with another. For example, SNOMED CT's code for <emphasis>Vital signs
                        monitoring</emphasis> can be mapped to LOINC's <emphasis>Vital signs with
                        method details panel</emphasis> and <emphasis>Vital signs with smoking
                        status and pain scale [VSP]</emphasis>.</para>
            <para>To create a map set, go to the <emphasis>Sets</emphasis> tab in the left panel,
                    make sure that <emphasis>View Group</emphasis> is set to <emphasis>Map
                        Set</emphasis> and select <emphasis>New</emphasis> to open the form.</para>
                    <para><figure xml:id="mapsets-table">
                        <title>Map Sets list</title><mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%" fileref="images/mapset-table.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject></figure></para>
                    <para>There are 3 tabs in the Concept Details panel for the user to fill out:
                        <emphasis>Definition</emphasis>, <emphasis>Item Fields</emphasis>, and
                        <emphasis>Business Rules</emphasis>.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Definition - Enter the name, purpose, and any additional
                            information that users may need for the new map set. You can add more
                            fields, such as source code version, by selecting the <emphasis>Add More
                                Fields</emphasis> button on the left.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Item Fields - These are column headers to display when you view
                            the map sets. <emphasis>Source Description</emphasis>, <emphasis>Target
                                Description</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Equivalence Type</emphasis>
                            are selected by default, but you may add more fields or rearrange the
                            order of the columns displayed by selecting the <emphasis>Add More
                                Fields</emphasis> to Map Set Items button.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Business Rules - This is a free text comment box for additional
                                information that users may find useful, such as the use case and
                                guidance on when to use the map set.</para>
                                                   </listitem>
                        
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>After entering all relevant information, press the
                        <emphasis>Save</emphasis> button at the top of the panel. You will add
                    concepts to this set later. The new map set should appear in the left panel's
                        <emphasis>Map Sets</emphasis> list. If you do not see it there, press the
                        <emphasis>Refresh</emphasis> button.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Adding concepts to a new Map Set</title>
                <para>At this point, make sure that the map set you just created is open on the
                        right panel. Select <emphasis>Edit</emphasis> on the top right corner of the
                        panel, then take a look at the <emphasis>Map Set Items</emphasis> list.
                        There should be a <emphasis>plus-icon</emphasis> you can select to begin
                        adding concepts to the list.</para>
                <para><figure xml:id="new-map-set">
                    <title>Adding Concepts to a Map Set: Step 1</title><mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="40%" contentdepth="40%" fileref="images/new-map-set.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject></figure></para>
                <para>After selecting the <emphasis>plus-icon</emphasis>, the list will fill with a
                        row of droplists. Type in the concepts you wish to link as the source and
                        target descriptions. Adjust the equivalence type as necessary, add a comment
                        as needed, and press the <emphasis>Save</emphasis> button to confirm your
                        modifications. <figure xml:id="new-map-set2">
                            <title>Adding Concepts to a Map Set: Step 2</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="40%"
                                        contentdepth="40%" fileref="images/new-map-set-2.png"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                            <para>To remove a concept, press the <emphasis>X-icon</emphasis> on the
                                very right of the map set list.</para>
                        </figure></para>
            </simplesect>
            </section>
            </section>
            <section><title>Search</title>
                <para>Knowledge has implemented Lucene, an open-source full-text search library, as
                one of its search engines. A search can be performed using keywords and Lucene query
                syntax. To begin searching, select the <emphasis>Search</emphasis> tab on the left
                panel, then fill in the fields as needed. Both <emphasis>Simple Search</emphasis>
                and <emphasis>Advanced Search</emphasis> use Lucene. For more details on the Lucene
                search syntax refer to the <link xlink:href="http://www.lucenetutorial.com"> Lucene
                    tutorial</link>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Simple Search – searches for descriptions that match the search
                            phrase</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Advanced Search – refines the search parameters further, e.g.
                            searching for terminology id, description types (Fully qualified name,
                            Regular name and Definition)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <section>
            <title>Simple Search</title>
            <para>Terminologies can be searched by keywords under the <emphasis>Search</emphasis>
                    tab in the task pane. Type in keywords in the <emphasis>Search Text</emphasis>
                    field, then select the <emphasis>Search</emphasis> button to start the search,
                        <xref linkend="search-tab"/>. </para>
            <para><emphasis>Simple Search</emphasis> allows users to search for the keywords typed
                    in the search box. Selecting the search button will return all descriptions that
                    match. Keywords used in simple search are single terms or phrases. A single term
                    is a single word such as <emphasis>test</emphasis> or
                        <emphasis>hello.</emphasis> A phrase is a group of words surrounded by
                    double quotes such as <emphasis>"hello dolly."</emphasis> If a group of words
                    without double quotes are used such as <emphasis>hello</emphasis>
                    <emphasis>goodbye</emphasis>, then the results will display results that contain
                    either “hello” or “goodbye.” Multiple terms can be combined with Boolean
                    operators to form a more complex query. Review Lucene query <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.lucenetutorial.com/lucene-query-syntax.html">keyword
                        matching</link>for more advanced search syntax. </para>
                <para>
                    <figure xml:id="search-tab"><title>Simple Search</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <alt>Simple Search</alt>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="50%" 
                                    fileref="images/simple-search.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para></section>
                
    
            <section>
            <title>Advanced Search</title>
            <para>Search results can be filtered by using the <emphasis>Advanced Search</emphasis>
                    section, see <xref linkend="advanced-search-results"/>. There are 4 options in
                    the <emphasis>Advanced Search</emphasis> section:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Search In – This option narrows the search for Search Text to search in
                                <emphasis>concept</emphasis>: <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis>Descriptions</emphasis> will search-in the
                                        descriptions of a concept,</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis>Semantics</emphasis> will search the properties
                                        of a concept, or</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis>Identifiers</emphasis> searches the alphanumeric
                                        IDs of a concept such as an SCTID or LOINC code.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Page size – select the number of results to display at a time.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Description Type – the system restricts the search to a particular
                            description type, such as <emphasis>Fully Qualified Name</emphasis>
                            (FQN), a <emphasis>Regular Name</emphasis>, and
                                <emphasis>Definition</emphasis> if selected. When <emphasis>All
                                Types</emphasis> is selected the search will be performed on
                                <emphasis>FQN</emphasis>,<emphasis>Regular Name,</emphasis> and
                                <emphasis>Definition</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>CSV Export – when selected, the search results list will export the
                            results list in CSV format.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Select the <emphasis>Search</emphasis> button in order to update the results when
                    advanced options are changed.</para>
            <example>
                <title>Advanced Search Example</title>
                <para>In this example, the search results are descriptions that contain
                            <emphasis>hypertension</emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis>
                        <emphasis>failure</emphasis>. The results list will contain a list of
                        matching concept, description, the terminology identifier, and status, <xref
                            linkend="advanced-search-results"/>.</para>
            </example>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="advanced-search-results">
                    <title>Advanced Search</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>Advanced search options</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="50%" 
                                fileref="images/advanced-search-results.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </section>
                <!-- TBD feature 
             <simplesect><title>Saved Searches</title>
                  <para>Search criteria can be saved for later user under the Search tab. To do so,
                      enter the search criteria and select the Search button. A results section
                      should appear below the search fields along with options to save the search and
                      to export the results to a CSV file. Select the Save Search link in order to
                      name and save the search.</para>
                  <para>Saved searches are retrieved under the saved searches section of the search
                      tab. This section is only visible if there are previously saved searches. Select
                      the desired search from a dropdown list and press the Search button to pull
                      results.</para></simplesect>-->
            <section><title>Search Results</title>
                <para>The search results are displayed in a list below the search criteria. The
                    default fields displayed in the search results list are <emphasis>Matching
                        Concepts, Matching Descriptions, Terminology Identifier, Status, and
                        Module</emphasis>, see <xref linkend="advanced-search-results"/>.</para>
            
            </section>
        </section>
        <section><title>Classifier</title>
            <para>The Knowledge Editor integrates a high performance Classifier called SnoRocket
                    (<link xlink:href="https://aehrc.com/snorocket/"
                    >https://aehrc.com/snorocket/</link>) which supports OWL EL++ and Concrete
                Domains. The classifier evaluates the stated relationships, based on <emphasis
                    role="italic">Description Logics </emphasis>upon which the terminology is
                defined, and generates the inferred relationships for each concept. The Knowledge
                Editor displays <emphasis role="italic">Stated and Inferred </emphasis>views of the
                concept in the <emphasis role="italic">Concept Details Pane </emphasis>and the
                Taxonomy displays <emphasis role="italic">Stated and Inferred </emphasis>as-a
                relationships based on the Taxonomy display options.</para>
                <section>
                    <title xml:id="run-classifier">Run the Classifier</title>
                    <para>There are two areas in the Knowledge Editor interface to initiate
                    classification: the navigation menu <emphasis>Shortcuts</emphasis> and the
                        <emphasis>Classifier</emphasis> tab, <xref linkend="classifier-tab"/>. </para>
                    <para>The first classification will evaluate all concepts in the environment,
                subsequent classifications will evaluate only modified concepts. The first
                classification duration will be less than 15 minutes, and subsequent classifications
                will be less than 10 minutes. A classification has three possible status values:
                    <emphasis>Running</emphasis>, <emphasis>Done</emphasis>, and
                    <emphasis>Failed</emphasis>.</para>
                    <para>To start classification select the <emphasis>Run Classifier</emphasis>
                    button. An entry will be added to the <emphasis>Classifier Run List</emphasis>.
                    Since the list does not update automatically when a classification is completed,
                    the user can select the <emphasis>Refresh Run List</emphasis> to force an update
                    of the Run List list.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="classifier-tab"><title>Classifier Details</title><mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/classifier-tab.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject></figure>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Classifier Results</title>
                    <para>When the classifier has completed, the status will change from
                        <emphasis>Running</emphasis> to <emphasis>Done</emphasis>. A user may view
                        classification results by selecting an entry in the <emphasis>Classifier Run
                        List</emphasis>. The results of classification are displayed on the right in
                        <emphasis>Classifier Details</emphasis>, 
                        <xref linkend="classifier-details"/>.</para>
                    <para>The classifier details will provide a summary at the top and details below
                of: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Affected concepts - a list of concepts that are changed by the
                                classifier.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Equivalent sets – any defined concepts that have identical
                                relationships. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Orphaned concepts – concepts that are not defined correctly and must
                                be corrected.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Cycles – the classifier finds cycles that would be difficult to find
                                just by looking at the definition of a concept. Cycles are
                                transitive relationships such as:<example>
                                    <title>Cycle Example</title>
                                    <para>If concept A's is-a definition is B and B is-a C, and C
                                        is-a A, this will flag a cycle error during
                                        classification</para>
                                </example></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
                  <para>The concepts under each of these categories are displayed in a list by
                    default. To hide the details of a category, select the caret symbol next to list
                    name to toggle between expanding and collapsing the list view. You also have the
                    option of adding concepts to your briefcase to correct any issues.</para>
                    <para>
                        <figure xml:id="classifier-details"><title>Classifier Details</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject><imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" 
                                fileref="images/classifier-details.png"/></imageobject>
                            </mediaobject></figure>
                    </para>
                </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>New Concepts</title>
            <para> New concepts can be added to Knowledge in several steps, then classified to
                create inferred relationships. </para>
            <para>To begin creating a new concept, select the <emphasis>New Concept</emphasis> from
                either the <emphasis>Taxonomy</emphasis> tab or under the
                    <emphasis>Shortcuts</emphasis> menu (see figure <xref linkend="new-concept-1"
                />). The <emphasis>New Concept Form</emphasis> should appear in the
                    <emphasis>Concept Panel</emphasis>.<figure xml:id="new-concept-1">
                    <title>How to Add a New Concept: Step 1</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                                fileref="images/new-concept-buttons.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure></para>
                <para>On the New Concept form, you must fill out the following informaiton to create
                the concept:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Parent - Select one or more parents that the concept will be related
                            to. Begin typing to view a list of suggested parent concepts. Select
                                <emphasis>Add Parent</emphasis> to add an additional one.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Concept name - Enter in the new concept's name</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>This concept is a Value Set</emphasis> checkbox - If you are
                            creating a value set or simple assemblage, check this box, see <xref
                                linkend="new-value-set"/>. Otherwise, leave it unchecked.</para>
                        <para>
                            <figure xml:id="new-concept-2">
                                <title>How to Add a New Concept: Step 2</title>
                                <mediaobject>
                                    <imageobject>
                                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1"
                                            fileref="images/new-concept-form.png"/>
                                    </imageobject>
                                </mediaobject>
                            </figure>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>Next, press <emphasis>Create</emphasis> to save the new concept. The
                application will ask you to confirm your changes because new concepts cannot be
                deleted after creation, they can only be inactivated.</para>
            <para>Once the concept is created, the concept will display in
                    <emphasis>edit-mode</emphasis>. Here, the <emphasis>Fully Qualified Name,
                    Regular Name, and Dialects</emphasis> are already pre-filled. Feel free to add
                additional descriptions or names as needed, add or edit dialects, set active
                statuses, and more. <figure xml:id="new-concept-3">
                    <title>How to Add a New Concept: Step 3</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1"
                                fileref="images/edit-new-concept.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure></para>
            <para>For advanced users, the <emphasis>Axiom </emphasis>can also be edited. Axioms
                display the stated and inferred relationships of the concept. To view the available
                actions, select the <emphasis>Edit</emphasis> icon. <figure xml:id="new-concept-4">
                    <title>Editing Axioms</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" fileref="images/edit-axiom.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                    <para>Press <emphasis>Save</emphasis> at the top of the page to confirm all
                        changes once edits are done.</para>
                    <para>New concepts can only be found immediately in the taxnomy tree after
                        creation, if the <emphasis>Taxonomy Tree</emphasis> view is set to
                            <emphasis>Stated</emphasis>if the . If you do not see the concept, make
                        sure that the taxonomy tab is displaying Stated concepts, not inferred. If
                        the <emphasis>Taxonomy Tree</emphasis> is set to
                            <emphasis>Inferred</emphasis> run the classifier, refer to <xref
                            linkend="run-classifier"/> and upon completion of classification the
                        concept is displayed in the <emphasis>Inferred</emphasis> view.</para>
                </figure></para>

        </section>
         
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="knowledge-qa.xml" xpointer="qa-section"/>
        
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="knowledge-export.xml" xpointer="export-and-version"/>
        
       <section><title>Briefcase</title>
           <para>The <emphasis>Briefcase</emphasis> temporarily holds concepts that can be reviewed
                and/or edited later. For example, the <emphasis>Briefcase</emphasis> can be used: </para>
           <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                   <para> To hold equivalent (duplicates) concepts that are flagged as a result of
                        classification. To edit and view the details of the equivalent concept you
                        can add the concept to the <emphasis>Briefcase</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
               <listitem>
                   <para>To add a concept from a <emphasis>Value Set </emphasis>to the
                            <emphasis>Briefcase</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist>
           
           
           <para>The <emphasis>Briefcase</emphasis> is viewable from the <emphasis>Task
                    Pane</emphasis> of the Knowledge Editor, see screen shot below. <figure
                    xml:id="briefcase">
                    <title>Briefcase</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>The briefcase options Select All Items, Remove Selected Items, and
                            Refresh List.</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%"
                                fileref="images/briefcase-panel.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure></para>
      
        <section>
            <title>Adding a concept to the Briefcase from the Taxonomy</title>
            <para>Concepts in the taxonomy can be added to the <emphasis>Briefcase</emphasis> by
                    right-clicking to view the context menu, and selecting <emphasis>Add to
                        Briefcase</emphasis>. Some of the concepts displayed in lists and the
                        <emphasis>Concept Details Panel</emphasis> can also be added by this
                    method.</para>
            <para><figure xml:id="context-menu"><title>Context Menu</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%" 
                                fileref="images/context-menu.jpg"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                 </figure></para>
        </section>
           <section><title>Adding a concept to the Briefcase from Classifier Results</title>
               <para>To add a terminology to the <emphasis>Briefcase</emphasis> from some lists such
                    as Classifier page, select the briefcase icon (not all lists have this feature).
                    In the example below, there is an <emphasis>Add to Briefcase</emphasis> icon on
                    the 5th column of the members list and an option to <emphasis>Add all to
                        Briefcase</emphasis> above the list.</para>
               
           </section>
           
           <section><title>Adding a concept to the Briefcase from a Value Set</title>
               <para>
                   <figure xml:id="add-briefcase"><title>Add to Briefcase</title>
                       <mediaobject>
                           <alt>Members tab under the concept Lateralizable body structure reference
                                set with a list that contains the option to add to briefcase in the
                                5th column</alt>
                           <imageobject>
                               <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75" contentdepth="75%" 
                                   fileref="images/add-to-briefcase.png"/>
                           </imageobject>
                       </mediaobject>
                   </figure></para>
           </section>
              <section><title>Removing concepts from the briefcase</title>
                  <para>There are two options to remove concepts from the Briefcase:
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Remove all concepts in the list by selecting the <emphasis>Select All
                                    Items</emphasis> button and then selecting the <emphasis>Remove
                                    Selected Items</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To remove one or more concepts but <emphasis>not all</emphasis>
                                concepts from the <emphasis>Briefcase</emphasis> select the box to
                                the right of the concept to be removed and select the
                                    <emphasis>Remove Selected Items</emphasis> button.</para></listitem>
                </orderedlist></para></section>
                <simplesect><title>Refreshing the Briefcase List</title>
                    <para>If you do not see the concept(s) just added, try refreshing the list by
                   selecting <emphasis>Refresh List</emphasis>.</para></simplesect>
             </section>
    </section>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="knowledge-concept-viewer.xml" xpointer="concept-details"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="knowledge-navigation-bar.xml" xpointer="navigation-bar-description"/>
    
    <section xml:id="context-menu-section"><title>Context Menu</title>
        <para>A context menu appears when users right-click on the concept name either on the
            taxonomy tree <xref linkend="taxonomy-context-menu"/> or in the title of concept details
            panel <xref linkend="concept-details-context-menu"/>. Some lists contain a context menu
            througout the application.</para>
        <para>The context menu contains the following options:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open concept – opens the concept details information</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open concept in new Concept Viewer – opens the concept details information
                        in a third panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add to briefcase – add the concept to  briefcase, which can be viewed  in
                        the briefcase tab.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Copy concept, UUID, SCTID, description and SCTID – copies the information described.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Edit concept – opens the concept in edit mode.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Edit concept in new viewer – opens the concept in edit mode, in a third concept
                        details panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clone concept – duplicates the concept information as a new concept.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clone concept in new viewer – duplicates the concept information as a new
                        concept and opens a new concept details panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create child concept – creates a new child concept with the same information as the selected
                        concept and uses the selected concept as the parent.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create child concept in new viewer – creates a new child concept with the
                        same information as the selected concept, uses the selected concept as the
                        parent and opens a third Concept Details panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inactivate concept – sets the selected concept's state to inactive. If the
                        concept disappears from the taxonomy, display options are set to not display
                        inactive concepts.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Activate concept – sets the selected concept's state to active. This option is only visible in the context menu
                        if the selected concept is inactive.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="taxonomy-context-menu">
                    <title>Taxonomy Context Menu Options</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%" 
                                fileref="images/taxonomy-context-menu.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                            <phrase>Right click options</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            <figure xml:id="concept-details-context-menu">
                <title>Concept Details Context Menu Options</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%" 
                            fileref="images/cursor-over-concept-details.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>Right click options</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        
    </section>
    
</chapter> 
