<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">

        
<title>Introduction to Knowledge Web-based Application</title>
    <section><title>Overview</title>
        <para>MindComputing Knowledge is an intuitive full featured web-based application designed
            to be used. We will describe how to get the most value out of Knowledge by using its key
            features, such as search, creating a new concept, creating value sets, running the
            classifier, and exporting your work in Solor's RF2 compatible format and the future
            Solor's object release format.</para>
        <para>Knowledge is based on HSPC's project Solor. Knowledge has similar functionality to Solor's desktop application but 
              Knowledge also differs. Our most basic difference is that Knowledge has defined a REST API and is a 
              web-based applicaiton. Knowledge utilizes Solor's common model approach to integrating Meaningful Use Standards 
              (SNOMED CT, LOINC and RxNorm) and local terminologies to import into the Knowledge application. In addition, Knowledge can
              also load Meaningful Use Standards and local terminologies without utilizing Solor's common model integration.</para>
        <para>The Knowledge application has 3 components the: Editor, Manager, and a Terminology Server:</para>
           <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>The <emphasis>Knowledge Editor</emphasis> provides all authoring functionality, such as creating new concepts, modify concepts, 
                            creating value sets, modifying value sets, classifying, search, mapping and exporting content. 
                            The application supports the SNOMED CT RF2, and Solor RF2 compatible export out-of-the-box. </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>                
                  <para>The <emphasis>Knowledge Manager</emphasis> provides user administration functions, such as user creation, disabling a user, 
                            and user roles within a project. In addition, Manager has project management functions such as, project creation. </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Our <emphasis>Terminology Server</emphasis> supports runtime terminology requirements. This includes a complete implementation of Fast Healthcare 
                          Interoperability Resources (FHIR) Application Programming Interface (API) as an enterprise cloud computing service.</para>
               </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Editor</title>
            <para>The Editor is an interactive application that allows you to: search, view, edit
            concepts, create new concepts, and create valuesets. By default, the Editor is divided
            into 3 areas: the <emphasis role="bold">task pane</emphasis>band the <emphasis
                role="bold">concept viewer</emphasis> pane, and <emphasis role="bold"
                >navigation</emphasis>. When you select a concept on the task pane, its details can
            be viewed in the concept viewer on the right. <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor layout as described above.</alt>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/editor-layout.png" width="600px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure></para>
            <section><title></title></section>
        </section>
        <section><title>Knowledge Manager</title>
            <para>
            
            </para>
        </section>
        <section><title>Terminology Server</title>
            <para>
                
            </para>
        </section>
</chapter>  
 