<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">

        
<title>Introduction to Knowledge</title>
    
    <para>Knowledge is an intuitive full featured web-based application designed
          to be used by individuals, and organizations who need to manage their medical terminology needs to improve
          healthcare delivery and reimbursement. The following chapters describe the functionality that enables 
          the creation of new content, the modification of content, and releasing content to satisfy our customers needs.</para>
    
    <para>Knowledge is based on <link xlink:href="https://www.logicahealth.org/">Logica's</link>
       Open Source project <link xmlns:xlink="https://www.solor.io/">Solor</link>. Mind Computing has taken the Solor project
        and created Knowledge a web-based application. Knowledge also utilizes Solor's common model
        approach to integrating Meaningful Use Standards, such as SNOMED CT, LOINC and RxNorm.
        Additionally, Knowledge can also integrate locally created content and import this created
        content into the Knowledge application where this terminology can be integrated with
        Meaningful Use Standards. Knowledge can load Meaningful Use Standards and locally created
        terminologies without utilizing Solor's common model. </para>
    
    
    <para>The Knowledge application has 3 components the: Editor, Manager, and a Terminology Server. The <emphasis>Knowledge Editor</emphasis> 
          provides all authoring functionality, such as creating new concepts, modify concepts, creating value sets, modifying value sets, 
          classifying, search, mapping and exporting content. The Knowledge Manager provides the functionality to create new users and modify a user's role
          the user has the administrator role. Our <emphasis>Terminology Server</emphasis> supports runtime terminology requirements. This includes a complete implementation of Fast Healthcare 
          Interoperability Resources (FHIR) Application Programming Interface (API) as an enterprise cloud computing service.</para>
    <para><link xlink:href="http://cnn.com">test</link></para> 
    
</chapter>  
 
