<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Version and Export</title>
    <section xml:id="export-and-version">
        <title>Export and Version</title>
        <para>Knowledge users with Content Manager or Administrator roles can create versions or
            export content. This feature can be accessed by selecting <emphasis>Export
                Content</emphasis> from the drop down <emphasis>Shortcuts</emphasis> menu in the
                <emphasis>Navigation bar</emphasis>
            <xref linkend="shortcuts"/> The <emphasis>Create Export</emphasis> pop-up will appear -
            see Figure 1.1 Export. The primary purpose of creating versions is to make releases and
            content available to internal and external customers in release file format. Currently
            Knowledge supports the generation of a SNOMED CT Release File Format 2 (RF2) release
            files.</para>
        <para>Knowledge users with Content Manager or Administrator roles can create versions or
            export content by accessing this functionality from the <emphasis>Task Pane</emphasis>,
            see <xref linkend="export"/>; Editors can export content only and access this
            functionality from the <emphasis>Shortcuts</emphasis> menu, <xref linkend="shortcuts"/>.
            The primary purpose of creating versions is to make releases and content available to
            internal and external customers in release file format. Currently Knowledge supports the
            generation of a SNOMED CT Release File Format 2 (RF2) release files.</para>
        
         <section xml:id="export-steps">
            <title>Export with Editor Role</title>
            <para>To create an export with Editor role select <emphasis>Export</emphasis> under the
                    <emphasis>Shortcuts</emphasis> menu, <xref linkend="shortcuts"/> and provide the
                parameters specified in the <emphasis>Export Form</emphasis>, <xref linkend="export"
                />:</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Select modules - Select the modules that you want to export from. The
                            edit module is selected by default. Select more than one module by
                            holding the CTRL key while selecting multiple modules.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Content range - Select the date range for the content you are
                            exporting. Note that when the files are exported, the content's date
                            stamp will be updated to the selected start date.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Generate SCTID for content with missing IDs - Select this option when
                            SCTIDs should be added to any newly created SNOMED CT concepts that do
                            not have SCTIDs. Include the namespace identifier provided by SNOMED
                            international when this option is selected.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Export type - SNOMED CT RF2 is selected by default. The Solor RF2
                            compatible release will be available in a future Knowledge
                            release.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                <figure>
                    <title xml:id="export">Export</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>Create an Export modal displays a form with the following information:
                            select modules, content range, generate SCTIDs, namespace, export type,
                            and buttons Create and Cancel.</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="60%" contentdepth="60%"
                                fileref="images/export.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>When an export is initiated a message is shown informing the user that an export
                is in process, see <xref linkend="messages-export"/>. Once the export is ready,
                Knowledge will notify you that the file is ready for download. Click on the export
                message, and your browser will prompt you to download the file to your computer. The
                download is made available for 5 mins and then expires.<figure>
                    <title xml:id="messages-export">Export</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>Create an Export modal displays a form with the following information:
                            select modules, content range, generate SCTIDs, namespace, export type,
                            and buttons Create and Cancel.</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="60%" contentdepth="60%"
                                fileref="images/export-messages.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure></para>
        </section>
             
        <section><title>Create a Version and Export</title>
            <subtitle>With Administrator or Content Manager Role</subtitle>
             <para>If the user has the role of Administrator or Content Manager the
                    <emphasis>Version and Export</emphasis> tab in the <emphasis>Task
                    Pane</emphasis> is displayed. The <emphasis>Version and Export</emphasis> tab
                allows the user to create a version or initiate an export by selecting the version
                or export button. </para>
            <para>
                <figure>
                    <title xml:id="export-or-version-admin">Version and Export</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>Export or Version Button</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                                fileref="images/export-and-version.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <title xml:id="short-cuts-admin">Shortcuts Menu</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>Export or Version Button</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                                fileref="images/short-cuts-admin-role.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
           
            <section><title>Export</title> <subtitle>As an Administrator or Content Manager</subtitle>
                <para>An Administrator or Content Manager can initiate an export by selecting the
                        <emphasis>Export</emphasis> button in the <emphasis>Version and
                        Export</emphasis> tab or selecting <emphasis>Export</emphasis> from the
                        <emphasis>Shortcuts</emphasis> menu. The workflow is the same as described
                    in <xref linkend="export-steps"/>. </para>
            </section>
            
        <section><title>Version</title>
            <para>When content is ready to be released, a Content Manager or Administrator can
                    create a version by selecting the <emphasis>Create a Version</emphasis> located
                    in the <emphasis>Shortcuts </emphasis>menu or in the <emphasis>Export and
                        Versions</emphasis> tab. A form will display, <xref
                        linkend="create-version-form"/> asking for the following information:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Module location - This is where the new version module will be
                                located in the taxonomy after creation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Version name – the user specified name of the version
                                module.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Content version date - This optional field will update the content
                                modification dates of the concepts to the date selected. If it is
                                left blank, no changes will be made to the original dates on each
                                concept.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Content range – Select the date range for the content you want to
                                create a version for. To better assist you, you can optionally
                                select the <emphasis>Select by version date</emphasis> link to pick
                                a date based on a previous version.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Run Classifier – Gives the user the option to run the classifier
                                as a step in generating a version.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Perform QA Test - QA tests are necessary to ensure accurate data.
                                The version may not be created if there is a QA error. You can
                                perform the test independently before creating a version or run it
                                in this process. If you choose to run QA in this version creation
                                and QA is unable to complete, the version will not be
                                created.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Generate SCTIDs for content with missing IDs - If there is any
                                SNOMED content with missing SCTIDs, the system can generate them for
                                you. Include the namespace identifier provided by SNOMED
                                international when this option is selected.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Namespace - If you choose to generate SCTIDs, this is the SNOMED
                                identifier that is provided to you by SNOMED CT.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Create and download and export file - Downloads a compressed file
                                of all of the contents.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Save a copy to the repository - Publishes the exported file into
                                the repository server.<note>
                                    <para>This is configurable for each customer and is not
                                        configured in the Knowledge demonstration
                                        enviornment.</para>
                                </note></para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Export Type<footnote>
                                    <para>The Solor RF2 comptabible export will be supported in a
                                        future Knowledge release.</para>
                                </footnote> – SNOMED CT RF2 is supported at this time. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>
                <figure>
                    <title xml:id="create-version-form">Create a Version</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>Create a Version modal displays a form with the following information:
                            select modules, content range, perform QA test, perform classification,
                            generate SCTIDs, namespace, export type, and buttons Create and Cancel.</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="40%" contentdepth="40%"
                                fileref="images/create-version.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>Select <emphasis>Create Version </emphasis>to begin the backend versioning
                    process. A message is displayed to indicate the versioning process has started,
                    see <xref linkend="version-initated"/>. The time to create a version will depend
                    on the options selected, such as classification and QA. <figure>
                        <title xml:id="version-initated">Version Initiated</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <alt/>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="600%" contentdepth="60%"
                                    fileref="images/version-initiated.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
                    <para>When version creation is complete the progress table is updated, see <xref
                        linkend="version-export-progress"/>, and the results of create version are
                    displayed, see <xref linkend="gen-version-results"/>. 
                        <figure>
                            <title xml:id="version-export-progress">Version or Export Progress</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <alt></alt>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="60%" contentdepth="60%"
                                        fileref="images/version-export-progress.png"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </para>                      
            <para>If <emphasis>Perform QA</emphasis> tests was selected and you wish to view the
                    results, select the <emphasis>Open QA Run</emphasis> link. If <emphasis>Run
                        Classifier</emphasis> was selected and you wish to view the classification
                    results select the link <emphasis>Open Classifier Run</emphasis>. You will be
                    brought to either the QA or Classifier results depending on what was selected.
                    If <emphasis>Create and Download an Export File</emphasis> was selected the
                    export file can be downloaded to the user's computer by selecting the
                        <emphasis>Release file available</emphasis> link. In the Knowledge
                    demonstration environment the export results will be available for a limited
                    time and are not uploaded to a repository. In a production Knowledge environment
                    the customer can choose to include uploading a version export to a repository.<figure>
                        <title xml:id="gen-version-results">Version Results</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <alt/>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="60%" contentdepth="60%"
                                    fileref="images/gen-version-results.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
            
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
</chapter>


