<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Navigation Bar</title>
<section xml:id="navigation-bar-description"><title>Navigation Bar</title>
    <para>The Editor allows the ability to modify content, create content, view content, create
            versions, and export content. One of the areas to access these functions is in the
            navigation bar. </para>
    <para><figure xml:id="navigation-bar">
        <title>Navigation Bar</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor navigation displaying the Editor logo, and
                menu options for Projects, Export Management, Authoring, Manager, and User
                name Admin</alt>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="40%" contentdepth="40%"
                    fileref="images/nav-editor-layout2.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure></para>
    <para>The navigation bar provides the following options:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Projects - If your account has more than one project assigned, switch
                        between them by selecting this menu item.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Shortcuts - Used for multiple actions that can be found in tab-specific
                        areas of the application.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Manager - this option takes you to the Knowledge Manager Homepage. For the
                        content editor and manager, account settings can be modified here; for the
                        admin, user permissions and info are located here.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>User - the menu under the user's name provides the ability to update
                        global settings, manage account, and to log out.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    <section><title>Projects</title>
       <para>This menu displays the projects that a user is assigned to. The user can switch between
                projects with this menu option as long as there is more than one project assgined,
                and the Knowledge environment they are working in has more than one project defined.
                The default is to have one project per Knowledge instance.</para></section>
    <section><title>Shortcuts</title>
        <para>The shortcuts submenu provides a quick way for the user to access certain actions.
                These include:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New concept – to create a new concept.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New map set – to create a new map set.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New value set – to create a new value set.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run classifier – performs a classification run.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Export content – displays the export content modal.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a version – displays the create a version modal.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run QA test – performs a quality assurance check. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            <figure xml:id="shortcuts">
                    <title>Shortcuts Menu</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt></alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" 
                                fileref="images/shortcuts-menu2.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>All of these actions can be performed by going through the shortcut menu or
                through features within specific tabs and panels in the <emphasis>task pane</emphasis>, 
            refer to <xref linkend="editor-functions"/>.</para>
        </section>
            
    <section><title>Manager</title>
        <para>The Manager option is only available to an <emphasis>Administrator</emphasis>
            or <emphasis>System Manager</emphasis> administrator. If selected the user will 
            be taken to the Knowledge Manager area. Here a user with the appropriate permissions can
            modify user accounts, create new accounts, etc. for more details refer to 
            <xref linkend="manager-doc" /> </para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Username Menu</title>
        <para>The menu under the user's name provides the ability to modify global settings, manage
                your account, view the user guide, and log out. Global settings contain filters and
                customizations for how you want to view the content. Manage account takes you to the
                Manager portal of Knowledge, where your profile and login information can be
                modified. 
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Global Display Settings – a user can specify information that is displayed</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Manage Account – a user can modify their account information</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Help – user documentation for Knowledge</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Logout – signs you out of Knowledge</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para><figure xml:id="user-menu">
            <title>User Menu</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <alt></alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="left" 
                        fileref="images/user-menu-options.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
        
        <section><title>Global Display Options</title>
            <para>Global display options enables the user to customize the information that is seen
                    throughout the Knowledge application. For example: uncheck <emphasis>Show
                    Only Active Concepts</emphasis> and select the <emphasis>apply</emphasis> button. The 
                <emphasis>Inactive</emphasis> concepts and descriptions will display,
                  see <xref linkend="inactive-concepts" />. </para>
            <para><figure xml:id="display-options">
                <title>Global Display Options</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <alt></alt>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%"
                            fileref="images/global-display-options.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            </para>
            <para><figure xml:id="inactive-concepts">
                <title>Inactive Concepts and Descriptions</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <alt></alt>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%"
                            fileref="images/inactive-concepts-descriptions-displayed.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para></section>
    </section>
    
        
</section> 
</chapter>
