<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Concept Viewer</title>
       <section xml:id="concept-viewer">
           <title>Concept Details</title>
            <para>Concepts represent a clinical meaning which is assigned a unique identifier, have
            descriptions that describe the concept,  have relationships that relate concepts to
            eachother, and OWL axioms that provide a logical definition to the concept. The logical
            definition is used by the <emphasis>Classifier</emphasis> to infer additional
            relationships between concepts. When a user selects a concept from the Taxonomy view,
            search results, or the briefcase details about the selected concept are displayed in the
            Concept Details panel, refer to <xref linkend="concept-details-overview"/>. 
                This view contains a variety of information about the
            concept as described below: 
                <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Fully Qualified Name (FQN) – human readable unique word or phrase which
                        represents clinical meaning. And FQN </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem >
                    <para></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Regular Name (NAM) – is a term of a specified type that describes the
                        concept. A concept can have more than one Regular Name.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Status – defines whether the concept is active or inactive</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Module – identifies which module the concept belongs in e.g. a SNOMED CT
                        concept is in SNOMED CT core module</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para/>
        <para>
           <figure xml:id="concept-details-overview">
               <title>Concept Details</title>
               <mediaobject>
                   <alt>Figure of the Concept Details pane.</alt>
                   <imageobject>
                       <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="60%" contentdepth="60%"
                           fileref="images/concept-details-overview.png"/>
                   </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
           </figure>
        </para>
           <para>The pane lists the general concept information such as STAMP (define STAMP), its
            descriptions which include additional names it may be known by in other languages and
            dialects, and the axiom history which illustrates its taxonomy relationship. Details
            such as the inferred information or inactive items can be toggled on by selecting
            "Display options" in the upper right corner, and its refset relationships and history
            can be found in tabs within the same panel.</para>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <alt>Figure of the Display Options modal from the concept viewer. Displays options
                    such as "Show authors, language, modules, filter STAMP date," and more.</alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images" width="750px"/>
                </imageobject>
                
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para>Optionally another <emphasis role="bold">concept viewer</emphasis> pane can be opened
            and will display on the far right side of the window. There are three alternatives to
            open another concept viewer: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Right-click the concept you wish to review and select "<emphasis role="bold"
                        >open in new concept viewer</emphasis>". </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Highlight the concept you want to see in a new viewer and press "<emphasis
                        role="bold">keyboard shortcut tbd, e.g. ctrl+alt+n</emphasis> " to open a
                    new concept viewer. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>In the top navigation pane, select <emphasis role="bold"
                        >"Authoring"</emphasis>, then <emphasis role="bold">"Launch Third
                        View"</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> 
           <section><title>Create New Concept</title>
               <para></para></section>
           <section><title>Show Concept Information</title>
                <para></para></section>
           <section><title>Display Concept History</title>
               <para></para></section>
           <section><title>Show Value Set Membership</title>
               <para></para></section>
           <section><title>Edit Concept</title>
               <para></para></section>
           <section><title>Clone Concept</title>
               <para></para></section>
           <section><title>Concept Display Options</title>
               <para></para></section>
           <section><title>Close Pane</title>
               <para></para></section>
       </section>
</chapter>
   

