<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

    
    <appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Axiom Details</title>
    <section><title>Introduction</title>
        <para></para>
        
    </section>
 
    <section><title>Axioms</title>
        <para>Each Concept is logically defined by it's relationships to other concepts.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Classifier</title>
    <para>The Knowledge Editor integrates a high performance Classifier--SnoRocket <link
            xlink:href="https://aehrc.com/snorocket/">https://aehrc.com/snorocket/</link>--which
        supports OWL EL++ and Concrete Domains. The classifier evaluates the stated relationships
        based on <emphasis role="italic">Description Logics </emphasis>upon which the terminology is
        defined and generates the inferred relationships for each concept. The Knowledge Editor
        displays <emphasis role="italic">stated and inferred </emphasis>views of the concept in the
            <emphasis role="italic">concept viewer pane </emphasis>and the Taxonomy displays
            <emphasis role="italic">stated and inferred </emphasis>is-a relationships based on the
        Taxonomy display options.</para>
    <simplesect>
        <title>How Do I Run the Classifier?</title>
        <para>There are 2 places in the Knowledge Editor interface to run the classifier: at the
            main navigation menu under "Authoring" and in the "Classifier" tab on the left pane. </para>
        <para>The initial run of the classifier after the start of the system will result in all
            concepts being evaluated. Subsequent classifications will only evaluate modified
            concepts, also known as incremental classification. Incremental classification will
            continue so long as the classifier status cache is maintained. This number is only a
            measure of how much work the classifier did. </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>How Do I View Previous Classifier Results?</title>
        <para>When you open the Classifier tab under the Authoring interface, there is a table of
            previously run classifications. You may view classifications  results selecting a
            different classification run from the dropdown "Classifier runs".</para>
        <para>To view any of these runs, select one and it will display in a concept viewer on the
            right.</para>
        <para>Here, a summary of attributes and types are displayed including:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Added "Is a" Types</para>
                    <para>This indication that an is-a relationship has been added to the concept by the classifier.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inactived "Is a" Types</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>New Attributes</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inactivated Attributes</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cycles Detected</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Equivalents Detected</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>To review the concepts under each of these summaries, select the row. A
            table listing the identificed concepts will display below the summary list. You also
            have the option of adding concepts to your briefcase.</para>
        <para>If you discover any inaccuracies or equivalencies after a classification, edits must
            be made directly at the concept level. Refer to "How to Edit a Concept" for information
            on modifying
            terminologies.<?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190620T144233-0700" comment="Link to Create-Edit section"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
    </simplesect>
   </section>
  
    </appendix>

