<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Navigation Bar</title>
<section xml:id="navigation-bar"><title>Navigation Bar</title>
    <para>The Editor allows the ability to modify, create content, view content, create versions,
            and export content. One of the areas to access these functions are found in the top
            navigation bar. </para>
    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor navigation displaying the Editor logo, and
            menu options for Projects, Export Management, Authoring, Manager, and User
            name Admin</alt>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                fileref="images/nav-editor-layout2.png" />
        </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject></para>
    <para>The navigation options are:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Projects - If your account has more than one project assigned, switch
                        between them by selecting this menu item.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Shortcuts - Used for multiple actions that can be found in tab-specific
                        areas of the application.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Manager - this option takes you to the Knowledge Manager Homepage. For the
                        content editor and manager, account settings can be modified here; for the
                        admin, user permissions and info are located here.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>User - the menu under the user's name provides the ability to update
                        global settings, manage account, and to log out.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    <section><title>Projects</title>
       <para>This menu displays the projects that a user is assigned to. The user can switch between
                projects with this menu option as long as there is more than one project assgined,
                and the Knowledge environment they are working in has more than one project defined.
                The default is to have one project per Knowledge instance.</para></section>
    <section><title>Shortcuts</title>
        <para>The shortcuts submenu provides a quick way for the user to access certain actions.
                These include:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New concept – to create a new concept.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New map set – to create a new map set.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New value set – to create a new value set (note that the "This concept
                            is a Value Set" item needs to be checked on the form).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run classifier – performs a classification run. To view results, go to
                            the Classifier tab on the left panel.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Export content – displays the export content modal.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a version – displays the create a version modal.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run QA test  – performs a quality assurance check. To view results, go
                            to the QA tab on the left panel.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist><figure xml:id="shortcuts">
                    <title>Shortcuts Menu</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/shortcuts-menu.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>All of these actions can be performed by going through the shortcut menu or
                through features within specific tabs and panels.</para></section>
    <section><title>Manager</title>
        <para>The Manager option is only available to the administrator. This will take the administrator to 
            the Knowledge Manager area to manage users, roles, and other items.</para></section>
    <section><title>Username</title>
        <para>The menu under the user's name provides the ability to update global settings, manage
                account, view the user guide, and to log out. Global settings contain filters and
                customizations for how you want to view the content. Manage account takes you to the
                Manager portal of Knowledge, where your profile and login information can be
                modified. </para></section>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Export Content</title>
        <para>There are two types of exports that can be created: a SNOMED CT RF2 file, and a
                Solor.io compatible RF2 file. To export a file, select the modules and date range
                that you want, select the remaining information in the form, then press "Create
                Export".</para>
        <para>When an export is initiated, several steps happen in the background before a file is
                packaged for download. Once it is ready, your browser will prompt you to download
                the file to your computer. If another file is needed, go through the create export
                form again.</para>
        <para>The create an export form contains the following fields:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Select modules - Select the modules that you want to export from. The
                            module that you have edits in is selected by default.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Content range - Select the date range for the content you are
                            exporting. Note that when the files are exported, the content's date
                            stamp will be updated to the selected start date.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Generate SCTID for content with missing IDs - If there are any SNOMED
                            content with missing SCTIDs, the system can generate them for you.
                            Include the namespace identifier provided by SNOMED international when
                            this option is selected.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Export type - select the appropriate file type for the system to
                            create.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        <para><figure xml:id="export-content"><title>Export</title>
            <mediaobject>
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="mnham" timestamp="20190624T121747-0700" comment="Images are temporary, need new ones once features are developed." flag="done"?>
                        <alt>Create an Export modal displays a form with the following information:
                            select modules, content range, generate SCTIDs, namespace, export type,
                            and buttons Create and Cancel.</alt><?oxy_comment_end?>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" scalefit="1" fileref="images/export.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Creating a Release Version</title>
        <para>When a module is ready for a release, the content manager can go through the Create a
                Version workflow to upload content to the repository.</para>
        <para>To create a version release, go to the Export Management interface and on the left
            pane there is a table of Exports and QA, filtered by Path. Select the "Actions…"
            dropdown and "Create an Export". </para>
        <para>A modal appears asking which path the release should be created under, the file
            type for export, and a dialogue for release version. Check the box for release
            version, modify the version number if needed, then select "Create" to confirm and
            execute the task. The version number is automatically set to your current date in
            year-month-date format.</para>
    </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>QA Tests</title>
            <para>QA Tests flag terminologies that have broken concept rules in the requested
                release/export, including domain attribute errors and description duplicates. This check
                can be run individually or as part of an export request. To do so, select the desired
                action from the "Create…" dropdown on the Export Management interface.</para>
            <para>Once the QA test has completed its analysis, select the run you just requested from
                the Exports and QA table on the left to review the results on the right pane. There is a
                relationship tree categorizing the results for you to select from. When you select a
                category, its details will appear in the bottom half of the pane with the options to
                review the concept described and to whitelist the concept.</para></simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>What is whitelisting?</title>
                <para>Whitelisting a terminology in the QA Test Results pane means that the error the
                    system found is acceptable and no action needs to be done. You can choose to
                    whitelist a concept by clicking the "Whitelist" link in the table results.</para>
                <para>
                    <figure xml:id="qa-tests"><title>Quality Assurance Tests</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <alt>The details for "All active stated relationships should be the same moduleID of the source concept" 
                                table displaying 3 concepts, a message associated with each describing QA problem, the concept ID, 
                                and a "Click to WHitelist" button.</alt>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata  align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" 
                                    fileref="images/whitelist-qatests.png" />
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    </para>
            </simplesect>
 
    </section>
    <section><title>Authoring</title>
       <para></para>
       <section><title>New Concept</title>
          <para></para></section>
        <section><title>Run Classifier</title>
           <para></para></section>
    </section>
    <section><title>User Menu</title>
       <para></para></section>
    
</chapter>
