<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Logging In to Knowledge</title>
    <para>When the administrator creates an account for you, you will receive an email, which will
        contain login information (be sure to check your spam folder). If you do not receive an
        email with your account and login information, please contact your Knowledge Administrator. </para>
    <section>
        <title>User Roles</title>
        <para>A user is given at least one role and can also have more than one role in Knowledge.
            There are six roles in Knowledge: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Read : users with this role can view content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Editor: user's can modify content, create new content, search, classify,
                        and export content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Content Manager: the Content Manager has all the capabilities of the
                        Editor role, export content, and can release content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>System Manager: the System Manager can has administrative privileges to
                        manage users and their roles</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Administrator: administrators can create user accounts, modify user
                        accounts, edit content, create content, export content and release
                        content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Automated: This is a role used for system to system communication</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Login</title>
        <para>To login, enter your username (is not case sensitive) and password (is case
            sensitive). If <emphasis>Remember My Username</emphasis> is selected your username will
            be remembered the next time you login. If you forget your username or password select
            the appropriate link on the Knowledge Login screen and an email will be sent to you with
            your username or a link to reset your password. <figure>
                <title>Login</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%"
                            fileref="images/login-page.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>Login Page</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>You have the options to log into Knowledge using a Google account or Microsoft
            365 account as well. The account must be associated with the main login in order to work
            properly (visit your Profile Settings to update the e-mail address). If there is no
            account linked to the Google or Microsoft e-mail that is used, Knowledge will
            automatically create a new account and notify the administrator.</para>
        <para>If you have difficulty logging in, selecting the "Can't log in?" link to reset your
            password. The system will lock the account after 5 failed attempts. At this point,
            contact the application administrator in order to unlock your account.</para>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Knowledge Homepage</title>
            <para>When you login into Knowledge you will see the Knowledge Manager Homepage as shown
                in <xref linkend="author-login"/>. </para>
            <para>From this page you can: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>select the <emphasis>Profile</emphasis> menu option to change your
                            profile information</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>add</emphasis> a user or <emphasis>modify</emphasis> a
                            user's role if you are an Administrator</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>select the <emphasis>Go To Editor</emphasis> button to go to the
                            Knowledge Editor</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>select the <emphasis>Go To API</emphasis> button to view the Rest API
                            documentation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>select the <emphasis>Go To Auth API </emphasis>button to view the
                            Authentication API documentaiton</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>select the <emphasis>Logout</emphasis> button to logout of the
                            application</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="author-login">
                    <title>Knowledge Homepage</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%"
                                fileref="images/knowledge-manager.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                            <phrase>Knowledge Manager Homepage</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Edit Profile</title>
        <para>Select the <emphasis>Profile</emphasis> menu option to change:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Display name</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>User name</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Email address</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Change password</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>To save changes select the <emphasis>Save</emphasis> button. Selecting
            the Cancel button will discard changes made. <figure>
                <title>User Profile</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%"
                            fileref="images/Edit-profile.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>Edit Profile</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
    </section>
</chapter>

<?oxy_options track_changes="on"?>