<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Navigation Bar</title>
<section xml:id="navigation-bar-description"><title>Navigation Bar</title>
    <para>The Editor allows the ability to modify content, create content, view content, create
            versions, and export content. One of the areas to access these functions is in the
                <emphasis>Navigation Bar</emphasis>. </para>
    <para><figure xml:id="navigation-bar">
        <title>Navigation Bar</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <alt>Figure of the Knowledge Editor navigation displaying the Editor logo, and
                menu options for Projects, Export Management, Authoring, Manager, and User
                name Admin</alt>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="40%" contentdepth="40%"
                    fileref="images/nav-editor-layout2.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure></para>
    <para>The Navigation Bar provides the following options:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Projects - If your account has more than one project assigned, switch
                        between them by selecting this menu item.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Shortcuts - Used for multiple actions that can be found in tab-specific
                        areas of the application.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Manager - This option displays for Content Managers, and Administrators
                        and takes the user to the Knowledge Manager Homepage. This option is not
                        visible to Read-Only and Edit-Only users.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>User - The menu under the user's name provides the ability to update
                        global settings, manage account, find application help, and to log
                        out.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    <section><title>Projects</title>
       <para>The <emphasis>Projects Menu</emphasis> displays all of the projects that a user is
                assigned to. The user can switch between projects with this menu option as long as
                there is more than one project assigned, and the Knowledge environment they are
                working in has more than one project defined. The default is to have one project per
                Knowledge instance.</para></section>
    <section>
            <title>Shortcuts</title>
            <para>The <emphasis>Shortcuts</emphasis> sub-menu provides a quick way for the user to
                access certain actions including: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a version – displays the create a version modal. This option is
                            only visible to users with content manager permissions and above.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Export content – displays the export content modal.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New concept – to create a new concept.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New map set – to create a new map set.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New value set – to create a new value set.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run classifier – performs a classification run.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run QA test – performs a quality assurance check. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <figure xml:id="shortcuts">
                    <title>Shortcuts Menu</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt/>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/shortcuts-menu2.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>All of these actions can be performed by going through the shortcut menu or
                through features within specific tabs <emphasis>Task Pane</emphasis>, refer to <xref
                    linkend="editor-functions"/>.</para>
        </section>
            
    <section>
            <title>Manager</title>
            <para>The Manager option is only available to an Administrator or System Manager
                administrator. When selected, the user will be taken to the Knowledge Manager area.
                Here, a user with the appropriate permissions can modify user accounts, create new
                accounts, etc. For more details refer to <xref linkend="user-management-section"/>
            </para>
        </section>
    
    <section><title>Username Menu</title>
        <para>The menu under the user's name provides the ability to modify global settings, manage
                your account, view the user guide, request technical support, and log out of the
                application, <xref linkend="user-menu"/>.<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Global Display Settings – contains filters and customizations for what is
                            displayed throughout the user interface.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Manage Account – enables a user to modify their user profile.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Help – user documentation for Knowledge.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Contact Technical Support – send a technical support request.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Logout – signs you out of Knowledge.</para>
                    </listitem></itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <para><figure xml:id="user-menu">
            <title>User Menu</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <alt></alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="left" 
                        fileref="images/user-menu-options.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
        
        <section><title>Global Display Settings</title>
            <para>When a user is created, the display options are configured with default settings.
                    A user can modify the display settings using the <emphasis>Global Display
                        Settings</emphasis>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>The following options in the Global Display Settings panel are not
                            fully implemented and will not be documented here: Module Flags, Path
                            Flags, Value Set Flag. It is recommended that users <emphasis
                                role="strong">ONLY</emphasis> modify settings that are documented in
                            this section.</para>
                    </footnote> panel. Changes to the display settings in the <emphasis>Global
                        Display Settings</emphasis> panel affects the displayed information in both
                    the <emphasis>Task Pane</emphasis> and the <emphasis>Concept Viewer
                        Pane</emphasis>, refer to <xref linkend="editor-functions"/>. However, the
                        <emphasis>Concept Viewer Pane</emphasis> and the <emphasis>Task
                        Pane</emphasis> can override the <emphasis>Global Display
                        Settings</emphasis> using the <emphasis>Display Options</emphasis> located
                    in the top right hand corner of each pane. The configurable options in
                        <emphasis>Global Display Settings</emphasis> are: <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>General Options – a user can change the order in which the
                                descriptions are displayed in the taxonomy view and the number of
                                concepts displayed in the taxonomy.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Display Options – a user can configure the properties displayed,
                                stated or inferred views of the taxonomy, and modules.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            <section xml:id="general-display-options" ><title>General Options</title>
                <para>In the default configuration, FQN is the preferred description to display in
                        the taxonomy. The taxonomy will display 250 child concepts per concept
                        (additional concepts are available through pagination) and the default
                        language is set to English. See  <xref linkend="general-display-options"/>
                        outlined in red.</para>
                <para><figure>
                    <title>General Display Options</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                                <alt/>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%"
                                        contentdepth="75%"
                                        fileref="images/general-global-display-options.png"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                </figure></para></section>
             
            <section xml:id="display-options-section"><title>Display Options</title>
                <para>Similar to <emphasis>General Options</emphasis>, the<emphasis> Display
                            Options</emphasis> are set to default settings when a user's account is
                        created (see <xref linkend="display-options"/> areas circled in red). These
                        options mostly effect the views in the <emphasis>Concept Viewer</emphasis>
                        and the <emphasis>Taxonomy</emphasis>.</para>
                <para><figure xml:id="display-options">
                    <title>General Display Options</title>
                     <mediaobject>
                         <alt></alt>
                         <imageobject>
                             <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%"
                                 fileref="images/global-display-options.png"/>
                         </imageobject>
                      </mediaobject></figure> </para>
                <example><title>Display Inactive Descriptions</title>
                <para>To show inactive descriptions in the <emphasis>Concept Viewer</emphasis> and
                                <emphasis>Taxonomy</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                                >deselect</emphasis> the <emphasis>Show Only Active
                                Concepts</emphasis> checkbox, and select <emphasis>Apply
                                changes</emphasis>. Inactive descriptions are italicized in the application.<mediaobject>
                                <alt/>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%"
                                        contentdepth="75%"
                                        fileref="images/inactive-concepts-descriptions-displayed.png"
                                    />
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </para></example>
            </section>
        </section>
         <section><title>Manage Account</title>
            <para>A user can modify their account profile by selecting <emphasis>Manage
                        Account</emphasis>. From there, the <emphasis>Edit Profile</emphasis> is
                    presented, see <xref linkend="user-edit-profile"/>. A user can modify their
                    email address, User Name, Display Name, and password. To save changes to your
                    profile, select the <emphasis>Save</emphasis> button. To return to the Knowledge
                    Editor, select your user menu at the top right, select
                    <emphasis>Home</emphasis>, then select <emphasis>Editor</emphasis> button. <note>
                        <para>The <emphasis>System Token</emphasis> is needed only by
                                <emphasis>Software Developers</emphasis>.</para>
                    </note>
                </para>
             <para><figure xml:id="user-edit-profile">
                 <title>Edit Profile</title>
                 <mediaobject>
                     <alt></alt>
                     <imageobject>
                         <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%"
                             fileref="images/user-edit-profile.png"/>
                     </imageobject>
                 </mediaobject>
             </figure></para>
         </section>
         <section><title>Help</title>
             <para>Selecting <emphasis>Help</emphasis> will open the <emphasis>User
                        Documentation</emphasis> for Knowledge. </para></section>
         <section><title>Contact Technical Support</title>
            <para>Selecting <emphasis>Contact Technical Support</emphasis> will bring the user to a
                    web-page where they can send their question and describe their issue to our
                    technical support team, <xref linkend="tech-support"/>. An email response will
                    be sent to the user as soon as possible.</para>
             <para><figure xml:id="tech-support">
                 <title>Contact Technical Support</title>
                 <mediaobject>
                     <alt></alt>
                     <imageobject>
                         <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%"
                             fileref="images/tech-support.png"/>
                     </imageobject>
                 </mediaobject>
             </figure></para>
         </section>
    </section>
    </section>  
        
</chapter>
