<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xml:id="editor-chapter" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Knowledge Editor</title>
    
    <para>The Editor allows users to view, modify, create concepts, modify concepts, classify,
        create versions, export versions, create value sets and modify value sets. This chapter
        provides an overview of the Editor layout and details on authoring content. Users are able
        to see changes made by all users in real-time. </para>
    
    <para>There are two roles that a user can have which changes the functionality available: Author
        and Administrator role. The Administrator role has all the functionality as an Author with
        the addition of the ability to Release content. The functionality to Release content is
        present in the navigation bar and is described below.</para>
    
    <section><title xml:id="editor-functions" >Editor Layout</title>
        <para>The Knowledge Editor is divided into three sections: the <emphasis role="italic"
                >task</emphasis> pane, the <emphasis role="italic">concept viewer</emphasis>, and
            the <emphasis>navigation</emphasis> bar (see <xref linkend="layout"/> below). While each
            of these functions are described in more details in the succeeding sections, a
            description of each area is provided below: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Task Pane</emphasis> – The Task Pane consists of
                        several tabs that contain the following functionality: <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Taxonomy – the Taxonomy tab displays the content in a
                                    hierarchical view. It is always the default view when a user
                                    logs into Knowledge.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Sets – displays value sets and maps; the user can create, edit
                                    and view them here.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Search – the search function enables the user to search for
                                    specific descriptions, ids and other values.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Classifier – the user can run the classifier and view results
                                    of classification.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>QA – data checks can be initiated and results can be
                                    viewed.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Export and Versions – users with the appropriate permissions
                                    can export content and/or create a version.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Briefcase – is similar to a bookmarks list. Throughout the
                                    editor, there are tables that will allow users to add concepts
                                    to the Briefcase. Users can then view or modify them
                                    here.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Concept Viewer</emphasis> – The Concept Viewer
                        displays details of the concept or item selected in the task pane.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Navigation</emphasis> – The Navigation bar enables
                        fast access to functions e.g. New Concept, Run Classifier, Return to
                        Knowledge Manager page, Modify global display options</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <figure xml:id="layout">
                <title>Knowledge Editor Layout</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                            fileref="images/editor-layout.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Taxonomy View</title>
           <para>In the Taxonomy view, users can navigate through the concept hierarchy under the
            taxonomy tree. The Taxonomy also displays the concepts with their parents and their
            children. Users can traverse the tree by selecting the caret symbol on the left of the
            tree to display the selected concept's children.</para>
            <para>The tree-like structure of the Taxonomy View allows users to navigate content from
            a "top-down" view – users can navigate up or down in the lineage of the content by
            selecting the <emphasis>caret</emphasis> symbol on the left. The user can also select to
            display the <emphasis role="italic">inferred</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"
                >stated</emphasis> view of the content (Knowledge displays the <emphasis
                role="italic">inferred</emphasis> view by default). The inferred view shows the
            parent-child lineage that is derived by inferences through a set of logical rules and
            related concepts; the <emphasis role="italic">stated</emphasis> view shows the
            parent-child lineage that is set by the author when creating the concept. </para>
            <para><figure xml:id="taxonomy-view">
                <title>Taxonomy</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                            fileref="images/taxonomy-view.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
           
        <simplesect><title>Status</title>
                  <para>In addition, the user can display <emphasis role="italic">active</emphasis>
                only concepts or both <emphasis role="italic">active</emphasis> and <emphasis
                    role="italic">inactive</emphasis> concepts. Inactive concepts will display in
                    <emphasis>italics</emphasis>. The default is set to display
                    only<emphasis>active</emphasis> concepts. To see both types, change the settings
                under "Display Options".</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect><title>Display Type</title>
            <para>The user has an additional option to display the <emphasis role="italic">Fully
                    Qualified Name</emphasis> (FQN) or the <emphasis role="italic">Normal Name
                </emphasis>(NAM) of the concept.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect><title>Refresh the Taxonomy</title>
            <para>The user is also able to force a refresh of the taxonomy by selecting the
                    <emphasis>Refresh</emphasis> button. This is useful when multiple concepts are
                expanded and the user would like to collapse them all.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect><title>Concept Type – Defined versus Primitive</title>
            <para>In Knowledge, concepts are defined as either a <emphasis>defined</emphasis> or
                    <emphasis>primitive</emphasis>. <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata format="SVG" fileref="images/green-circle.svg"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <textobject>
                                    <phrase>Defined concept</phrase>
                                </textobject>
                            </inlinemediaobject>Defined – A concept that is
                                <emphasis>defined</emphasis> is represented by a green circle. A
                            concept is considered defined by unique relationships between its
                            relatives (e.g. siblings and parents)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <inlinemediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata format="SVG" fileref="images/hexagon.svg"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </inlinemediaobject> Primitive – A concept that is
                                <emphasis>primitive</emphasis> is represented by an orange hexagon
                            and signifies that its attributes and parents composing the concept are
                            non-definitive characteristics. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para></simplesect>
        <simplesect><title>Linking the Taxonomy View with Search Results</title>
            <para>In the Knowledge Editor, the user can connect/link the concept selected in the
                Taxonomy to the Concept Viewer Panel, by default the connection or linkage is set.
                This means when users select a concept in the taxonomy, the Concept Viewer will
                display the details of that concept. The same is true if a user selects a result
                from a search. Linkage can be modified  by toggling the linkage icon in the upper
                left-hand corner of the concept details panel. <figure xml:id="search-linked">
                    <title>Linked</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="75%"
                                fileref="images/linkage-icon.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="search-unlinked">
                    <title>Unlinked </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="70%"
                                fileref="images/unlinked-icon.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                    <para>If a concept becomes unlinked and users click on a different term to
                        review, a new Concept View Panel will open. A maximum of two concept viewers
                        can be opened. If two Concept Viewer Panels are already open and both
                        concept viewers are linked, the system will choose to display the new
                        concept selected on one of the existing panels. If both concept viewers are
                        unlinked the concept viewers will not display the concept information of the
                        selected concept.</para>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </simplesect></section>
         
        <section><title>Sets</title>
              <para> The <emphasis>Sets</emphasis> tab allows a user to create, and modify value
            sets, and map sets. Value sets are a collection of concepts that is used for a specific
            purpose (e.g. Wound Color Value Set would contain the concepts needed to describe the
            color of a wound by a clinician). A map set is a mapping between one terminology and
            another (e.g. SNOMED CT to LOINC mapping). </para> 
                <section><title>Creating a Value Set</title>
                <para>A value set is also known as a simple assemblage or refset and contains a
                collection of concepts used for a particular purpose determined by its author. For
                example: The SNOMED CT Value Set – Lateralizable body structure reference set is a
                user defined simple assemblage (or value set) created for values used to record the
                measurement site of a patients heart rate, where the values could be finger, ear
                lobe, and wrist. There are two ways to create a new value set: by selecting "Create
                Refset" under the Shortcuts navigation menu, or by selecting the "New" button under
                the Sets tab in the Authoring viewing pane. On the Create New Value Set page, fill
                out the information needed, check the box for "This concept is a Value Set," and
                select "Create". After the refset is created, you will see the ability to add
                concept members on the left pane. </para>
                    <simplesect>
                <title>Adding Members to a Value Set</title>
                <para> To add members to a value set, select the "Edit" link when viewing the value
                    set's details. This will take you into an edit view where concepts can be added,
                    removed, or imported. </para>
                <para>Select "Add Member" to find concepts to add, select the remove icon to remove
                    them, and select the add to briefcase icon to add any of them to your briefcase. </para>
                <para>When you are ready to save the members list, select "Compare Sync" to review
                    your changes. </para>
                <para>If there are any conflicts, the table will display the information to help you
                    decide how to sync the new data into the refset. </para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Removing Value Set Members</title>
           
            
                <para>To remove members from a refset, select the "Edit Members" button when viewing
                    the refset details. This will take you to Edit Mode, where you can remove
                    members from the table by selecting the "X" icon. The system will display your
                    selection in the table "Value Set membership Changes" for review. Press Save to
                    confirm your updates.</para>
            </simplesect> </section>
                
                <section><title>Creating a Map Set</title>
                    <para> A map set associates codes that have the same or similar meaning in one
                system with another. For example, SNOMED CT's code for "Vital signs monitoring" can
                be mapped to LOINC's "Vital signs with method details panel" and "Vital signs with
                smoking status and pain scale [VSP]".</para>
            <para>To create a map set, go to the Sets tab in the left panel, make sure that "View
                Group" is set to "Map Set" and select New to open the form.</para>
                    <para><figure xml:id="mapsets-table">
                        <title>Map Sets Table</title><mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/mapset-table.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject></figure></para>
                    <para>There are 3 tabs in the Concept Viewer panel for the user to fill out:
                        Definition, Item Fields, and Business Rules.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Definition - Enter the name, purpose, and any additional
                                information that users may need for the new map set. You can add
                                more fields such as source code version by selecting the "Add More
                                Fields" button on the left.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Item Fields - These are column headers to display when you view
                                the map sets. Source description, target description, and
                                equivalence type are selected by default, but you may add more
                                fields or rearrange the order the columns display by selecting the
                                "Add More Fields to Map Set Items" button.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Business Rules - This is a free text comment box for additional
                                information that users may find useful, such as the use case and
                                guidance on when to use the map set.</para>
                                                   </listitem>
                        
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>After entering all relevant information, press the save button at the top
                of the panel. The new map set sould appear in the left panel's Map Sets table. If
                you do not see it there, press the Refresh button.</para>
            </section>
            </section>
            <section><title>Search</title>
                <para>Search can be performed in the Authoring interface through keywords and Lucene
            query syntax. Knowledge has implemented Lucene, an open-source full-text search library,
            as one of its search engines. To begin searching, select the “Search” tab on the left
            panel, then fill in the fields as needed. Both Simple Search and Advanced Search use
            Lucene. For more details on the Lucene search syntax refer to the <link
                xlink:href="http://www.lucenetutorial.com"> Lucene tutorial</link>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Simple Search – searches for descriptions that matches the search
                        phrase</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Advanced Search – refines the search parameters further searching for
                        terminology id, description types (fully qualified name, name, and
                        definition)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
            <section>
            <title>Simple Search</title>
            <para>Terminologies can be searched by keywords under the Search tab in the task pane.
                Type in keywords in the “Search Text” field, then select the “Search” button to
                start the search, <xref linkend="search-tab"/>. </para>
            <para>Simple search allows
                <?oxy_delete author="linds" timestamp="20200327T110829-0400" content="you"?><?oxy_insert_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T110829-0400"?>users<?oxy_insert_end?>
                to search for the
                keyword<?oxy_insert_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T110839-0400"?>s
                <?oxy_insert_end?><?oxy_delete author="linds" timestamp="20200327T110839-0400" content=" that you"?>
                typed in the search box. Selecting the search button will return all descriptions
                that match. Keywords used in simple search are single terms or phrases. A Single
                Term is a single word such as <emphasis>"test"</emphasis> or
                    <emphasis>"hello"</emphasis>. A Phrase is a group of words surrounded by double
                quotes such as <emphasis>"hello dolly"</emphasis>. If a group of words without
                double quotes are used such as <emphasis>hello</emphasis>
                <emphasis>goodbye</emphasis>, then the results will display results that contain
                either “hello” or “goodbye”. Multiple terms can be combined with Boolean operators
                to form a more complex query. Review Lucene query <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.lucenetutorial.com/lucene-query-syntax.html">keyword
                    matching</link>for more advanced search syntax. </para>
                <para>
                    <figure xml:id="search-tab"><title>Simple Search</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <alt>Simple Search</alt>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata  align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="50%" 
                                    fileref="images/simple-search.png" />
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para></section>
                
    
            <section>
            <title>Advanced Search</title>
            <para>Search results can be filtered by using the Advanced Search section, see <xref
                    linkend="advanced-search-tab"/>. There are 4 options in the Advanced Search
                section:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T115004-0400" comment="Maybe break these out into sub-bullets for each of the 3 options. That would make it easier to see the 3 different options for Search In, if nothing else "?>
                    <para>Search In –
                        <?oxy_delete author="linds" timestamp="20200327T110932-0400" content="t"?><?oxy_insert_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T110929-0400"?>T<?oxy_insert_end?>his
                        option narrows the search for <emphasis>Search Text</emphasis> to concept
                            <emphasis>Descriptions</emphasis>, <emphasis>Semantics</emphasis>, or
                            <emphasis>Identifiers</emphasis>. When <emphasis>Descriptions</emphasis>
                        is selected the search will search-in the <emphasis>Descriptions</emphasis>
                        of a <emphasis>concept</emphasis>. A search in
                            <emphasis>Semantics</emphasis> searches the properties of a concept, and
                        a search in <emphasis>Identifiers</emphasis> searches the alphanumeric IDs
                        of a concept such as an SCTID or LOINC code.</para><?oxy_comment_end?>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Page size –
                        <?oxy_delete author="linds" timestamp="20200327T110959-0400" content="s"?><?oxy_insert_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T110959-0400"?>S<?oxy_insert_end?>elect
                        the number of results to display at a time.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Description Type –
                        <?oxy_delete author="linds" timestamp="20200327T111002-0400" content="t"?><?oxy_insert_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T111002-0400"?>T<?oxy_insert_end?>he
                        sytem restricts the search to a particular description type, such as
                            <emphasis>Fully Qualified Name</emphasis> (FQN), a <emphasis>Regular
                            Name</emphasis>, a <emphasis>Definition</emphasis> if selected. When
                            <emphasis>All Types</emphasis> is selected the search will be performed
                        on <emphasis>FQN</emphasis>,<emphasis>Regular Name</emphasis> and
                            <emphasis>Definition</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T115056-0400" comment="I dont see this option in the drop-down for Description Type "?>
                    <para>CSV Export –
                        <?oxy_delete author="linds" timestamp="20200327T111013-0400" content="w"?><?oxy_insert_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T111013-0400"?>W<?oxy_insert_end?>hen
                        selected<?oxy_insert_start author="linds" timestamp="20200327T111017-0400"?>,<?oxy_insert_end?>
                        the search results table will export the results table in CSV
                        format.<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Select the search button in order to update the results when advanced options are
                changed.</para>
            <example>
                <title>Advanced Search Example</title>
                <para>In this example, the search results are descriptions that contain
                        <emphasis>hypertension</emphasis>
                    <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis>
                    <emphasis>failure</emphasis>. The results table will contain a list of matching
                    concept, description, the terminology identifier, and status, <xref
                        linkend="advanced-search-results"/>.</para>
            </example>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="advanced-search-results">
                    <title>Advanced Search for 'Hypertension + failure'</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <alt>Advanced search options</alt>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="50%"
                                fileref="images/advanced-search.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </section>
                <!-- TBD feature 
             <simplesect><title>Saved Searches</title>
                  <para>Search criteria can be saved for later user under the Search tab. To do so,
                      enter the search criteria and select the "Search" button. A results section
                      should appear below the search fields along with options to save the search and
                      to export the results to a CSV file. Select the "Save Search" link in order to
                      name and save the search.</para>
                  <para>Saved searches are retrieved under the "saved searches" section of the search
                      tab. This section is only visible if there are previously saved searches. Select
                      the desired search from a dropdown list and press the "Search" button to pull
                      results.</para></simplesect>-->
            <section><title>Search Results</title>
                <para>The search results are displayed in a table below the search criteria. The
                default fields displayed in the search results table
                are<?oxy_delete author="linds" timestamp="20200327T111047-0400" content=":"?>
                matching concept, matching description, terminology identifier, status, and module,
                see <xref linkend="advanced-search-results"/>.</para>
            
            </section>
        </section>
        <section><title>Classifier</title>
            <para>The Knowledge Editor integrates a high performance Classifier called SnoRocket
                <link xlink:href="https://aehrc.com/snorocket/"
            >https://aehrc.com/snorocket/</link>which supports OWL EL++ and Concrete Domains. The
            classifier evaluates the stated relationships based on <emphasis role="italic"
                >Description Logics </emphasis>upon which the terminology is defined and generates
            the inferred relationships for each concept. The Knowledge Editor displays <emphasis
                role="italic">stated and inferred </emphasis>views of the concept in the <emphasis
                role="italic">concept viewer pane </emphasis>and the Taxonomy displays <emphasis
                role="italic">stated and inferred </emphasis>is-a relationships based on the
            Taxonomy display options.</para>
                <section>
                    <title>Run the Classifier</title>
                    <para>There are two areas in the Knowledge Editor interface to initiate
                classification: the navigation menu <emphasis>Short Cuts</emphasis> and the
                    <emphasis>Classifier</emphasis> tab, <xref linkend="classifier-tab" />. </para>
                    <para>The first classification will evaluate all concepts in the environment,
                subsequent classifications will evaluate only modified concepts. The first
                classification duration will be less than 15 minutes, and subsequent classifications
                will be less than 10 minutes. A classification has three possible status values:
                    <emphasis>Running</emphasis>, <emphasis>Done</emphasis>, and
                    <emphasis>Failed</emphasis>.</para>
                    <para>To start classification select the <emphasis>Run Classifier</emphasis>
                button. An entry will be added to the <emphasis>Classifier Run List</emphasis>. The
                user can select the <emphasis>Refresh Run List</emphasis> to force an update of the
                run list table.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="classifier-tab"><title>Classifier Details</title><mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/classifier-tab.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                        <para/></figure>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>View Classifier Results</title>
                    <para>When the classifier has completed, the status will change from
                        <emphasis>Running</emphasis> to <emphasis>Done</emphasis>. A user may view
                        classification results by selecting an entry in the <emphasis>Classifier Run
                        List</emphasis>. The results of classification are displayed on the right in
                        <emphasis>Classifier Details</emphasis>, 
                        <xref linkend="classifier-details"/>.</para>
                    <para>The classifier details will provide a summary and details of: 
                   <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Affected concepts - this is a list of concepts are
                            classification.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Equivalent sets – shows any defined concepts that have identical
                            relationships.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Orphaned concepts – are concepts that are not defined correctly and
                            must be corrected.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Cycles – the classifier finds cycles that would be difficult to find
                            just by looking at the definition of a concept e.g. A ->B ->C
                            ->A.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist></para>
                  <para> The concepts under each of these categories are displayed by default. To
                hide the details of a category, select the caret symbol next to table name, it
                toggles between expanding and collapsing the table view. You also have the option of
                adding concepts to your briefcase to correct any issues.</para>
                    <para>
                        <figure xml:id="classifier-details"><title>Classifier Details</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject><imagedata
                                align="left" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                                fileref="images/classifier-details.png" /></imageobject>
                            </mediaobject></figure>
                    </para>
                </section>
       
       <section><title>Briefcase</title>
           <para>The briefcase temporarily holds concepts that can be reviewed and/or edited later. 
               For example, the briefcase can be used: </para>
           <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                   <para>
                       To hold equivalent (duplicates) concepts that are flagged as a result of
                       classification. To edit and view the details of the equivalent concept you can add
                       the concept to the briefcase.</para></listitem>
               <listitem>
                   <para>To add a concept from a Value Set to the briefcase</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
           
           
           <para>The briefcase is viewable from the Task Pane of the Knowledge Editor, see screen
                shot below.
               <figure xml:id="briefcase"><title>Briefcase</title>
                   <mediaobject>
                       <alt>The briefcase options
                           "Select All Items, Remove Selected Items, and Refresh List".</alt>
                       <imageobject>
                           <imagedata  align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%" 
                               fileref="images/briefcase-panel.png" />
                       </imageobject>
                   </mediaobject>
               </figure></para>
       </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding a concept to the Briefcase from Taxonomy List</title>
            <para>Most of the concepts in the taxonomy list can be added to the briefcase by
                right-clicking to view the context menu, and selecting "Add to Briefcase". Some of
                the concepts displayed in tables and the Concept Viewer panel can also be added by
                this method.</para>
            <para><figure xml:id="context-menu"><title>Context Menu</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="75%" contentdepth="75%"
                                fileref="images/context-menu.jpg"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                 </figure></para>
        </section>
           <section><title>Adding a concept to the Briefcase from Classifier Results</title>
               <para>To add a terminology to the briefase from some lists such as classifier page,
                   select the briefcase icon (not all tables have this feature). In the example
                   below, there is an "Add to Briefcase" icon on the 5th column of the members
                   table and an option to "Add all to Briefcase" above the table.</para>
               
           </section>
           
           <section><title>Adding a concept to the Briefcase from a Value Set</title>
               <para>
                   <figure xml:id="add-briefcase"><title>Add to Briefcase</title>
                       <mediaobject>
                           <alt>Members tab under the concept "Lateralizable body structure reference
                               set" with a table that contains the option to add to briefcase in the
                               5th column</alt>
                           <imageobject>
                               <imagedata  align="left" scalefit="1" width="75" contentdepth="75%" 
                                   fileref="images/add-to-briefcase.png" />
                           </imageobject>
                       </mediaobject>
                   </figure></para>
           </section>
              <section><title>Removing concepts from the briefcase</title>
                  <para>There are two options to remove concepts from the Briefcase:
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Remove all concepts in the list by selecting the <emphasis>Select All Items</emphasis>button
                        and then selecting the <emphasis>Remove Selected Items></emphasis></para></listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To remove one or more concepts but <emphasis>not all</emphasis> concepts from the briefbase
                            select the box to the right of the concept to be removed and select the
                            <emphasis>Remove Selected Items</emphasis> button.</para></listitem>
                </orderedlist></para></section>
                <simplesect><title>Refreshing the Briefcase List</title>
                    <para>If you do not see the concept(s) just added, try refreshing the list by
                   selecting <emphasis>Refresh List</emphasis>.</para></simplesect>
             </section>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
        href="knowledge-concept-viewer.xml" xpointer="concept-viewer"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="knowledge-navigation-bar.xml"
        xpointer="navigation-bar-description"/>
    
    <section><title>Context Menu</title>
        <para>A context menu appears when users right-click on the concept name either on the
            taxonomy tree <xref linkend="taxonomy-context-menu"/> or in the title of concept details
            panel <xref linkend="concept-details-context-menu"/>. Some tables contain a context menu
            througout the application.</para>
        <para>The context menu contains the following options:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open concept – opens the concept details information</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open concept in new concept viewer – opens the concept details information
                        in a third panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add to briefcase – add the concept to  briefcase, which can be viewed  in
                        the briefcase tab.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Copy concept, UUID, SCTID, description and SCTID – copies the information described.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Edit concept – opens the concept in edit mode.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Edit concept in new viewer – opens the concept in edit mode, in a third concept
                        details panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clone concept – duplicates the concept information as a new concept.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clone concept in new viewer – duplicates the concept information as a new
                        concept and opens a new concept details panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create child concept – creates a new child concept with the same information as the selected
                        concept and uses the selected concept as the parent.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create child concept in new viewer – creates a new child concept with the same information as the selected
                        concept, uses the selected concept as the parent and opens a third concept viewer panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inactivate concept – sets the selected concept's state to inactive. If the
                        concept disappears from the taxonomy, display options are set to not display
                        inactive concepts.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Activate concept – sets the selected concept's state to active. This option is only visible in the context menu
                        if the selected concept is inactive.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="taxonomy-context-menu">
                    <title>Taxonomy Context Menu Options</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%" 
                                fileref="images/taxonomy-context-menu.png" />
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                            <phrase>Right click options</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            <figure xml:id="concept-details-context-menu">
                <title>Concept Details Context Menu Options</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" scalefit="1" width="50%" contentdepth="50%" 
                            fileref="images/cursor-over-concept-details.png" />
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>Right click options</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
    </section>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="knowledge-export.xml"
        xpointer="export"/>
</chapter> 
