<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>User Management</title>
     <para>Knowledge's application administrator can create new user accounts, modify a users role, disable an
         account.
        permissions, and users. Most of these workflows are viewable in a separate section of the
        application called Knowledge Manager. Editors and content managers have permissions to the
        section called Knowledge Editor.</para>
    
        <section>
            <title>Adding New Users</title>
            <para>To add a user, select the "Accounts and Roles" option in the main navigation. On
                this page, there should be a table that lists all users in the application along
                with filter options to aide in user search. Select the "New Account" button on this
                page.</para>
            <para>On the Create a New Account page, fill in the appropriate information. Select the
                permissions that the user will have for ALL projects assigned, this is described as
                Global in the application. Project-specific permissions can be assigned on the Edit
                Account Profile page after the account is created.</para>
            <para>In order for the new user to access the project contents, the account must be
                assigned the appropriate projects and roles, so after account creation, select the
                user from the View Accounts and Roles page. You can assign the requested projects to
                the user under the "Assign to Project" dropdown. Select "Add" to confirm the
                assignment.</para>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="" width="750px"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> To modify roles and permissions per project, select "Edit
                Roles" for the specific project on the Edit Account Profile page. There, you can
                assign additional permissions to the user if different projects require different
                access levels.</para></section>
         <section>
            <title>Modifying User Permissions</title>
             <para></para> </section>
         <section>
            <title>Assigning Projects to Users</title>
             <para></para></section>   
  
</chapter>

