<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <title>Content</title>
    </info>
    <para>The ISAAC infrastructure expects resources—such as terminology sources—to be avaible from
        a Maven-compliant artifact repository. </para>
    <para>A repository manager is a dedicated server application designed to manage repositories of
        binary components. The usage of a repository manager is considered an essential best
        practice for any significant usage of Maven.</para>
    <section xml:id="section_6b81d168-3737-4876-8333-c7b1df7a2731">
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>A repository manager serves these essential purposes:</para>
        <itemizedlist xml:id="itemizedlist_497c272b-0065-412a-b3d8-bc830f40d18d">
            <listitem>
                <para>act as dedicated proxy server for public Maven repositories</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>provide repositories as a deployment destination for your Maven project
                    outputs</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_2a2be55f-6f3d-4220-b18a-e5beb35da480">
        <title>Benefits and Features</title>
        <para>Using a repository manager provides the following benefits and features:</para>
        <itemizedlist xml:id="itemizedlist_da55f46a-1b54-499f-af88-3ca52c0d827c">
            <listitem>
                <para>significantly reduced number of downloads off remote repositories, saving time
                    and bandwidth resulting in increased build performance</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>improved build stability due to reduced reliance on external
                    repositories</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>increased performance for interaction with remote SNAPSHOT repositories</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>potential for control of consumed and provided artifacts</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>creates a central storage and access to artifacts and meta data about them
                    exposing build outputs to consumer such as other projects and developers, but
                    also QA or operations teams or even customers</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>provides an effective platform for exchanging binary artifacts within your
                    organization and beyond without the need for building artifact from
                    source</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Publishing RF2 sources as Maven Artifacts</title>
        <para>An example project that converts SNOMED RF2 zip distribution files into maven
            artifacts, and can publish those artifacts in a users local repository, or on an
            artifact repository is available on git hub. The project is named the Solor source
            artifact transformer, and is available at the following URL: </para>
        <para><link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/informatics-architecture/solor-source-artifact-transformer"
            /></para>
        <para>This project contains example conversions for: </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="itemizedlist_6510a31c-60e3-4c99-bf31-61448f59ea36">
                <listitem>
                    <para>The International Edition of SNOMED Clinical Terms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Australian Extension to SNOMED Clinical Terms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Spanish Extension to SNOMED Clinical Terms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The LOINC Extension to SNOMED Clinical Terms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The United Kingdom Clinical Extension to SNOMED Clinical Terms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The United Kingdom Drug Extension to SNOMED Clinical Terms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The United States Extension to SNOMED Clinical Terms</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>