<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Logical Nesting</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <figure>
            <title>Example of Compositional Grammar with a nested laterality</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_logicalNesting_00.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>A Nested Expression is an expression that is defined within another expression, the
            enclosing expression. Due to simple recursive <link
                xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scope_(programming)">scope</link><footnote><para>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scope_(programming)</para></footnote> rules, a
            Nested Expression is itself invisible outside of its immediately enclosing expression.
            The nesting is theoretically possible to any ideas of depth, although only a few levels
            are normally used in practice. Nested Expressions have been a part of SNOMED CT
            post-coordinated expressions for years and are able to be represented as a part of the
            compositional grammar. </para>
        <para>However, SNOMED International is not currently permitting the use of nesting outside
            of post-coordinated expressions. The rationale as stated in the <link
                xlink:href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1tqNEA6S4fEF4fgj15OPabYA2E0VTz8epxvRRwczKizQ/edit#heading=h.yijdvy700v01"
                >SNOMED CT Logic Profile Enhancements document</link><footnote><para>https://docs.google.com/document/d/1tqNEA6S4fEF4fgj15OPabYA2E0VTz8epxvRRwczKizQ/edit#heading=h.yijdvy700v01</para></footnote> is due to two main reasons
            currently limiting the use of nested expressions:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Lack of support in RF2</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Potential for arbitrary levels of nesting</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>The ability to have Nested Expressions applied to pre-coordinated concepts
            in SNOMED CT would be beneficial to fully define concepts where the values
            for attributes are currently not represented as pre-coordinated concepts,
            for example lateralized body structures. Since creating pre-coordinated
            concepts to cover every aspect of medicine would lead to combinatorial
            explosion, Nested Expressions allow for the creation of a wide variety of
            concepts to supplement content that is currently missing from the
            international release. However, since nested expressions can be recursive,
            there need to be some limitations on the amount of expressivity allowed to
            keep content creation using nested expressions understandable and
            reproducible and to keep quality checks simple. Although Nested Expressions
            are easily represented in the compositional grammar syntax and OWL, they
            would require major changes to the SNOMED CT RF2 structure.</para>
        <para>The purpose of this study is to identify a sample of expressions that are not nested
            and do not require nesting and a sample of expressions that should be nested and where a
            model for nesting is proposed. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Pharmaceutical / Biological Concepts</title>
        <para>During our work on partonomy, the need to use Nested Expressions to
            fully define products in two instances was identified. The first instance involved concepts that did
            not have a precoordinated concept available to fully define drugs that were representing
            packages that contain multiple drugs. The second set of concepts represented a powder
            that is packaged separately from the solution used to mix prior to use. The model below
            represents the pharmacy model tested, and it has not been updated to the
            new drug model SNOMED International released in January 2018.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Example of starter pack that contains multiple tablets. Diagram contains the current SCT definition (top) and the updated definition (bottom) using partonomy with a nested expression.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_logicalNesting_01.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <title>Example of an injection powder that is packaged separate from the solvent. Diagram contains the current SCT definition (top) and the updated definition (bottom) using partonomy with a nested expression.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_logicalNesting_02.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Findings and Procedures Involving Laterality</title>
        <para>Our work on identifying Findings and Procedures that incorrectly use laterality has
            identified a set of concepts that are not currently modeled correctly due to a
            lateralized body structure not existing as a precoordinated concept. Rather than add
            these concepts to an extension or submit them for addition, they could easily use nested
            expressions to represent the missing body structure concepts that have a laterality
            attribute assigned to them.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Current definition of Chronic deep venous thrombosis of femoral veins of both lower extremities (disorder) where laterality is not correctly defined.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_logicalNesting_03.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <title>Updated definition of Chronic deep venous thrombosis of femoral veins of both lower extremities (disorder) where laterality is represented as a nested expression.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_logicalNesting_04.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Recommendations</title>
        <para>Support for Nested Expressions in the international and national releases would
            require major changes to the RF2 specification and are not a part of the recommended
            Logic Profile Enhancements. In addition, there must be constraints on the ability to
            model Nested Expressions to ensure errors are not introduced due to the ability to
            infinitely Nest Expressions. While Nested Expressions are not supported at the
            international and national level due to distribution issues, there is a definite benefit
            for including them in local extensions. </para>
        <para>Using Nested Expressions to represent missing lateralized anatomy concepts will cut
            down the need to request new body structure concepts or temporarily creating new
            concepts in local extensions that will have to be reconciled with each
            international/national release. Representation of package concepts using Nested
            Expressions was the chosen method rather than creating new concepts in an extension.
            However, these concepts would be much better suited as a pre-coordinated concept in the
            international or national release as they have the potential to be used for data
            recording or retrieval. Any further uses of nesting outside of laterality would need to
            be evaluated and constrained to ensure that modeling can be easily checked for
            completeness and consistency. Outside of the two use cases tested for Nested
            Expressions, one could make modifications to findings and procedures that are used as
            values for defining relationships. However, in most cases these concepts would probably
            be better suited as pre-coordinated concepts.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Resulting Artifacts</title>
        <para>Two Reference Sets were created:(1) those
            reviewed concepts where nesting could be used to represent both the product and
            laterality nesting and (2) those reviewed concepts that would not need nesting.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Additional Issues</title>
        <para>When modeling the Pharmaceutical/Biological Product hierarchy, a model developed by
            Solor developers was used to test concrete domains. SNOMED International has since
            started utilizing the new drug model in the January 2018 international release, which
            will make the Solor developer model obsolete once the SNOMED model is implemented. The
            new SNOMED CT drug model will allow for the addition of more fully defined content
            including the addition of more values to represent concepts that include units of
            presentation like cartridges. With the new SNOMED model, removal of definitions added
            during previous work has begun, where some were partially modeled via an automated
            update. For example:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>318166002 |Bendrofluazide+potassium 2.5mg/7.7Mmol m/r tablet
                        (product)|</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>318171009 |Bendrofluazide+potassium 2.5mg/8.4Mmol m/r tablet
                        (product)|</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>134499006 |Budesonide + formoterol fumarate 100/6mcg breath-actuated dry
                        powder inhaler (product)|</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>134498003 |Budesonide+eformoterol fumarate 200/6mcg breath-actuated dry
                        powder inhaler (product)|</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>318165003 |Bumetanide+potassium 500mcg/7.7Mmol m/r tablet
                        (product)|</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>447089002 |Amlodipine 5mg + hydrochlorothiazide 25mg + olmesartan
                        medoxomil 40mg tablet (product)|</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>In the Pharmaceutical/Biological Product hierarchy, allergy kits that are
            represented as separate concepts were identified and should potentially be considered duplicates:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>358640003 Silver birch allergy initial kit (product)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>358641004 Silver birch allergy maintenance kit (product)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>346734001 Timothy grass allergy initial kit (product)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>346754000 Timothy grass allergy maintenance kit (product)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>346735000 Treemix allergy initial kit (product)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>346755004 Treemix allergy maintenance kit (product)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
