<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Meronomy / Partonomy</title>
    <para>All examples in this section are as of the April 2017 SNOMED CT US Edition Release. Many
        of the examples below have since been corrected in subsequent releases.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Meronomy /
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190313T130843-0600" comment="Above it&apos;s referred to as Meronomy/Partonomy.  I think all references to it should be consistent.  Which is correct?" flag="done"?>Partonomy<?oxy_comment_end?>
            is a type of hierarchy that deals with part-whole relationships. <emphasis role="italic"
                >Part-of</emphasis> Relationships are:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Transitive – a part of a part is also a part of the whole, example
                        below:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Atrioventricular junction: Part of = Entire Heart</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Entire Heart: Part of = Entire heart and pericardium</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Entire heart and pericardium: Part of = Entire middle mediastinum,
                                Part of = Entire cardiovascular system </para>
                            <para>Therefore, Atrioventricular junction is a part of the Entire heart
                                and pericardium, Entire middle mediastinum, and the entire
                                cardiovascular system.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Reflexive – a part is a part of itself</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Antisymmetric – nothing is a part of its parts</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The Entire Heart is not a part of the Atrioventricular
                                junction</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>Unless properly identified, it is difficult for a reasoner to determine
            if it is part or whole. </para>
        <para>This study evaluated the representation of <emphasis role="italic"
                >Part-of</emphasis> relationships in the Body Structure, Pharmaceutical/Biologic
            Product, and Laboratory Procedure (LOINC) hierarchies, and developing and testing a
            proposed model where appropriate.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Tooling</title>
        <para>termMed’s termSpace authoring tool was used to evaluate the proposed model for the
            three hierarchies. termSpace currently supports Object Properties with reflexive and
            transitive properties. For the Pharmaceutical/Biological Product hierarchy, Nested
            Expressions were used to represent the powders used for injection solutions, as they do
            not currently exist as pre-coordinated concepts. termSpace can represent LOINC concepts
            to support the partonomy modeling of laboratory concepts; however, these concepts will
            need to be transformed into a SNOMED RF2 format in order to load them into termSpace.
            However, the LOINC model was unable to be tested due to the complexities of adding LOINC
            to termSpace. Collaboration will continue with termMed to represent LOINC in termSpace
            to potentially test the model in future iterations.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Body Structure Concepts</title>
        <para>There are currently 42,596 <emphasis role="italic">Part-of</emphasis> Relationships
            assigned to Body Structure concepts remaining from the 2003 decision to transform them
            to non-defining. </para>
        <para>SNOMED International is currently in discussions with the Foundational Model of
            Anatomy (FMA) to collaborate on an anatomy model in SNOMED CT. SNOMED International is
            currently modeling <emphasis role="italic">Part-of</emphasis> relationships in a Protégé
            version of the Body Structure hierarchy; however, they are only exporting the resulting
                <emphasis role="italic">IS-A</emphasis> relationships. As a part of the <emphasis
                role="italic">IS-A</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Part-of</emphasis>
            Modeling Subproject at SNOMED International, they plan to perform Quality Assurance (QA)
            to the <emphasis role="italic">Part-of</emphasis> relationships and assign
            sub-attributes of <emphasis role="italic">Part-of</emphasis>:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Regional part of</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Constitutional part of</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Systemic part of</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>SNOMED International is currently in the process of documenting the updated Anatomy
            Model at:
            https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/IAP/Revision+of+IS-A+relationships+for+anatomy </para>
        <para>FMA also includes a role hierarchy for <emphasis role="italic">Part-of</emphasis>
            relationships.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>FMA Part-of Role Hierarchy</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_meronmoyPartonomy_00.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <section>
            <title>Proposed Body Structure Model</title>
            <para>With the forthcoming update to the SNOMED CT Anatomy concept model, exploration of
                this area is not recommended for concept model work, but instead focus on the
                Pharmaceutical/Substance and Laboratory hierarchies, where no current implementation
                of partonomy is planned.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Pharmaceutical / Substance Concepts</title>
        <para>At this time, SNOMED project groups have not held a discussion around partonomy for
            Pharmaceutical/Substances. The most promising area where partonomy would apply within
            the Pharmaceutical Product hierarchy are products that are made up of two or more
            products, for example a package that contains two separate tablets. For example,
            Clarithromycin 500mg tablet and lansoprazole 30mg capsule would be considered parts of a
            concept like 317329000 |Clarithromycin 500mg tablet and lansoprazole 30mg capsule and
            amoxycillin 500mg capsule pack (product)|. Concepts like this are different from a
            single product that contains two or more active ingredients. These packages can be made
            of products that have different active ingredients or can be products that have the same
            active ingredient, but different strengths for each product in the package.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Proposed Pharmaceutical / Substance Model</title>
            <para>Add a new attribute |Has packaging component (attribute)| that will
                take as a value another concept from the product hierarchy. This will be a <emphasis
                    role="italic">Part-of</emphasis> attribute and will need to be transitive and
                reflexive. These concepts will need to have a new hierarchy to live under as they
                are not really subtypes of the product that make up the packages but are packages
                that contain them. Creating a new hierarchy named “Package” containing
                multiple products (product) and as needed create sub-hierarchies to ease
                navigation is suggested.</para>
            <para>Below are examples of the products that potentially require the addition of new
                product concepts in order for the new attribute to be modeled or require the use of
                nested expressions to represent the missing content. The pilot study represented
                these concepts using nested expressions, however if the model were implemented in
                the International Release of SNOMED CT, it may require creating pre-coordinated concepts.<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Disodium etidronate 400mg tablet and calcium carbonate 1.25g
                            effervescent tablet pack (product) – Disodium etidronate 400mg tablet
                            and calcium carbonate 1.25g effervescent tablet exist and will be used
                            to fully define this concept. The purpose of the parent concept,
                            346404007 |Disodium etidronate+calcium carbonate (product)|, must be
                            determined. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Lutropin alfa 75iu injection (pdr for recon)+solvent (product) –
                            solvent is packaged separate from the powder. Being able to model the
                            solvent part + the powder part will allow for a fully defined
                            concept.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>There are some drugs, mainly multi-tablet packages that do have the individual
                clinical drugs represented as pre-coordinated concepts and will not require the use
                of a nested expression.<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190313T135043-0600" comment="This is another concept that is now inactive in SNOMED.  Does that matter?  If yes, should all referenced concepts be reviewed and replaced as needed?" id="ut5_ynq_hhb" flag="done" mid="2"?>
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190403T091024-0500" comment="Should we state, as of April 2017 Release?  The problem with examples of modeling errors is that they will eventually (hopefully) get fixed." parentID="ut5_ynq_hhb" flag="done" mid="3"?>
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190507T160535-0600" comment="Yes, see my comment in another section re: adding disclaimer at the beginning of the document (i.e., once) stating something like all cited SNOMED examples are from whichever version you used.  You may want to add that they are subject to change and/or being retired in SNOMED." flag="done"?>
                        <para>324934004<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="3"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?>
                            |Proguanil hydrochloride 100mg tablet and chloroquine phosphate 250mg
                            tablet pack (product)| - Proguanil hydrochloride 100mg tablet and
                            chloroquine phosphate 250mg tablet both exist as separate
                            pre-coordinated concepts and could be used to fully define this
                            concept.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Quetiapine 25mg+100mg+150mg tablet starter pack (product) – This
                            concept is a representation of three separate tablets contained within a
                            pack. All three tablets exist as separate pre-coordinated concepts and
                            could easily be fully defined with three separate “Has
                            packaging” components. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Laboratory Concepts</title>
        <para>Part-of Relationships will be useful in the definition of LOINC concepts that
            represent Panels. These panel concepts contain both individual laboratory tests and
            other panel concepts. Panels may also require multiple sufficient sets to represent
            tests that are not always a part of the panel but optional. </para>
        <figure>
            <title>LOINC Panel with optional parts</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_meronmoyPartonomy_01.svg"  scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <section>
            <title>Proposed Laboratory Model</title>
            <para>Add a new attribute that applies to concepts in the Observable
                Entity hierarchy named Contains lab test (attribute). This attribute will take other
                Observable Entity concepts as values and will be transitive and reflexive.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>LOINC Panel with multiple levels of parts</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_meronmoyPartonomy_02.svg"  scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>To fully represent the information contained within the LOINC Panel spreadsheet,
                an Ordered RefSet would have to be created because the tests contained in the panel
                are ordered in the spreadsheet.</para>
            <para>In order to represent the optional tests that are sometimes part of a Panel there
                are several options. These optional tests and panels could be represented in an
                Association Reference Set, but a better representation may be using multiple
                sufficient sets.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>
