<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Procedural Knowledge Representation</title>
    <para>Generally, Procedural Knowledge can pertain to Clinical Decision Support, e.g. </para>
    <para>• Standard ways of performing a procedure</para>
    <para>• Treatment protocols for diseases</para>
    <para>• Standard evidence-based Order Sets</para>
    <para>Applied Procedural Knowledge can enable the use of Clinical Decision Support,
        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190507T125958-0600" comment="I don&apos;t think these need to be capitalized." id="vnl_sx2_c3b" mid="1"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190615T214857-0400" comment="Stylistically, these are often captalized in Informatics Literature. I personally like capitalizing to make it clear that these are distinct concepts in the list. This can be re-visited in the proofing stage, or Stephanie we can discuss this more if you feel strongly. " parentID="vnl_sx2_c3b"?>Clinical
        Pathways, and Knowledge Artifacts<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="1"?> (KNARTs)
        that
        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190507T130127-0600" comment="It&apos;s not clear to me if this is referring only to KNART or clinical pathways, CDS, and KNARTs.  If all of them, then don&apos;t they standardize more than just documentation?" flag="done"?>standardize
        patient documentation<?oxy_comment_end?>, quality improvement interventions, and protocols
        focused on specific clinical domains and patient situations.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction to Clinical Decision Support  </title>
        <para>As defined by Osheroff et al <emphasis role="bold">Clinical decision
                support</emphasis> (CDS) “provides clinicians, staff, patients, or other individuals
            with knowledge and person-specific information, intelligently filtered or presented at
            appropriate times, to enhance health and health care.”<citation>Osheroff</citation> The
            available evidence shows that CDS —when implemented properly with formal management—can
            reduce errors, improve the quality of care, reduce cost, and ease the cognitive burden
            on health care providers.  <citation>CDSOptimize</citation>  As a result, the impetus
            for achieving standardized, widespread adoption of CDS across health systems is clear. </para>
        <para>CDS encompasses a variety of tools to enhance decision-making in the clinical
            workflow. Examples of CDS tools include but are not limited to: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>order sets created for particular conditions or types of patients</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>recommendations/databases that can provide information relevant to particular
                    patients</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>reminders for preventive care</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>documentation templates</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>diagnostic support</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>alerts about potentially dangerous situations. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para><emphasis>*Some of these ‘types’ of CDS are explored and discussed further in
                subsequent sections that follow. </emphasis></para>
        <para>Osheroff also published “The CDS 5 Rights framework” <citation>5Rights</citation>which
            asserts that, to improve targeted healthcare decisions/outcomes with well developed and
            deployed CDS interventions, the interventions must provide:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>the <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis>  information,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to the <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis> people,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>in the <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis> intervention formats,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>through the <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis> channels,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>at the <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis> points in workflow.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Understanding and leveraging effectively the 'what, who, how, where, when' information
            process/workflow dimensions is central to configuring useful CDS and Quality Improvement
            approaches.</para>
        <para>Appropriate use of CDS can help achieve adequate levels of patient safety, care
            quality, patient centeredness, and cost effectiveness. The AMIA CDS Roadmap Development
            Steering Committee describes three pillars for realizing this promise of CDS
                <citation>Osheroff</citation>: </para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Best Knowledge Available When
                        Needed</emphasis></para>
                    <para>CDS is well organized, accessible, and written, stored and transmitted in
                        a format that makes it easy to build and deploy CDS interventions that
                        deliver the knowledge into decision-making </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">High Adoption and Effective Use</emphasis></para>
                    <para>CDS tools are widely implemented, extensively used, and produce
                        significant clinical value while making financial and operational sense to
                        their end-users and purchasers</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Continuous Improvement of Knowledge and CDS
                            Methods</emphasis></para>
                    <para>Both CDS interventions and clinical knowledge undergo continuous
                        improvement based on feedback, experience, and data that are easy to
                        aggregate, assess, and apply.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>In order for the vision of the AMIA CDS Roadmap Steering Committee to be achieved, the
            science of CDS needs to support implementers, clinicians, and technology vendors in
            developing CDS tools that are shareable, standards-based, publicly-available, and
            patient-centered. Namely, the translation of evidence-based clinical practice guidelines
            into implementable clinical tools needs to occur in a manner that is consistent,
            systematic, and comprehensive. There have been a number of historical efforts that have
            aimed to achieve interoperable and robust CDS tools and artifacts that appropriately
            translate guidelines into care (see subsequent section about the History of CDS
            Expression Logic). The Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality depicts the following
            image representing the “CDS lifecycle” for the following
                areas<citation>CDSConnect</citation>:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>authoring CDS tools and artifacts that leverage knowledge sources such as
                        clinical practice guidelines, quality measure specifications, and
                        peer-reviewed journal articles; </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>publishing CDS tools to a public repository (e.g., AHRQ’s CDS
                        Connect);</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>implementing CDS tools in a community (i.e., learning network) and
                        collecting on-the-ground stories and evaluation metrics to then inform the
                        subsequent design, build, and implementation of future CDS tools. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/CDS%20Connect%20Lifestyle.svg" scale="65"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Lack of Standardized Encoded Clinical Data - Impact on CDS</title>
        <para>In this section, we will explore an important question regarding appropriate and
            highly-reliable CDS: <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">how can we provide patient safe
                    clinical decision support given the lack of standardization relating to how we
                    encode data?</emphasis></emphasis> We will discuss the challenges faced by
            authors, implementers and evaluators of CDS implementations by considering the following
            example CDS intervention by Adam Wright et al in the NIH-funded “IQ-MAPLE” study (i.e.,
            Improving Quality by Making an Accurate Problem List in the EHR).
                <citation>IQMAPLE</citation> In IQ-MAPLE, the investigators designed CDS
            interventions in the EHRs of four study sites to alert physicians when a candidate
            problem (e.g., Asthma, COPD, Hypertension, Hyperlipidemia) was detected that was missing
            from the patient's problem list (i.e., absence of structured input of diagnosis
            codes/terms to specify the key condition of interest). The clinician would then be able
            to accept the alert and add the problem, override the alert, or ignore it entirely. The
            investigators conducted a randomized trial and evaluated the effect of the problem list
            alert on three endpoints: alert acceptance, problem list addition rate and clinical
            quality. </para>
        <para>In IQ-MAPLE, a team of clinical experts and informaticians designed and validated a
            series of problem inference algorithms, using rules-based techniques on structured data
            in the electronic health record (EHR) and natural language processing on unstructured
            data. Then, they created CDS rules for suggesting conditions to add to a patient’s
            problem list that may have included the following example criteria:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>queries for the presence or absence of a diagnosis code (e.g., ICD-10CM,
                        SNOMED CT value sets by key condition) included in a patient’s problem list
                        or encounter diagnosis; </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>queries looking for currently active medications (e.g., RXCUI value sets
                        by medication classes) in the patient’s record; </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>queries for lab values (e.g., LOINC value sets) that are within a
                        specified range</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>various combinations and compound queries made up of the aforementioned
                        sub-queries.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Even though the CDS rules and value sets in the IQ-MAPLE study were created centrally,
            there would have inevitably been variation in the implemenations of the rules against
            clinical data at the 4 study sites. A report produced out of the collaboration between
            the ONC and the National Academy of Medicine (NAM) stated that there are at least four
            important technical challenges to sharing and therefore standardizing implementations of
            CDS content: (1) insufficient standardization of patient data representation; (2)
            insufficient standardization of CDS knowledge representation; (3) insufficient
            standardization of CDS integration mechanisms; and (4) a need to align with broader
            standardization initiatives. <citation>CDSOptimize</citation>
        </para>
        <para>Fundamentally, the representation and usage of clinical data and CDS knowledge across
            the 4 IQ-MAPLE study sites would have varied. One of the reasons that CDS interventions
            are difficult to implement between health care systems is because different EHR systems
            and health care systems utilize different underlying patient data models and CDS
            integration mechanisms. Even different instantiations of use of the same EHR systems,
            differ in how they represent patient data. The ONC and NAM report stated that "[b]ecause
            CDS relies on inferencing using patient data, this heterogeneity in patient data
            representation poses an immense obstacle to sharing CDS."
                <citation>CDSOptimize</citation> In IQ-MAPLE,  there were likely vast variations in
            the EHR user interfaces for how clinical data was entered in problem lists,
            representation of lab results, status and recording of currently active medications, and
            other miscellaneous clinical data inputs in patients’ encounter notes. (see ‘Clinical
            Input form’ in the Statement Representation Chapter) </para>
        <para>In addition, there were likely variations in the usage of the value set and
            terminology content at the 4 study organizations. Therefore, there may have been
            discrepancies in how the CDS rules were triggered when they were deployed. For example,
            perhaps physicians at one of the study sites had been trained to only use diagnosis
            codes that align with Hierarchical Condition Category (HCC) codes in CMS’
            risk-adjustment model. These physicians would not have used any other diagnosis codes
            that may have existed in the IQ-MAPLE authored value sets for the CDS alerts. The other
            three study sites may not have operationalized such specific workflows thereby reducing
            the standard representation of the IQ-MAPLE CDS alert implementations between the
            different medical centers. </para>
        <para>The following challenges plaguing CDS implementations were described in a report
            produced out of the collaboration between the ONC and the National Academy of
                Medicine.<citation>CDSOptimize</citation>
        </para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Various pathways for implementation of CDS within different health care
                        organizations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Lack of standards and incentives to use and improve CDS</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Poor data quality</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Gaps in the evidence. </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>These challenges are due in part – according to the summary of Kawamoto's commentary
            in the ONC and NAM report – to a lack of clear standards for CDS content representation:
            "standards are not always defined clearly enough, so a developer will make a decision
            that enables content to work within [test] systems...but are not scalable
                nationally."<citation>CDSOptimize</citation> Consequently, there are vendor-specific
            solutions and organization-specific solutions that exist with "either a laborious
            configuration of external licensed content or a laborious reinvention of the wheel as
            the organization creates its own content." <citation>CDSOptimize</citation> Instead of
            creating a knowledge represention based on a standardized clinical data representation,
            current efforts are focused on creating and re-creating one-off "solutions". Even the
            latest CDS content standards, including Clinical Quality Language (CQL), CDS Hooks, and
            OpenCDS have yet to achieve "the necessary level of detail in the standards and how they
            are applied to clinical decisions."<citation>CDSOptimize</citation></para>
        <para>Therefore, one of the overarching challenges of standards that aim to make CDS
            shareable and interoperable is that there is currently not a robust way to associate
            rules in knowledge-based systems with other dependencies in clinical data representation
            systems to ensure proper operation. Current CDS standards are silent on the notion of
            identifying a safe configuration of dependencies between (a) the expression-logic for
            rules-based CDS techniques, (b) the value sets with codes and terms to define clinical
            concepts of interest contained in the CDS rules, and (c) the variability of how clinical
            data within the value sets and rules are inputted, modeled, and stored in data
            repositories. </para>
        <para>These challenges have been explored by Wright et al when they studied CDS
            functionality at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and illustrated ways in which clinical
            decision support systems malfunction and identified patterns of such malfunctions.
                <citation>CDSMalfunction</citation> As a part of this study, a survey of 29 Chief
            Medical Information Officers (CMIOs) showed that 93% of CMIOs experience CDS system
            malfunctions, and two-thirds experienced the malfunctions at least annually. <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>One such malfunction was described as involving <emphasis role="bold"
                                ><emphasis role="underline"> inappropriate dependencies between and
                                amongst the electronic health record system, clinical decision
                                support system, and other external systems</emphasis></emphasis>
                        (e.g., lab information systems) . For example, “an alert for monitoring
                        thyroid function in patients receiving amiodarone stopped working when an
                        internal identifier for amiodarone was changed in another system.”
                            <citation>CDSMalfunction</citation>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Wright et al also found that <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                                role="underline">inappropriate configuration of dependencies
                                perpetuated mistakes in underlying databases and value set
                                management</emphasis></emphasis>: “a malfunction in an external drug
                        classification system caused an alert to inappropriately suggest
                        antiplatelet drugs, such as aspirin, for patients already taking one”.
                            <citation>CDSMalfunction</citation></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Thirdly, Wright et al wrote about how <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                                role="underline">inappropriate dependencies on EHR software caused
                                numerous spurious alerts to fire</emphasis></emphasis>.
                            <citation>CDSMalfunction</citation></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring CDS -  Design &amp; Testing
                Considerations</emphasis></title>
        <para>As described above, Wright et al learned that Brigham and Women’s Hospital did not
            have a system to track the siloed components of their EHR and CDS systems, nor did they
            have a process for tracking changes to the CDS rules, logic, and terminology
            implementations that were tied to other dependencies upstream or downstream in the
            implementation and process flow. Therefore, in IQ-MAPLE, the investigators tried to keep
            a closer eye on the design and functionality of CDS tools including the background work
            required to update and maintain these complex systems.</para>
        <para>To test the validity of their IQ-MAPLE CDS alert implementations, each study site
            organization might have built a testing environment to implement the CDS rules to detect
            whether each suggestion of a condition to add to a patient’s problem list was
            “appropriate” or not. Such a testing environment allowed the CDS alerts to “silently”
            fire after they were built. In other words, the alerts were built and set to fire on
            patients in the back-end of the systems. End-users would NOT receive alerts at this
            stage. The alerts would “silently” fire for two weeks or some other agreed upon trial
            period. Then, the implementers would generate the list of patients for whom the silent
            alerts fire. </para>
        <para>Next, basic face-validity would be performed upon perusal of the patient lists for
            whom the alerts silently fired. For a condition with a high prevalence like
            hypertension, an implementer may not be surprised to see hundreds of alerts firing in a
            2-week span in their hospital, clinic, or medical center. Conversely, if the condition
            for a problem-list suggestion CDS rule is rarer, such as Sickle Cell Disease, then it
            would not be surprising to only see a handful of alerts fired in a 2-week silent run. If
            implementers thought that the count of alerts seemed off based on condition prevalence,
            then this could inform an analysis of the alert implementation and/or rules without
            having to do a more time-consuming chart-audit. </para>
        <para>Next, patient charts for whom the alerts silently fire were abstracted to validate
            that the alerts fired on appropriate people. In this step, it may suffice to validate a
            smaller subset of patient records rather than validating hundreds of patient-charts for
            whom alerts may silently fire. If the alerts were accurate at some threshold (e.g., 90%)
            based on the chart audit, then the alert could be marked as “appropriate” at a given
            institution. If inaccuracies arise in the chart audit during the silent firing testing
            phase, it may reveal errors in the implementation, or in the rules themselves prior to
            go-live deployment. </para>
        <para>This sort of CDS testing environment would also allow for intra-organizational
            comparison of value set implementations or to assess the impact of inter-organizational
            updates to standard clinical terminologies over time. It could also be used to detect
            changes to CDS expression-logic or rule changes and study the impact on the clinical
            data prior to deployment to better understand the impact of proposed updates. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Metrics for Monitoring CDS Implementations before and after Go-Live
                Deployment</title>
            <para>This section will describe quality metrics for monitoring CDS performance. The ONC
                and NAM report highlighted the impetus for measuring whether CDS interventions are
                working: “ To optimize CDS and increase adoption and acceptance, it will be critical
                to determine which interventions are firing at the appropriate times and are then
                accepted by the clinical care team and patients and changing care for the better.
                This capability will be important at both the local and national scale if the goal
                is to reduce the burden on providers and health systems to each identify important
                lessons on their own." <citation>CDSOptimize</citation> The following table shows
                examples of measures to determine the impact of CDS interventions.
                    <citation>refine</citation><table frame="all">
                    <title>Examples of measures commonly captured to measure the effects of CDS
                        interventions </title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Measure</entry>
                                <entry>Examples</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>CDS satisfaction, usage, usability </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>usability assessments from end-users, end-user
                                                feedback, use of CDS from logs</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Workflow impact, efficiency</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>time to complete work tasks before and after CDS,
                                                e.g., direct order entry, medication turn-around
                                                time</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>CDS use by clinicians</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>alert use, rate of alerts firing alert
                                                overrides</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>number of times CDS alerts happen: (e.g.,
                                                  absolute counts, central tendency, percent change
                                                  over time)</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Healthcare services utilization and efficiencies</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>reductions in unnecessary or inappropriate
                                                laboratory test orders</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Costs</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>resource management, provider medication (number,
                                                type, class) and laboratory test costs</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Unintended consequences (includes all measure types
                                    above)</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>alert fatigue, overrides of serious alerts,
                                                adverse events due to CDS</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Clinical objectives addressed with CDS </entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Care processes, adherence to guidelines</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>adherence to clinical guidelines; time to ordering
                                                of important medications</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Patient safety </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>error reports, adverse events, transfers to ICU,
                                                death, medication prescribing errors</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Patient Outcomes</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>disease management related to adoption of
                                                guidelines (e.g., blood pressure control, lipid
                                                levels, H1ac levels), hospital lengths of stay,
                                                rehospitalizations </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table></para>
            <section>
                <title>Signs of an Effective CDS Roll-Out </title>
                <para>Health IT.gov published a how-to manual for healthcare organizations to
                    monitor CDS rollout plans and included the following criteria:
                        <citation>rollout</citation></para>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>All end-users were adequately trained for using the intervention
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>End-users felt the trainings were well-timed in relation to the
                                roll-out </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>End-users did not feel overwhelmed by the introduction of
                                CDS</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>End-users know how to provide feedback and get support if
                                needed</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Changes in workflow were smooth and improved care processes</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Statistical Process Control Methods for CDS Anomaly Detection</title>
                <para>A CDS malfunction (aka true positive anomaly) occurs when the CDS rule does
                    not function as it was designed or expected to. The question that an evaluator
                    of CDS interventions may ask is: <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Predict, given
                            an expected number of events will happen, how many events will happen
                            over time?</emphasis></emphasis>? When monitoring CDS count data over
                    time, the underlying denominator likely will vary insignificantly. Therefore,
                    statistical process control (SPC) charts can be created and the following tests
                    can be performed: <citation>kassakian</citation></para>
                <para>Test #1 the presence of a single point outside the control limits using the
                    threshold 3*standard deviation.</para>
                <para>Test #2 two of three consecutive points are more than 2 standard deviations
                    from the average line and both on the same side of the average line.</para>
                <para>Test #3 eight or more consecutive points on the same side of the average
                    line.</para>
                <para>Test #4 consisted of 6 or more values steadily increasing or
                    decreasing.</para>
                <para>SPC anomaly detection can be attempted on time points for various time scales
                    (e.g., weekly and monthly scale). To determine the characteristics and
                    performance of SPC detection methods sensitivity, specificity, precision and the
                    F measure can be determined.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Best Practices for CDS Knowledge Management and Deployment</title>
        <para>As aforementioned in the section “Introduction to CDS”, the AMIA CDS Roadmap
            Development Steering Committee describes three pillars for realizing the promise of CDS
                <citation>Osheroff</citation>: (1) Best Knowledge Available When Needed, (2) High
            Adoption and Effective Use, and (3) Continuous Improvement of Knowledge and CDS
            Methods.</para>
        <para>Given our discussion of challenges that plague CDS implementations, we propose a 4th
            pillar to be explicitly added to this framework: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Standardization Related to how we Encode and Represent
                        Clinical Data</emphasis></para>
                <para>The underlying clinical data that feeds into CDS tools, interventions, and
                    deployments must be represented, version-controlled, and encoded in a
                    consistent, comprehensive, and systematic way. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section>
            <title>Best Practices for CDS Knowledge Management</title>
            <para>Below are some suggestions for <emphasis role="underline">Best Practices for CDS
                    Knowledge Management</emphasis>: <citation>WrightWebinar</citation></para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Implement a clear, standard process for submission, review, evaluation,
                        prioritization, and creation of all new CDS</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Maintain an up-to-date inventory of all CDS, including type (e.g., alert,
                        order set), owner(s), dates of creation, dates of review, sources of
                        evidence, clinical areas affected, and short description</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Manage terminologies and value sets using formal processes (e.g.,
                        Solor)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Periodically review the clinical evidence and assertional knowledge
                        underlying CDS rules and update as needed</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Use a formal software change control process for all CDS updates</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Enable review of the logic for CDS rules in human-readable format by
                        clinical end-users (e.g., in a portal or repository)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Best Practices for CDS Deployment</title>
            <para>Below are some suggestions for Best Practices for CDS Deployment:
                    <citation>WrightWebinar</citation></para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Use a process where changes to value set terminology codes made by SDOs,
                        value set developers, or by ancillary department internal systems are
                        communicated and pushed to CDS authors, implementers, and evaluators to be
                        analyzed for impact before the changes are made</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Employ a process where changes to attribute values (e.g., units of
                        measurement) are communicated and pushed to CDS authors, implementers, and
                        evaluators to be analyzed for impact before the changes are made</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Test and deploy EHR vendor patches and upgrades in a timely manner</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inform users of significant CDS changes</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Require IT staff to use automated tools to migrate CDS rules between EHR
                        system environments (e.g., test and production)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Ten Commandments for Effective CDS</title>
            <para>Bates et al published the<emphasis role="italic"> Ten Commandments for Effective
                    Clinical Decision Support: Making the Practice of Evidence-based Medicine a
                    Reality</emphasis> with “the goal…to present generic lessons from [their CDS]
                experiences that may be useful to others, including informaticians, systems
                developers, and health care organizations.” <citation>CDS10</citation> The paper
                includes the follow Ten Commandments for Effective CDS
                <citation>CDS10</citation>:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Speed is Everything</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>“[T]he speed of an information system is the parameter that users
                                value most. If the decision support is wonderful, but takes too long
                                to appear, it will be useless.” </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Anticipate Needs and Deliver in Real
                        Time</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>“[A]pplications must anticipate clinician needs and bring
                                information to clinicians at the time they need it” </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Fit into the User’s Workflow</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>“Understanding clinician workflow, particularly when designing
                                applications for the outpatient setting, is critical.”</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Little Things Can Make a Big
                        Difference</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Usability matters a lot. CDS must be understandable, useful and
                                encompass the needed functionality. Furthermore, CDS should be easy
                                to learn, efficient to use, easy to remember, subjectively pleasing,
                                and contain few (or no) errors. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Recognize that Physicians Will Strongly Resist
                            Stopping</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Bates et al “found that physicians strongly resist suggestions not
                                to carry out an action when [they did] not offer an alternative,
                                even if the action they are about to carry out is virtually always
                                counterproductive.”</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Changing Direction Is Easier than
                            Stopping</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CDS can be a powerful tool for changing physician behavior. Bates
                                et al were “especially effective when the issue at hand is one
                                attribute of an order the physician probably does not have strong
                                feelings about, such as the dose, route, or frequency of a
                                medication or the views in a radiographic study.”</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Simple Interventions Work Best</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>“If you cannot fit a guideline on a single screen, clinicians will
                                not be happy about using it.”</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Ask for Additional Information Only When You Really
                            Need It</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>“[The likelihood of success in implementing a computerized
                                guideline is inversely proportional to the number of extra data
                                elements needed.”</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitor Impact, Get Feedback, and
                        Respond</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>“Carefully evaluate and prune the CDS knowledge base.”</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Manage and Maintain Your Knowledge-based
                            Systems</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Maintaining the knowledge within the system and managing the
                                individual pieces of the system are critical to successful delivery
                                of decision support. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Historical Context for Representing the Expression Logic of Clinical Decision
            Support</title>
        <para>While there have been advancements over the past few decades in implementing clinical
            data standards (e.g., SNOMED CT, LOINC), there is still room to improve portability of
            CDS implementations across healthcare organizations. Different health care institutions
            may increasingly have their clinical data encoded according to standards-based
            terminologies, but each site will still require human intervention and hand-crafted
            implementations of computerized CDS including patient safety alerts and health
            maintenance reminders intended to improve population health. One implementation of a CDS
            alert at the Veterans Health Administration, for instance, is not completely
            transferrable to another institution, even if the organization is using the same Health
            IT system. Analysts at each organization will have to modify the underlying query so
            that it is computable against their respective clinical database structure. Furthermore,
            not all clinical concepts are recorded and stored in the same way in different EHR
            implementations; what may be structured in one system may be free text in another. While
            the Health Quality Measure Format (HQMF), Quality Data Model (QDM), and Clinical Quality
            Langauge (CQL) are the more recent efforts to improve standard representations of CDS
            expression logic, efforts date back to the mid 1970’s when early implementers of
            computer-based clinical information systems were first recognizing the value of
            computer-based decision support into their designs. </para>
        <para>Notably, Clem McDonald’s work on the Regenstrief Medical Record System exemplifies
            important early work in pseudocode logic expression. McDonald realized that the number
            of CDS reminders and alerts would quickly increase, so rather than hand-crafting each
            rule into computer code with programmers, he created one of the first CDS rule languages
            called CARE. <citation>McCallie</citation> The CARE language allowed clinical experts
            and those without programming expertise to structure if-then logic of alerts using a
            flexible scripting language that could be interpreted by programmers to implement
            against the patient record system. As computerized EHRs continued to spread to other
            academic medical centers in the years that followed, it became clear that a standard way
            to replicate the expression logic of CARE-style if-then decision rules would be needed.
            In the late 1980s, informaticists at Columbia led an important initiative to standardize
            CDS scripting language and created the Arden Syntax or Medical Logic Modules, the goal
            of which was to encode if-then-else rules in a standard format that could be computed
            against different EHR systems, regardless of the location or specific vendor. Arden
            Syntax logic modules were novel in that they consisted of standard sections called
            ‘categories’, and each category contained several ‘slots’. For instance, the ‘logic’
            slot contained the actual clinical logic of a rule, and the ‘action’ slot defined the
            message that the rule would display to the clinician-user. Modern EHRs often still use
            this framework even if the full Arden Syntax is not used: when a clinician’s workflow
            reaches a trigger point, then a rule in the system is fired, and evaluates the clinical
            logic attached to the trigger point. <citation>McCallie</citation></para>
        <para>By the mid 1990’s, CDS rules using the Arden Syntax began to spread to numerous
            commercial systems, however dissemination was limited in that rules written in one
            facility would not run against any other system. While the ‘logic’ slot contained
            machine-executable if-then-else code, there was also a ‘curly brace’ part of the syntax
            that only contained a human-readable textual description of the database process and
            actions necessary for the rule to access clinical data in the EHR. This required
            human-interpretation and hand-crafting at each specific site and this challenge was
            referred to as the “curly brace problem”. <citation>McCallie</citation> This challenge
            to achieve portability across environments has persisted throughout the 1990s to 2000s
            to the current day. These challenges were only worsened when guideline-based techniques
            were introduced attempting to separate clinical problems into a series of linked
            clinical decisions. There were some notable efforts such as Guideline Interchange Format
            (GLIF), PROforma, SAGE, and GEM, which aimed to incorporate a guideline’s logic into the
            executable part of decision logic, however these languages suffered due to a lack of
            maturity of standards to integrate the guideline engines into EHRs
                directly.<citation>McCallie</citation></para>
        <para>In 1998, HL7 found the “curly brace” problem to be unsolvable by the Arden approach
            and began efforts to create expression logic standards based on HL7 Version 3 Reference
            Information Model (RIM).<citation>RIM</citation> One attempt was the GELLO Expression
            Language, which in theory was supposed to access and manipulate clinical data by common
            clinical entities; however RIM was not proven to be a very practical representation of
            the complexity of real-world data. Only a small number of vendors were successfully able
            to implement RIM-based EHRs and therefore the vision of GELLO and HL7 V3 efforts
            remained unproven. In 2013, HL7 replaced GELLO with ECA (“Event, Condition, Action”), an
            expression in XML data structures intended to abstract the representation of expression
            logic. Shortly thereafter, the standards community realized the benefit in aligning CDS
            logic expression with those of eCQMs as the goals of CDS rules are often used to prompt
            clinicians to achieve improved clinical quality outcomes, and therefore HL7 defined
            QUICK – the Quality Improvement and Clinical Knowledge model. <citation>quick</citation>
            QUICK and ECA have now been wrapped up into Clinical Quality Language (CQL) which
            attempts to capture lessons learned from Arden, GELLO, and ECA. </para>
        <para>An emerging Health Level Seven (HL7) International standard that might help with
            electronic processing of eCQM and CDS logic is the Clinical Quality Language (CQL), a
            new specification that focuses on a common model for representing expression logic for
            CQMs and Clinical Decision Support. According to CMS’ eCQI Resource Center, CQL will be
            used in all quality measure specifications in the future, will replace the Quality Data
            Model (QDM), and is intended to reduce the burden on implementers for consuming measure
            artifacts. CQL representations of eCQMs will replace the QDM pseudocode historically
            published in HQMF files; it aims to provide a human-readable, conceptual-level language
            to define eCQMs and clinical decision support independent of specific data models, such
            as the QDM or FHIR (Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resource). </para>
        <para>CMS is rapidly rolling out the CQL standard in its eCQMs and CDS for the 2019
            reporting year. The goal of CQL moving forward is to use emerging Application
            Programming Interfaces like
            FHIR<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T095537-0600" comment="I don&apos;t think yoy need to spell this out again as you already did that in the preceding paragraph." flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?>as
            a way to allow for more direct access to clinical data that does not require the
            overhead of RIM mapping. <citation>Jiang</citation> The potential for FHIR and CQL in
            CDS and eCQM implementations remains to be seen, however, the community is optimistic. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Tools that Enhance CDS</title>
        <para>CDS encompasses a variety of tools to enhance decision-making in the clinical
            workflow. In this section, we will define and discuss Standard Operating Procedures,
            Clinical Practice Guidelines, Clinical pathways, Treatment Protocols, Order Sets, and
            KNARTs.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Standard Operating Procedures</title>
            <para>Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) "are a specific set of practices that are
                required to be initiated and followed when specific circumstances arise. In clinical
                care, clinicians have historically been familiar with SOPs in specific types of
                restricted contexts. For example, emergency room physicians have SOPs for patients
                who are brought in an unconscious state; nurses in an operating theater have SOPs
                for the forceps and swabs that they hand over to the operating surgeons; and
                laboratory technicians have SOPs for handling, testing, and subsequently discarding
                body fluids obtained from patients." <citation>SOP</citation></para>
            <para>Now that EHRs and electronic clinical data in some capacity are essentially
                ubiquitous in the US, Health IT implementations often come with tools making it
                possible to achieve SOPs "into routine clinical practice; that is, not for special
                patients (e.g. those who are unconscious) or for special circumstances (e.g.
                clinical trials), but for every patient in everyday clinical
                    care."<citation>SOP</citation></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Guidelines</title>
            <para>Practice Guidelines are systematically developed statements on medical practices
                that assist a clinician in making decisions about appropriate diagnostic and
                therapeutic healthcare services for specific medical conditions. These guidelines
                should be evidence-based, and use research evidence along with clinical expertise
                and patient preferences in providing care. Guidelines are usually developed by
                authoritative professional societies and organizations. Guidelines that provide
                clinicians and patients the recommendations for screening, diagnostic and
                therapeutic actions that are known or believed to favorably affect the health
                outcomes of patients. Guidelines are not meant to replace the clinical judgement of
                the individual provider or establish a standard of care. They are meant to be
                flexible and are only considered recommendations. Where Guidelines are meant to be
                flexible, standards are a rigid set of criteria, meant to be followed under any
                circumstances. These are practices that are medically necessary for the management
                of a clinical condition.<citation>Guidelines</citation></para>
            <section>
                <title>Examples of Guidelines</title>
                <para>The Society of Nuclear Medicine &amp; Molecular Imaging in collaboration with
                    other professional society creates and hosts 'Procedure Standards' for a
                    variety of comprehensive procedure guidelines describing how to perform medical
                    and research procedures. <citation>snmmi</citation>
                </para>
                <para>Similarly, the American Academy of Family Physicians (AAFP) develops
                    evidence-based clinical practice guidelines (CPGs), which serve as a framework
                    for clinical decisions and supporting best practices. Clinical practice
                    guidelines are statements that include recommendations intended to optimize
                    patient care. They are informed by a systematic review of evidence, and an
                    assessment of the benefits and harms of alternative care options. CPGs should
                    follow a sound, transparent methodology to translate best evidence into clinical
                    practice for improved patient outcomes. Additionally, evidence-based CPGs are a
                    key aspect of patient-centered care.<citation>CPG</citation>
                </para>
                <para>AHRQ's Guidelines and Measures (GAM), provides users a place to find
                    information about legacy guidelines and measures clearinghouses, 'National
                    Guideline Clearinghouse' (NGC) and 'National Quality Measures Clearinghouse'
                    (NQMC). The NGC mission was to provide physicians and other health care
                    professionals, health care providers, health plans, integrated delivery systems,
                    purchasers and others an accessible mechanism for obtaining objective, detailed
                    information on clinical practice guidelines and to further their dissemination,
                    implementation, and use. The NQMC mission was to provide practitioners, health
                    care providers, health plans, integrated delivery systems, purchasers and others
                    an accessible mechanism for obtaining detailed information on quality measures,
                    and to further their dissemination, implementation, and use in order to inform
                    health care decisions. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Clinical Pathways </title>
            <para>Clinical Pathways are one of the main tools used to manage the quality in
                healthcare concerning the standardization of care processes. They intend to reduce
                variability and clinical practice thereby improving outcomes. Clinical pathways
                appeared as a result of the adaptation of the documents used in industrial quality
                management, the Standard Operating Procedure, whose goals are to improve efficiency
                in the use of resources and to finish work in a set time. </para>
            <para>Clinical pathways incorporate evidence-based guidelines and protocols for common
                diagnoses, conditions and procedures into algorithms. These algorithms are used by
                the multidisciplinary care team in providing care to the patient.</para>
            <para> Items addressed on the clinical pathway may include:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Patient assessment and monitoring</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Tests and procedures</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Treatments</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Consultations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Medications</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Activity</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Nutrition</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Education</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Targeted length of stay</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Outcome Criteria</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Notification for deviations</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Standardizing treatments improves the continuity and coordination of care provided
                by all disciplines involved. This should result in greater quality of care and
                decreased costs. </para>
            <section>
                <title>Pathways vs SOPs vs Guidelines</title>
                <para>Rao et al provide definitions to help compare/contrast SOPs, guidelines, and
                    clinical pathways: </para>
                <para xml:id="__p7">"The terms SOPs, guidelines and pathways are defined by
                    different medical bodies. Furthermore, whereas clinical practice guidelines are
                    systematically developed statements that assist decisions about appropriate
                    health care for specific circumstances,SOPs are more specific than guidelines
                    and are defined in greater detail. They provide a comprehensive set of rigid
                    criteria outlining the management steps for a single clinical condition or
                    aspects of organization.</para>
                <para xml:id="__p8">Guidelines are rigorously developed using evidence-based
                    medicine criteria and consist of two distinct components: the evidence summary
                    and the detailed instructions for the application of that evidence to patient
                    care. For the common health care provider, guidelines require local adaptation
                    to suit local circumstances and to achieve a feeling of ownership, both of which
                    are important factors in guideline uptake and use. SOPs, therefore, help bridge
                    the gap between evidence-based medicine, clinical practice guidelines, and the
                    local realities at the point-of-care." <citation>SOP</citation></para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Treatment Protocols</title>
            <para>Standardized treatment protocols decrease variability and improve the quality of
                clinical care by simplifying the treatment options, particularly in primary health
                care. Standard treatment protocols can be developed by preparing new treatment
                guidelines or by adapting or adopting existing national or international guidelines.
                    <citation>Protocols</citation> When embedded in electronic health records,
                treatment protocols can serve as clinical decision support at the point of care so
                no opportunities are missed to achieve control.
                <citation>millionhearts</citation></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Order Sets</title>
            <para>Order sets are a group of related orders which a user can issue that apply to a
                specified diagnosis or a particular period of time. Order sets reduce both time
                spent entering orders and terminal usage, helping to improve user acceptance of
                computer-based physician order
                    entry.<citation>orderset</citation><citation>ordersets2</citation></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Artifacts (KNARTs)</title>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190513T164136-0500" comment="Should this be it&apos;s own section?" flag="done"?>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T094315-0600" comment="I think it should." flag="done" mid="5"?>
            <para><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="5"?>KNART is a Clinical Decision Support
                Knowledge Artifact and it's a structured way of documenting the content/knowledge
                for three different types of CDS interventions: 1) event condition action (ECA) rule
                (e.g., clinical reminder), 2) order sets, and 3) documentation templates (VA has
                called them SMARTForms or PNCS forms in the past). </para>
            <para>KNARTs are a standard HL7 format. While they are not the actual executable CDS
                interventions, they provide the information that a developer can take and then
                implement within an EHR. The main benefit to KNARTs is that you can share them with
                other healthcare organizations in a standardized manner that they can take and
                implement within their own EHR, if they choose.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
   
</chapter>
