<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Language</title>
     <para>Language is used to describe identified components. While the initial focus of Solor will be to use the English language versions from the foundational coding systems, support for other languages will be included as a part of Solor.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Language Layer Concerns</title>
        <section xml:id="section_ed272173-6351-49e9-8503-abffd8bc18bb">
            <title>Language</title>
            <para>SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm as well as other coding systems have various ways of
                representing language. </para>
            <para>Descriptions in SNOMED CT include one Fully Specified Name and at least one
                synonym for each language. The Preferred and Acceptable Synonyms per language are
                then specified in a Language Reference Set. Any additional synonyms, other than the
                preferred, that are relevant for a language would be identifed as acceptable.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Description and RefSet Values for Myocardial infarction</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Description Term</entry>
                            <entry>Description Type</entry>
                            <entry>Refset(s)</entry>
                            <entry>Refset Acceptability</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Myocardial infarction (disorder)</entry>
                            <entry>Fully Specified Name</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Myocardial infarction</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Infarction of heart</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Cardiac infarction</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Heart attack</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>MI - myocardial infarction</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Myocardial infarct</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>RxNorm identifies language in the RXNCONSO file in the STR field. The language of
                the name is specified in the LAT field and the source the name comes from is
                represented in the STT field. The names in the RXNCONSO are not unique as the same
                name can come from multiple sources.</para>
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>RxNorm Strings Associated With "100 ML Acetaminophen 10 MG/ML
                        Injection"</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Property</entry>
                                <entry>STR</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Prescribable Synonym</entry>
                                <entry>acetaminophen 1000 MG in 100 ML Injection</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>RxNorm Name</entry>
                                <entry>100 ML Acetaminophen 10 MG/ML Injection</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>RxNorm Synonym</entry>
                                <entry>acetaminophen 1000 MG per 100 ML Injection</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>RxNorm Synonym</entry>
                                <entry>100 ML APAP 10 MG/ML Injection</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para>LOINC has names spread across multiple fields with the Fully Specified Name
                constructed as a concatenation of the six parts. It also contains a Long Common Name
                and a Short Name. The screenshot from Komet below exemplifies the 6 LOINC parts:
                Component, Method, Property, Scale, System, and Timing. </para>
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>LOINC Representation of "Glucose [Presence] in Urine by Test strip --4.5
                        hours post 75 g glucose PO"</title>
                    <tgroup cols="6">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>COMPONENT</entry>
                                <entry>PROPERTY</entry>
                                <entry>TIME_ASPCT</entry>
                                <entry>SYSTEM</entry>
                                <entry>SCALE_TYP</entry>
                                <entry>METHOD_TYP</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Glucose^4.5H post 75 g glucose PO</entry>
                                <entry>PrThr</entry>
                                <entry>Pt</entry>
                                <entry>Urine</entry>
                                <entry>Ord</entry>
                                <entry>Test strip</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T132017-0600" comment="In the PDF, this example is cutoff and you can&apos;t see the full middle panel section and you can only see the first letter of each of the 6 components.  Needs fixing."?>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/LOINC_komet.png" scale="20"/><?oxy_comment_end?>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></para>
            <para>Descriptions within a coding system can span multiple languages. For example,
                &quot;deja vu&quot; exists in both the French and English languages as it is the
                description used to describe the memory finding.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_2f530c57-07b6-4abf-9399-db11515f1977">
            <title>Dialect</title>
            <para>Merriam-Webster's Dictionary defines a dialect as &quot;a regional variety of
                language distinguished by features of vocabulary, grammar, and pronunciation from
                other regional varieties and constituting together with them a single
                language&quot;. Two common differences between dialects deal with spelling variants
                and phrases that have alternate meanings. An example of a spelling variant would be
                &quot;Anesthetic&quot; in the US dialect versus &quot;Anaesthetic&quot; in the
                British dialect. The same word in one dialect can mean have a different meaning in
                another, for example
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T153845-0700" comment="Is there a reason that quotes weren&apos;t used with this, like they were in the prior example?" flag="done"?>&quot;napkin&quot;<?oxy_comment_end?>
                in the US is used to describe a piece of cloth or paper used to wipe the hands and
                mouth at a table while in the UK it is used to describe a diaper. </para>
            <table>
                <title>Description and RefSet Values for Epidural anesthesia</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Description Term</entry>
                            <entry>Description Type</entry>
                            <entry>Refset(s)</entry>
                            <entry>Refset Acceptability</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Epidural anesthesia (procedure)</entry>
                            <entry>Fully Specified Name</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Epidural anesthesia</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Peridural anesthesia</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Local anesthetic epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LA - Local anesthetic epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Epidural anaesthesia</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Peridural anaesthesia</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Local anaesthetic epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LA - Local anaesthetic epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Extradural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_7a5f5087-2a21-4b5e-8993-53fd045b53ff">
        <title>Cross Cutting Concerns</title>
        <section xml:id="section_ce7e4daf-e50d-4ada-93c7-305f036ce86d">
            <title>Understandability, Reproducibility, and Utility</title>
            <para>The language used to describe a component must be concordant with the underlying
                semantics of the object being identified. Therefore, there needs to be guidelines in
                place to ensure only correct terms are associated with an object in Solor.</para>
            <para>Having a consistent naming convention defined will assist with textual queries to identify duplicates when concepts are primitive and not able to be fully defined using relationships within Solor. Having a consistent way of representing Fully Specified Names will alleviate the issue of users creating duplicate concepts like &quot;Disorder of immune function&quot; and &quot;Immune function disorder&quot;.</para>
            <para>Consistent naming is also important to support effective retrieval.  For example, the SNOMED CT concept 386560004 |Glasgow coma score finding (finding)| has 13 children all with the string Glasgow coma scale instead of Glasgow coma score.  </para>
            <para>Another common issue is to add a synonym to a concept that is more specific than
                the concept itself. A concept should only have synonyms that accurately represent a
                concept and not any of its children. If a synonym has a more specific meaning, a new
                concept should be created.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_c3d7371d-1785-4e89-b280-9b4a53cd3665">
            <title>Language
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T154146-0700" comment="This section should be revised so it can be read as in the prior sections.  Here&apos;s it&apos;s just a list of what appear to be definitions.  You at least need some introductory paragraph that explains what you have listed here. " flag="done"?>Query<?oxy_comment_end?>
                Requirements</title>
            <para>For a search engine to retrieve meaningful results, it must be able to understand
                common usages of everyday jargon, similar to how synonyms are used to help broaden
                the way to express the same word. This section describes several strategies used to
                help with a query.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Word variants</emphasis> – Similar to synonyms, word
                variants are used to express the same word. While synonyms are explicitly created as
                a term to describe a concept (for example, SNOMED's "Heart attack" and "Myocardial
                infarction"), word variants are utilized during searching to assist in finding the
                correct concept, rather than explicitly creating the term. Hypothetical example - if
                "kidney failure" is a term created for a concept, a word variant of 'renal' could be
                created for 'kidney'. Instead of explicitly creating a separate term of "renal
                failure", this word variant could be utilized during searching to find all concepts
                that have the explicit term of "kidney failure" when a user enters "renal failure"
                by replacing "renal" with "kidney". This would create the burden of creating all
                possible variant terms for a given word.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Misspellings</emphasis> – Certain terms are more commonly
                misspelled when searching over healthcare descriptions. The ability for a search
                mechanism to recognize them and to search over both the correct and incorrect
                spellings will help to identify the correct concept. For example, perineal vs
                peroneal and aphagia vs aphasia. </para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Word order</emphasis> – Terms can be combined in different ways
                to mean the same synonym. The ability to search over a term in varying order of
                phrases is important. For example, Disorder of the eye vs Eye disorder.</para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Components query</emphasis> – The importance of this searching
                strategy comes into play when a certain focus is desired for the search result. For
                example, in LOINC, there may be circumstances where a certain axis is desired for
                the search. Similarly, a certain hierarchy may be desired when searching in SNOMED.
                For example, "cold" is a synonym of common cold (a disorder) in SNOMED, and also
                exists as "cold sensation quality" (a qualifier value). By allowing users to limit
                the search criteria (disorder vs. qualifier), the most appropriate query result will
                be returned to the user.</para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Active and inactive</emphasis> – Concepts and terms will come
                in and out of use over time. This is often indicated by an active/inactive
                designation. In order to properly return concepts/terms that are active, query
                parameters must contain a parameter to designate if the query result should/should
                not return active and inactive concepts or terms.</para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Regular Expressions</emphasis> - Regular expression or regex is
                a sequence of characters that defines a search pattern. This pattern would allow a
                user to retrieve results based on a certain pattern. For example "a|b*" would return
                all "a", "b" and other b's that fits the pattern such as "bb", "bbb", "bab", etc.
                Since the depth and breadth of regular expression is beyond the scope of this
                document, various syntaxes, usage and explanation can be found in many resources
                such as <link xlink:href="https://regexr.com/"/>.</para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Grouping Results by hierarchy</emphasis> - This search
                requirement can be thought of as a complement to "components query". After casting a
                wide net, results could be a bag of various terms (common cold vs. feeling cold)
                that may be cumbersome for users to sift through if it is not organized in an
                orderly fashion. Therefore, if results are placed together in a logical grouping, it
                would assist the user in finding the appropriate query result. For example, in
                SNOMED, it may be worthwhile to group results by hierarchy (disorder vs. procedures)
                to allow a user to look for a result in a desired domain or in RxNorm where all
                Ingredient results are grouped separately from Semantic Clinical Drug
                results.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
