<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Parking lot/Ideas Discussed and Discarded</title>
    <section xml:id="_Ref493848005">
        <title>Confusion About Negation: “Absent” and “Not Present”</title>
        <para>Negation as a logical concept is subject to many ambiguities and
            inconsistencies, in healthcare applications and general usage<footnote
                xml:id="__EN4__">
                <para>Horn L. A Natural History of Negation. University of Chicago Press,
                    1989.</para>
            </footnote>. For example, the semantic distinctions between the statements “he
            didn’t say she was ill” and “he said she was not ill” are subtle and open to
            varying interpretations. When such distinctions appear in medical records and
            are used as the basis for inference or data retrieval, it’s important that a
            clear and formal semantic exists that is shared by those who record the
            information, those who later review the information and use it in medical
            decision making, and those who write software that aggregates, abstracts,
            infers, or performs other logical computations on the information.</para>
        <para>One important distinction in medical documentation is that of a clinical
            phenomenon being documented as “absent” versus the phenomenon not being
            documented as “present.” For example, does the explicit documentation of “No
            abdominal tenderness” mean the same thing as no documentation of “abdominal
            tenderness”? Would the interpretation be different if the phenomenon were
            instead “jaundice” or “HIV”? Would it matter if the presenting complaint at the
            time that observation were documented were “vomiting” versus “ankle sprain”?
            Depending on the clinical context, the specific phenomenon in question, and the
            assumptions of individuals using the medical record, the interpretation of
            “absent” versus “not present” could be the same or quite different. Today’s
            representation and inferencing models for electronic health records do not
            provide enough clarity and control to safely interpret negation in these
            situations.</para>
        <para>Finally, current ontology-based models for representing clinical observations
            sometimes result in gross errors when subsumption inferences are applied to
            negated clinical concepts. For example, the SNOMED-CT model incorrectly infers
            that the documentation of “No myocardial infarction” in a patient implies that
            the patient has “No heart disease” whatsoever. A model that correctly handles
            subsumption testing over negated clinical concepts is required to support
            correct (and safe) inferencing in electronic health records.</para>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Potential Problems and Issues</title>
        <para>Although it helps to solve the problems described Section <xref
            linkend="_Ref493868573"/>, the models presented in this paper for consolidating
            “Findings” and “Observable Entities” into “Phenomena” and for normalizing the
            representation and querying of negated phenomena also entail certain challenges and
            limitations.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Negative Values for Phenomena</title>
            <para>The model does not allow interval values that include negative real numbers. In
                rare cases, clinical phenomena require such values, for example the phenomenon of
                “Max ST deflection” in an EKG, which can be either positive or negative.</para>
            <para>A potential solution in these cases is to change the modeling of certain phenomena
                so that they only take on positive numeric values. In the example above, this
                strategy would entail the specification of separate phenomena for “Max ST
                depression” and “Max ST elevation”. Further work is required to determine how often
                phenomena with negative values occur and whether the proposed strategy is effective
                is all such cases. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Values from Enumerated Value Sets that are not Numeric or not Ordinal</title>
            <para>Certain clinical phenomena have values that are simply not numeric, and to which
                the model for representing and processing interval values does not cleanly apply.
                The following phenomena and their corresponding enumerated value sets illustrate
                this point.</para>
            <para>Eye-Color: Values = (Blue, Green, Brown, Black, … )</para>
            <para>Eye-Color : Values = (1=Blue, 2=Green, 3=Brown, 4=Black, … )</para>
            <para>Dysphagia: Values = (never, rarely, sometimes, frequently, always)</para>
            <para>Patellar tendon reflex: Values = (1+, 2+, 3+, 4+)</para>
            <para>To address the reality of such observations in the medical record, the assignment
                of interval values may need to be limited to only those phenomena whose values are
                naturally numeric or can be characterized as present, absent, or indeterminate (for
                which interval values are defined). An alternative would be to always assign such
                phenomena the interval value “(0,∞]” (Present), and denote the property values using
                a different attribute (such as “color”, “frequency”, of “intensity” in the cases
                above).</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Units of Measure for Non-Quantitative Values</title>
            <para>Consolidating “Findings” and “Observable Entities” allows the use of a numeric
                interval value to denote the presence or absence of clinical observations that
                wouldn’t otherwise have numeric values, such as “nausea” or “dizziness.” Interval
                values also allow one to denote the presence and the cardinality of certain clinical
                phenomena using a single value, such as for “Daily cigarette use” or “Pressure
                ulcers”.</para>
            <para>In both situations however, there is no natural unit of measure to associate with
                the interval values. To the degree that there’s benefit in consistently assigning a
                unit of measure to all values, this void presents a problem.</para>
            <para>A possible solution is to have a “null” unit of measure, indicating that the value
                is not associated with any unit of measure. This strategy may not be unfamiliar to
                data modelers and data analysts, in that certain LOINC lab codes already include
                such a designation (such as for Urine Specific Gravity, a dimensionless
                measurement). Alternatively, one could create special-purpose units of measure to
                associate with dimensionless values. Again, this strategy has been adopted for
                certain LOINC lab codes, such as pH (which includes a special “[pH]” unit of
                measure) or manual cell count (which includes the special “per high powered field”
                unit of measure).</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Subsumption over all Refining Attributes of Phenomena</title>
            <para>As described in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493858870"/>, correct application of
                the tri-valued model for querying phenomena requires that interval values be
                assigned to the entirety of each phenomenon (including all of its refining
                attributes). Further, the correct applications of the axioms in Section <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493866647"/> also require that subsumption testing between
                phenomenon (i.e., application of the “Is-A()” predicate within these axioms) include
                all of the refining attributes to which interval values have been assigned. If
                subsumption testing is performed using only a subset of the attributes to which
                interval values are assigned, the axioms will produce incorrect results.</para>
            <para>The point is illustrated through several examples shown in <xref
                linkend="_Ref493941874kec"/>. </para>
            <para>Note, for example, that if subsumption testing between phenomenon 1 and phenomenon
                3 excludes the “Observation-Date” value in phenomenon 3, and “Observation-Date” is
                within the scope of the attributes to which the interval value “[2,2]” has been
                assigned, then phenomenon 3 will be subsumed by phenomenon 1 and the axioms of
                Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> will infer that phenomenon 1 is present.
                However, upon inspection, it is clear that the presence of two pressure ulcers in
                the right leg on Oct. 4, 2017 does not necessarily imply the presence of any
                pressure ulcers on July 7, 2017. Subsumption testing that correctly included the
                “Observation-Date” attribute would have prevented this incorrect inference and
                concluded that the existence of pressure ulcers on July 7, 2017 was indeterminate
                based on the available data.</para>
            <para>Similarly, if subsumption testing between phenomenon 5 and phenomenon 2 excludes
                the “Laterality” attribute of the anatomical location of phenomenon 5 (a nested
                attribute), and “Laterality” is within the scope of the attributes to which the
                interval value “[0,0]” has been assigned, then phenomenon 5 will be subsumed by
                phenomenon 2 and the axioms of Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> will infer
                that phenomenon 5 is absent. Again, however, intuition should make clear that the
                absence of a pressure ulcer on left leg on July 18, 2017 does not necessarily imply
                the absence of a pressure on the right leg on that same date. Inclusion of the
                “Laterality” attribute in the subsumption test would have prevented this incorrect
                inference, and caused the axioms of Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> to
                conclude that the presence of a stage-2 pressure ulcer in the right leg on that date
                was indeterminate based on the data.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref493941874kec">
                <title>Examples of correct and incorrect application of subsumption testing
                    involving post-coordinated phenomena.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/correct-and-incorrect-subsumption.png"
                            scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The point of these examples is to underscore the importance of including all of
                the refining attributes to which interval values are assigned in any subsumption
                tests that are later performed. In practice, however, this may not be a trivial
                undertaking. For example, subsumption testing between date values of different
                granularities (year vs. month vs. day) is not supported by standard description
                logic reasoners, so that a phenomenon observed in July 2017 may not correctly
                subsume the same observation observed on July 12, 2017. Further, the correct
                semantics of subsumption between date values when assigned to clinical observations
                may not be straightforward. For example, assigning an Observation-Date value of
                “July 2017” to a phenomenon could mean that the phenomenon was observed at
                <emphasis>some point</emphasis> in July 2017, or it could mean that the
                phenomenon was observed throughout the duration of July 2017. The intended meaning
                has implications for whether a phenomenon with the Observation-Date value of “July
                2017” should subsume a phenomenon with the Observation-Date value of “July 18, 2017”
                with respect to the application of the axioms in Section <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493866647"/>.</para>
            <para>Similar questions arise regarding the scope of attributes to which interval values
                should be assigned, and which ones comprise refining attributes of the phenomenon
                itself (such as laterality, observation-date, severity, etc.), and which ones
                comprise meta-attributes that do not refine the phenomenon (such as identity of the
                observer, method of observation, purpose of the observation, etc.). Strictly
                speaking, meta-attributes should be excluded from the scope of interval-value
                assignments and (therefore) from subsumption testing, but in certain cases it may
                not be clear which attributes are truly refining attributes and which are meta-data,
                and that distinction may even be context specific. For example, method of
                observation may be a significant attribute of the observed phenomenon in certain
                cases, but not others. All of these issues remain to be examined and resolved before
                one can correctly and reliably apply the models presented here.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>“Cognitive Dissonance”</title>
            <para>The final challenge in using the models described here is the unintuitive nature
                of representing the values of all clinical observations using numeric intervals, as
                formalized in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493843805"/>. The notion that entirely
                qualitative clinical observations such as “nausea” and “dizziness” have quantitative
                interval values may be difficult for those implementing and working with the
                proposed model to grasp and accept. Similarly, the model produces certain
                unintuitive characterizations of clinical observations that only have numeric
                values, such as the conclusion that a “Serum Potassium” observation is “Present” if
                it’s value is &gt; 0, and otherwise is “Absent”. It remains to be seen whether those
                using the model can overcome potential “cognitive dissonance” in encountering such
                implications.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_42c69960-bcd0-49a5-ad2b-3dbf1bfd68e9">
        <title>Compound Clinical Statements: Separable vs. Inseparable Components</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Discussion:</emphasis></para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Do we think of clinical statements with “values” only as numerical
                    values? Or would other statements be considered having values,
                    e.g.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patient position = sitting</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Priority = routine</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Route of Administration = sublingual</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>If statements can have values other than numerical values, the BP use case
            could look like the example below:</para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="43*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="31*"/>
                <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="26*"/>
                <tbody valign="top">
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">USE CASE</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">SEPARABLE
                                STATEMENTS</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">INSEPARABLE
                                COMPONENTS</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry morerows="6" valign="middle">
                            <para>BP of 120/80 mmHg on right brachial artery, patient in
                                sitting position for at least 5 min., using adult BP cuff,
                                urinary bladder voided within 30 min. before
                                measurement</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Systolic BP = 120 mmHg</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Diastolic BP = 80 mmHg</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Time since last urination = 30 min. or less</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Measurement body site = right brachial artery</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Device used = adult cuff</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Body position = sitting</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Sitting time before measurement = 5 min. or more</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>The “panel” above would consist of the following statements:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Systolic BP = 120 mmHg</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Diastolic BP = 80 mmHg</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Time since last urination = 30 min. or less</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Measurement body site = right brachial artery</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Device used = adult cuff</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Body position = sitting</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Time in sitting position = 5 min. or longer</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>If statements can have values other than numerical values, the Medication use
            case could look like the example below:</para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="43*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="31*"/>
                <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="26*"/>
                <tbody valign="top">
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">USE CASE</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">SEPARABLE
                                STATEMENTS</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">INSEPARABLE
                                COMPONENTS</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry morerows="6" valign="middle">
                            <para>Administration of nitroglycerin 0.4 mg tablet sub-lingual
                                every 5 minutes as needed for chest pain; maximum 3 tablets
                                (routine)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Strength = 0.4 mg</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Administration</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Frequency = every 5 minutes </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Nitroglycerin</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Maximum dosage = 3 tablets</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>As needed</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Dose form = tablet</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Route of Administration = sublingual</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Indication = Chest pain</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry valign="bottom">
                            <para>Priority = Routine</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry valign="bottom"/>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>The “panel” above would consist of the following statements:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Administration of nitroglycerin as needed</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Medication strength = 0.4 mg</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Frequency = every 5 minutes</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Maximum dosage = 3 tablets</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Dose form = tablet</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Route of Administration = sublingual</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Indication = chest pain</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Priority = routine</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>After discussion, decision was made to only define separable components as
            components with numerical or pseudo-numerical values and components, that can
            have present/absent values, if these are directly related to the focus of the
            statement. </para>
    </section>
</appendix>
