<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Data Registries</title>
    <para>Data registries are organised systems with a 'predetermined scientific, clinical or public
        health purpose.' Data registries are used to prospectively collect, analyse and disseminate
        data related to a population with specific characteristics in common, for example people
        with a particular condition, having a certain treatment or using a health-related service.
        They are cohort studies that are developed with a predetermined health-related aim.</para>
    <para>Registry limitations:<footnote>
            <para><link
                    xlink:href="https://rwe-navigator.eu/use-real-world-evidence/sources-of-real-world-data/patient-registries/"
                /></para>
        </footnote>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Quality of data and methods</emphasis>:
                                patient registries are only as good as the underlying data
                                collection and methods. It is critical that the research design is
                                robust and the relevant outcomes are defined appropriately.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Incorrect or missing data</emphasis>:
                                problems with remembering information or recalling information
                                correctly can be an issue with patient-reported data.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Confounding and bias</emphasis>: there may
                                be issues such as channeling bias to newer treatments for sicker
                                patients, information bias and selection bias.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Heavy investment in time and
                                    resources</emphasis>: commitment and engagement are needed from
                                participating patients. It can be difficult to recruit patients and
                                it can take time to accumulate data, resulting in delays between
                                data collection and reporting (sometimes years). Such data can
                                become out of date in fast-changing disease areas.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Lack of standards and uniformity</emphasis>:
                                lack of standardised data collection across hospitals, regions and
                                countries prevents the pooling of data across registries.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Lack of comparator</emphasis>: in
                                product-specific registries having no comparator prevents assessment
                                of relative effectiveness.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
</chapter>
