<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>From Information to Knowledge</title>
    <para>In this chapter we aim to walk through a "round trip" use case that illustrates how
        information flows from structured clinical input (using clinical concepts from the
        terminology and foundational layers), to a logical representation modeled in analysis normal
        form, to storage in a data repository, and then to a query for decision support. </para>
    <para>The example that we will illustrate is hypertension disability benefits for veterans. If a
        veteran's hypertension is related to his/her time in service, then he/she may be eligible
        for VA disability benefits. </para>
    <para>The Department of Veterans Affairs utilizes a hypertension VA disability benefits
        questionnaire for clinicians to complete. The questionnaire states that “for the VA
        disability rating purpose, the term hypertension means that the diastolic pressure is
        predominantly 90mm or greater, and isolated systolic hypertension means that the systolic
        blood pressure is predominantly 160mm or greater with a diastolic blood pressure of less
        than 90 mm.”</para>
    <para><link xlink:href="https://www.vba.va.gov/pubs/forms/VBA-21-0960A-3-ARE.pdf">See
            questionnaire by clicking here.</link></para>
    <para>For VA purposes, the initial diagnosis of hypertension or isolated systolic hypertension
        must be confirmed by readings taken two or more times on at least three different days.
        Blood pressure results may be obtained from existing medical records or through scheduled
        visits for blood pressure measurements.</para>
    <para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The first question of the hypertension VA disability benefits questionnaire,
                    question 1A asks “does the
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190806T091219-0600" comment="Previously in this section, &quot;Veteran&quot; was capitalized.  Recommend being consistent.  " flag="done"?>veteran<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    now have or has he or she ever been diagnosed with hypertension or isolated
                    systolic hypertension?”</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Question 2A relates to the veteran’s history with hypertension. Here the VA
                    asks the clinician to “describe the history, including the onset and course, of
                    the veteran’s hypertension condition.”</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Section 3 relates to other pertinent physical findings, complications, and
                    conditions of the veteran’s hypertension.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Section 4 of the hypertension VA disability benefits questionnaire is about
                    the functional impact of hypertension on the veteran. Here the VA asks, “does
                    the veteran’s hypertension or isolated systolic hypertension impact his or her
                    ability to work?” </para>
                <para>Clinicians at VA will then enter these data from the questionnaires and
                    represent them as "clinical statements" into VA’s EHR. This data entry (i.e.,
                    structured clinical input) will depend on the manner in which the information is
                    presented to the clinicians and how they enter the data, such as by constraining
                    the information to allow only certain values to be entered, e.g. through a
                    drop-down list, radio buttons, or breaking up large chunks of related
                    information into smaller parts. Therefore, clinicians at different VA Medical
                    Centers may enter the same data from the hypertension disability questionnaire
                    in different formats. Furthermore, there may be additional variation based on
                    whether clinicians choose to use ICD-10-CM to represent a hypertension diagnosis
                    or whether they choose to use a code from SNOMED CT. </para>
                <para>To help reduce this variation, informaticists and terminologists may model
                    these clinical statements using a logical model, such as the latest models from
                    CIMI, or perhaps by using Analysis Normal Form (ANF). [insert hyperlink to ANF
                    example for hypertension in statement chapter]</para>
                <para>From an aggregated data standpoint, the VA will want to enable processes that
                    normalize every representational format that confers the same meaning as being
                    equivalent. These equivalent representations of the information coming from the
                    hypertension questionnaire will then be stored in VA's data repository and made
                    available for information exchange, retrieval, and querying for clinical
                    decision support (CDS). The goal at a large integrated health system like the VA
                    is to normalize the data in the data repository so that queries and clincal
                    decision support expression logic can be shareable and re-usable across every
                    medical center, clinic, provider, and patient. </para>
                <para>One of the overarching challenges of standards that aim to make CDS shareable
                    and interoperable is that there currently is not a robust way to associate rules
                    in knowledge-based systems with other dependencies in clinical data
                    representation systems to ensure proper operation. For example in the
                    hypertension disability questionnaire, a CDS alert may be configured to fire if
                    a patient's BP is greater than or equal to
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190903T153104-0600" comment="Is this correct?  Should it be 160/90? I didn&apos;t see the questionnaire reference 140 at all." id="ybt_3jb_z3b" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190905T144308-0500" comment="Correct.  This has been changed." parentID="ybt_3jb_z3b" flag="done" mid="2"?>160/90<?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
                    at a recent encounter. The same alert may also fire based on the presence of a
                    SNOMED CT or ICD-10-CM code in a patient's encounter diagnosis or problem list.
                    The same alert may also fire based on the presence of 1 or more
                    anti-hypertensive medications present in the patient's record. All of the
                    underlying expression-logic behind this alert, and the terminologies utilized to
                    represent the labs, diagnoses, and medications need to be configured in a
                    controlled manner. </para>
                <para>Current CDS standards are silent on the notion of identifying a safe
                    configuration of dependencies between (a) the expression-logic for rules-based
                    CDS techniques, (b) the value sets with codes and terms to define clinical
                    concepts of interest contained in the CDS rules, and (c) the variability of how
                    clinical data within the value sets and rules are inputted, modeled, and stored
                    in data repositories. </para>
                <para> </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>
</chapter>

