<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Solor Architecture</title>
    <section>
        <title>Versioning Overview</title>
        <para/>
        <para>When dealing with the complexities of the various layers of the informatics
            architectural separation of concerns, one of the most important things to note is that
            any one of Solor's architectural layers will be undergoing modifications at any given
            point in time, as various Standards Development Organizations go through each of their
            various drafting, balloting, and approval lifecycles. Therefore it is important to
            establish as a foundation for Solor a versioning and modularity architecture that allows
            changes and subchanges to be referenced uniquely so that all parties can be on the same
            page as to a particular version.</para>
        <para/>
        <para>For example, the following diagram shows how each module could be given a unique
            version number and contain all layers of the architectural stack. In the instance that a
            particular versioned module needs to be extended, an extension module could be added to
            that main versioned module without the need to go to a completely new full module
            version. This arrangement accounts for the constant change in the healthcare
            interoperability space while still allowing two organizations to baseline on the same
            version for testing or exchange purposes (i.e. Module M13, Extension E25)</para>
        <para/>
        <figure>
            <title>Versioning; Modules and Extensions</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/modules_and_extensions_r3.jpg" scale="50"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Architecture</title>
        <para>An interoperable, integrated terminology model concerns (a) the foundation and
            building blocks of the common model; (b) how the transformation process of disparate
            standards into the common model is made repeatable and interoperable with other
            environments; and, (c) how the modules of the common model are tightly versioned
            controlled over time. </para>
        <para>In this chapter we are concerned with detailing Solor’s architectural foundation that
            will support semantic interoperability. We achieve this foundation in two ways:</para>
        <para>1. Use of SNOMED CT, RxNorm, and LOINC as the primary building blocks for the
            foundational architecture (more on this in chapter 3).</para>
        <para>2. Enablement of semantic operability within the foundational architecture through
            normalization of representation and achieving coherence within and among the primary
            building blocks of the architecture.</para>
        <para/>
        <para>Solor is an ecosystem that allows users to import, transform, and view content from
            disparate medical terminologies, all in one common model. Users can navigate and search
            Solor content, view details of the data elements, and select specific concepts to view
            more information. As Solor is open-source, developers are encouraged to build on top of
            existing functionalities.</para>
        <para>We adopted contemporary software principles to create a multilayered architecture for
            integrating standard medical terminologies. We sought to adhere to three main principles
            in our architectural design: (a) to store concepts from medical terminologies so that
            one could apply classifiers and identifiers; (b) to allow for versioning and updates
            over time in a way that preserved concept orientation; and, (c) to promote
            collaborative, distributive workflows for developers. </para>
        <section><title>Building Blocks</title><para>Solor has two fundamental building blocks:
                concepts and semantics. Concept is defined as an idea or a general notion. When
                abstracted out, it can be used to represent any idea, whether that is a medically
                related idea (e.g., heart attack) or an idea to represent metadata (e.g., a synonym
                or a fully specified name). A semantic enables addition of semantic data to the
                underlying concept’s content, in a standardized way that provides for the same means
                of identifying, modularizing, and versioning. In other words, a semantic is attached
                to a concept to provide contextual meaning to the concept. Semantics can be grouped
                together in a collection to form an ‘assemblage’. An assemblage consists of
                semantics that reference a component and provide additional data to that member for
                some purpose. Solor also has ‘description semantics’ with additional metadata
                specifying details including but not limited to ‘language’ and ‘description
                type’.</para><para><emphasis role="bold">Concept:</emphasis> represents any idea,
                whether that is medically related (e.g., heart attack) or metadata (e.g.,
                author)</para> •Fields: Universally Unique ID <para><emphasis role="bold">String
                    Semantic:</emphasis> provides identifier to the concept in a standardized
                way</para> •Fields: Source Terminology Code <para><emphasis role="bold">Description
                    Semantic</emphasis>: provides a human-readable description</para> •Fields:
            Fully-Specified Name, Long Common Name, Short Name, and Display Name <para><emphasis
                    role="bold">Logic Graph Semantic</emphasis>: provides description logic for
                traversing hierarchies and for specifiying the view of the relationships between and
                amongst data elements </para>•Fields: Parent-child-sibling relationship <para><emphasis role="bold"
                    >Assemblage</emphasis>: Grouping set (i.e., “assemblage”) specifically created
                to store all of the data elements, data types, and metadata for a particular use
                case</para> •Fields: Variable to accommodate a variety of use cases. For
                instance,
                [<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T084629-0700" comment=" Would it be better to revise this to StringA, StringB, StringC, StringD)?" flag="done"?>String<?oxy_comment_end?>A,
                    StringB, StringC, StringD], [ID, String, Integer, Concept ]  <figure>
                        <title>Solor Common Model Content</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/common_model.png" scalefit="1"
                                    width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></section>
        <section>
            <title>Transformation Overview</title>
            <para>After a standards developer releases its content, a process will need to occur to
                transform data from its native format into Solor components. This programmatic
                process is tailored to each incoming data stream, where it will account for data
                represented in its original format. Other than
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T102621-0700" comment="Should this be &quot;transforming&quot; instead?" flag="done"?>transform<?oxy_comment_end?>ing
                and applying versioning coordinates, the underlying process will also address the
                notion of dependency. For example, SNOMED US Extension will have a dependency on
                SNOMED International, and relationships from the LOINC-SNOMED collaboration effort
                will have a dependency on SNOMED and LOINC. </para>
            <para>Once the content is in Solor, there is a step where equivalency is determined
                through various methods where concepts of the same idea are aggregated. For example,
                Gentamycin from SNOMED is the same as Gentamycin from LOINC, and is also the same
                Gentamycin from RxNorm. The end result from this process is the creation of a Solor
                concept that is devoid of any source information (but will have traceability). This
                end result is what will be exposed to the user to view and use. In the Gentamycin
                example, a user will find this concept that is devoid of any source information and
                will not need to know if this is the SNOMED/LOINC/RxNorm Gentamycin that needs to be
                selected. If the Gentamycin concept was used in the context of identifying what
                medication the patient is currently taking, then the underlying process will be able
                to transmit the RxNorm code if the receiving system is expecting RxNorm codes.
                Conversely, if Solor were adopted more universally, the transmitted information
                could be isolated to the Solor Gentamycin rather than a distinct code from a
                specific terminology. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Identifiable Components</title>
            <para>A universally unique identifier (UUID) is a 128-bit number used to identify
                information in computer systems.(ref] ) The identifiable component layer of Solor
                manages the reproducible assignment of UUIDs to all imported components as well as
                the assignment of primordial UUIDs to all internally generated components. If
                imported components already provide UUIDs to identify components, those UUIDs will
                be used. The identifiable component layer must allow components to have more than
                one UUID identifier, and if previously independent components are given each other’s
                identifiers as alternate identifiers, the identifiable component layer must
                dynamically merge the parts of these previously distinct components into a single
                integrated component. This merging of components by merging identifiers is a simple
                means for managing duplicated content as it is identified.</para>
            <para>
                <link linkend="_msoanchor_1">[CR(-A1]</link><link
                    xlink:href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4122"
                    >http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4122</link>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Chronology</title>
            <section>
                <title>STAMP Coordinate</title>
                <para>The chronology component of the architecture layer provides a means to
                    generically represent the revisions to a component over time, and to index those
                    revisions by status (e.g., active, inactive), effective time of change, author
                    of change, module within which the change occurred (international edition, US
                    extension, etc.), and the development path of the change (development, release
                    candidate, etc.). Taken together, these fields can be referred to as a version’s
                    STAMP
                    (<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T103043-0700" comment="Why does the diagram below in the STAMP column refer to &quot;state&quot; vs. &quot;status&quot;?" flag="done"?>status<?oxy_comment_end?>,
                    time, author, module, and path). STAMP provides a foundation for version control
                    and configuration management of all the components of the information
                    architecture. The STAMP will provide a means to modularize content so that
                    modules can be turned on and off depending on specific use cases, and that
                    modular content can be developed independently from unrelated modules. This
                    modularity will enable simplified development and quality assurance processes
                    for each module. The following figure shows the UML representation of Solor’s
                    chronology layer on the left, and that of STAMP on the right.</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Chronology and STAMP</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/stamp_chronology_2.png" scalefit="1"
                                width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>There are also more nuanced components within Status, Time, Author, Module,
                    and Path that can be configured. These include: ‘Allowed States’ (related to
                    Status), precedence, and the ability to specify groups of modules in a ‘Module
                    Set’. Precedence can be set to stratify the mathematical constructs surrounding
                    the components (e.g., path, time) so that one component can be prioritized over
                    the other. </para>
                <para>In summary, STAMP provides a high degree of configuration for navigating
                    versions of content and how that content may be interacted within the Solor
                    ecosystem. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Language Coordinate</title>
                <para>The language coordinate provides the ability to configure details around what
                    language of content to provide, and to select a particular dialect, and/or the
                    order of dialects available in the Solor ecosystem. This also provides the
                    ability for users to get the exact level of granularity of content they desire.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Logic Coordinate</title>
                <para>The logic coordinate allows configuration of description logics and formal
                    knowledge representation of Solor content. The fundamental modeling concept is
                    an axiom—a logical statement relating roles and/or concepts. Within the
                    l<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T141831-0700" comment="WIthin this same paragraph, why is this sometimes capitalized and sometimes it&apos;s not?  Same for Manifold Coordinate section below.  I think you should be consistent when referring to them." flag="done"?>ogic<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    coordinate, users can specify which classifier to use (e.g., Snorocket), and
                    which concepts they want to
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T141858-0700" comment="Should this be &quot;classify&quot;?" flag="done"?>classif<?oxy_comment_end?>y
                    in their given use case (e.g., Solor content vs. Health content). Users can also
                    specify how they want to configure the stated and inferred parent-child
                    (supertype-subtype) relationships that are either available in the source
                    terminology native logic, or through
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T142004-0700" comment="Recommend adding &quot;through&quot; between &quot;or&quot; and &quot;additional&quot;." flag="done"?>additional<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    integration provided by the Solor common model. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Manifold Coordinate</title>
                <para>In order to easily exchange the complex configurations of facets of the Solor
                    common model, we need a unifying object to do that. The Manifold Coordinate
                    restricts the instantiation of the configurations of the STAMP coordinate,
                    Language Coordinate, and Logic Coordinate to one object, and provides a global
                    access point to it (i.e., Singleton design pattern). In other words, it acts as
                    an abstraction layer between the nuanced configurability of the other
                    coordinates, and how it is ultimately executed with the Solor ecosystem is used.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>FLWOR </title>
                <para>FLWOR is an acronym for "For, Let, Where, Order by, Return". The programming
                    language <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery">XQuery</link>
                    defines FLWOR as an expression that supports iteration and binding of variables
                    to intermediate results. FLWOR is loosely analogous to <link
                        xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL">SQL</link>'s <link
                        xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Select_(SQL)"
                        >SELECT-FROM-WHERE</link> and can be used to provide join-like functionality
                    to <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML">navigating</link>
                    content.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <emphasis role="bold">For</emphasis>
                        <para> - selects a sequence of nodes</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Let</emphasis>
                        <para> - binds a sequence to a variable</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Where</emphasis>
                        <para> - filters the nodes</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Order by</emphasis>
                        <para> - sorts the nodes</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Return</emphasis>
                        <para> - what to return (gets evaluated once for every node)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>The advanced version control and modularity provided by the Solor Architecture
                    is embedded within a FLWOR framework. This allows for complex querying
                    capabilities to navigate and search for concepts, data elements, metadata, the
                    relationships between and amongst these data elements, and how they change over
                    time and/or differ between and amongst the modules. The complexities of these
                    queries are abstracted into a user-friendly graphical user-interface, and users
                    are provided precise options for configuring their queries and use cases.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Challenges</title>
        <para>Solor is an integrated clinical transformation process to represent and bring together
            disparate terminology standards by using a single model that can encompass any
            customized content. In our experience with building the Solor semantic architecture and
            transformation process, we have come to understand that health IT systems must address
            the following antipatterns: </para>
        <section>
            <title>Accidental Complexity</title>
            <para>Accidental (or incidental) complexity is complexity that arises in computer
                programs or their development process that is non-essential to the problem to be
                solved. While essential complexity is inherent and unavoidable, accidental
                complexity is caused by the approach chosen to solve the problem. Some examples of
                accidental complexity as they relate to informatics are described in the following
                sections.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Semantic-laden Identifiers</title>
                <para>Solving a distributed identifier allocation problem by using namespaces that
                    are assigned to organizations (or committees in the case of HL7), semantics are
                    often introduced into the identifier, which some developers use to identify what
                    organization created the components that were associated with those identifiers.
                    Exposing derivable semantics in the identifier can lead to complexity when
                    users/developers demand that the semantics be maintained, which may result in
                    unnecessary retirement as described in the next section. Reliance on UUIDs
                    rather than on identifiers with derivable semantics would eliminate this
                    complexity.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Unnecessary Retirement</title>
                <para>An unintended side effect of using identified namespaces as part of
                    distributed identifier
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T143300-0700" comment="I don&apos;t think the comma is needed." flag="done"?>assignment<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    is an increase in the complexity of transferring responsibility for a component
                    from one organization to another. This complexity includes an elaborate sequence
                    of marking a component for retirement in one release, actually retiring it in a
                    subsequent release, and creating an essentially identical component with an
                    identifier derived from the new organization’s namespace. Furthermore, there is
                    the need for the creation of mapping solutions to keep historical relationships
                    between components retired for these reasons to the current concepts that
                    replace them. Again, reliance on UUIDs rather than on identifiers with derivable
                    semantics would eliminate this complexity.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Post-coordination</title>
                <para>Terminology models sometimes make it necessary to require post-coordination to
                    provide domain coverage at the point of care, however, the information models we
                    use in healthcare typically can’t handle post-coordination well. Reliance on the
                    information model to represent post-coordination has introduced complexity that
                    might be avoided if we used a dynamic means to assign unique identifiers to
                    post-coordinated expressions.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Accidental Complexity Solutions </title>
                <para>Accidental complexity must be minimized in any good architecture, design, and
                    implementation. Working in short iterations with ongoing design reviews may help
                    reduce accidental complexity. We must also develop an example implementation in
                    parallel with the architecture, so that complexity can be identified early, and
                    evaluated critically with respect to the essential or accidental nature of that
                    complexity.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Design by Committee</title>
            <para>A project that has many designers involved but no unifying plan or vision.</para>
            <section>
                <title>No Unifying Vision</title>
                <para>Design by committee is the result of having many contributors to a project,
                    but no unifying vision. A complex software design is the product of a committee
                    process. The design has so many features and variations that it is infeasible
                    for any group of developers to realize the specifications in a reasonable time
                    frame.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Interoperability at the Expense of Operability</title>
                <para>Interoperability provides an illusion of operability between disparate
                    systems, and therefore there is no need to standardize.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Design by Committee Solutions</title>
                <para>A solution to design by committee is to articulate a set of architectural
                    principles to which architectural components will be evaluated against, and to
                    have the committee be advisory to an architect that provides the unifying
                    vision.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Stovepipe</title>
            <para>The Stovepipe Enterprise antipattern is characterized by a lack of coordination
                and planning across a set of systems. If every subsystem has a unique interface,
                then the system is overly complex. Absence of common multisystem conventions is a
                key problem for systems. For example, currently, essentially no terminology systems
                are the same with regard to their representation and semantics, despite the
                requirement that they must work together.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Overlapping and unreconciled models</title>
                <para>SNOMED CT and LOINC are classic examples of two terminologies that are
                    proposed for common use in health IT, but that are not well coordinated, and
                    have unreconciled content (content that is not made consistent or compatible).
                    As an example of unreconciled content, SNOMED CT
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T144810-0700" comment="Recommend revising &quot;all&quot; to &quot;both&quot;." flag="done"?>and<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    LOINC both have representations for Amoxicillin. In LOINC, Amoxicillin is a
                    textual value in the has-component field of the concept:</para>
                <para> </para>
                <para>AMOXICILLIN [MASS/VOLUME] IN SERUM OR PLASMA</para>
                <para>HAS-COMPONENT: AMOXICILLIN</para>
                <para> </para>
                <para>While SNOMED CT has the concept:</para>
                <para> </para>
                <para>AMOXICILLIN MEASUREMENT (PROCEDURE)</para>
                <para>COMPONENT: AMOXICILLIN (SUBSTANCE)</para>
                <para> </para>
                <para>In SNOMED CT, Amoxicillin is also a concept, rather than just a text
                    value.</para>
                <para> </para>
                <para>From an end-user’s perspective, the artificial separation and uncoordinated
                    development of these important systems has been a burden. RxNorm may help bridge
                    the medication components of the overlap, but there are other overlapping
                    domains (method, type of scale, system, time aspect, and non-pharmaceutical
                    components) that RxNorm does not cover. The UMLS may help us formally reconcile
                    some of these other domains, but if coordination and reconciliation can be part
                    of the development processes for these sources, rather than a cleanup exercise
                    for implementers, we can allocate resources to solving more compelling
                    problems.</para>
                <para>We hope that the newly announced cooperative agreement between IHTSDO (owners
                    of SNOMED CT) and the Regenstrief Institute (owners of LOINC), and the NLM
                    (owners of RxNorm) will change the coordination of these systems in a
                    significantly helpful way. Although SNOMED CT and LOINC are classic examples of
                    overlapping and unreconciled models, there are many other examples. The UMLS
                    identifies over 150 sources, most of which are uncoordinated, and have
                    independent models. These overlapping and unreconciled models create an
                    unnecessary burden for the implementer.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Uncoordinated development</title>
                <para>Today, related components from different organizations do not share their work
                    prior to a release. The result of this lack of sharing is that dependent
                    components are always out of date with the latest release of the underlying
                    standard. For example, how can you keep a mapping of SNOMED CT to ICD-10-CM
                    components up to date, when it takes 6 months after the release of SNOMED CT to
                    update and quality assure the map? As an implementer, does that mean you should
                    wait 6 months for the map to be updated before deploying the latest SNOMED CT
                    release? What if the new SNOMED CT release contains new content that may improve
                    the diagnosis, treatment, or prevention of disease? Is it really acceptable to
                    delay implementation of the latest SNOMED CT release by 6 months while waiting
                    for dependent system components to be updated after the fact?</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Stovepipe solutions</title>
                <para>The primary solution for the stovepipe systems we are working with is to break
                    down the barriers that prevent collaborative development of content, tools,
                    processes, and ultimately architecture. Today, deployment delay is not a
                    significant issue because clinical decision support is relatively nascent, and
                    pharmacy, laboratory, and clinical systems are poorly integrated. However, if we
                    successfully create compelling decision support on an integrated and shareable
                    platform, coordination of development and release cycles among clinical
                    terminologies, logical representation, clinical facts, and clinical knowledge
                    bases will become increasingly important. We must prepare for success and work
                    to better coordinate development among dependent components.</para>
                <para>Here we propose leveraging opportunities that are helping to break down these
                    barriers. Those opportunities include acquisition and development of open-source
                    tooling. Improvements in open-source tooling will help break down collaborative
                    barriers significantly. Such improvement is a fundamental focus of our
                    architecture effort. The solution to the stovepipe antipattern is effective
                    collaboration without barriers of proprietary concern.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Summary</title>
        <para>Currently, medical terminologies come from different sources and are represented by
            disparate models. However, by using a common model that integrates these terminologies
            seamlessly, Solor's architectural layer can display content from different sources after
            the Solor transformation process. Users will consequently not need to burden themselves
            with unnecessary complexities, and can instead focus on the meaning of medical content.
            Built upon an architecture intended to facilitate semantic interoperability, Solor
            stores concepts with UUIDs and classifiers, is maintained by robust version control, and
            promotes modular, collaborative development. Next steps include developing a list of
            agency-specific and industry-specific use cases for Solor upon which a formative
            evaluation approach and data collection and analysis can be conducted.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
