<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Solor Intro</title>
<para>
                <table frame="border" border="1">
                    <caption>Current Motivation and Foundation Review</caption>
                    <col width="12%"/>
                    <col width="12%"/>
                    <col width="12%"/>
                    <col width="12%"/>
                    <col width="12%"/>
                    <col width="12%"/>
                    <col width="12%"/>
                    <col width="12%"/>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Section</th>
                            <th>Section Name</th>
                            <th>Description, Topics</th>
                            <th>Comments</th>
                            <th>Perspective</th>
                            <th>Readability</th>
                            <th>Intent/usefulness</th>
                            <th>Suggestion</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody align="left">
                        <tr>
                            <td>0.0</td>
                            <td>Preface</td>
                            <td>Definition of symbolic information, interpretational infrastructure. </td>
                            <td>At a very high-level this is what SOLOR is</td>
                            <td>High-level</td>
                            <td>Good, not too technical</td>
                            <td>Useful for orienting people to one of the goals of SOLOR which is to
                                provide a user-friendly way to navigate disparate content</td>
                            <td/>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>0.1</td>
                            <td>Motivation and foundation</td>
                            <td>Gaps in C-CDA citing whitepaper to call out gaps in adherence to
                                standard terminologies. The architectural stack is introduced. </td>
                            <td>Percent breakdown of gaps in C-CDA by source terminology. I think a
                                lot could be added to this section. </td>
                            <td>In the weeds, introduce SOLOR, define architectural stack</td>
                            <td>Okay, but if this is the first part people read we should set the
                                stage and introduce basic concepts</td>
                            <td>Why should people care about the remaining 400 pages?</td>
                            <td>Each of the layers in the architetural stack should be defined at a
                                high level. In defining SOLOR, we say it should be working hand in
                                hand with the clinical statement model, but the clinical statement
                                model is not yet defined. The current challenges that close the
                                section are broad and not well defined</td>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>1.0</td>
                            <td>SOLOR</td>
                            <td>Essential challenge of informatics and why we should care about
                                knowledge assets</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td>Technical, very high level about health informatics</td>
                            <td>Jargon heavy</td>
                            <td>Explain why we should care about foundational pro blems with
                                application of codes and terms .</td>
                            <td>Not clear what knowledge assets are. This section could be
                                simplfied. </td>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>1.1</td>
                            <td>The Menagerie</td>
                            <td>Defines health informatics architecture and says that there are many
                                disparate terminologies that are neither coordinated in their
                                authoring nor in their update process. </td>
                            <td/>
                            <td>Technical, very high level about health informatics</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                            <td>This section, as it is, should be named "Health Informatics
                                Architecture". If we want it to be about the menagerie then we
                                should define examples of disparate clinical terminologies in this
                                section. </td>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>1.2</td>
                            <td>Semantic Interoperability Architecture</td>
                            <td>Defines semantic interoperability architecture, but then goes on to
                                say that the purpose of this document is NOT to define semantic
                                interoperability but to define foundational interoperability. </td>
                            <td>Explains how SOLOR uses SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNORM to build coherent
                                architecture</td>
                            <td>Technical</td>
                            <td>Convoluted</td>
                            <td>The numbered bullet points highlight how SOLOR aims to build its
                                architecture at a high level</td>
                            <td/>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>1.3</td>
                            <td>Life Critical Systems (All)</td>
                            <td>SOLOR should support life-critical systems. This section goes on to
                                define many facets of life-critical systems. This is at a higher
                                level than the previous sections about health IT systems overall and
                                not specifically about architecture. </td>
                            <td/>
                            <td>Very high-level about life-critical systems and software</td>
                            <td>Flow could be better</td>
                            <td>Explain how SOLOR is useful in the grander scheme of things. </td>
                            <td>Give examples of how exactly SOLOR supports each of the sub-headers
                                in this section. </td>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>1.4</td>
                            <td>Architectural Challenges (All)</td>
                            <td>Challenges related to building architecture that supports
                                terminology models. Again, these are back in the weeds related to
                                architecture.</td>
                            <td>I like this section, but it should be later in Part 1</td>
                            <td>In the weeds about integrated terminology systems</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td>This is useful in highlighting that there there are challenges to
                                consider. </td>
                            <td>Move towards end of the section</td>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>1.5</td>
                            <td>SOLOR enabling milestones (All)</td>
                            <td>List of other efforts like UMLS, SNOMED CT etc. This is broader
                                again describing various terminologies and coordination efforts. </td>
                            <td>These should be defined earlier in the Menagerie in my opinion</td>
                            <td>In the weeds about terminology</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                            <td>Move into Menagerie section and abbreviate it?</td>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>1.6</td>
                            <td>Data Elements Modeling</td>
                            <td>Clinical data elements, how these relate to statements and how SOLOR
                                may help. This section on its own is a self-contained white paper.
                                This should be a separate section, out of place. </td>
                            <td>Defines data elements and their common attributes, goes on to
                                explain how SOLOR would assist. </td>
                            <td>Informatics-specific perspective </td>
                            <td>The section reads well but doesn’t fit in with the other topics</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td>This entire section seems out of place here</td>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>2.0</td>
                            <td>ISAAC</td>
                            <td>Architecture: definitions of foundational, interaction architecture.
                                The benefits of having layers in the architectural stack. </td>
                            <td>Good definitions, but should be grouped together with section 1.2
                                above. </td>
                            <td>Technical, in the weeds about SOLOR architecture</td>
                            <td>Jargon heavy but it's decent</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>2.5.1, 2.5.2</td>
                            <td>Benefits of derivable layers, Binding between layers</td>
                            <td>Benefits of derivable layers should probably go with the
                                introduction of the architectural diagram at the start of the
                                section.</td>
                            <td>Architecture</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>

                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>3.0</td>
                            <td>KOMET</td>
                            <td>This section is empty</td>
                            <td>Look at Frozen Compendium: 21, 9, Appendix A</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>
                            <td/>

                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Overview of current SIA part 1 structure</emphasis></para>
            <para> "The Preface is about symbolic info and interpretational infrastructure. The
                motivation section sets the stage by describing CCDA's and lack of mapping to
                terminologies. Integrated terminology model is needed. The motivation section then
                mentions the architectural stack and 2 broad challenges related to the architecural
                stack. </para>
            <para> The book starts with Chapter 1 called SOLOR with a description of the overall
                challenge of informatics and why we need improved systems for CDS, patient safety
                etc. Then the paper defines health informatics architecture, and points out the
                menagerie of various terminologies that are not coordinated in their processes.
                Next, the semantic interoperability architecture is introduced; however the scope of
                this document is to describe the foundational architecture NOT the semantic
                interoperability architecture. </para>
            <para> The following section introduces life-critical systems and how a foundational
                architecture is needed to save lives. </para>
            <para> Next, the text goes back into the details of architectural challenges related to
                terminology models. After this we get a description of various terminologies and
                coordination efforts that have enabled SOLOR. </para>
            <para> Chapter 2 brings us back to informatics architecture again, providing definitions
                of foundational and interaction architecture and the needs for the architectural
                layers. Then we dive into the benefits of the layers. </para>
            <para> Chapter 3 is reserved for KOMET which is blank. " </para>

            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommended SIA part 1 structure</emphasis></para>
            <para>
                <table frame="border" border="1">
                    <caption>Recommended Part 1 Structure</caption>
                    <col/>
                    <col width="50%"/>
                    <col width="50%"/>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Part</th>
                            <th>Section</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody align="left">
                        <tr>
                            <td>Preface</td>
                            <td/>
                            <td>The goal of this book to describe informatics architecture. Define
                                this at a high-level somehow. </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="5">0</td>
                            <td rowspan="5">
                                <para>Motivation and the Architectural Stack</para>
                            </td>
                            <td>Setting the stage, starting first with why informatics is of urgent
                                importantance for CDS and patient safety. Then, define the essential
                                challenges of informatics. Perhaps here mention that the scope of
                                this book is to define and explore informatics architecture.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Informatics Architecture: definitions of foundational, interaction
                                architecture etc. The benefits of having layers in the architectural
                                stack. </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Broadly introduce the architetectural stack and a overall defintion
                                of each. </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Life-critical systems need this sort of architectural stack upon
                                which they can save lives. </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>Design principle</para>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="7">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="4">Foundation Intro</td>
                            <td>Definitions for building blocks : concepts, semantics etc </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Introducing health informatics arch. and disparate terminologies.
                                Deep dive into SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm, UMLS etc. and how these
                                efforts are siloed. </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Introduce the notion of informatics architecture. Re-iterate the
                                fact that this chapter focuses on the foundational level of the
                                stack. </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Description of Foundational Layer: [this is a bit of a black box to
                                me]</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="2">SOLOR back-end</td>
                            <td>SOLOR' Architecture will help provide an integrated model. Describe
                                the transformation process, chornology process. </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Architectural Challenges we must address</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>SOLOR front-end</td>
                            <td>KOMET: Knowledge management enviornment is the user-interface to the
                                front-end. Define user-interface principles, DevOps processes. </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommended Part 1 (Opening) structure</emphasis></para>
            <para>PREFACE</para>
            <para>States the goals to explore informatics architecture. </para>
            <para>MOTIVATION </para>
            <para>Begin by highlighting medical errors and how health IT can assist and save lives.
                Then, the essential challenge of informatics is defined and discussed which has
                limited our ability to truly be effective. In this book we will define and explore
                informatics architecture. </para>
            <para>Definitions for informatics architecture: what is foundational architecture and
                interaction architecure. Introduce the architectural stack and overall defintiion of
                each layer. Discuss the benefits of a architectural stack composed of layers. </para>
            <para> FOUNDATION </para>
            <para>Define building blocks of foundational/semantic informatics: concepts, semantics,
                etc. Then introduce and describe health informatics architecture, including the
                landscape of disparate terminologies. Describe SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm, and efforts
                like UMLS are siloed. </para>
            <para> RE-introduce the notion of informatics architecture. Re-iterate that this chapter
                is about the foundational level of the stack. The description of the foundational
                layer will follow [this is a black box to me]. </para>
            <para> The section that follows will include SOLOR and how it helps the foundational
                layer. SOLOR's architecure and architectural challenges that remain to be solved
                will be dicussed. Finally, SOLOR's front-end knowledge management enivornment will
                be described, including important design elements that were incorporated. " </para>
            <para>–––––––––––––––––––––––––––</para>
            <para>A recent whitepaper<footnote>
                    <para>John D. Amore, et. al; “Interoperability Progress and Remaining Data
                        Quality Barriers of Certified Health Information Technologies”, July 6,
                        2018</para>
                </footnote> cited that great strides have been made in healthcare data
                interoperability in the past decade…the vast majority of clinicians and patients
                have access to some portion of their health data in electronic format, thanks to the
                proliferation of electronic health record (EHR) systems installed in clinical care
                environments. The data in these EHRs usually follow HL7’s Consolidated Clinical
                Document Architecture (C-CDA) as it has become the generally accepted primary data
                standard for structured clinical data exchange.</para>

            <para>However, the whitepaper also found that significant gaps exist in the accurate
                encoding of the data contained in those C-CDA documents – in an analysis conducted
                of C-CDA documents produced by various EHR vendors and clinical organizations, the
                four most frequent problems identified as part of this analysis were that
                medications should be encoded in RxNorm (frequency of medication appearing in 13.7%
                of sampled test case documents), vital signs and results should use LOINC (9.2% of
                sampled documents), vital signs, and results should use unified code of units of
                measure (UCUM) for physical values (8.7% of sampled documents) and the inclusion of
                conflicting status information for medications (6.7% of sampled documents)<footnote>
                    <para>Ibid, Page 6</para>
                </footnote>.</para>
            <para> These issues can have a direct impact on patient safety and point to the need to
                be able to consistently represent and encode clinical data and observations. This is
                the next great challenge to conquer for health data interoperability to positively
                influence patient outcomes nationwide through clinical decision support. </para>
            <para> SOLOR (System of Logical Representation) is an effort that is directly tackling
                these issues of representation. SOLOR is an integrated medical terminology system,
                based on the overlapping but distinct terminology systems of SNOMED, LOINC and
                RxNorm. SOLOR was designed to unambiguously define what can be measured (concepts).
                Working hand in hand with SOLOR, there needs to be a clinical statement model, of
                which there are quite a few (HL7 FHIR, CIMI, ANF) which defines how to record a
                measurement. Measurements may be quantitative or existential. </para>
            <para>The following diagram shows how SOLOR and clinical statement models are
                interrelated in the architectural stack: <figure>
                    <title>Architectural Stack - proposed new graphics</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Architectural_layers_2.png" align="center"
                                scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>–––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––</para>
            <annotation>
                <para>Proposal: <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Reverse the order of the blocks as we are reading top to
                                bottom.</para>
                            <para>Language -> ... -> Procedural</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                            <para>Remove all the 'curved arrows' to reduce complexity</para>
                            <para>Perhaps when we reach Procedural section, we can introduce the
                                top-down view and reintroduce the graphics with curved arrow</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>For this Motivation and Foundation section, write to what Keith
                                presented - describe each layer at a high level, and get into more
                                granular layer in each subsequent section</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </para>
            </annotation>

            <para>––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––</para>
            <annotation>
                <para>Recommend taking this para out</para>
            </annotation>
            <para> Current challenges include the following: <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Further tooling and guidance need to be developed to be able to show
                            how concepts can be modeled in SOLOR and particular statement models
                            applied</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Gaps need to be addressed in the various statement models in terms of
                            representing measurements consistently, especially with existential
                            (non-quantitative) measurements</para>
                        <para>ab</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>

</chapter>