<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>SOLOR Foundation</title>
    <para/>
    <para>When dealing with the complexities of the various architectural layers, one of the most
        important things to note is that any one of SOLOR's architectural layers will be undergoing
        modifications at any given point in time, as various Standards Development Organizations go
        through each of their various drafting, balloting, and approval lifecycles. Therefore it is
        important to establish as a foundation for SOLOR a versioning and modularity architecture
        that allows changes and subchanges to be referenced uniquely so that all parties can be on
        the same page as to a particular version.</para>
    <para/>
    <para>For example, the following diagram shows how each module could be given a unique version
        number and contain all layers of the architectural stack. In the instance that a particular
        versioned module needs to be extended, an extension module could be added to that main
        versioned module without the need to go to a completely new full module version. This
        arrangement accounts for the constant change in the healthcare interoperability space while
        still allowing two organizations to baseline on the same version for testing or exchange
        purposes (i.e. Module M13, Extension E25)</para>
    <para/>
    <figure>
        <title>Versioning; Modules and Extensions</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/modules_and_extensions_r2.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
</chapter>
