<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Solor Assertional Knowledge</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Previously we discussed definitional knowledge which defines purely structural
            relationships among concepts. Definitional knowledge relationships do not represent how
            concepts influence or relate to each other in a clinical setting. This type of
            information is represented by assertional knowledge. For example, shortness of breath
            may be caused by myocardial infarction.</para>
        <para>Assertional knowledge represents facts related to a domain of study and is used to
            provide nuance and context to a concept, but does not define it. For example, Aspirin is
            used to treat pain, but it can also be used to treat fevers, prevent blood clots, reduce
            the risk of stroke and heart attack and many other things. The two major goals of
            including assertional knowledge are (1) to enhance usability and (2) improve
            documentation quality when using a terminology. Additional facts about clinical concepts
            can also be provided to support reasoning for automated quality monitoring and clinical
            decision support.<citation>Elkin_Terminology</citation></para>
        <para>Assertional knowledge is key to supporting interface implementation of terminologies.
            Assertional knowledge can support interface implementations of terminology by:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Assisting end users in adding clinical modifiers to concepts</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Representing relationships between clinical concepts and patient
                        populations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clarifying whether synonyms have the same meaning</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1513664/"/></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Solor Representation</title>
        <para>The Solor representation of Assertional Knowledge reaches beyond the patient as the
            subject of record and observations and evaluation results about the patient. It
            represents knowledge that can be applied to the patient's care, e.g. the patient's
            treatment or diagnostics. </para>
        <para>The Solor capability of associating statements enables the use of Assertional
            Knowledge to clinical decision support applications, clinical pathways and general
            information (“info button”) that can be made available to users of EMR systems. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Examples of Assertional Knowledge</title>
        <section>
            <title>Facts Supporting Reasoning</title>
            <para>Attributes like the ones below are common in proprietary interface terminologies
                and represent assertional knowledge that can then be mapped to standard reference
                terminologies like SNOMED CT or RxNorm.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>“Aspirin treats pain”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>“Penicillin treats bacterial infections”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>“Myocardial infarction is associated with chest pain”</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The VA's National Drug File - Reference Terminology (NDF-RT) has assertional
                knowledge contained in relationships like:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>may_treat {}  DISEASE_KIND – therapeutic use or indication of a generic
                        ingredient preparation or drug</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>may_prevent {}  DISEASE_KIND – preventative use or indication of a
                        generic ingredient preparation or drug</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>may_diagnose {}  DISEASE_KIND – diagnostic use or indication of a generic
                        ingredient preparation or drug</para>
                    
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Structure Product Labeling has assertional knowledge contained in sections
                such as:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Indications</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Contraindications</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding Clinical Modifiers</title>
            <para>Prior to 2012, SNOMED CT included qualifying relationships that could be used for
                creating a user interface that would post-coordinate concepts using pre-approved
                attribute value pairs.  With the introduction of the RF2, qualifying relationships
                were no longer released in favor of the Machine Readable Concept Model (MRCM).  The
                MRCM is a more comprehensive and flexible format for representing relationships and
                values that can be used to refine concepts.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Relationships Between Clinical Concepts and Patient Populations</title>
            <para>An example of a relationship between a clinical concept and patient population is
                pregnancy is not present in men or women who have had a hysterectomy or who are
                post-menopausal.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Clarifying synonymy</title>
            <para>Assertional knowledge relationships can be used to clarify whether synonyms are
                accurate representations of the same concept. For example, thorax pain and chest
                pain could be defined in a similar way, but thorax pain may imply to a healthcare
                provider that the pain is in the chest wall rather than internally as the term chest
                pain may imply.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190516T103116-0700" comment="Maybe we should frame this more in terms of &quot;Interface Support&quot;... Interface terminology perhaps implies that we need to create something distinct, rather than just a configurtation of one or more dialects. Other terms maybe better. 

Having the use case here up front that describes the need we are trying to fill can be good. So that&apos;s consistent with Tim&apos;s need more content/examples. "?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190501T104321-0500" comment="Need more content.  Add examples." flag="done" mid="7"?>Interface
            Terminology<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="7"?></title>
        <para>An interface terminology can be defined as a "systematic collection of clinically
            oriented phrases (terms) whose purpose is to support clinicians' entry of patient
            information into computer programs, such as clinical note capture and decision
            support tools". <citation>Elkin_Terminology</citation></para>
        <para>"Healthcare providers generally use interface terminologies to accomplish one of
            two tasks: 1) encoding clinical narrative into a structured form, or, 2) reviewing
            structured clinical information that has previously been encoded using a different
            terminology. In supporting such uses, interface terminologies must enable correct
            and rapid interaction between clinicians and structured clinical data, support
            facile use by healthcare providers through easy understandability, and integrate
            well with other clinical computerized systems in the environment." <citation>Rosenbloom_model</citation></para>
        <section>
            <title><abbrev>Desiderata for Supporting Interface Terminology Usability
            </abbrev></title>
            <para>The fundamental metric for evaluating an interface terminology is how well it
                performs in supporting correct, complete, and efficient data encoding or review
                by humans. <citation>Rosenbloom_model</citation> There are six desiderata
                relevant to interface terminology usability.
                <citation>Elkin_Terminology</citation></para>
            <section>
                <title>Completeness of Synonym Coverage</title>
                <para>An adequate representation of synoynms in an interface terminology can
                    increase the teriminology's usability. Interface terminologies should
                    represent the richness present in colloquial phrases of medical discource
                    and represent the variety of different types of synoynms that exist: </para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">Alternate
                    Terms</emphasis></emphasis>:  "Myocardial Infarction" for  "Heart
                    Attack"</para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold"
                    >Acronyms</emphasis>:</emphasis> "MI" for "Myocardial Infarction"</para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">Definitional
                    phrases</emphasis>:</emphasis> "Ischemic injury" for "necrosis of
                    heart muscle cells resulting from absent or diminished blood flow in a
                    coronary artery"</para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold"
                    >Eponyms</emphasis>:</emphasis> "Levine sign" for "a clenched fist held
                    over the chest indicating ischemic cardiac chest pain"</para>
                <para>However, rich synonymy may increase the chances that a given term may be
                    used to represent more than one concept (e.g., "cold" for "low temperature"
                    and for "upper repiratory tract viral infection". Parameters for metrics for
                    evaluating the completeness of synonym coverage in clinical interface
                    terminologies include:</para>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">Concept
                        Accuracy</emphasis>:</emphasis> how closely a term's meaning cooresponds
                    with the underlying concept it represents; and,</para>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">Synonym
                        Expressivity</emphasis>:</emphasis> how well a term's semantic
                    character matches the words in the phrase it is meant to represent rather
                    than the underlying meaning. </para>
                <para>For example a patient describes having a "feathery discomfort occurring
                    across the chest". Within a clinical terminology there is a concept for
                    "chest discomfort" and modifiers like "soft" and "anterior chest wall". The
                    end-user selects "noncrushing" to represent "feathery". The concept accuracy
                    of "noncrushing" for "feathery" is adequate beause the two have the same
                    meaning. However, "noncrushing" does not fully express the character of
                    "feathery". </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Balance between Precoordination and Postcoordination</title>
                <para>There are one of two general approaches to representing knowledge domains
                    by clinical terminology.</para>
                <para>In one approach, developers <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                    role="underline">precoordinate</emphasis></emphasis> (or enumerate)
                    all possible complex concepts apriori and essentially create a list of all
                    the complex concepts that can be expressed. A strength of this approach is
                    increasing the chances a user will find a desired concept. Disadvantages
                    include making a terminology so large that search becomes burdensome, and
                    reduced flexibility in situations where the terminology does not contain
                    concepts that a user may need. </para>
                <para>An alternative is <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline"
                    >postcoordination</emphasis></emphasis> in which users compose
                    complex concepts by assembling general concepts and modifiers as needed. An
                    advantage is increased flexibility for representing a wide range of
                    concepts. Disadvanatges include increased variation and inconsistent
                    application of terminologies against clinical data, increased ability to
                    create nonsensical complex concepts from modifiers and concepts, and
                    inefficiency since postcoordination processes can be time-consuming. </para>
                <para>Bringing these two approaches together can optimize a terminology's
                    flexibility, ease of use, and overall coverage. "Compositional balance"
                    makes concept selection tasks efficient by reducing the effort to assemble
                    complex concetps from general concepts, and reducing the time needed to
                    search through long lists of precoordinated concepts. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Inclusion of Adequate and Relevant Assertional Medical Knowledge</title>
                <para>Assertional knowledge is information that provides nuance and context to a
                    concept but does not specifically define it. The two major goals of
                    including assertional knowledge in an interface terminology are to enahance
                    usability and to improve documenation quality when using terminology. For
                    instance, assertional knowledge may help bring together clinically related
                    concepts and modifiers a user is likely to consider and document together.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Formal Concept Representation</title>
                <para>Ideally, a terminology is represented in a formal way to promote easy use for
                    automated data storage, management, and analysis. Description logics can
                    formally model and specify the relationships that exist among concepts and
                    modifiers and provide a structured representation of the knowledge domain. For
                    instance, in the following
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190528T234635-0400" comment="Need to update the following image."?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190806T090107-0600" comment="Yes, the font without the blue background is very light and should be in a darker color instead of light grey." id="rnr_hzd_r3b" mid="4"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190808T095157-0400" comment="We will fix in a future iteration" parentID="rnr_hzd_r3b" mid="3"?>screenshot<?oxy_comment_end mid="3"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="4"?><?oxy_comment_end?>,
                    when "Diabetes mellitus type 1" is selected, the options for "type 2" are hidden
                    and de-emphasized to the user.</para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/InterfaceTerm_DL.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Support for Human-Readability</title>
                <para>The goal of interface terminologies is to optimize the user experience.
                    Increasing efficiency and clarity of data review are key considerations for
                    helping clinicians access, read, and understand encoded clinical data. A
                    simple approach is to use relatively colloquial terms and display common
                    phrases and words. More complex approaches include "auto-complete" features
                    - when a user selects a concept (e.g., "chest pain") and modifiers (e.g.,
                    "anterior", "dull" "present"), the system may leverage tagged terminologies
                    to generate the natural language sentence (e.g., anterior dull chest pain is
                    present"). </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Application Independence</title>
                <para>Ideally, interface terminologies should exist as separate application
                    components that share a common data model with EHRs or other computer-based
                    systems. With this approach, terminology content development and evolution
                    can be distinct from software iteration cycles and queues. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    
</chapter>
