<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Solor Assertional Knowledge</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Previously we discussed definitional knowledge which defines purely structural
            relationships among concepts. Definitional knowledge relationships do not represent how
            concepts influence or relate to each other in a clinical setting. This type of
            information is represented by assertional knowledge. For example, shortness of breath
            may be caused by myocardial infarction.</para>
        <para>Assertional knowledge represents facts related to a domain of study and is used to
            provide nuance and context to a concept, but does not define it. For example, Aspirin is
            used to treat pain, but it can also be used to treat fevers, prevent blood clots, reduce
            the risk of stroke and heart attack and many other things. The two major goals of
            including assertional knowledge are (1) to enhance usability and (2) improve
            documentation quality when using a terminology. Additional facts about clinical concepts
            can also be provided to support reasoning for automated quality monitoring and clinical
            decision support.<citation>Elkin_Terminology</citation></para>
        <para>Assertional knowledge is key to supporting interface implementation of terminologies.
            Assertional knowledge can support interface implementations of terminology by:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Assisting end users in adding clinical modifiers to concepts</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Representing relationships between clinical concepts and patient
                        populations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clarifying whether synonyms have the same meaning</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1513664/"/></para>
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T085715-0600" comment="Is this supposed to be here?"?>Qualifying
            relationships<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Solor Representation</title>
        <para>The Solor representation of Assertional Knowledge reaches beyond the patient as the
            subject of record and observations and evaluation results about the patient. It
            represents knowledge that can be applied
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190507T124918-0600" comment="Recommend adding &quot;the patient&apos;s care&quot;" flag="done"?>to
            the patient's care, <?oxy_comment_end?>e.g. the patient's treatment or diagnostics. </para>
        <para>The Solor capability of associating statements enables the use of Assertional
            Knowledge to clinical decision support applications, clinical pathways and general
            information (“info button”) that can be made available to users of EMR systems. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Examples of Assertional Knowledge</title>
        <section>
            <title>Facts Supporting Reasoning</title>
            <para>Attributes like the ones below are common in proprietary interface terminologies
                and represent assertional knowledge that can then be mapped to standard reference
                terminologies like SNOMED CT or RxNorm.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>“Aspirin treats pain”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>“Penicillin treats bacterial infections”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>“Myocardial infarction is associated with chest pain”</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The VA's National Drug File - Reference Terminology (NDF-RT) has assertional
                knowledge contained in relationships like:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>may_treat {}  DISEASE_KIND – therapeutic use or indication of a generic
                        ingredient preparation or drug</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>may_prevent {}  DISEASE_KIND – preventative use or indication of a
                        generic ingredient preparation or drug</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>may_diagnose {}  DISEASE_KIND – diagnostic use or indication of a generic
                        ingredient preparation or drug</para>
                    
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Structure Product Labeling has assertional knowledge contained in sections
                such as:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Indications</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Contraindications</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding Clinical Modifiers</title>
            <para>Prior to 2012, SNOMED CT included qualifying relationships that could be used for
                creating a user interface that would post-coordinate concepts using pre-approved
                attribute value pairs.  With the introduction of the RF2, qualifying relationships
                were no longer released in favor of the Machine Readable Concept Model (MRCM).  The
                MRCM is a more comprehensive and flexible format for representing relationships and
                values that can be used to refine concepts.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Relationships Between Clinical Concepts and Patient Populations</title>
            <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T092429-0600" comment="Recommend insert before this &quot;An examples of a relationship between a clinical concept and patient population is&quot;."?>Pregnancy<?oxy_comment_end?>
                is not present in men or women who have had a hysterectomy or who are
                post-menopausal.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Clarifying synonymy</title>
            <para>Assertional knowledge relationships can be used to clarify whether synonyms are
                accurate representations of the same concept. For example, thorax pain and chest
                pain could be defined in a similar way, but thorax pain may imply to a healthcare
                provider that the pain is in the chest wall rather than internally as the term chest
                pain may imply.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    
</chapter>
