<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hrefhref="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Solor Intro</title>

       
    <blockquote>
        <para>"My Design in this Book is not to explain the Properties of Light by Hypotheses, but to propose and prove them by Reason and Experiments."
        </para>
        <attribution>Isaac Newton</attribution>
    </blockquote>
    <section>
        <title>Preface</title>
            <para>Symbolic information uses symbols to represent perception, interpretation,
                communication, knowledge, facts, data, and planning. Symbolic information is
                specifically concerned with symbolic representation and interpretational infrastructure.<citation>Information</citation></para>
            <para>An interpretational infrastructure establishes meaning, value, and usefulness for the
                symbols, and can generate and decode the symbols. Without consistent meaning of the
                symbols, there can be no stable knowledge, facts, or data. After the initial assignment
                or development of meaning, the interpretation of symbols must remain consistent if the
                symbols are to be used for perception, memory, communication, or planning.</para>
            <para>Symbols have no meaning or usefulness without an interpretational infrastructure.
                Because the symbols and the interpretational infrastructure are both essential, they
                must develop or evolve together.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Motivation and Foundation</title>
        <para>The essential challenge of informatics practice within the healthcare
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T083636-0700" comment="Recommend removing comma." flag="done"?>enterprise<?oxy_comment_end?>
            is to quickly deliver a high fidelity reasoned interpretation of principles and facts to
            the point of care—and then to quickly aggregate these point of care experiences for
            analytic analysis so that new principles and facts can be formulated and validated as
            part of a continuous optimization of healthcare knowledge and delivery. To effectively
            answer this challenge, we must focus on simplification and integration of knowledge
            assets, and on build, test, deploy, and release processes for delivering these assets to
            the points of care and analysis. This focus on perhaps mundane topics is not because we
            think that novelty has no place in our work; rather, that without a focus on aspects of
            our delivery challenge that are often treated as peripheral to the overall problem, we
            cannot achieve reliable, rapid, low-risk knowledge-asset development and delivery in an
            efficient manner.</para>
        <para>
            <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190429T152943-0700" comment="I put this in as content that needs to be integrated. "?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T121616-0600" comment="I don&apos;t think this has been defined yet and should be spelled out." flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?>The
                Veterans Health Administration’s (VHA) Office of Knowledge Based Systems’ (KBS)
                Informatics Architecture’s (IA) mission is to continuously improve the safety,
                functionality, and effectiveness of Healthcare IT systems and standards. We
                accomplish this IA mission by evaluating existing systems and standards
                architecture, and then designing incremental improvements and novel solutions. IA
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T121730-0600" comment="This is missing a word - what is IA creating?"?>creates
                <?oxy_comment_end?>that can be pragmatically evaluated and deployed and collaborates
                with standards organizations and implementers to realize the enhanced architecture. </para>
            <para>IA specifically approaches its evaluation and improvement efforts according to the
                principles of a High-Reliability Organization (HRO), in that we look for areas where
                processes may break down to the detriment of patients, providers, or the overall
                organization, and seek to reduce or eliminate these opportunities for breakdown
                through improvements in the underlying architecture. Our efforts at identifying the
                risk to patients from “interoperability by mapping” is one example of problem
                identification and architectural improvement. <citation>SolorWhitepaper</citation></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
        </para>
        <para>The Veteran’s Administration (VA) ISAAC (InformaticS Architecture ACceleration) effort
            seeks a holistic approach to architecture that supports novelty within a rigorous—and
            vertically integrated—deployment pipeline that enables knowledge engineers, developers,
            testers, build managers, and operations personnel to work together effectively to
            deliver assets to the points of care and analysis. This pipeline must support integrated
            delivery of iterative revisions of specifications, services, and content which are today
            delivered by isolated silo organizations that place the implementation burden upon their
            consumers. This pipeline will be built from existing software-based best practices, and
            will embrace DevOps culture and practice by emphasizing collaboration and communication
            while automating the process of product delivery. ISAAC’s KOMET (KnOwledge Management
            EnvironmenT) realizes ISAAC’s architecture within a DevOps environment that integrates
            development, testing, publication, and delivery of specifications, content, and services
            into a vertically integrated environment that supports continuous delivery.</para>
        <para>A 2018 whitepaper
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T122124-0600" comment="This link didn&apos;t appear to work in the PDF." flag="done"?><citation>interoperabilityprogress2018</citation><?oxy_comment_end?>
            cited that great strides have been made in healthcare data interoperability in the past
            decade…the vast majority of clinicians and patients have access to some portion of their
            health data in electronic format, thanks to the proliferation of electronic health
            record (EHR) systems installed in clinical care environments. The data in these EHRs
            usually follow HL7’s Consolidated Clinical Document Architecture (C-CDA) as it has
            become the generally accepted primary data standard for structured clinical data
            exchange.</para>
        <para>However, the whitepaper also found that significant gaps exist in the accurate
            encoding of the data contained in those C-CDA documents – in an analysis conducted of
            C-CDA documents produced by various EHR vendors and clinical organizations, the four
            most frequent problems identified as part of this analysis were that medications should
            be encoded in RxNorm
            (<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T083855-0700" comment="Is this saying that while these standards should be used, the cited percentages are showing that in fact, in the majority of cases they are not being used?  If yes, I think this should be re-worded to make that clear." id="kzf_r5j_1hb" flag="done" mid="6"?><?oxy_comment_start author="bechang" timestamp="20190308T081510-0700" comment="Yes, that is the intent of what these numbers show.  Added a sentence at the end of the paragraph to make this clear." parentID="kzf_r5j_1hb" flag="done"?>frequency<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="6"?>
            of medication appearing in 13.7% of sampled test case documents), vital signs and
            results should use LOINC (9.2% of sampled documents), vital signs, and results should
            use unified code of units of measure (UCUM) for physical values (8.7% of sampled
            documents) and the inclusion of conflicting status information for medications (6.7% of
            sampled
                documents)<citation><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T122935-0600" comment="Same - link didn&apos;t work in PDF." flag="done"?>interoperabilityprogress2018<?oxy_comment_end?></citation>.
            In short - even though standards and value sets exist for the encoding of data in EHRs,
            in the vast majority of instances this is simply not being done.</para>
        <para>These issues can have a direct impact on patient safety and point to the need to be
            able to consistently represent and encode clinical data and observations. This is the
            next great challenge to conquer for health data interoperability to positively influence
            patient outcomes nationwide through clinical decision support. </para>
        <para>When considering these challenges, it can be daunting to consider from where to start.
            There are hundreds of thousands of clinicians around the world, and up to the current
            century each was documenting their observations from seeing patients in their own way.
            Granted there have been efforts over the years to standardize medical terminology in
            order to encode it properly into systems, but even then there are instances where
            nuances of medical observations cannot be captured consistently, from something as basic
            as nuances of language (e.g.. English versus Chinese) to the specifics of how a
            measurement was actually taken procedurally - for example, in arriving at a quantitative
            measurement such as 90 beats per minute for a patient's pulse, one clinician may have
            used a pulseometer, while another may have arrived at that measurement using fingers to
            the patient's left wrist and a stopwatch. While the quantitative measurement is the
            same, the procedural information should also be documented and the differences
            noted.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Separation of Concerns</title>
        <para>A systematic way to think about this (borrowed from the software development industry)
            is something called Separation of Concerns. Separation of Concerns is an architectural
            design principle that allows a complete system to be subdivided into several distinct
            sections. If concerns are well separated from each other, individual sections may be
            able to be reused, as well as worked on and updated independently to address new
            requirements and use cases. This is especially useful and important in a medical context
            given how many different health information and clinical terminology projects are
            ongoing at any given time, efforts that are often uncoordinated and led by disparate and
            unrelated standards development organizations.</para>
        <para>The following diagram shows how the concept of Separation of Concerns can be applied
            to the problem of systematically and consistently representing data from clinical
            observations: <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/PASTF.png" scale="50"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T101254-0700" comment="As a novice in this, it&apos;s confusing to me in the PASTA diagram above to reference all of the alayers as the &quot;architecture&quot; but then also have &quot;architecture&quot; as one of the layers in the diagram.  Then in Section 2, you&apos;re referring to the &quot;various architectural layers,&quot; which again I think refers to the diagram shown here vs. the &quot;architecture&quot; layer.  Is there anything tht can be done to simplify or clarify this?" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
        <para>Starting from the bottom to the top of the Separation of Concerns diagram, the layers
            of the informatics architectural separation of concerns are described as: </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Solor
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190403T104727-0600" comment="I think this needs to be revised to &quot;Solor Architectural Foundation&quot; since that is how it&apos;s now shown in the diagram. This may require other references to it throughout the document to be changed." flag="done"?>Architectur<?oxy_comment_end?>al
                Foundation</emphasis> – Provides an interoperable, integrated common terminology
            model which concerns (a) the foundation and building blocks of the common model; (b) how
            the repeatable transformation process of disparate standards into the common model
            promotes interoperability with other environments; and, (c) how the modules of the
            architecture are tightly version controlled over time. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Terminology Knowledge</emphasis> – Structured sets of medical
            terms and codes that define concepts of interest, including descriptions, dialects,
            language, and semantic hierarchy. This layer also incorporates logical operators and
            description logic such as ‘representation of absence’. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Statement Model</emphasis> – Packaging of the terminology
            content in standardized data structures so that they can be readily consumed by the
            information retrieval process for analysis. Within the data structures, additional
            detail to describe subject, numerical, and categorical information related to concepts
            can be added in this layer.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Assertional Knowledge</emphasis> – Translation of guidelines to
            assist clinical decision making. This includes facts and knowledge upon which concepts
            and combinations of concepts can assimilate into protocols.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Procedural Knowledge</emphasis> – Information about standard
            ways to carry out specific procedures as well as other procedural guidelines, e.g.
            treatment protocols for diseases and
            o<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T101327-0700" comment="I don&apos;t think &quot;Order Sets&quot; needs to be capitalized." flag="done"?>rder<?oxy_comment_end?>
            sets focused on particular patient situations. Procedural knowledge, together with
            assertional knowledge, enables clinical decision support, quality measurement, and
            supports patient safety. This layer
            i<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T101352-0700" comment="This isn&apos;t a complete sentence and needs revision.  Should it be part of the prior sentence?" id="o1r_2vj_1hb" flag="done" mid="12"?><?oxy_comment_start author="bechang" timestamp="20190308T081906-0700" comment="Clarified." parentID="o1r_2vj_1hb" flag="done"?>ntegrates<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="12"?>
            the architectural and terminology layers, incorporates the statement model for
            information retrieval, and uses the assertional layer to apply rules.</para>
        <para>Examining a clinical procedure for controlling hypertension illustrates each of the
            layers of the informatics architectural separation of concerns. At the Terminology
            layer, there may be various codes and terms from disparate source terminologies to
            define the hypertension concept. For example, the concept “essential hypertension” is
            defined by the ICD-10 CM code I10 and 59621000 in SNOMED CT. Ideally, these overlapping
            codes and terms would be oriented to the same parent concept during the transformation
            and integration process at the Solor Architectural Foundation layer. Furthermore, any
            updates over time to code sets or value sets that define hypertension (in the NLM’s
            Value Set Authority Center for instance) would be maintained by continuous integration
            at the Solor Architectural Foundation layer. Moving to the statement layer, blood
            pressure measurement values may be packaged as a numerical measurement (e.g., systolic
            BP = 140 mmHg) or the categorial data (e.g., pregnancy induced hypertension vs. renal
            hypertension) within a standard data structure to facilitate information exchange or
            retrieval, such as within a FHIR Observation Resource. At the Assertional layer,
            guidelines such as the recommendation to control hypertension to under 140/90 mmHg might
            be translated into a clinical workflow facilitated by Health Information Technology
            (HIT). If HIT is involved with programmed Clinical Decision Support, there may be
            additional rules to suggest hypertension medications (e.g., beta-blockers, ACE
            inhibitors) while also including rules to
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T101503-0700" comment="&quot;to&quot; should be inserted here." flag="done"?>avoid<?oxy_comment_end?>
            medication
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T101538-0700" comment="I don&apos;t think this should be hyphenated." flag="done"?>contra<?oxy_comment_end?>indications.
            Finally, at the Procedural-level, there may be a treatment protocol for different kinds
            of hypertension, including the considerations of, e.g. patient age, co-morbidities etc.,
            which can be generated by an electronic clinical decision support system (Statement +
            Assertional layers). </para>
    </section>

</chapter>
