<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Solor Assertional Knowledge</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Previously we discussed definitional knowledge which defines purely structural
            relationships amongs concepts. Definitional knowledge relationships do not represent how
            concepts influence or relate to each other in a clinical setting. This type of
            information is represented by assertional knowledge.  For example, shortness of breath
            may be caused by myocardial infarction.</para>
        <para>Assertional knowledge represents facts related to a domain of study and is used to
            provide nuance and context to a concept, but does not define it. For example, Aspirin is
            used to treat pain, but it can also be used to treat fevers, prevent blood clots, reduce
            the risk of stroke and heart attack an many other things. The two major goals of
            including assertional knowledge are (1) to enhance usability (2) improve documentation
            quality when using a terminology. These additional facts provide additional reasoning
            capabilities that can be the basis for automated quality monitoring and clinical
            decision support.<citation>Elkin_Terminology</citation></para>
        <para>Assertional knowledge is key to supporting interface implementation of terminologies.
            Assertional knowledge can support interface implementations of terminology by:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>assist end users in adding clinical modifiers to concepts</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>representing relationships between clinical concepts and patient
                        populations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>clarifying whether synonyms have the same meaning</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para/>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1513664/"/></para>
        <para>Qualifying relationships</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Solor Representation</title>
        <para>The Solor representation of Assertional Knowledge reaches beyond the patient as the
            subject of record and observations and evaluation results about the patient. It
            represents knowledge that can be applied
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190507T124918-0600" comment="Recommend adding &quot;the patient&apos;s care&quot;" flag="done"?>to
            the patient's care, <?oxy_comment_end?>e.g. the patient's treatment or diagnostics.  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Examples of Assertional Knowledge</title>
        <para>• “Aspirin treats pain”</para>
        <para>• “Penicillin treats bacterial infections”</para>
        <para>• “Myocardial infarction is associated with chest pain”</para>
        <para>The Solor capability of associating statements enables the use of Assertional
            Knowledge to clinical decision support applications, clinical pathways and general
            information (“info button”) that can be made available to users of EMR systems. </para>
        <para/>
        <para>NDF-RT has assertional knowledge contained in relationships like:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>may_treat {}  DISEASE_KIND – therapeutic use or indication of a generic
                    ingredient preparation or drug</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>may_prevent {}  DISEASE_KIND – preventative use or indication of a generic
                    ingredient preparation or drug</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>may_diagnose {}  DISEASE_KIND – diagnostic use or indication of a generic
                    ingredient preparation or drug</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Structure Product Labeling has assertional knowledge contained in sections such
            as:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Indications</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Contraindications</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
