<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
  <title>Why Analysis Normal Form? A Normal Form for Clinical Statements</title>
  <para>A <glossterm baseform="Clinical Statement">clinical statement</glossterm> is a definite and
    clear representation of a clinically-significant fact or situation that was observed to exist or
    happened. A clinical statement can be expressed as a <glossterm baseform="Statement Narrative"
      >narrative</glossterm> that provides a written account that can be naturally read by humans,
    as well as a <glossterm baseform="Normal Form">normal form</glossterm> which is a
    machine-processable representation of the statement's data as a standardized and encoded
    fundamental form. Today, clinical statements are often represented in unpredictable and
    denormalized forms, which makes reliable and safe decision support challenging, and reduces the
    quality of other types of data processing. </para>
  <para>Healthcare organizations are striving to become <glossterm
      baseform="High Reliability Organization">high reliability organizations (HROs)</glossterm>,
    characterized by high levels of safety under inherently risky, technologically-complex, and
    demanding conditions. <link linkend="bib1">[1]</link>
    <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190723T000019-0400" comment="Moved from previous section and removed redundant reference/bibliography, reworded" flag="done"?>Deployment
    of EHR systems is nearly ubiquitous in the US and there is increasing opportunity to leverage
    standards-based clinical statements<!--a substantial number of extant EHR mapped data sets--> to
    improve population health through quality measures, case reporting, and decision support. The
    ability to measure and improve outcomes relies on consistent, high-quality data that was
    aggregated from a variety of systems. Analysis using normal form allows HROs to
    <?oxy_comment_end?>derive added knowledge from data and reach high levels and safety. <link
      linkend="bib2">[2]</link> A <emphasis>standard</emphasis> normal form can help replicate HROs
    across our industry.</para>
  <para>In this document, we present <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190722T235418-0400" comment="We should reserve the keyword &quot;normal&quot; for &quot;ANF&quot; - other clinical statements are either strcutured or standard-based - ANF should be the &quot;normal&quot; representation - the result of normalization of CIFs and other standard-based clinical satetement." flag="done"?>
    <!--normal forms--><?oxy_comment_end?> background on other logical
      <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T082039-0400" comment="glossary HL7" flag="done"?><glossterm
      baseform="Health Level Seven">HL7</glossterm><?oxy_comment_end?> and
      <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T082028-0400" comment="glossary ISO" flag="done"?><glossterm
      baseform="International Organization for Standardization">ISO</glossterm><?oxy_comment_end?>
    clinical statement models, and focus on the need for—and logical specification of—an <glossterm
      baseform="Analysis Normal Form">Analysis Normal Form (ANF)</glossterm>.
    <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190722T235956-0400" comment="Expanded this section." flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T085644-0700" comment="Insert introduction of URU here (Understandable, Reproducible, and Useful. " flag="done" mid="5"?>ANF
    is a <emphasis role="bold">normal</emphasis>
    <emphasis role="bold">form</emphasis> intended to safely and reliably support data analysis that
    can be used to aggregate data created using any standard or non-standard input form or exchange
    mechanism.<?oxy_comment_end?> The ANF Reference Model, is a <glossterm baseform="Logical Model"
      >logical model</glossterm> and part of the <glossterm>CIMI</glossterm> library of
    models.</para><?oxy_comment_end mid="5"?>
  <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190722T224830-0400" comment="Moved the URU references fron SoC section and expanded how URU is embodied by ANF." flag="done"?>
  <para>ANF is a model for clinical statements used in analysis that meet the following criteria:
        <emphasis><glossterm baseform="Understandable, Reproducible, Useful">Understandable,
        Reproducible, and Useful</glossterm></emphasis>
    (<?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T082722-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?>URU<?oxy_comment_end?>)
      <link linkend="bib3">[3]</link><link linkend="bib4">[4]</link></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"><glossterm baseform="Understandable"
          >Understandable</glossterm></emphasis>. The content of an <glossterm
          baseform="ANF Statement">ANF statement</glossterm> can be processed by health IT systems
        and understood by most healthcare providers, without reference to private or inaccessible
        information. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"><glossterm baseform="Reproducible"
          >Reproducible</glossterm></emphasis>. Multiple users or systems apply the ANF to the same
        situations and source data with an equivalent result. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"><glossterm baseform="Useful">Useful</glossterm></emphasis>. The
        ANF statement is fit-for-purpose—it has practical value for data analysis, in support of
        clinical decision support, research, and population health that requires information
        aggregated across health IT systems. </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>This document describes how information systems can improve patient safety and outcomes by
    increasing the precision of clinical information using a normal form to enhance and support
    quality data and analysis. </para>
  <section>
    <title>Motivation: Why Do We Need ANF? </title>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T122636-0700" comment="Also move to prior section (1.). This isn&apos;t specific to ANF, and provides more general background. " flag="done"?>Information
      systems record and manage clinical statements using a variety of standard or ad-hoc models.
      However, both treatment and analysis of clinical statements require consistency not only at
      the format level (e.g. <glossterm>CDA</glossterm>, FHIR, V2) but also the content model (i.e.
      an instance of an <link xlink:href="https://www.iso.org/standard/62416.html"><glossterm
          baseform="ISO/TS Detailed Clinical Models">ISO/TS 13972</glossterm></link> DCM, CIMI
      model, etc.). <link linkend="bib5">[5]</link> In most cases the data quality is the greatest
      obstacle to analysis, but even in the case of structured, semantically-clear information,
      inconsistency across sources of information raises obstacles to analysis. Analysis of
      aggregate information managed by health information networks poses the greatest challenge
      today because a meaningful use of data for patient outcomes or research requires a common
      format, semantic clarity, and quality data.<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T122653-0700" comment="Also move to prior section (1.). This isn&apos;t specific to ANF, and provides more general background. " flag="done"?>Not
      only is there a potential for a lack of consistency with representing clinical statements with
      current <glossterm baseform="Detailed Clinical Model">detailed clinical modeling</glossterm>
      efforts, but there is also further variation in how the data is entered into information
      systems by end-users. This reality has a direct impact on patient safety if a clinical
      statement is recorded and displayed differently across the continuum of care. Clinicians
      author clinical statements and enter them into their organization’s EHR systems where they are
      represented as some type of <glossterm baseform="Structured Clinical Input Forms">"Clinical
        Input Form"</glossterm> (CIF). This concept describes the representation of any natural
      language processing or data entry mechanism used by clinicians to record clinical statements.
      Vendors may compete on usability which may result in proprietary CIF data, or, clinical
      statements are based on standards-based models (e.g. CIMI, openEHR archetypes). For the
      purposes of this document, the type or usability of CIF data structures are not in scope. We
      assume that <emphasis role="bold">any suitably encoded</emphasis> clinical statement may be
      normalized. <?oxy_comment_end?></para>
    <para>Ideally, clinical information is modeled in a manner that is most efficient for use. This
      is a problem because there are many different use cases for clinical information with a wide
      range of requirements. There is no single model that can be the most efficient model for all
      the various use cases. Maximum efficiency for each use case necessitates that any particular
      clinical information be available in multiple modeled forms. These models, although different
      in form, semantically represent the same information, and are known as <glossterm
        baseform="Isosemantic Model">isosemantic models</glossterm>. Any particular detailed
      clinical model exists within a family of isosemantic siblings. </para>
    <para>Clinical statements can be expressed and documented in many different ways in EHR systems,
      where clinical input forms provide different options to document the same clinical statement.
      These differences pose challenges for how the data is modeled, how the data is stored, and
      therefore has implications on data retrieval, data analysis, and accuracy of clinical analysis
      results. </para>
    <section>
      <title>Variation by Implementation: Clinical Input Forms</title>
      <para>Clinicians enter clinical statements into their organization’s EHR typically in a manner
        that we call here
        <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T122744-0700" comment="a Clinical Input Form (CIF) and link to glossary. " flag="done"?>
        clinical input<?oxy_comment_end?> form (CIF), or the manner in which
        <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T122821-0700" comment="A Clinical Presentation Form (CPF) and link to glossary. " flag="done"?>information
        is presented<?oxy_comment_end?> to the clinicians and how they enter the data, such as by
        constraining the information to allow only certain values to be entered - for instance,
        through a drop-down list, radio buttons, or breaking up large chunks of related information
        into smaller parts, or through natural language processing.</para>
      <para>Let's consider the following example, represented below, in which <link
          linkend="CIF_EHR_1">data collected by an EHR</link> combines information reported by
        devices with findings and interpretation: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A vital signs monitor transmits the systolic and diastolic blood pressure
              including date/time and the id of the device. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The nurse marks the measurement as "verified". </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Next, the nurse documents how the measurement was performed: </para>
            <para>
              <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                  <para>using an adult cuff size</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>in prone position</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>brachial artery</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>on the left side</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>the micturition context is left empty/unknown<footnote><para>Studies have shown that systolic blood pressure measurements could increase 10 to 15mmHg with
                        a full bladder. Micturition, the process of emptying the bladder, is
                        therefore a data element that can be recorded with some Clinical Input
                        Forms. <link linkend="bibA">[6]</link><link linkend="bibB">[7]</link><link
                          linkend="bibC">[8]</link>
                      </para></footnote></para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Next, the physician adds an interpretation. </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist><figure xml:id="CIF_EHR_1">
          <title>Blood Pressure Statement recorded by an EHR system</title>
          <mediaobject role="bordered">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/BP data capture.svg" scale="60" align="center" format="SVG"
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <caption>
            <para><emphasis>In this example the CIF provides the measurement information from the
                device to be verified by a nurse. The nurse adds annotations describing how the
                measurement was taken (at rest, prone) and the location (left brachial artery). The
                user may also fill in information about micturition, if known. A physician may
                interpret the measurement to be indicative of hypertension.</emphasis>
            </para>
          </caption>
        </figure></para>
      <para><link linkend="Display_EHR_2">Another EHR system</link> may capture or display a subset
        of information in CIFs about the blood pressure measurement—omitting "micturition context"
        and pre-coordinates site and laterality as:</para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Right brachial artery</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Left brachial artery</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The image below illustrates another distinct CIF in which the user interface captures a
        set of clinical statements related to Blood Pressure. </para>
      <para>In the first case, the clinical input form has separate drop-down constraints to enter
        the artery and laterality as distinct concepts. In the alternative data entry form, the
        location and laterality are represented by a single, compound concept. This variation
        present in CIFs may also have implications on how the clinical statement is modeled. </para>
      <figure xml:id="Display_EHR_2">
        <title>Alternative Blood Pressure representation in a second EHR system</title>
        <mediaobject role="bordered">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/EHR-2.svg" scale="60" align="center" format="SVG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <caption>
          <para><emphasis>In this second CIF example, a similar system (or an alternative
              configuration of the same system) may support a different set of options to verify and
              record blood pressure measurement. This representation combines laterality and site
              and excludes details related to micturition.</emphasis></para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Analysis Normal Form </title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Analysis Normal Form</emphasis> (ANF) is a logical model intended to
      represent a <emphasis role="bold">normalized</emphasis> view of aggregate clinical statements
      recorded during treatment for analysis, research, clinical decision support, and other
      purposes. ANF can be used to represent any isosemantic clinical statements irrespective of how
      the information was captured at its source (i.e. information systems or medical devices). ANF
      <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T085712-0700" comment="can" flag="done"?>can<?oxy_comment_end?>
      be used in conjunction with other models intended to ensure that clinical information is
      structured and complete at the time of entry (e.g. CIMI models, <link
        xlink:href="https://www.iso.org/standard/62416.html">ISO/TS 13972</link> Detailed Clinical
      Models) or exchanged among systems (e.g. HL7 CDA templates, <glossterm
        baseform="HL7 V2 Messaging Profile">HL7 V2 message profiles</glossterm>, FHIR profiles). </para>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T085757-0700" comment="Clinicians, researchers, and HIT developers" flag="done"?>Clinicians,
      integrators, health IT developers, and researchers<?oxy_comment_end?> face different
      priorities, forcing trade-offs to be made that optimize data entry brevity at the cost of
      computability. ANF represents a collection of patterns and approaches to provide a
      <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T085955-0700" comment="ANF does not provide predictable transformations, it provides a predictable (URU) normal form that can be used by transformation developers. " flag="done"?>predictable
      <?oxy_comment_end?>normal form to aggregate data sets across multiple
      <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T122129-0700" comment="and therefore can be used as a predictable formal form for transformation. " flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?>systems
      <!--through normalization-->. The more normalized a data set is, the simpler it will become to
      analyze, and errors will be reduced. In addition to improving analysis, ANF introduces the
      ability to compare statements with ease and no loss of semantic integrity.
      <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190710T093048-0500" comment="Bibliography?" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?></para>
    <section>
      <title>Objectives and Purpose of ANF</title>
      <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T090631-0700" comment="Change to more active voice... &quot;ANF&apos;s main purpose is the normalized representation of statements...&quot;" flag="done"?>ANF<?oxy_comment_end?>'s
        purpose is to introduce standards-based, normalized representation of clinical statements
        from a heterogeneous source using an objective <emphasis role="bold"
            ><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T085855-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?><glossterm
            baseform="Measure">measure</glossterm><?oxy_comment_end?></emphasis> to help evaluate
        the result, presence, and magnitude of a specific finding, request or observation. ANF
        requires an ability to classify the <emphasis role="bold"
            ><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T085913-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?><glossterm
            baseform="Topic expression">topic</glossterm><?oxy_comment_end?></emphasis> of a
        statement using standard terminology expressions. ANF defines responsibility for different
        representational aspects of input data along well-defined compositional layers (see <link
          linkend="SoC_Section">Separation of Concerns</link>). In practice, information systems may
        create normal data natively or transform other representations of clinical statements (e.g.
        C-CDA templates, FHIR profiles) to normal form (i.e., ANF).</para>
      <para>Overall, ANF allows healthcare enterprises to normalize information aggregated across
        multiple sources to better support a set of analysis. ANF enhances the ability to analyze
        and compare clinical statements aggregated across systems and organizations and provide a
        logical model to:<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Specify a common form for clinical statements extracted from EHR systems and
              FHIR.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Provide a common analysis form to data exchange paradigms (e.g. HL7 messages, FHIR
              and CDA).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T122226-0700" comment="Don&apos;t put bulleted lists inside of bullited lists. Maybe put in a transition paragraph, then a new bullited list. " flag="done"?>Enhance
              clinical data for use in <glossterm>Clinical Decision Support</glossterm> Systems,
              Clinical Quality Measures and National Registries, Healthcare Guidelines and
              Protocols, and Epidemiological Research.</para><?oxy_comment_end?>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Assumptions for ANF</title>
      <para>ANF provides a precise statement specification that is comparable and sharable between
        multiple care providers, health enterprises, and standards-based Healthcare Information
        Technology (HIT) systems. ANF does not define the terminology specification but relies on
          <glossterm baseform="Terminology Knowledge">terminology knowledge </glossterm> to specify
        the meaning of clinical statements. ANF coded data may use single codes, as well as any
        legal terminology expression defined within the terminology layer of the <link
          linkend="SoC_Section">architecture</link>.</para>
      <para>ANF
        supports<?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T123126-0700" comment="supports—but does not require—postcoordinated compositional terminologies" flag="done"?>
        pre-coordinated and
          <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T110517-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done" mid="22"?><glossterm
          baseform="Post-coordinated concept"
        >post-coordinated</glossterm><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="22"?> terminology
        expressions to provide greater content coverage than can be achieved by relying only on
          <glossterm baseform="Pre-coordinated concept">pre-coordinated concepts.</glossterm>
        Post-coordinated compositional terminologies are more expressive and can achieve better
        analysis than can be achieved by relying only on pre-coordinated concepts. </para>
      <para>Successful analysis requires appropriate data quality necessary for systems to define a
        precise
        <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T110833-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?>topic<?oxy_comment_end?>,
        <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T110839-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?>category<?oxy_comment_end?>,
        and clear
        <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T110912-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?>measure<?oxy_comment_end?>
        or
          <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T110921-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?><glossterm
          baseform="Evaluation Result">result</glossterm><?oxy_comment_end?> of what was observed,
        requested, or assessed during treatment. ANF can be applied to any input data and any
        formalism as long as the data semantics and terminology are sufficiently precise to define
        the elements mandatory for analysis. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
 