<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Representing Statements</title>
    <blockquote>
        <attribution>Isaac Newton</attribution>
        <para>My Design in this Book is not to explain the Properties of Light by Hypotheses, but to
            propose and prove them by Reason and Experiments.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The purpose of this part is: </para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem spacing="compact">
            <para>To define a <emphasis>statement</emphasis> for the purpose of data
                representation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To define the types of <emphasis>statements</emphasis> and their
                    <emphasis>attributes</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To provide a set of guidelines to model <emphasis>statements</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>A statement is an expression of facts or plans. We will use two common—and misleadingly
        simple—statement topics: <emphasis>Pulse Rate</emphasis> and <emphasis>Blood
            Pressure</emphasis> as expository statements. If a patient told a clinician that their
        pulse rate was 120 and their BP was 160/95, or a clinician told a patient that they should
        keep their resting <emphasis>pulse rate</emphasis> below 70, and their <emphasis>Blood
            Pressure</emphasis> below 120/70, they would be mutually understood. The ability for the
        creator of the statement and the interpretor of the statement to each believe that they
            <emphasis>understand</emphasis> the statement is the first requirement. </para>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190313T143945-0600" comment="Why is the heading repeated here, both with same section number and this one with additional info?" flag="done"?>Clinical<?oxy_comment_end?>
                Observation Modeling</title>
            <subtitle>Supporting Domain Semantics, Flexibility, and Interoperability</subtitle>

            <author>
                <personname>Walter Sujansky</personname>
            </author>

            <date>2017-02-14</date>
        </info>

        <section xml:id="Intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>

            <para>This white paper emerged from discussions among informaticists, computer
                scientists, and medical doctors about the appropriate modeling of clinical
                observations in information systems. The participants included representatives of
                the VHA-DoD, CIMI, HL7-FHIR, FHIM, SNOMED-CT, and OpenEHR initiatives<footnote xml:id="__FN1__">
                    <para>VHA = Veterans Health Administration; CIMI = Clinical Information Modeling
                        Initiative; HL7-FHIR = HL7 Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources
                        working group; FHIM = Federal Health Information Modeling.</para>
                </footnote>. The paper does not necessarily represent a consensus among the
                discussants or the viewpoint of any particular discussant. Its purpose is to provide
                background on the topic, to summarize a number of the viewpoints expressed, and to
                provide preliminary recommendations for further consideration. The contents are
                subject to further modification as the discussion evolves.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ClinObsModels">
            <title>Statement Models</title>

            <para>Statement models (<footnote xml:id="__FN2__">
                    <para>Statement models are also referred to as “Clinical Observation Models,”
                        “Archetypes,” “Clinical Event Models,” and “Clinical Models” in the
                        informatics literature and vernacular.</para>
                </footnote>) are conceptual-level data models of the discrete statements about
                patients that can be stored in, processed by, and retrieved from a clinical
                information system. Statement models are defined for discrete types of clinical
                statements such as blood pressure measurements, lab test results, physical exam
                findings, patient-reported symptoms, clinical diagnoses, and other
                observations.</para>

            <para>Statement models define the structure and semantics of discrete clinical
                observations as formal “types” that are later instantiated to represent specific
                recorded observations that apply to particular patients. Like object types in
                programming languages, these type definitions include enumerations of the specific
                data elements that may make up the observation, the datatypes used to populate those
                elements, and which elements must be populated in every instantiated object versus
                optionally populated. <xref linkend="_Ref474327938" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows
                the graphical depiction of an example statement model for a blood pressure
                measurement.</para>

            <figure xml:id="_Ref474327938">
                <title>Example clinical object model for a blood pressure measurement</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image2com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <section>
                <title>The Role of Clinical Observation Models</title>

                <para>In general, clinical observation models serve at least two purposes:</para>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Statement models <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>standardize</emphasis></emphasis> the capture,
                            retrieval, and exchange of clinical observations within and between
                            information systems. As seen in <xref linkend="_Ref474327938" xrefstyle="select:label"/>, even relatively basic observations can
                            comprise numerous sub-components. Different implementers of clinical
                            information systems may model these sub-components and their
                            relationships in arbitrarily different ways, which can prevent different
                            software modules from managing and processing the same observations
                            consistently and correctly. Formal and agreed-upon statement models
                            provide a shared model of each type of observation that enables software
                            modules created by different implementers to handle the same
                            observations uniformly. Note that such software modules may comprise
                            different parts of the same information system (such as the user
                            interface and the rules engine of a single EHR) or entirely different
                            information systems (such as distinct EHRs from different commercial
                            vendors).</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Statement models <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>de-couple</emphasis></emphasis> the creation and
                            maintenance of domain-specific objects in clinical medicine (such as
                            observations) from their technical implementation in software code and
                            database structures. The types of clinical observations that may be
                            recorded in software systems are numerous, diverse, and subject to
                            relatively frequent modification over time, as well as customizations
                            across clinical sub-domains. Meanwhile, the technical implementation of
                            software applications and clinical databases is an arduous process that
                            requires the careful design, detailed writing, and extensive testing of
                            software code. Whenever changes are required to an application or
                            database, a time-consuming and costly implementation process must be
                            applied. Clinical applications and databases, however, that are
                            implemented at a more abstract level can process <emphasis>any
                            </emphasis>statement models that conform to a certain high-level
                            reference model. Such implementations may not need to change as
                            statement models are added or updated. Statement models can therefore
                            serve as conceptual-level objects that represent domain-specific data
                            and drive domain-specific functionality without being tightly coupled,
                            at least in theory, to the underling implementation of the information
                            system.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para><xref linkend="_Ref474505861" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows how statement models serve
                    both of these purposes in an information system. Note how the set of clinical
                    information models serves as a “view” or “interface” to all clinical data that
                    may be stored by and retrieved from the information system. The design of the
                    statement models is flexible and must conform only to a “reference model” of basic data
                    structures. These basic structures are, in fact, the only objects tightly
                    coupled with the underlying application and database implementations. In this
                    manner, the statement models provide a standard conceptual model against which all
                    data-input, data-query, and data-exchange functions operate, and that can be
                    readily extended without (again, in theory) costly modifications to the
                    underlying application and database. The approach for creating and maintaining
                    information systems in this way is called <emphasis>Model Driven
                        Development</emphasis>.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474505861">
                    <title>The role of clinical observation models in electronic health record
                        systems</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image3com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>

  </section>      
</section>
