<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Representing Statements</title>
    <blockquote>
        <attribution>Isaac Newton</attribution>
        <para>My Design in this Book is not to explain the Properties of Light by Hypotheses, but to
            propose and prove them by Reason and Experiments.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The purpose of this document is: </para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>To define a <emphasis>statement</emphasis> for the purpose of data
                representation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To define the types of <emphasis>statements</emphasis> and their
                    <emphasis>attributes</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To provide a set of guidelines to model <emphasis>statements</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>A statement is an expression of facts or plans. We will use two common—and misleadingly
        simple—statement topics: <emphasis>Pulse Rate</emphasis> and <emphasis>Blood
            Pressure</emphasis> as expository statements. If a patient told a clinician that their
        pulse rate was 120 and their BP was 160/95, or a clinician told a patient that they should
        keep their resting <emphasis>pulse rate</emphasis> below 70, and their <emphasis>Blood
            Pressure</emphasis> below 120/70, they would be mutually understood. The ability for the
        creator of the statement and the interpretor of the statement to each believe that they
            <emphasis>understand</emphasis> the statement is the first requirement. </para>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190313T143945-0600" comment="Why is the heading repeated here, both with same section number and this one with additional info?" flag="done"?>Clinical<?oxy_comment_end?>
                Observation Modeling</title>
            <subtitle>Supporting Domain Semantics, Flexibility, and Interoperability</subtitle>

            <author>
                <personname>Walter Sujansky</personname>
            </author>

            <date>2017-02-14</date>
        </info>

        <section xml:id="Intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>

            <para>This white paper emerged from discussions among informaticists, computer
                scientists, and medical doctors about the appropriate modeling of clinical
                observations in information systems. The participants included representatives of
                the VHA-DoD, CIMI, HL7-FHIR, FHIM, SNOMED-CT, and OpenEHR initiatives<footnote xml:id="__FN1__">
                    <para>VHA = Veterans Health Administration; CIMI = Clinical Information Modeling
                        Initiative; HL7-FHIR = HL7 Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources
                        working group; FHIM = Federal Health Information Modeling.</para>
                </footnote>. The paper does not necessarily represent a consensus among the
                discussants or the viewpoint of any particular discussant. Its purpose is to provide
                background on the topic, to summarize a number of the viewpoints expressed, and to
                provide preliminary recommendations for further consideration. The contents are
                subject to further modification as the discussion evolves.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ClinObsModels">
            <title>Statement Models</title>

            <para>Statement models (<footnote xml:id="__FN2__">
                    <para>Statement models are also referred to as “Clinical Observation Models,”
                        “Archetypes,” “Clinical Event Models,” and “Clinical Models” in the
                        informatics literature and vernacular.</para>
                </footnote>) are conceptual-level data models of the discrete statements about
                patients that can be stored in, processed by, and retrieved from a clinical
                information system. Statement models are defined for discrete types of clinical
                statements such as blood pressure measurements, lab test results, physical exam
                findings, patient-reported symptoms, clinical diagnoses, and other
                observations.</para>

            <para>Statement models define the structure and semantics of discrete clinical
                observations as formal “types” that are later instantiated to represent specific
                recorded observations that apply to particular patients. Like object types in
                programming languages, these type definitions include enumerations of the specific
                data elements that may make up the observation, the datatypes used to populate those
                elements, and which elements must be populated in every instantiated object versus
                optionally populated. <xref linkend="_Ref474327938" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows
                the graphical depiction of an example statement model for a blood pressure
                measurement.</para>

            <figure xml:id="_Ref474327938">
                <title>Example clinical object model for a blood pressure measurement</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image2com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <section>
                <title>The Role of Clinical Observation Models</title>

                <para>In general, clinical observation models serve at least two purposes:</para>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Statement models <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>standardize</emphasis></emphasis> the capture,
                            retrieval, and exchange of clinical observations within and between
                            information systems. As seen in <xref linkend="_Ref474327938" xrefstyle="select:label"/>, even relatively basic observations can
                            comprise numerous sub-components. Different implementers of clinical
                            information systems may model these sub-components and their
                            relationships in arbitrarily different ways, which can prevent different
                            software modules from managing and processing the same observations
                            consistently and correctly. Formal and agreed-upon statement models
                            provide a shared model of each type of observation that enables software
                            modules created by different implementers to handle the same
                            observations uniformly. Note that such software modules may comprise
                            different parts of the same information system (such as the user
                            interface and the rules engine of a single EHR) or entirely different
                            information systems (such as distinct EHRs from different commercial
                            vendors).</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Statement models <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>de-couple</emphasis></emphasis> the creation and
                            maintenance of domain-specific objects in clinical medicine (such as
                            observations) from their technical implementation in software code and
                            database structures. The types of clinical observations that may be
                            recorded in software systems are numerous, diverse, and subject to
                            relatively frequent modification over time, as well as customizations
                            across clinical sub-domains. Meanwhile, the technical implementation of
                            software applications and clinical databases is an arduous process that
                            requires the careful design, detailed writing, and extensive testing of
                            software code. Whenever changes are required to an application or
                            database, a time-consuming and costly implementation process must be
                            applied. Clinical applications and databases, however, that are
                            implemented at a more abstract level can process <emphasis>any
                            </emphasis>statement models that conform to a certain high-level
                            reference model. Such implementations may not need to change as
                            statement models are added or updated. Statement models can therefore
                            serve as conceptual-level objects that represent domain-specific data
                            and drive domain-specific functionality without being tightly coupled,
                            at least in theory, to the underling implementation of the information
                            system.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para><xref linkend="_Ref474505861" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows how statement models serve
                    both of these purposes in an information system. Note how the set of clinical
                    information models serves as a “view” or “interface” to all clinical data that
                    may be stored by and retrieved from the information system. The design of the
                    statement models is flexible and must conform only to a “reference model” of basic data
                    structures. These basic structures are, in fact, the only objects tightly
                    coupled with the underlying application and database implementations. In this
                    manner, the statement models provide a standard conceptual model against which all
                    data-input, data-query, and data-exchange functions operate, and that can be
                    readily extended without (again, in theory) costly modifications to the
                    underlying application and database. The approach for creating and maintaining
                    information systems in this way is called <emphasis>Model Driven
                        Development</emphasis>.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474505861">
                    <title>The role of clinical observation models in electronic health record
                        systems</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image3com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="OpenEHR">
            <title>OpenEHR: An Example Framework for Clinical Observation Modeling</title>

            <para>In considering the appropriate design of statement models, it’s useful to review how such
                models will be used in practice within a Model Driven Development architecture.
                    OpenEHR<footnote xml:id="__FN3__">
                    <para>Demski H, Garde S, Hildebrand C. Open data models for smart health
                        interconnected applications: the example of openEHR. BMC Med Inform Decis
                        Mak. 2016 Oct 22;16(1):137. (available at <link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27770769">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27770769</link>).</para>
                </footnote><superscript>,</superscript><footnote xml:id="__FN4__">
                    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.openehr.org/what_is_openehr">http://www.openehr.org/what_is_openehr</link>.</para>
                </footnote> offers one such architecture that is relatively complete and mature, so
                it serves as a good example. <xref linkend="_Ref474334719" xrefstyle="select:label"/> illustrates the components of the OpenEHR architecture, which are further
                described below.</para>

            <figure xml:id="_Ref474334719">
                <title>OpenEHR architecture</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image4com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <section xml:id="_Ref474420488">
                <title>OpenEHR Reference Model</title>

                <para>The foundation of the OpenEHR architecture is a reference model that contains
                    only the most generic set of objects and data types needed to define the
                    contents of an EHR. These objects include organizing structures such as
                    “Folders”, “Compositions”, and “Sections”, as well as generic clinical data
                    objects such as “Entries”, “Clusters” of entries, and “Elements” that comprise
                    the entries. The reference model also includes several dozen data types that may
                    be used to populate the values of Elements, such as “Quantity”, “Text”, and
                    “Timed Event”. Collectively, these constructs define the general building blocks
                    available to construct more detailed models for representing clinical
                    observations, actions, and other data in EHRs. <xref linkend="_Ref474335678" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows the constructs of the OpenEHR reference
                    model and how they are hierarchically organized to create the “scaffolding” for
                    patient records.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474335678">
                    <title>OpenEHR Reference Model</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image5com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>Within the reference model, the “Observation” class is a specific sub-type of
                    the “Entry” object, and it is used to record information from a direct
                    observation or measurement on a patient or to record the perspective of the
                    patient, such as in history taking. The Observation class includes only a small
                    number of data elements that are inherited by all clinical observation models,
                    such as “Subject” (the person to whom the observation applies) and “Information
                    Provider” (the person or agent who generated the observation). Otherwise, all
                    Entries and Elements used to record actual observations are specified within
                    sub-types of the Observation class, which OpenEHR calls “Archetypes.”</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>OpenEHR Archetypes</title>

                <para>Archetypes are clinical object models that specify:</para>

                <orderedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The set of Elements that may be used to represent various kinds of
                            observations</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>The datatypes used to populate those Elements</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which Elements must be populated versus being optional, and</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Whether Elements can have only one or may have multiple values.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>The values of Elements, themselves, may be collections of other Elements
                    (“Clusters”) or instances of other Archetypes (effectively, nested Archetypes).
                        <xref linkend="_Ref474337532" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows the graphical
                    representation of an OpenEHR archetype.</para>

                <para>For primitive Elements, the Archetype may define further constraints that
                    define how the Element may be populated, as shown in the callouts of <xref linkend="_Ref474337532" xrefstyle="select:label"/>. For example, the value
                    of the “Systolic” Element in the Blood Pressure Artifact is specified to be a
                    “Quantity” datatype, to represent the property of “Pressure”, and to be recorded
                    using the units of measure “mm[Hg]”. Similarly, the “Position” Element is
                    specified to be a “Coded Text” datatype and to be populated by one of several
                    enumerated code values, with the code for “Sitting” being the default if no
                    other value is specified.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474337532">
                    <title>Example of an OpenEHR Archetype</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image6com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>OpenEHR Archetypes must be defined using only the constructs of the underlying
                    Reference Model, as shown in <xref linkend="_Ref474334719" xrefstyle="select:label"/>. This constraint ensures that the Archetypes may
                    be stored and processed by the underlying database and application
                    implementations, which are otherwise loosely bound to the specific structures of
                    the Archetypes themselves.</para>

                <para>The OpenEHR framework uses a specific structured language to define
                    Archetypes, the Archetype Definition Language (ADL). <xref linkend="_Ref474337532" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows the graphical
                    rendering of an Archetype, although the actual definition is specified using a
                    text-based ADL expression (not shown). Other Model-Driven Development
                    frameworks, of course, may use different languages for defining statement models and
                    different graphical rendering methods.</para>

                <para>Like structured data types and object classes in programming languages,
                    Archetypes specify and constrain in detail how instances of actual data
                    (clinical observations, in this case) may be represented within the information
                    system. These specifications govern how software modules must create instances
                    of those observations (i.e., modules such as graphical user interfaces or EDI
                    interface engines) and how software modules may retrieve and process instances
                    of those observations (i.e., modules such as user displays or decision-support
                    rule engines). Using conceptual-level Archetypes rather than low-level data
                    structures for these purposes allows domain experts to formally specify
                    Archetypes, and (in theory, at least) de-couples Archetype specifications from
                    low-level implementation dependencies.</para>

                <para>OpenEHR currently includes several hundred Archetypes<footnote xml:id="__FN5__">
                        <para>See <link xlink:href="http://www.openehr.org/ckm/">http://www.openehr.org/ckm/</link> for an online listing.</para>
                    </footnote>, including many for clinical observations. The framework, however,
                    remains very much a work in progress, and many Archetypes remain in draft
                    form.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>OpenEHR Templates</title>

                <para>To support specific use cases and system functions, OpenEHR allows Archetypes
                    to be combined and/or further constrained to create purpose-specific data
                    structures called “Templates”. Templates may then drive the automated generation
                    of computing artifacts used to collect, retrieve, or export clinical
                    observations (see <xref linkend="_Ref474334719" xrefstyle="select:label"/>).</para>

                <para><xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows an example
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190313T152535-0600" comment="Why are some items in the template below numbered while others are not?" id="z4q_w3l_fhb" flag="done" mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190326T122423-0500" comment="The numbering you notice in the image below comes directly from the OpenEHR template.  See https://www.openehr.org/ckm/#" parentID="z4q_w3l_fhb" flag="done"?>OpenEHR<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?>
                    Template that represents the information captured during an initial visit to a
                    heart failure clinic. Note that the template combines a number of Archetypes,
                    such as Blood Pressure, Pulse, and Full Blood Count, as well as adds
                    navigational and organizational nodes such as “Physical Exam.” The latter nodes
                    are also Archetypes, specifically sub-classes of the Section object specified in
                    the Reference Model.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474415737">
                    <title>Example of an OpenEHR Template</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image7com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>Although not shown in <xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/>, Templates may also include additional constraints applied to their
                    constituent Archetypes. Such constraints may entail the inclusion of only a
                    subset of the Archetype’s Elements, the allowance of only a subset of the coded
                    values specified for an Element, the designation of default values for Elements,
                    etc. The purpose of these constraints is to customize an Archetype for use in a
                    specific context, while ensuring that any data collected or retrieved using
                    Templates that contain the Archetype conform to the Archetype’s underlying
                    constraints.</para>

                <para>For example, <xref linkend="_Ref474416536" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows a
                    graphical user interface (“Screen Form”) for data entry generated from the
                    heart-failure Template in <xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/>. Because the Template design constrained the Blood Pressure Archetype to
                    include only the “Systolic” and “Diastolic” Elements (as opposed to the full set
                    of Elements shown in <xref linkend="_Ref474337532" xrefstyle="select:label"/>),
                    the Screen Form displays only those two Elements. Note that the display includes
                    the units of measure and allowed value ranges specified for the “Systolic” and
                    “Diastolic” Elements, as derived from the complete Archetype. In this manner,
                    all data collected via Screen Forms generated from the Template in <xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/> will conform to the
                    constraints specified within the Archetypes that the Template includes. This
                    aspect of Model Driven Development allows the observation modeling features and
                    constraints that are formally specified in Archetypes to be uniformly and
                    automatically applied across various uses of the Archetypes (through Templates)
                    within and across information systems.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474416536">
                    <title><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190313T152917-0600" comment="In the example, why does Pulse appear to be under Weight and BP under Height?" id="iyc_rjl_fhb" flag="done" mid="4"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190326T123023-0500" comment="They are not under Pulse and Height, but are different data types.  Weight and Height can only have one value whereas Pulse and BP can have multiple values as they can be taken multiple times during an encounter.  If you look closely you can see that Weight and Height have the constraint (1..1) and Pulse and BP have (0..*)" parentID="iyc_rjl_fhb" flag="done" mid="5"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190403T114103-0600" comment="Okay, thanks.  To my untrained eyes, and particularly because of the indenting under Weight and Height, it looked as though they were included under them." flag="done"?>Example<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="5"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="4"?>
                        of a Screen Form generated from an OpenEHR Template</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image8com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Querying OpenEHR Data</title>

                <para>Although OpenEHR Templates may combine and further constrain Archetypes to
                    enable purpose-specific data collection and data processing, the querying of
                    OpenEHR data need not consider the structure of any individual Templates that
                    were used to instantiate clinical observations. Rather, querying requires
                    knowledge of only the Archetypes, the underlying Reference Model, and any
                    controlled terminologies used in the definition of Archetypes (See
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T113916-0600" comment="In the figure, unless this is a reference to a source other than VA, recommend revising spelling of &quot;artefacts&quot; to &quot;artifacts.&quot;  Also, the oval for Terminology Bindings probably should be brought to the front so it&apos;s not cutoff by the rectangle currently in front of it." id="wtk_gpl_fhb" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190326T131257-0500" comment="This is how it is spelled in the OpenEHR documentation and this image is taken directly from there." parentID="wtk_gpl_fhb" flag="done" mid="7"?><xref linkend="_Ref474421318" xrefstyle="select:label"/><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="7"?> for a graphical representation
                    of these dependencies).</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474421318">
                    <title>Architectural components used in querying of OpenEHR data.</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image9com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>As discussed above, all persisted observation data must conform to the
                    constraints of the Archetypes used to collect them (even if those Archetypes are
                    combined and further constrained in Templates). Further, none of the
                    navigational elements of Templates (such as the grouping of Archetypes into a
                    “Physical Exam” category, as shown in <xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/>) influence the semantics of the Archetype data
                    collected via Templates. Specifically, the semantics of a clinical observation
                    represented by an Archetype should exist independently of any encompassing
                    navigational or organizational category in which that Archetype may appear
                    within a Template (Archetypes must be carefully designed to confer this
                    property).</para>

                <para>At the same time, queries may reference sub-parts of an OpenEHR medical record
                    in which the Archetype instances were recorded. These named sub-parts of a
                    record, such as “Problem List” and “Medication Order List,” are also Archetypes
                    defined to specialize the “Section” class of the Reference Model (see <xref linkend="_Ref474420488" xrefstyle="select:label"/>).</para>

                <para>Finally, queries may also reference the terminology model from which specific
                    codes were drawn when defining clinical observation Archetypes. For example, a
                    query could seek to retrieve any patient with a diagnosis subsumed by the coded
                    concept “Cardiovascular Disease,” although no Archetype specifically references
                    that very general disease concept. Such a query would rely upon the hierarchical
                    subsumption relationships represented in the terminology model to associate the
                    general “Cardiovascular Disease” concept with the specific disease concepts
                    (such as “Atherosclerosis”) that are actually referenced in defined
                    Archetypes.</para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="PatternsForModeling">
            <title>Patterns for Clinical Observation Modeling</title>

            <para>Model-Driven Development provides a useful framework to build EHR systems that
                include standardized representations of medical data and that are flexible and
                extensible. However, the ultimate effectiveness of these EHR systems depends to a
                great extent on the specific design of the clinical observation models they include.
                As discussed, the same types of observations may be modeled in many different ways,
                and the design choices made will
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T114421-0600" comment="I think &quot;will&quot; should be added between &quot;made&quot; and &quot;influence.&quot;" flag="done"?>influence<?oxy_comment_end?>
                the ease and consistency with which the clinical observation models can be used.
                This section discusses some of those choices and the design criteria that should
                govern them.</para>

            <section>
                <title>Clinical Observations in the Abstract</title>

                <para>It’s useful to consider what clinical observations essentially are. In the
                    abstract, they are discrete patient descriptors that document information
                    gathering, diagnostic testing, and decision making about patients. Such
                    descriptors may include, for example, a diagnosis, an LDL cholesterol level, a
                    systolic blood pressure measurement, an Apgar score, a patient-reported symptom,
                    or a family history.</para>

                <para>Each clinical observation pertaining to a patient consists in the abstract of
                    two general components:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <emphasis role="underline">Aspect</emphasis> of the patient that
                            is being described, either implicitly or explicitly. For example, the
                            observation “The patient’s systolic BP is 130 mmHg” explicitly describes
                            the Aspect “Systolic Blood Pressure,” whereas the observation “The
                            patient has asthma” implicitly describes the aspect “Diagnosis”. If the
                            general form of a patient descriptor is “The patient has X of Y”, the
                            aspect denotes “X”.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <emphasis role="underline">Value or Magnitude</emphasis> of the
                            descriptor. For example, the observation “The patient’s systolic BP is
                            130 mmHg” specifies the magnitude “130” whereas the observation “The
                            patient has asthma” specifies the value “Asthma”. If the general form of
                            a patient descriptor is “The patient has X of Y”, the value or magnitude
                            denotes “Y”.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <para>The aspect and the value/magnitude of an observation may, themselves, be
                    further modified or qualified to denote the complete semantics of the
                    observation. For example, the aspect “Systolic Blood Pressure” in the example
                    above could be further qualified by the date/time that the measurement was taken
                    or the position of the patient at the time it was taken. Likewise, the magnitude
                    “130” in the example above could be further qualified to specify that the units
                    of measure that apply are “mmHg”.</para>

                <para>Sometimes, a third component of a clinical observation is specified:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <emphasis role="underline">Context</emphasis> in which the
                            clinical observation occurred or was recorded. This component typically
                            denotes information that is important to record but does not directly
                            modify the Aspect or the Value/Magnitude. Examples may include who
                            specifically reported the observation (e.g., the patient versus the
                            patient’s mother) or what instrument or technique was used to collect
                            the observation (e.g., by rhythm strip versus 12-lead EKG). Notably,
                            there is sometimes a fuzzy distinction between information that modifies
                            the Aspect of a clinical observation and information that denotes its
                            Context. For example, the fasting state of a patient at the time a serum
                            LDL cholesterol measurement was taken could be considered to denote the
                            Context of the measurement (with the Aspect being simply “Serum LDL
                            Cholesterol”) or the fasting state could denote a qualifier of the
                            Aspect (with the Aspect being “Serum LDL Cholesterol, with FastingState
                            = True”).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <para>Based on these abstract components of a clinical observation, the same
                    observation can be modeled in different ways. The examples in <xref linkend="_Ref474687508" xrefstyle="select:label"/> show reasonable
                    variations in the use of aspect, value, and context to represent the same
                    observation semantics.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474687508">
                    <title>Example variations in modeling of clinical observations</title>

                    <para><inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/image10com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        <inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/image11com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject>
                    </para>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="_Ref474506814">
                <title>General Design Patterns for Clinical Observations</title>

                <para>At least three general structural patterns may be considered for the design of
                    clinical observation models:  Assertion, Evaluation, and Belief:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">Assertion</emphasis> pattern. No Aspect is
                            explicitly specified; a Value, with possible qualifiers is always
                            specified; a Context is optionally specified. Example:</para>

                        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Aspect = NULL </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Value = (Asthma, with type = intrinsic, with severity = mild,
                                    with status = active)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>

                        <para>This pattern assumes that, for every Value, the Aspect of the patient
                            that is being described is implicit and unambiguous, and therefore need
                            not be explicitly specified. The pattern is most naturally suited for
                            symptoms, exam findings, past medical history findings, and diagnoses,
                            where the assumption usually holds. However, exceptions exist. For
                            example, the Assertion pattern cannot distinguish between a
                            patient-reported symptom of “arm weakness,” and a physical exam finding
                            of “arm weakness” (unless “patient-reported” or “physical-exam” are
                            denoted as Contexts). .</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">Evaluation</emphasis> pattern. An Aspect is
                            always specified; a Value, with possible qualifiers is always specified;
                            a Context is optionally specified. Example:</para>

                        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Aspect = Serum LDL Cholesterol </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Value = (185, with units-of-measure = mmHg)</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Context = Fasting</para>
                            </listitem>

                        </itemizedlist>

                        <para>This pattern explicitly specifies the Aspect and considers it the
                            “question” that the observation is addressing. The Value constitutes the
                            “answer” to the question. The pattern is most naturally suited to
                            observations represented as “attribute/value” pairs, such as simple
                            testing results (blood glucose, FEV1), scoring instruments (Apgar,
                            Braden scores), and patient characteristics with quantitative or ordinal
                            values (pulse, pain intensity).</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">Belief</emphasis> pattern. An Aspect, with
                            possible qualifiers, is always specified; a Value, with possible
                            qualifiers is always specified; a Context is optionally(but rarely)
                            specified. Examples:</para>
                        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Aspect = Diagnosis </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Value = (Asthma, with type = intrinsic, with severity = mild,
                                    with status = active)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>

                        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Aspect = Serum LDL Cholesterol, with Fasting-State = True </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Value = (185, with units-of-measure = mg/dL)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>

                        <para>This pattern is the most general and can be applied equally to
                            symptoms, findings, diagnoses, test results, scoring instruments, and
                            quantitative characteristics. It does require, however, that an Aspect
                            is explicitly specified in all cases as part of the observation model
                            (although this constraint does not necessarily require that the Aspect
                            be specified by users at the time the observation is instantiated, since
                            user-interface functionality may populate the Aspect automatically and
                            “behind the scenes” for observations where it is implied and
                            unambiguous).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Desiderata for Clinical Observation Model Design Patterns</title>

                <para>Given that multiple design patterns exist for clinical observations, it’s
                    useful to consider design criteria that can guide modeling choice. Among the
                    best known criteria for designing clinical concepts are the properties of
                    Understandability, Reproducibility, and Usability (URU)<footnote xml:id="__FN6__">
                        <para>Walker D. GP Vocabulary Project—Stage 2 Report: SNOMED Clinical Terms
                            (SNOMED CT); November, 2004. Available from: <link xlink:href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Gp-Vocabulary-Project-Stage-2-Snomed-Clinical-Walker/4353b85e1afbeb93b81b38398f94882c6d5119cd">https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Gp-Vocabulary-Project-Stage-2-Snomed-Clinical-Walker/4353b85e1afbeb93b81b38398f94882c6d5119cd</link>.</para>
                    </footnote>, defined as follows:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">Understandability</emphasis>: Concept
                            definitions should be understandable by average clinicians and others
                            who use the definitions (such as data analysts), given brief
                            explanations.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline"><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T121945-0600" comment="For readability and consistency purposes, I think it would be better if the Reproducibility and Usability were put in the positive vs. negative aspects, as Understandability is.  Possible revised wording is shown below.
Reproducibility:  The retrieval and representation of the same concept should be consistent regardless of the nature of the interface, user preferences, or time of entry.
Usability:  One should model concepts, concept properties, and distinction among concepts only for which there is current use in healthcare." flag="done"?>Reproducibility<?oxy_comment_end?></emphasis>:
                            The retrieval and representation of the same concept should be
                            consistent regardless of the nature of the interface, user preferences,
                            or time of entry.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">Usefullness</emphasis>: One should model
                            concepts, concept properties, and distinction among concepts only for
                            which there is current use in healthcare.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <para>Among these criteria, reproducibility is arguably the most important in
                    selecting an optimal design pattern for clinical observations, because the
                    property of reproducibility most influences the value of clinical observations
                    as <emphasis>standardized</emphasis> representations of clinical information
                    that can be shared by different software modules and information systems. As
                    illustrated in <xref linkend="_Ref474505861" xrefstyle="select:label"/>,
                    multiple software modules may use the same clinical observation models to
                    implement distinct functions. To ensure that the creation, use, and exchange of
                    clinical data is done uniformly, the clinical object models must not vary
                    according to the contexts in which they are created or processed, i.e., they
                    must be reproducible.</para>

                <para>To help ensure reproducibility, modelers should follow at least two guidelines
                    when creating clinical observation models: Avoid arbitrary variation and
                    explicitly represent clinically relevant distinctions. <xref linkend="_Ref474506327" xrefstyle="select:label"/> illustrates relevant
                    examples and counterexamples of these guidelines. Note that the first example
                    shows three different modeling patterns for the same type of observation. In
                    this case, it would be preferable to model all observations of this type using
                    only one of the patterns (applying any one of the patterns to all three
                    observations is left as an exercise for the reader). The second example shows an
                    observation for which the complete clinical meaning of the finding (“Weakness in
                    Right Arm”) depends on whether it was objectively discerned by the physician
                    through examination, or just subjectively reported by the patient.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474506327">
                    <title>Guidelines for designing clinical observation models</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image12com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para><xref linkend="_Ref474689633" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows a
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T123151-0600" comment="I think it would be helpful if this were followed by an example that showed the proper way to model this."?>poorly<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    designed clinical observation model that violates the reproducibility criterion.
                    Using this model, the family history of a particular problem or diagnosis could
                    be represented in two different ways, depending on the user’s preference. Such
                    variation in the representation of the same observation entered by one user or
                    another will necessarily complicate subsequent data querying and analysis. For
                    example, a data analyst seeking all patients with a family history of coronary
                    artery disease would have to search both the “Per problem” and the “Per family
                    member” paths of each “Family History” observation stored in the EHR.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474689633">
                    <title>A poorly designed clinical observation model</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image13com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Recommendations</title>

                <para>Given the Model-Driven Development approach and the design considerations
                    described above, two general options exist for specifying clinical observation
                    models:</para>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">Standardize on a single design
                                pattern</emphasis> for all clinical observation models (i.e., either
                            the Assertion, Evaluation, or Belief pattern described in <xref linkend="_Ref474506814" xrefstyle="select:label"/>). This approach
                            may facilitate the tasks of data analysts and software developers, who
                            will need to learn many clinical observation models to use them
                            effectively in application development, CDS rule design, clinical
                            measure specifications, etc.</para>

                        <para>With this option, the “Belief” pattern is likely preferred, as it is
                            the most generic and supports all manner of clinical observations, as
                            described in <xref linkend="_Ref474506814" xrefstyle="select:label"/>.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">Allow multiple design patterns</emphasis>,
                            specific to individual types of observations models (e.g., all lab
                            results, all symptoms, all physical exam findings), or even to specific
                            observation models (e.g., distinct models for skin turgor versus knee
                            reflex). This approach offers maximum flexibility in modeling specific
                            clinical observations in the most natural manner. Because individual
                            clinical observation models will often be quite complex and extensive in
                            any case (as seen from the examples in this report), the basic pattern
                            they follow (i.e., Assertion vs. Evaluation vs. Belief) may be the least
                            of the variations among them that data analysts and software developers
                            will need to be concerned with. Hence, it may not practically matter
                            whether clinical observation models conform to a single pattern or to
                            multiple patterns, as long as the models are clearly documented.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T123808-0600" comment="What does this mean...in summary?"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190403T115123-0600" comment="Starting here, a lot of my comments and questions were not addressed.  I think they should be or at least let me know why they were not." mid="12"?>In
                    net<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="12"?>,
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T123734-0600" comment="I have to admit that given the ANF model and how simple it is, option 2 being the preferred option surprised me.  It may be due to my lack of understanding of all of this and how they relate to each other."?>option
                    2 may be the preferred approach<?oxy_comment_end?>. Modelers should allow for
                    multiple design patterns, as needed, but strive for maximum standardization for
                    any specific type of observation (i.e., lab result versus symptom versus
                    diagnosis, etc.). Such an approach will enable maximum flexibility for modeling
                    different observations in an optimal fashion, while minimizing arbitrary
                    variations among clinical observation model designs.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para>A <emphasis> statement</emphasis> represents an entry in a record that documents in a
            structured/computable manner information about a subject of information, such as a
            patient or a relative of the patient, and that is asserted by a particular source,
            recorded, and potentially verified.</para>
        <para>Clinicians author clinical statements and enter them into their organization’s
            electronic health record (EHR). Clinicians typically input the information via a manner
            that we call here the
                <emphasis><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T163411-0600" comment="On 1/6/19, Joey Coyle sent an email to me and Keith recommended renaming CIF to something else.  He said &quot;In writing this I&apos;ve realized that current CIMI and all the models we do at Intermountain are not about clinical input.  In fact, we have found that these models are usually too post-coordinated for clinical input screens, and user facing applications have to use more pre-coordinated valuesets for the job at hand.  The application then deconstructs these codes into our more post-coordinated models.  The post-coordination is actually more for storage and consistent querying than it is for data input.&quot;

I don&apos;t recall seeing a reply from Keith but wanted to raise the issue to see if changes should be made as needed in this document based on Joey&apos;s recommendation."?>clinical
                input form (CIF)<?oxy_comment_end?></emphasis>. However, the CIF is not a literal
            form that clinicians select and enter data in. Rather, it refers to the manner in which
            information is presented to the clinicians and how they input the data, such as by
            constraining the information to allow only certain values to be entered, such as through
            a drop-down list or radio button, or breaking up large chunks of related information
            into smaller parts. For example, when a clinician orders a medication, rather than
            selecting this information all at once with a single item, they will choose the various
            parts of the medication order, such as:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Kind of drug and strength (e.g., Acetaminophen 150 mg)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Amount and how often the patient should take the medication (e.g., 1 tablet
                    twice daily)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Duration (e.g., 2 days)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Any constraints (e.g., do not exceed a total daily dosage of 600 mg)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Ideally, the way the information is presented to clinicians is in a manner that is
            most efficient for the clinicians to use. However, what is an efficient way for
            clinicians to select and input data may not be the most efficient way for data analysts
            to use when they are querying data once it has been normalized and stored in a database,
            such as when creating a new CDS rule or compiling prevalence statistics. For this, the
            data is normalized using the <emphasis>analysis normal form (ANF)</emphasis> and stored
            in a database. Again, the ANF is not necessarily a physical structure, but is how a data
            analyst might see the data when they are looking at it in a database, and not as
            clinicians would see it in the user interface (i.e., CIF).</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Clinician collects data via Clinical Input Form.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Data is normalized via Transformation process from CIF to ANF à
                    Representable/storable in multiple types of databases, which <emphasis role="underline">could</emphasis> include VistA but a separate process would
                    need to be performed to make that happen.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Data analyst who is using or querying the data (e.g., creating a CDS rule or
                    working on prevalence statistics) via ANF (it is how the data is represented or
                    stored in the database; must know enough about the data to know what is stored
                    in the topic vs. what is stored as a result or detail).</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <table frame="topbot" rowsep="0" colsep="0" xml:id="table_f39f17ff-b1f9-4701-85db-324fb78b9f2b">
            <title>General Statement Model</title>
            <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="102.37pt"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="292.9pt"/>
                <thead>
                    <row rowsep="1">
                        <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Statement</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Narrative:</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Topic:</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Subject of information:</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Statement time:</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Act:</entry>
                        <entrytbl cols="3">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1.86*"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                            <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="6.48*"/>
                            <tbody>
                                <row rowsep="0">
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                </row>
                                <row rowsep="0">
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" namest="c2" nameend="c3"/>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </entrytbl>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>


        <para> </para>
        <editorial-rule>
            <title>Topic</title>
            <mathphrase>The <emphasis>topic</emphasis> is the center of interest or activity
                represented by the statement. A few examples of topics include <link
                    xlink:href="#ge_solor_Insulin_dependent_diabetes_mellitus_type_1A_cc0759c3-623e-3417-badb-8dbad681e0f5"><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata>
                                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T130906-0600" comment="The examples of topics shown here have a lot of white space shown after them in the PDF and it&apos;s distracting.  Recommend you just type the examples instead in a bulleted list." id="eyq_p4g_3hb"?>
                                <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190405T140343-0500" comment="This is the result of copying concepts out of KOMET and inserting them into the document.  We will research what is wrong with why they are displaying this way.  " parentID="eyq_p4g_3hb" mid="16"?>
                                <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="242px" height="14px">
                                    <text x="1" y="7"
                                        style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                            >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                            style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; "
                                            >&#xF2D8; </tspan>
                                        <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Insulin dependent diabetes mellitus type 1
                                        A</text>
                                </svg><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="16"?>
                            </imagedata>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></link>, <link
                    xlink:href="#ge_solor_Pulse_rate_1f621ed0-b2b9-37bf-ba99-cdcdc1a6e24a"><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata>
                                <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="75px" height="14px">
                                    <text x="1" y="7"
                                        style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                            >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                            style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #5ec200; stroke: #5ec200; "
                                            >&#xF060; </tspan>
                                        <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Pulse rate]</text>
                                </svg>
                            </imagedata>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></link>, <link
                    xlink:href="#ge_solor_Administration_of_medication_8a39a4e6-97c8-3ab1-b589-71edfe1f32ce"><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata>
                                <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="165px" height="14px">
                                    <text x="1" y="7"
                                        style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                            >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                            style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #5ec200; stroke: #5ec200; "
                                            >&#xF12F; </tspan>
                                        <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Administration of medication]</text>
                                </svg>
                            </imagedata>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></link> . For each of these topics, the information that
                must be described is quite different, so CIMI describes topic types that contain the
                appropriate properties to describe the required information for the given topic. The
                number of topic types will change as CIMI progresses, but currently the allowable
                topic types are EvaluationResult, Assertion, and Procedure.</mathphrase>
        </editorial-rule>

        <editorial-rule>
            <title>Subject of information</title>
            <mathphrase>The <emphasis>Subject of Information</emphasis> represents who or what the
                statement refers to. In most cases, the <emphasis>Subject of Information</emphasis>
                refers to who or what the record within which this statement is embedded is about.
                In such cases, the <emphasis>Subject of Information</emphasis> may be referred to as
                the <emphasis>Subject of Record</emphasis>. In other cases, the <emphasis>Subject of
                    Information</emphasis> may refer to a relative of the <emphasis>Subject of
                    Record</emphasis> (mother, father, uncle...), and would be recorded
                appropriately in such circumstance. </mathphrase>
            <para/>
        </editorial-rule>

        <editorial-rule>
            <title>Statement time</title>
            <mathphrase>The Statement time is the time the statement is made. The statement time is
                independent of the period of time that a statement refers to, which may be past,
                present, or future, and is represented separately as part of the act. </mathphrase>
        </editorial-rule>

        <editorial-rule>
            <title>Act</title>
            <mathphrase>The Act is information that details the act related to the topic, either a
                request act, or a performance act.</mathphrase>
        </editorial-rule>
        <section xml:id="section_c7e8075d-6b35-41ba-897d-4ff54af45576">
            <title>Statement Layer Concerns</title>
            <para/>
            <para>The statement layer is primarily concerned with representation of instance data. </para>
            <section xml:id="section_fbd977ae-5780-48a3-87e2-0106a3c8dc80">
                <title>Measurement</title>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="section_29e5b4bb-bb99-42f0-bf5f-0456f4963bb1">
                <title>Reporter</title>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="section_5e801113-26fb-4edb-99d0-681bad2b9aa1">
                <title>Performer</title>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="section_d9921384-af14-4701-91d3-9f7b781afac8">
                <title>Subject of information</title>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_084eb260-3f85-44fc-a55e-447e2b404a81">
            <title>Crosscutting Concerns</title>
            <section xml:id="section_90257289-0292-45bc-b014-52fcdf1be4c0">
                <title>Query</title>
                <para/>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="section_12d7f603-3acd-4e35-b9b8-3f4994aa2d70">
            <title>Understandable, Reproducible, and
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T131224-0600" comment="Should this be Usable, to be consistent with prior section on URU, where it says it&apos;s:  Understandability, Reproducibility, and Usability?  Same where &quot;Useful&quot; is shown below." id="dhf_f3m_fhb"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190326T153718-0500" comment="should be Useful instead of Usability
" parentID="dhf_f3m_fhb" mid="15"?>Useful<?oxy_comment_end mid="15"?><?oxy_comment_end?></title>
            <para>Given a narrative, fill out the form. </para>
            <example xml:id="example_dc87fd7a-561e-4335-ae79-9bde3fb1fc05">
                <title>Pulse observed to be 110</title>
                <para>A patient tells their health-care provider that they had a <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_Pulse_rate_1f621ed0-b2b9-37bf-ba99-cdcdc1a6e24a"><inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata>
                                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T131339-0600" comment="1) Same a prior comment:  in the PDF there is a lot of white space in this and it&apos;s distracting and recommend just typing it.
2) THere isn&apos;t anything in the narrative that states the pulse rate was 110 - shouldn&apos;t there be?"?>
                                    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px" height="14px">
                                        <text x="1" y="7" style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;">[<tspan dy="1.5" style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #5ec200; stroke: #5ec200; ">&#xF060; </tspan>
                                            <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Pulse rate]</text>
                                    </svg><?oxy_comment_end?>
                                </imagedata>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></link> on Monday, April 23rd at 9:15 am Pacific
                    Standard Time. </para>
            </example>
            <example xml:id="example_7b0c38f2-acf3-48a8-a2d7-c06cf0e007cc">
                <title>Resting pulse requested to be less than 70</title>
                <para>A health-care provider tells a patient that they would like their resting
                    pulse to be less than 70. </para>
            </example>
            <para>In the case of a human
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T132121-0600" comment="Should this be spelled as &quot;interpreter&quot; instead?" flag="done"?>interpreter<?oxy_comment_end?>,
                they can often believe that they understand a statement, even when there is a great
                deal of information missing from the statement. In the above example, it was
                probably assumed that the units used to measure the blood pressure was mm/Hg, that
                the patient was at rest and seated, and that the pressure was measured from a
                brachial artery, either the brachial artery in the right arm, or the brachial artery
                in the left arm. </para>
            <para>In a face-to-face interaction, statements can often be clarified to
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T132219-0600" comment="What if assumed content isn&apos;t always correct?  Could it also deny it?"?>confirm<?oxy_comment_end?>
                assumed content, and to ensure effective communication of information from the
                creator to the interpretor. When recording statements for future interpretation,
                such verification of assumed content cannot be performed. This inability to clarify
                statements after the fact requires that statements sufficiently record the
                circumstances necessary to reproducibly interpret the statement.</para>
            <editorial-rule>
                <title>Understandable</title>
                <mathphrase>Editorial rules must be understandable to an editor or user simply by
                    reading the definition or rule. A statement must be understandable to the
                    creator and the interpreter.</mathphrase>
            </editorial-rule>
            <editorial-rule>
                <title>Reproducible</title>
                <mathphrase>Independent observers encountering a topic and equivalent circumstances
                    will record equivalent statements.</mathphrase>
            </editorial-rule>
            <editorial-rule>
                <title>Useful</title>
                <mathphrase>The representation must be useful for the purposes that the modeling is
                    intended to support. </mathphrase>
            </editorial-rule>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_f73a5fd3-af2d-4e34-8a4b-3854a63e7ffd">
            <title>Structured Statement</title>
            <para>Narrative: Pulse observed to be 100 bpm on Monday,
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T132951-0600" comment="Need to add &quot;2018&quot; here and in the narrative below since you included it in Statement time." flag="done"?>April
                23rd, 2018 <?oxy_comment_end?>at 9:15 am Pacific Standard Time</para>
            <para>Action Topic: Pulse</para>
            <para>Circumstance: facts or conditions relevant to an action; Two types of action:
                request, performance</para>
            <para>
                <table frame="topbot" rowsep="0" colsep="0" xml:id="table_9b08a484-6589-430a-bcb5-060703de35c3">
                    <title>Patient pulse representation of narrative with Structured
                        Statement</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="96.98pt"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="298.78pt"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row rowsep="1">
                                <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Performance Statement</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Narrative:</entry>
                                <entry>Pulse observed to be 100 bpm on Monday, April
                                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T132844-0600" comment="Need to add &quot;2018&quot; here since you showed it below in Statement time." flag="done"?>23rd<?oxy_comment_end?>,
                                    2018 at 9:15 am Pacific Standard Time</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Topic:</entry>
                                <entry>Pulse</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Subject of information:</entry>
                                <entry>Patient of Record</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Statement time:</entry>
                                <entry>Monday, April 23rd 2018 at 9:15 am Pacific Standard
                                    Time</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Act:</entry>
                                <entrytbl cols="3">
                                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1.86*"/>
                                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="6.48*"/>
                                    <tbody>
                                        <row rowsep="0">
                                            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Circumstance:</entry>
                                            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Timing:</entry>
                                            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                        </row>
                                        <row rowsep="0">
                                            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Result:</entry>
                                            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" namest="c2" nameend="c3">120 beats per minute </entry>
                                        </row>
                                    </tbody>
                                </entrytbl>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <section xml:id="section_5307a5f5-3008-4c0c-948b-f0a13c3e059c">
                <title>Modeling Principles</title>
                <para>The modeling guidelines were developed in accordance with the principles shown
                    below.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Separation of Concerns:</emphasis> As defined by
                                Wikipedia<footnote xml:id="__FN1A__">
                                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation_of_concerns">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation_of_concerns</link>
                                </para>
                            </footnote>: Separation of Concerns (SoC) is a design principle for
                            separating a computer program into distinct sections, such that each
                            section addresses a separate concern. A concern is a set of information
                            that affects the code of a computer program. A concern can be as general
                            as the details of the hardware the code is being optimized for, or as
                            specific as the name of a class to instantiate. A program that embodies
                            SoC well is called a modular program. Modularity, and hence separation
                            of concerns, is achieved by encapsulating information inside a section
                            of code that has a well-defined interface. Encapsulation is a means of
                            information hiding. Layered designs in information systems are another
                            embodiment of separation of concerns (e.g., presentation layer, business
                            logic layer, data access layer, persistence layer). The value of
                            separation of concerns is simplifying development and maintenance of
                            computer programs. When concerns are well-separated, individual sections
                            can be reused, as well as developed and updated independently. Of
                            special value is the ability to later improve or modify one section of
                            code without having to know the details of the other sections, and
                            without having to make corresponding changes to those sections.</para>
                        <para>The use of immutable objects (see Immutability principle below) is a
                            technique that fulfills the Separation of Concerns principle.</para>
                        <para>Attributes that describe specific semantic concepts should be grouped
                            together into a single class and not be spread across a number of
                            classes. Doing the latter leads to tight coupling between classes. Doing
                            the former leads to better decomposition of a potentially complex
                            domain.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis> Attributes for a Role (e.g.,
                            Practitioner) should not be mixed with attributes for an Entity (e.g.,
                            Person). This allows a person to assume a number of roles over their
                            lifetime or to function in more than one role.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Immutability: </emphasis>An Immutable Object as
                            defined by Wikipedia<footnote xml:id="__FN2A__">
                                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/immutable_object">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/immutable_object</link>
                                </para>
                            </footnote>: Used in object-oriented and functional programming, an
                            immutable object is something that cannot be changed after it is
                            created, in contrast to mutable objects that can be changed after they
                            are created. There are multiple reasons for using immutable objects,
                            including improved readability and runtime efficiency and higher
                            security.</para>
                        <para>Although building immutable objects…requires a bit more up-front
                            complexity, the downstream simplification forced by this abstraction
                            easily offsets the effort. One of the benefits of switching to a
                            functional mindset is the realization that tests exist to check that
                            changes occur successfully in code. In other words, testing’s real
                            purpose is to validate mutation – and the more mutation you have, the
                            more testing is required to make sure you get it right. If you isolate
                            the places where changes occur by severely restricting mutation, you
                            create a much smaller space for errors to occur and have few plates to
                            test.</para>
                        <para>Finally, one of the best features of immutable classes is how well
                            they fit into the composition abstraction.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Composition Over Inheritance:
                            </emphasis>Composition over inheritance (or composite reuse principle)
                            in object-oriented programming is the principle that classes should
                            achieve polymorphic behavior and code reuse by their composition (by
                            containing those instances of other classes that implement the desired
                            functionality) rather than inheritance from a base or parent
                            class.</para>
                        <para>To favor composition over inheritance is a design principle that gives
                            the design higher flexibility. It is more natural to build
                            business-domain classes out of various components than trying to find
                            commonality between them and creating a family tree.</para>
                        <para>Initial design is simplified by identifying system object behaviors in
                            separate interfaces instead of creating a hierarchical relationship to
                            distribute behaviors among business-domain classes via inheritance. This
                            approach more easily accommodates future requirements changes that would
                            otherwise require a complete restructuring of business-domain classes in
                            the inheritance model.</para>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Item for
                                Consideration:</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis> Should we say that we
                                only allow inheritance for a single concern, i.e., we can subtype
                                measurement but not subtype a combination of phenomenon type and
                                measurement type?</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Statement Model Stability:</emphasis> Stability
                            is different from immutability. Stable means that the model can still
                            meet unanticipated requirements without having to change. It is not
                            acceptable to change the model every time a new way to administer a drug
                            or to treat a condition is identified. By representing these types of
                            potentially dynamic concerns in the terminology expressions, as opposed
                            to static fields in a class structure, we do not have to change the
                            model every time something new is discovered. As Terry Winograd said,
                            anticipating breakdowns, and providing a space for action when they
                            occur, is a design imperative.</para>
                        <para>In some regards, in this context “stable” means “not brittle.” A model
                            easily broken by changes that someone could anticipate is one possible
                            definition of brittle. A stable model is critical in the phase of a
                            known changing landscape. We do that by isolating areas of anticipated
                            change into a dynamic data structure. That dynamic data structure may
                            also be immutable in an object that represents a clinical
                            statement.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Overall Model Simplicity: </emphasis>In cases
                            where different principles collide, we shall favor the enhancement of
                            simplicity of the entire system over simplicity in one area of the
                            system.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Cohesion: </emphasis>Related classes should
                            reside in the same module or construction. The placement of a class in a
                            module should reduce the dependencies between modules.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Reusability: </emphasis>Architectural patterns
                            should encourage class reusability where possible. Reusability may
                            further refine encapsulation when composition is considered.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Assumption-free: </emphasis>Implied semantics
                            must be surfaced explicitly in the model.</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Example: </emphasis>Implicit in the
                                    statement, “I order a book from Amazon” are: paying for the
                                    book, delivery of the book to some location, and the transfer of
                                    ownership of the book from the vendor to the client.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Design by Composition and/or Class
                                Specialization: </emphasis>The capture of additional model
                            expressivity must be captured by composition and/or by class
                            specialization. The modeling approach should avoid the use of design by
                            constraint (except for terminology binding and attribute type
                            constraints) as it violates proper decoupling and encapsulation. An
                            example of design by constraint is to create a single procedure class
                            containing
                            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T143951-0600" comment="Previously it was said that design by constraint should be avoided except for attribute type constraints.  Is the example here different from that?"?>all
                            attributes<?oxy_comment_end?> for all known procedures and constraining
                            out irrelevant attributes in a more specialized model. This approach is
                            very difficult to implement and violates numerous object-oriented best
                            practices.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">No False Dichotomies: </emphasis>Dichotomies
                            that are not completely disjoint (mutually exclusive) lead to arbitrary
                            classification rules and result in ambiguity based on different
                            assumptions about the domain. These must be avoided.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Model Should Avoid Semantic Overloading
                                (semantic precision): </emphasis>Semantic overloading occurs when a
                            model attribute’s meaning changes entirely, depending on context. While
                            the refinement of the semantics of an attribute in a subclass is
                            acceptable, a change of meaning is problematic. For instance, in FHIR,
                            the Composition class defines an attribute called Subject. In some
                            subclasses, the attribute may be the entity that this composition refers
                            to (e.g., the patient in a medical record). In other cases, it is the
                            topic being discussed by the composition (e.g., a medication orderable
                            catalog).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Convention Over Configuration:
                            </emphasis>Convention over configuration (also known as coding by
                            convention) is a software design paradigm used by software frameworks
                            that attempt to decrease the number of decisions that a developer using
                            the framework is required to make without necessarily losing
                            flexibility.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Model Consistency:</emphasis> Patterns should
                            allow the consistent representation of information that is commonly
                            shared across models. For instance, attribution and participation
                            information should be captured consistently. Failure to do so forces
                            implementers to develop heuristics to capture and normalize attribution
                            information that is represented or extended differently in different
                            classes (e.g., FHIR).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Model Symmetry: </emphasis>There should be
                            symmetry in the models wherever we can have it.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Iterative development and validation using use cases</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>


                <para>
                    <table frame="topbot" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
                        <title><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T150005-0600" comment="For both Pulse Measurement and Pulse Request statements, why isn&apos;t the info for the rest of the fields included, as applicable, particularly Narrative and Topic?"?>Pulse<?oxy_comment_end?>
                            Measurement Statement</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row rowsep="1">
                                    <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Performance Statement</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Narrative:</entry>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Topic:</entry>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Subject of information:</entry>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Statement time:</entry>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Performance Act:</entry>
                                    <entrytbl cols="3">
                                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1.86*"/>
                                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="6.48*"/>
                                        <tbody>
                                            <row rowsep="0">
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Circumstance:</entry>
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Timing:</entry>
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                            </row>
                                            <row rowsep="0">
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Result:</entry>
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" namest="c2" nameend="c3">120 beats per minute </entry>
                                            </row>
                                        </tbody>
                                    </entrytbl>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                </para>
                <para>
                    <table xml:id="table_7e8ac57c-08f8-4f1e-b1fc-af55f26c991d" colsep="0" rowsep="0" frame="topbot">
                        <title>Pulse Request Statement</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*" colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row rowsep="1">
                                    <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Request Statement</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row rowsep="0">
                                    <entry>Narrative:</entry>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                                <row rowsep="0">
                                    <entry>Topic:</entry>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Subject of information:</entry>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Statement time:</entry>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                                <row rowsep="0">
                                    <entry>Request Act:</entry>
                                    <entrytbl cols="3">
                                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="2.14*"/>
                                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="6.35*"/>
                                        <tbody>
                                            <row rowsep="0">
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Circumstance:</entry>
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Timing:</entry>
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                            </row>
                                            <row rowsep="0">
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Repetition:</entry>
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                            </row>
                                            <row rowsep="0">
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Requested
                                                  result:</entry>
                                                <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" namest="c2" nameend="c3">&lt; 70 beats per minute</entry>
                                            </row>
                                        </tbody>
                                    </entrytbl>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="section_70b0a98c-07ee-461f-943d-56b055dabf64">
                <title>Measurement</title>
                <para>
                    <editorial-rule>
                        <title>Measurement</title>
                        <mathphrase>Define measurement</mathphrase>
                    </editorial-rule>
                    <editorial-rule>
                        <title>Lower bound</title>
                        <mathphrase>The lower bound is the smallest reported value of the
                            measurement. If only one value is reported, then the lower bound is the
                            same as the upper bound.</mathphrase>
                    </editorial-rule>
                    <editorial-rule>
                        <title>Upper bound</title>
                        <mathphrase>The upper bound is the largest reported value of the
                            measurement. If only one value is reported, then the upper bound is the
                            same as the lower bound. </mathphrase>
                    </editorial-rule>
                    <editorial-rule>
                        <title>Include lower bound</title>
                        <mathphrase><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T151038-0600" comment="Recommend revising sentence to:  Indicate if the lower bound is withi or outside the interval represented by this measurement.  Same for Include upper bound below." flag="done"?>Indicate<?oxy_comment_end?>
                            if the lower bound is within or outside the interval represented by this
                            measurement.</mathphrase>
                    </editorial-rule>
                    <editorial-rule>
                        <title>Include upper bound</title>
                        <mathphrase>Indicate if the upper bound is within the interval represented
                            by this measurement, or outside the interval represented by this
                            measurement.</mathphrase>
                    </editorial-rule>
                    <editorial-rule>
                        <title>Resolution</title>
                        <mathphrase>An optional numeric representation of the resolution of this
                            measurement, using the same semantics as the measurement itself.
                        </mathphrase>
                    </editorial-rule>
                    <editorial-rule>
                        <title>Measure semantic</title>
                        <mathphrase>A concept that defines the semantic interpretation of the upper
                            and lower bounds of this measurement.</mathphrase>
                    </editorial-rule>
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="section_b139fa1d-0462-42f7-bc7a-182d28e32efd">
            <title>Statement Types</title>
            <para>The types of clinical statements are listed and described below. The rationale for
                selecting these types is: Clinicians basically do two categories of things with a
                patient that need to be documented as clinical statements.</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Performance of action</emphasis>: Actions may
                        include passive observation of a phenomenon related to patients and their
                        health status or family history, and may also include active interventions,
                        such as providing education or administering medications or documenting that
                        a patient is participating in exercise to improve their overall health
                        status.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Request for action</emphasis>: Requests for future
                        actions may include defining goals, consultation with other providers, or
                        active interventions.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE: </emphasis>Given that this work is not finalized yet,
                it is possible that additional clinical statement types may need to be added in the
                event
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T152038-0600" comment="Since that contract ended and apparently did not result in identifying new statement types that are needed, should this sentence be revised?"?>during
                creation of the KNARTs<?oxy_comment_end?> there are clinical terminology artifacts
                identified that do not fit into any of the types listed above.</para>
            <para>Any statement that states or implies an “if/then” clause should be expressed and
                captured as an Event Condition Action (ECA) rule.</para>
            <para>Example: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>“Free-text reminder: Consider [ordering X procedure] for patients with
                        suspected pericarditis, myocarditis, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, or
                        pulmonary hypertension.”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Implied “if/then” clause: <emphasis role="bold">IF</emphasis>
                        pericarditis, myocarditis, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, or pulmonary
                        hypertension is suspected – <emphasis role="bold">THEN</emphasis> consider
                        ordering X procedure.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Rather than capturing the above statement as a free text reminder,
                        building an appropriate ECA rule should be considered.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <section xml:id="section_e50dee69-daff-4b15-8e2b-a2eb6bc21b21">
                <title>Performance Statements</title>
                <para>An action statement describes an action that has previously been performed,
                    and – if applicable - the results of that action. As shown in the examples
                    below, this can range from documenting that a subject of record: </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Was observed to have the presence or absence of a clinical
                            phenomenon</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Underwent a specific test/screening or procedure, and its resultant
                            value, if any</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Was administered a medication or other substance </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Was provided educational materials</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Has any other state or specific characteristic that is clinically
                            relevant</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>If the action statement:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Regards a measurement that was taken, all information about that
                            measurement will be included as part of the clinical statement, such as
                            its value and unit of measure and any details about how the measurement
                            was taken. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Results in an order(s) placed during the same encounter that was made
                            to learn more about the phenomenon or to monitor it, then a link will be
                            made to the order(s). </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Examples of Action clinical statements:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Systolic blood pressure of 120 mmHg taken from right brachial artery
                            while seated and no more than 30 minutes from when the patient last
                            urinated</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Diabetes mellitus is present</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Diabetes mellitus is not present</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Three dot blot hemorrhages</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Dot blot hemorrhage is present</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patient taking one Acetaminophen 100 mg tablet by mouth daily as
                            needed for pain</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Positive screen for fall risk</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Negative screen for PTSD and depression</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Family history of colon cancer </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patient provided educational materials on pre-diabetes
                            diagnosis</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patient counseled on the health risks of continuing smoking </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="section_3cd03dbb-48dd-4bdc-8f29-fa20bfd459c9">
                <title>Request Statements</title>
                <para>A Request clinical statement describes a request for an action made by a
                    clinician. Most of the times, but not always, the object of the request (e.g.,
                    lab test, medication order) will be fulfilled by someone other than the
                    clinician (e.g., lab technician, pharmacist) making the request. All information
                    about the request will be documented in this clinical statement, including
                    information about details relating to the request, such as patient must fast for
                    12 hours before having a lipids blood test.</para>
                <para>Examples of Request clinical statements:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Lipids panel for patient Jane Doe. Patient must fast for 12 hours
                            prior to the blood test.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Head CT with contrast for patient John Doe. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Cardiology referral for patient Mary Smith.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Penicillin medication for patient Michael Smith to be taken twice a
                            day by mouth with food for 10 days.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Advised to participate in group tobacco cessation counseling once a
                            week.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Advised to lose 15 pounds within 3 months.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Advised to exercise at least 3 times a week for 30 minutes per day for
                            3 months. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Advised to decrease the number of packs smoked per day from 3 to 2
                            within 6 months by using a nicotine patch.</para>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_1b4e6bff-3a99-465f-95ae-89b8ac23bc6e">
            <title>Statement Building Blocks</title>
            <para>The following components are used in multiple places within clinical statements. </para>
            <para/>
            <section xml:id="section_a4879816-b718-4def-80a1-926f2850f40e">
                <title><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T152743-0600" comment="I changed this to all caps since that&apos;s how it&apos;s referred to previously." flag="done"?>STAMP<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    Coordinate</title>
                <para>The STAMP coordinate represents the versions of the integrated terminology and
                    statement model used to represent a clinical statement. </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref493843805">
                <title>Phenomena and Interval Values</title>
                <para>In many representation models, such as SNOMED-CT and CIMI, a somewhat
                    arbitrary distinction exists between the modeling of “Findings” and “Observable
                    Entities.” The former typically document the presence or absence of some
                    phenomenon in the patient (such as whether the patient has a pressure ulcer),
                    whereas the latter characterize some feature of the patient or the patient’s
                    condition (such as the number of pressure ulcers a patient has). <xref linkend="table_95d32b2d-0ebf-4caf-abb0-380bf1ff3551"/> shows an example of
                    the different representations for these two similar observations when modeled as
                    Findings versus Observable Entity.<table frame="topbot" rowsep="0" colsep="0" xml:id="table_95d32b2d-0ebf-4caf-abb0-380bf1ff3551">
                        <title>An undesirable redundancy in representing clinical
                            observations.</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Pressure Ulcer as Finding</entry>
                                    <entry>Pressure Ulcer as Observable Entity</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>[Pressure Ulcer(s)]→(value)→[Present]</entry>
                                    <entry>[Pressure Ulcer(s)]→(value)→5</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>[Pressure Ulcer(s)]→(value)→[Absent]</entry>
                                    <entry>[Pressure Ulcer(s)]→(value)→0</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry/>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table></para>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T153036-0600" comment="This paragraph doesn&apos;t make sense.  It also seems partially redundant of the paragraph above it." id="nf3_c5s_fhb"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190327T125559-0500" comment="Deleted paragraph above.  Will clarify paragraph in next round." parentID="nf3_c5s_fhb" mid="27"?>Because
                    the observation of pressure ulcers<link xlink:href="#con_224b97e0-b703-39f6-ba4b-aa27f5dc15aa"><inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata>
                                    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px" height="14px">
                                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T152917-0600" comment="Same as prior comment.  Recommend just typing this here."?>
                                        <text x="1" y="7" style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"><?oxy_comment_end?>[<tspan dy="1.5" style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; ">&#xF061; </tspan>
                                            <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Tetralogy of Fallot]</text>
                                    </svg>
                                </imagedata>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></link> in a patient could be correctly modeled as
                    either a Finding or Observable Entity Text before. <link xlink:href="#table_9b08a484-6589-430a-bcb5-060703de35c3"><inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata>
                                    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px" height="14px">
                                        <text x="1" y="7" style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;">[<tspan dy="1.5" style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; ">&#xF2D8; </tspan>
                                            <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Overriding structures]</text>
                                    </svg>
                                </imagedata>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></link> Text
                    after.<?oxy_comment_end mid="27"?><?oxy_comment_end?> any subsequent query to
                    determine whether a patient had a pressure ulcer would need to test for the
                    observation in two different ways: </para>
                <para><emphasis>IF EXISTS object WHERE object.conceptId = “3456_PressureUlcers” AND
                        (object.value = “Present” OR object.value &gt; 0)</emphasis></para>
                <para>This duality of representation complicates data querying and significantly
                    increases the possibility that data analysts will not be aware of and account
                    for all the ways that an observation may be represented, resulting in
                    false-negative query results.</para>
                <para>To resolve the arbitrary distinction between “Findings” and “Observable
                    Entities,” one must consolidate these redundant concept types into the single
                    concept type “Phenomenon.” Further, one must introduce a new data type to
                    represent the values of Phenomena, one that can express both the “presence”
                    (present/absent/indeterminate) and numeric (integer, real) values that Findings
                    and Observable Entities can currently represent, respectively. This new data
                    type is an “interval value.” </para>
                <para/>
                <section>
                    <title>The Interval Value Data Type</title>
                    <para>An interval value data type (or “interval value”) formally represents a
                        numeric interval between two non-negative real numbers. The interval can be
                        open or closed. Examples of interval values are:</para>
                    <para>[5,5], [0,10), (0,∞], [0,0]</para>
                    <para>The formal syntax of interval values is represented by the following
                        grammar:</para>
                    <para>Interval :: [ ‘[‘ | ‘(‘ ] N1 ‘,’ N2 [ ‘]’ | ‘)’ ]</para>
                    <para>N1 :: Non-Negative Real Number</para>
                    <para>N2 :: [ Non-Negative Real Number | ∞ ]</para>
                    <para>The semantics of this grammar are as follows:</para>
                    <para>‘[‘ and ‘]’ : Inclusive boundary (i.e. &gt;= and &lt;= )</para>
                    <para>‘(‘ and ‘)’ : Exclusive boundary (i.e., &gt; and &lt; )</para>
                    <para>∞: infinity, is &gt; every Non-Negative Real Number</para>
                    <para>N1 &lt;= N2</para>
                    <para>The interval value data type provides a single way to represent both
                        “presence” values and numeric values for a phenomenon. In general, the
                        interval value represents the numeric range within which the observed value
                        of a phenomenon occurs. Note that this formalism allows both exact values
                        and ranges of values to be expressed.</para>
                    <para>In the special case that the beginning and end point of an interval are
                        the same number, <emphasis>n</emphasis>, the meaning is that the value of
                        the phenomenon is <emphasis>exactly n</emphasis>. </para>
                    <para>[5,5] : exactly 5 ; [0,0] : exactly 0</para>
                    <para>In the special case that the beginning of the interval is a number,
                            <emphasis>n</emphasis>, and the end point is ∞, the meaning is that the
                        value of the phenomenon is <emphasis>&gt; n </emphasis>or
                            <emphasis>&gt;=n</emphasis>, depending on whether the interval is open
                        or closed.</para>
                    <para>(0,∞] : &gt; 0 ; [10,∞] : &gt;= 10</para>
                    <para>The interval value also represents whether a phenomenon is “present”,
                        “absent”, or “indeterminate”. Specifically, any interval value that includes
                            <emphasis>only </emphasis>numbers that are &gt; 0 also denotes the value
                        “present”. Any interval value that includes only the number 0, itself,
                        denotes the value “absent”. Any interval value that includes
                            <emphasis>both</emphasis> the number 0 and at least one number &gt; 0
                        denotes the value “indeterminate”. Lastly, there are two interval values
                        that explicitly denote “present” and “absent,” respectively. These values
                        may be assigned to phenomena that would not otherwise take on a numeric
                        value (such as “nausea”):</para>
                    <para>Nausea value = (0,∞] : present</para>
                    <para>Nausea value = [0,0] : absent </para>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Ref493768774"/> lists a number of phenomena and how their
                        current values (as “Findings” or “Observable Entities”) would be represented
                        instead as interval values under the model proposed here.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493768774">
                        <title>The semantics of interval values assigned to phenomena, as shown
                            through examples.</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/interval-values-for-phenomena.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Comparing Interval Values using IsWithin()</title>
                    <para>Phenomena that represent clinical observations must be assigned interval
                        values, so the querying of such phenomena for purposes of data retrieval and
                        data analysis requires the comparison of interval values. Specifically, one
                        must be able to test whether one interval value <emphasis>is
                            within</emphasis> (i.e., encompassed by) another interval value. For
                        example, if one wanted to retrieve only those patients who had between 1 and
                        5 pressure ulcers, one would test whether a patient had the phenomenon
                        “pressure ulcer” recorded with a value interval that was within the interval
                        [1,5]. Note that this test would retrieve patients who had pressure-ulcer
                        interval values, for example, of [1,1], [4,4], and [3,5], but not those who
                        had [0,0] or [1,10].</para>
                    <para>Formally, the comparison of two interval values is done using the
                        predicate <emphasis>IsWithin(
                            i</emphasis><subscript>1</subscript><emphasis>, i</emphasis><subscript>2
                            </subscript><emphasis>), </emphasis>where i<subscript>1</subscript>,
                            i<subscript>2 </subscript>are interval values. The values of the
                        IsWithin() predicate may be TRUE, FALSE, or UNKNOWN, determined as
                        follows:</para>
                    <para>TRUE =&gt; if a number is in i<subscript>1</subscript>, then it is
                        definitely in i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript>
                        “subsumes” i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para>FALSE =&gt; if a number is in i<subscript>1</subscript>, then it is
                        definitely NOT in i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript>
                            “i<subscript>1</subscript>is disjoint with”
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para>UNKNOWN =&gt; if a value is in, it may or may not be in
                            i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript> “overlaps”
                            i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para>Examples of interval-value comparisons:</para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin</emphasis>( [5,5], [0,10] ) =&gt; TRUE (interval
                            i<subscript>2</subscript> “subsumes” interval
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin</emphasis>( [15,20], [0,10] ) =&gt; FALSE (interval
                            i<subscript>2</subscript> “is disjoint with” interval
                            i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para><emphasis><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T095940-0600" comment="Why wouldn&apos;t this be false vs. unknown since upperbound for interval2 is 10 vs. 15?"?>IsWithin<?oxy_comment_end?></emphasis>(
                        [5,15], [0,10] ) =&gt; UNKNOWN (interval i<subscript>2</subscript>
                        “overlaps” interval i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para>Other useful examples:</para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [2,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                            TRUE</emphasis></para>
                    <para><emphasis><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T095750-0600" comment="Again, I definitely am not a mathematician and am just trying to understand this.  Why is this unknown vs. false since the interval2 excluded 0 and interval1 includes it?"?>IsWithin<?oxy_comment_end?>(
                            [0,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt; UNKNOWN </emphasis></para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( (0,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                            TRUE</emphasis></para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [0,0], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                            FALSE</emphasis></para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [0,0], [0,0] ) =&gt; TRUE</emphasis></para>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Querying Phenomena Using Interval Values</title>
                <para>Based on the definition of the IsWithin() predicate, patient records may be
                    queried for the presence or the numeric value of clinical observations using a
                    single formalism.</para>
                <section xml:id="section_4ba31e20-94ae-4d32-86a6-0d16fe45b3a9">
                    <title>UUID</title>
                    <para>The UUID is the means by which all clinical statement items that require
                        unique identifiers are identified. </para>
                </section>
                <section xml:id="section_a90e0e13-e26f-4e0f-95a1-bd3d6884c6fa">
                    <title>Logical Expression</title>
                </section>
                <section xml:id="section_d77f3cb2-b433-4811-acee-39c70e475f67">
                    <title>STAMP Coordinate</title>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="section_55e57c1b-49ed-47b3-8e74-b443103c0af8">
                <title>Compound Statements</title>
                <section xml:id="section_2beebad7-bd18-4e6d-8228-f67220a7750a">
                    <title>Use case: Systolic BP while seated with
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T102044-0600" comment="This is nit picky but the use case only says seated and doesn&apos;t specify feet on the floor.  I am short and can be seated but not have feet on the floor, such as when I&apos;m sitting on the exam table having my BP checked and my feet don&apos;t reach."?>feet<?oxy_comment_end?>
                        on the floor for 5 minutes</title>
                    <bridgehead renderas="sect1"><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T100537-0600" comment="Should this be under a numbered section heading?"?>Principles<?oxy_comment_end?></bridgehead>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 1:</emphasis> Clinical
                                statements have separable and inseparable components; clinical
                                statements with separable components are considered
                                    <emphasis>compound</emphasis> clinical statements.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 2:</emphasis> Separable
                                components are statements, which require a value. </para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>The values can be: </para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>numerical </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>pseudo-numerical, e.g. low/medium/high</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Present/absent</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 3:</emphasis> Clinical
                                statements with values can stand alone.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 4:</emphasis> Clinical
                                statements with present/absent values can be components that play a
                                role in the focus of the statement.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 5:</emphasis> Inseparable
                                components of clinical statements do not require values.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>Compound clinical statements with separable components should be
                        represented as “panels,” with each separable clinical statement as a “stand
                        alone” statement, which can be referenced by multiple “panels.”</para>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Examples:</emphasis></para>
                    <table xml:id="table_87bc807a-743b-4148-a89f-8daf97b8f242">
                        <title>Separable/Inseparable Statements - Blood Pressure Measurement Use
                            Case</title>
                        <tgroup cols="3">
                            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="42*"/>
                            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="31*"/>
                            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="26*"/>
                            <tbody valign="top">
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">USE CASE</emphasis></para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">SEPARABLE
                                            STATEMENTS</emphasis></para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">INSEPARABLE
                                                COMPONENTS</emphasis></para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry morerows="3" valign="middle">
                                        <para>BP of 120/80 mmHg on right brachial artery, patient in
                                            sitting position for at least 5 min., using adult BP
                                            cuff, urinary bladder voided within 30 min. before
                                            measurement</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Systolic BP = 120 mmHg</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Using adult BP cuff</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Diastolic BP = 80 mmHg</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Right brachial artery</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Time since last urination = 30 min. or less</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para> Sitting position</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Time in sitting position = 5 min. or more</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom"/>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                    <para>The “panel” above would consist of the following statements:</para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Blood pressure on right brachial artery, using adult cuff, with
                                patient in sitting position</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Systolic BP = 120 mmHg</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Diastolic BP = 80 mmHg</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Time since last urination = 30 min. or less</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Time in sitting position = 5 min. or more</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <table xml:id="table_d2260126-0da5-439f-ba68-4e59a7d67b21">
                        <title>Separable/Inseparable Statements - Administration of Nitroglycerin
                            Use Case</title>
                        <tgroup cols="3">
                            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="43*"/>
                            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="31*"/>
                            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="26*"/>
                            <tbody valign="top">
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">USE CASE</emphasis></para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">SEPARABLE
                                            STATEMENTS</emphasis></para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">INSEPARABLE
                                                COMPONENTS</emphasis></para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry morerows="6" valign="middle">
                                        <para>Administration of nitroglycerin 0.4 mg tablet
                                            sub-lingual every 5 minutes as needed for chest pain;
                                            maximum 3 tablets (routine)</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Strength = 0.4 mg</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Administration</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Frequency = every 5 minutes </para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Nitroglycerin</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Maximum dosage = 3 tablets</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Tablet</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom"/>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>As needed</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom"/>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Sublingual</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom"/>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>For chest pain</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry valign="bottom"/>
                                    <entry valign="bottom">
                                        <para>Routine</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                    <para>The “panel” above would consist of the following statements:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Administration of nitroglycerin tablets as needed, sublingual, for
                                chest pain, routine priority</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Medication strength = 0.4 mg</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Frequency = every 5 minutes</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Maximum dosage = 3 tablets</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Pseudo-numerical values</emphasis> are qualitative
                        scales, e.g.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Low/medium/high</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Mild/moderate/severe</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Tumor staging and grading</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>+ pos./++ pos./+++ pos.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Statements with absent/present values</emphasis> are
                        considered <emphasis role="bold">inseparable</emphasis> components, if they
                        are <emphasis role="bold">part of</emphasis> the focus of the
                        statement.</para>
                    <para><emphasis>Example statement</emphasis>: Patient has warm skin and blue
                        eyes.</para>
                    <para>Warm skin and blue eyes are the focus of this statement; both components
                        have a value of “present” and they are <emphasis role="bold">part
                            of</emphasis> the focus of the statement and are therefore considered
                        inseparable:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Blue eyes = present</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Warm skin = present</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>Other components, such as <emphasis>right brachial artery</emphasis> and
                            <emphasis>adult BP cuff</emphasis> in the BP measurement use case
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T101541-0600" comment="This contradicts what is shown in the table above, that clearly has them labeled as inseparable components."?>are
                        considered separable<?oxy_comment_end?>, although they may appear to be able
                        to stand alone and have values of present/absent.</para>
                    <para><emphasis>Example </emphasis><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>action</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis> statement:
                            </emphasis>Systolic<emphasis> </emphasis>BP 120 mmHg taken on right
                        brachial artery, using adult BP cuff</para>
                    <para>The right brachial artery and the adult BP have (implied) values of
                        “present”, but they are <emphasis role="bold">not part of the
                            focus</emphasis> of the statement (Blood pressure). Therefore, they are
                        considered separable.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Right brachial artery = present</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Adult BP cuff = present</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>The right brachial artery <emphasis role="bold">plays a role</emphasis> as
                        the site of the blood pressure. Similarly, the adult BP cuff <emphasis role="bold">plays a role</emphasis> as the device used to perform the
                        measurement. </para>
                    <para><emphasis>Example </emphasis><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>request</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis> statement:
                        </emphasis>BP measurement to take on right brachial artery, using adult BP
                        cuff</para>
                    <para>The right brachial artery and the adult BP have (implied) values of
                        “present”, but they are <emphasis role="bold">not part of the
                            focus</emphasis> of the statement (blood pressure). Therefore, they are
                        considered separable.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Right brachial artery = present</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Adult BP cuff = present</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>The right brachial artery <emphasis role="bold">plays a role</emphasis> as
                        the site of the blood pressure measurement. Similarly, the adult BP cuff
                            <emphasis role="bold">plays a role</emphasis> as the device used to
                        perform the measurement. </para>
                    <para>The two examples above show, that the focus of the statements does not
                        change. It is in both cases the blood pressure. The roles of the right
                        brachial artery and the adult BP cuff consequently do not change,
                        either.</para>
                    <para>The separable components of a clinical statements are also variables. BP
                        measurement can be performed at a different body site (e.g. left brachial
                        artery) or using a different device (e.g. digital BP machine). However, the
                        focus of the statement remains the same.</para>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Other examples:</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Head CT with contrast: Contrast media plays a role as an imaging
                                substance used</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Dobutamine stress echocardiogram: Dobutamine plays a role as a
                                substance to induce cardiac stress</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>BP measurement taken at doctor’s office: The office plays a role
                                as an environment</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Body temperature reported by nurse: The nurse plays a role as the
                                finding informer</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <section xml:id="section_1197e8bb-7ae1-480c-b421-f83af8b5c71a">
                        <title>Details</title>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 1:</emphasis> Details
                                    refine or further qualify the topic. Topic type and topic focus
                                    together with the details sufficiently define instance
                                    requests.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 2:</emphasis> Not
                                    every action or request requires details to be sufficiently
                                    defined.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 3:</emphasis> A
                                    detail has a key and a value, where the value can be a concept
                                    or a numeric range with unit.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Proposed Principle 4:</emphasis> A
                                    detail can be a separable or inseparable part of a complex
                                    clinical statement.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                        <para><emphasis role="highlight"><emphasis role="bold">The criteria for
                                    identifying the focus and details that are not part of the
                                    focus, but play a role in a clinical statement suggest that
                                    “details” are </emphasis><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">
                                    components, which </emphasis><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">play a
                                    role</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="bold"> and are
                                    therefore separable components.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Examples:</emphasis></para>
                        <table xml:id="table_3e60408b-f9f1-40c6-b9bd-444a00d75fe0">
                            <title>Separable/Inseparable Statements – Details</title>
                            <tgroup cols="7">
                                <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="13*"/>
                                <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="28*"/>
                                <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="12*"/>
                                <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="12*"/>
                                <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="13*"/>
                                <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="9*"/>
                                <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="13*"/>
                                <tbody valign="top">
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Detail</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Has (Pseudo-) Numeric
                                                  Value</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Has Present/Absent
                                                  Value</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Part of Focus of
                                                  Statement</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Plays Role</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Separable/</emphasis></para>
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Inseparable</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Actor</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Person making the request or documenting/reporting
                                                the action</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Approach/Access Route</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Passage used to reach the procedure site or take a
                                                measurement</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T102442-0600" comment="Again in the BP use case example, body position (sitting) was shown as inseparable.  Not sure if right brachial artery is considered approach/access route but if yes, then it too was shown in the example as inseparable vs. separable."?>Body
                                                position<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Position of the body during a
                                                procedure/test</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Priority</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Priority of the request, e.g. Stat or
                                                Routine</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Indication</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Reason that a request was made or an action
                                                taken</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Duration</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>A length of time, such as for 7 days, within 24
                                                hours, or as needed</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Frequency</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>How often something must be done, such as daily,
                                                twice per day</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Detail</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Has (Pseudo-) Numeric
                                                  Value</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Has Present/Absent
                                                  Value</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Part of Focus of
                                                  Statement</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Plays Role</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Separable/</emphasis></para>
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Inseparable</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Route of Administration</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Way in which something, such as a medication, is
                                                given to a patient, such as by mouth/oral,
                                                intravenously, sublingual</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Strength</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Strength of a unit of the medication/drug itself,
                                                such as 25 mg</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Amount</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Amount of the medication/drug that is to be taken
                                                at a given time, such as 2 tablets</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Dosage</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Equals strength multiplied by amount, e.g. 2
                                                tablets of 25mg equals 50mg</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Projection</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>The path taken by an x-ray beam or
                                                ultrasonographical wave as it passes through the
                                                body</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Substance used</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Substance such as contrast media for imaging or
                                                catecholamine for stress induction</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Device used</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T104135-0600" comment="Again, in the BP use case, the adult BP cuff was shown as an inseparable component."?>Device
                                                used to perform something, such as using a BP cuff
                                                to measure blood pressure <?oxy_comment_end?></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Device setting</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Specific settings for a device used to perform a
                                                procedure, such as O2 Flow Rate 5 to 12 L/min</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Informer</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Person who reports a test result or gives
                                                information about the patient</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Detail</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Has (Pseudo-) Numeric
                                                  Value</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Has Present/Absent
                                                  Value</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Part of Focus of
                                                  Statement</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Plays Role</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Separable/</emphasis></para>
                                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Inseparable</emphasis></para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Performer</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Person who performs an action</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Assessment Scale</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry valign="middle">
                                            <para>Reference scale use for scoring</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>no</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>yes</para>
                                        </entry>
                                        <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                                            <para>separable</para>
                                        </entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </tgroup>
                        </table>
                        <section xml:id="section_81cca6ed-501d-43d1-86d9-951b1955ab3b">
                            <title>Details/Roles in the Context of Use Cases</title>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Approach/Access
                                            Route</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Passage used to reach the procedure site or take a
                                                  measurement.<emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Excision of rib by <emphasis>cervical
                                                  approach</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Administration of enema via <emphasis>rectal
                                                  route</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Body
                                        Position</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The position of the body during a procedure/test. </para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Colonoscopy in <emphasis>right lateral
                                                  position</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Blood pressure measurement in
                                                  <emphasis>seated position</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>ECG in <emphasis>lying
                                                  position</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role:
                                            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T104600-0600" comment="Body Site was not included in the Details table above.  Should it have been?"?>Body
                                            Site<?oxy_comment_end?></emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The body site of a finding or a procedure</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Blood pressure measurement on
                                                  <emphasis>right brachial artery</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Removal of tattoo from <emphasis>left upper
                                                  arm</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Priority</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The priority of the request, such as Stat or
                                                Routine. </para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Blood sugar measurement 3 times/day,
                                                  <emphasis>routine</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Indication</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The reason for a request made or an action
                                                  taken.<emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>ECG to evaluate <emphasis>chest
                                                  pain</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>X-ray of hands to evaluate
                                                  <emphasis>rheumatoid arthritis</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Patient placed in observation status due to
                                                  <emphasis>suicidal thoughts</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Duration</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>A length of time, such as for 7 days, within 24
                                                hours</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Physical therapy for <emphasis>3
                                                  weeks</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Administration of Aspirin 200mg oral tablets
                                                  for pain as needed for <emphasis>2
                                                  days</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Frequency</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>How often something must be done, such as daily,
                                                twice per day or
                                                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T105008-0600" comment="How is this different from daily, which is already shown as an example?"?>once
                                                in a 24-hour period<?oxy_comment_end?>.</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Chest x-ray <emphasis>once daily</emphasis>
                                                  to evaluate pneumonia</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Psychiatric evaluation
                                                  <emphasis>bi-weekly</emphasis> for PTSD</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Route of
                                            Administration</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The way in which something, such as a medication,
                                                is given to a patient.</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Patient taking two Acetaminophen 100mg
                                                  tablets <emphasis>by mouth</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Strength</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The strength of the medication/drug</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Patient taking two Acetaminophen
                                                  <emphasis>100mg</emphasis> tablets by mouth</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Amount</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The amount of the medication/drug that is to be
                                                taken at a given time, such as 2 tablets. </para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Patient taking <emphasis>two</emphasis>
                                                  Acetaminophen 100mg tablets by mouth</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role:
                                            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T105154-0600" comment="This wasn&apos;t shown in the Details table above.  Should it have been?"?>Dose
                                            Form<?oxy_comment_end?></emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The form of preparation of a medication</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Patient taking <emphasis>two</emphasis>
                                                  Acetaminophen <emphasis>100mg</emphasis>
                                                  <emphasis>tablets</emphasis>
                                                  <emphasis>by mouth</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Dosage</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Equals strength multiplied by amount. </para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Patient taking two tablets of Acetaminophen
                                                  100mg each = <emphasis>amount of 200mg</emphasis>.
                                                  </para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Projection</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The path taken by an x-ray beam or
                                                ultrasonographical wave as it passes through the
                                                body </para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>MRI of brain <emphasis>sagittal and
                                                  transversal</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para><emphasis>Transthoracic</emphasis>
                                                  echocardiogram</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Substance
                                        Used</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Substance such as contrast media for imaging or
                                                catecholamine for stress induction</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Head CT with
                                                  <emphasis>contrast</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para><emphasis>Radioisotope</emphasis> study of
                                                  musculoskeletal system</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para><emphasis>Dye</emphasis> test of fallopian
                                                  tube</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Device Used</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>A device used to perform an action, such as using
                                                a sphygmomanometer to measure blood pressure or a
                                                ventilator to help a patient breath.</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Lithotripsy using
                                                  <emphasis>laser</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Biopsy using <emphasis>Watson
                                                  capsule</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Device
                                        Setting</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Specific settings for a device used to perform a
                                                procedure, such as </para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Oxygen therapy, <emphasis>O2 Flow Rate 5 to
                                                  12 L/min.</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Electrode setting for electro-surgery
                                                  <emphasis>12 watts</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role:
                                            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T110005-0600" comment="This one was also not shown in the table.  If the table wasn&apos;t all-inclusive, I think it would be best to show only examples in this section for details that were shown in the table, to avoid confusion."?>Family
                                            Member<?oxy_comment_end?></emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Blood relative of the patient, such as mother,
                                                maternal grandfather. This information is used to
                                                identify which family member(s) have a history of
                                                certain phenomena.</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para><emphasis>Maternal</emphasis> pyrexia</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Drug misuse by
                                                  <emphasis>father</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Informer</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Person reporting/documenting an action result or
                                                giving information about the patient.</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Patient medical history reported by
                                                  <emphasis>spouse</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Bedside blood sugar measurement reported by
                                                  <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T110057-0600" comment="This should be shown in italic font." flag="done"?><emphasis>nurse</emphasis><?oxy_comment_end?></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Role: Performer</emphasis></para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Person performing an action</para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Blood pressure measurement taken by
                                                  <emphasis>physician</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Diabetes education given by<emphasis>
                                                  dietician</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </section>
                    </section>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="section_bd1f7cf1-b2b8-4821-afab-3a4fe39c0b4a">
                <title>Encoded Statements </title>
                <section xml:id="section_238419b7-a2e8-478c-89ed-c15787f89031">
                    <title>Procedures</title>
                </section>
                <section xml:id="section_5531cfa4-c0bd-4f7d-80f0-ca2ce09964a8">
                    <title>Finding, Observation, and Phenomenon</title>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Statement Models</title>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T110646-0600" comment="Is this a placeholder until more information can be provided?  It&apos;s not a complete sentence."?>Analysis
                    normal form and clinical input form</para>
            </section><?oxy_comment_end?>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_74f143a7-6834-4d5e-9991-b7c87a6eb276">
            <title>Validation</title>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To provide a validation framework for inter-modeler reliability when
                            applied in the field. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190319T110739-0600" comment="WIll this section be updated since the KNART project is over?"?>To<?oxy_comment_end?>
                            provide information on how clinical statements will be modeled for the
                            KBS Clinical Decision Support (CDS) Knowledge Artifact (KNART) project.
                            Once the models are approved, model slots bound to terminologies will be
                            identified for subsequent terminology binding definitions proposed by
                            the VA Terminology Team. Modeling of clinical statements outside of the
                            CDS KNART project is currently beyond the scope of this effort.</para>
                        <para>These modeling guidelines were derived from several documented use
                            cases. The main goal of this effort is to provide a reproducible and a
                            principled approach to the formal capture of clinical knowledge within
                            Information Models and their references to underlying Terminology
                            Models. Currently, the proposal and examples are independent of any
                            specific terminology.</para>
                        <para>These guidelines will be distributed to a variety of participants to
                            contribute to a modeling exercise. After having read the guidelines,
                            participants will be asked to access a survey where they will view a
                            number of clinical statements and indicate how they would model them.
                                <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>When attempting the modeling
                                    exercise, it will be important to model per the guidelines
                                    specified in this document regardless of how existing
                                    terminologies, such as SNOMED-CT, may model these
                                    concepts</emphasis></emphasis>. In the future, an exercise to
                            reconcile approaches may be conducted but is out-of-scope at this
                            time.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
