<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">

    <title>Background: HL7 Clinical Statement Standards</title>
    <para>Clinical statement standardization has been a long-standing concern for HL7 and reuse of
      these content models across paradigms (e.g. messages, documents, services). Standardization
      has relied on model-driven approaches requiring a separation of concerns along with
      conceptual, logical, and implementation perspectives.</para>
    <para>HL7 Service-Aware Interoperability Framework (SAIF) organizes HL7 standards along three
      perspectives (i.e. conceptual, logical, and implementable). </para>
    <section>
      <title>HL7 Service-Aware Interoperability Framework (SAIF)</title>
      <para>To augment the HL7 Version 2 and Version 3 representations, HL7 introduced an
        architecture to allow for a clear separation of concerns among interoperability models and
        specifications from the abstract or conceptual to the most precise, implementable, and
        testable that ensures semantic interoperability. This architecture is the HL7 Service-Aware
        Interoperability Framework Canonical Definition (SAIF-CD).<link linkend="bib6"
        >[9]</link></para>
      <para>The SAIF-CD specification <link linkend="bib6">[9]</link> defines three SAIF
        Perspectives: Conceptual, Logical, and Implementable. These perspectives are not formally
        equivalent with <glossterm baseform="Object Management Group">Object Management Group’s
          (OMG)</glossterm> levels-of-abstraction in
          <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T120946-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?><glossterm
          baseform="Model Driven Architecture">Model-Driven Architecture
        (MDA)</glossterm><?oxy_comment_end?> even though it reuses the same derivation. Therefore,
        the Implementable Perspective is derived from the Logical Perspective and the Logical
        Perspective is derived from the Conceptual Perspective. This approach ensures that any
        implementable artifacts (i.e. service specifications, implementation guides) are traceable
        to business/clinical requirements and logical models of knowledge.</para>
      <figure xml:id="SAIF-CD-diagram">
        <title>Model Derivation based on SAIF-CD</title>
        <mediaobject role="bordered">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Perspectives.svg" format="SVG" scale="60" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <caption>
          <para><emphasis>Like other CIMI models, ANF is a Logical Model that may be used to create
              implementation specifications. </emphasis></para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
      <para>However, the SAIF Conceptual Perspective is not completely equivalent to the MDA concept
        of <glossterm baseform="Computationally Independent Model">Computationally Independent Model
          (CIM)</glossterm>, the Logical Perspective is not equivalent to the MDA <glossterm
          baseform="Platform Independent Model">Platform Independent Model (PIM)</glossterm>, nor is
        the Implementable Perspective equivalent to the MDA <glossterm
          baseform="Platform Specific Model">Platform Specific Model</glossterm> although this
        Perspective is the SAIF Perspective that most closely aligns with an MDA analogue.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Conceptual Perspective</title>
        <para>These artifacts are most commonly focused on the “Problem-Space” rather than the
          “Solution-Space,” and contain explicit, unambiguous descriptions of the various dimensions
          of the component (e.g. clinical statement) or system being specified. </para>
        <para>A fully-specified Conceptual Perspective thus should be both readable and traceable by
          Domain Experts and Subject Matter Experts and rigorous enough to serve as input into the
          development in the Logical Perspective.</para>
        <para>In HL7, the Conceptual Perspective is represented by
            <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T121224-0400" comment="glossary" flag="done"?><glossterm
            baseform="Domain Analysis Model">Domain Analysis Models
          (DAMs)</glossterm><?oxy_comment_end?> and business models that represent stakeholder
          requirements analyzed by subject matter and domain experts. This perspective precedes the
          development of either logical or implementable artifacts and it is key to successful
          testing of implementations. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Logical Perspective</title>
        <para>Artifacts in the Logical Perspective represent traceable translations of
          Conceptual-level artifacts into a form and format, usable by and useful to architects and
          “inward-facing analysts.” Also included are additional specification materials required by
          architects preparing artifacts for consumption by developers. The Logical Perspective
          contains platform-independent artifacts.</para>
        <para>There are no definite boundaries between the Logical and Implementable Perspectives.
          Therefore, it is important for organizations such as HL7 to standardize logical models
          used to generate/create implementable artifacts (i.e. implementation guides, profiles, and
          templates). <glossterm baseform="CIMI Clinical Statement">CIMI Clinical
            Statements</glossterm>, <link xlink:href="https://www.iso.org/standard/62416.html"
            >ISO/TS 13972</link> Detailed Clinical Models, and ANF statements all belong in this
          perspective.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Implementable Perspective</title>
        <para>Artifacts in the Implementable Perspective are typically defined by developers or
          standards implementers, often through discussion with software designers, architects, or
          system integrators. Note that the artifacts in the Implementable Perspective are not
          actual implementations, but rather implementable in a number of implementation instances.
          Thus, all the necessary technical bindings, including data types, value sets, class
          libraries, and interface specifications are part of the Implementable Perspective. FHIR
          implementation requires a combination of profiles and test cases to ensure that
          implementations meet the requirements used to derive the conceptual and logical
          models.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T172441-0700" comment="Can we point to examples of where the HL7 V3 Clinical Statement does not exhibit a clean separation of concerns? " flag="done"?>
      <title>HL7 Version 3 Clinical Statement<?oxy_comment_end?>
      </title>
      <para>Starting with HL7 Version 3 <link linkend="bib7">[10]</link> the minimum requirements
        for the interoperable clinical statement are:</para>
      <table>
        <info>
          <title>HL7 V3 Clinical Statement Definition</title>
        </info>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para><emphasis>“Clinical Statement for the care of patients (persons, animals and
                    other entities) is:</emphasis></para>
                <para><emphasis>An expression of a discrete item of clinical, clinically-related or
                    public health information that is recorded because of its relevance to the care
                    of a patient or other entities. Clinical or public health information can be
                    expressed with different levels of granularity and therefore the extent and
                    detail conveyed in a single statement may vary. To be regarded as a Clinical
                    Statement, a concept must be associated with a patient or other entity in a
                    manner which makes clear:</emphasis></para>
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Its temporal context</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Its relationship to the entity or entities</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para><emphasis>In the case of an observation, its
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190716T011135-0400" comment="&quot;mood&quot; is a modifier in HL7 V3 -- this is a direct quote of the V3 Clinical Statement." flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190708T104220-0700" comment="If we *must* use mood here, we need to give a definition of mood... Maybe a glossary entry. Do we have an abbreviated glossary and a glossary? Or?" flag="done" mid="55"?>mood<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="55"?>
                    and presence, absence or value</emphasis></para>
                <para><emphasis>In the case of a procedure, its mood and status</emphasis></para>
                <para><emphasis>This clarity may be achieved by:</emphasis></para>
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Explicit representation; or,</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Implicit application of defaults ONLY where explicitly modeled
                        rules state the appropriate defaults." </emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The V3 Clinical Statement Model is applied across CDA implementation guides including
        the US-Realm Consolidated CDA (C-CDA) to represent CDA document entries. A V3 Clinical
        Statement Model is a <glossterm baseform="Polymorphic model">polymorphic model</glossterm>:
        it can represent observations, procedures, encounters, public health reports, supply,
        medications, exposure, and derivations of clinical acts. The V3 Clinical Statement model
        provides a Statement Model with partial Terminology constraints. For example, Clinical
        Statements in a CDA document section need to be constrained to add the precision needed to
        support the Terminology Knowledge layer. CDA entry and sub-entry templates can be used to
        create precise implementations of the V3 Clinical Statement model for a specific type of
        clinical statement (e.g. Procedure Activity, Problem Observation) sharing a common statement
        model but different terminology and usage constraints. The US-Realm C-CDA specification
        consists of a set of templates that constrain the document, sections, and entries used in
        each section. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title xml:id="CIMIStatement">CIMI Statements</title>
      <para>The <glossterm baseform="Clinical Information Modeling Initiative">Clinical Information
        Modeling Initiative (CIMI)</glossterm> is defining a library of logical <glossterm
        baseform="Clinical Information Model">clinical information models</glossterm> using a common
      modeling formalism. CIMI intends to improve the interoperability of healthcare information
      systems through shared detailed clinical information models that can be used to generate
      platform-specific model specifications such as FHIR profiles, CDA templates, OpenEHR
      Archetypes, <link xlink:href="https://www.iso.org/standard/40784.html">ISO 13606</link>
      Archetypes, <link xlink:href="https://www.iso.org/standard/62416.html">ISO/TS 13972</link>
      DCMs,
      <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190721T172632-0700" comment="Is there an example of this grouping that relates to HTN? Or is CIMI more trying to define a normal form, and the isosemantic aspects are yet to be worked out? " id="kv2_dp5_43b" mid="6"?><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190730T231505-0400" comment="I believe CIMI is working on a library of detailed clinical models - CIMI models. " parentID="kv2_dp5_43b"?>CIMI
      models are grouped into semantically equivalent (or ‘isosemantic’) families of detailed
      clinical models<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="6"?>, which capture the same clinical
      meaning using different combinations of pre- and <glossterm
        baseform="Post-coordinated concept">post-coordinated concepts</glossterm> and corresponding
      information model structure. The central focus of the CIMI Reference Model is the CIMI
      Clinical Statement. A CIMI Clinical Statement represents structured electronic communication
      made about a patient typically documented as an 'entry' in the patient record. </para>
      <para>Unlike the V3 Clinical Statement Model applied in C-CDA, CIMI models are designed with
        Terminology Knowledge and provides a separate model for each type of statements, organized
        into a comprehensive library.</para>
      <para>For reader convenience,
        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190724T005719-0400" comment="Reference the chapter" id="drn_chr_43b"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T121953-0400" comment="Kyle, can you please hyperlink this to clinical-input-form.xml" parentID="drn_chr_43b" mid="55"?>CIMI
        clinical statements are further explained in an appendix of this document <link
          linkend="clinical-input-form">(See Current CIMI Modeling
        Efforts).</link><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="55"?><!--For example, CIMI Clinical
        Statement can be used to represent the following statements made about a patient. This can
        be the statement of a condition being present, a request for a procedure to be done, the
        results of lab tests or the patient’s family history of cancer.-->
      </para>
    </section>

    <!--

  <section>
    <title>About this Document</title>
    <para>This document describes how information systems can improve patient safety and outcomes by
      increasing the precision of clinical information using a normal form to enhance and support
      quality data and analysis. In the subsequent chapter we will provide a deep dive into the
      building blocks and constructs for ANF, in a chapter containing the ANF Reference Model and
      illustrative examples of ANF modeling. </para>
    <para>Subsequently, we will outline how the various building blocks and attributes work together
      to create ANF Clinical Statements. We then provide the ANF Modeling Methodology, including a
      list of modeling principles and rules. Next, we discuss how clinical statements can be
      transformed and normalized into ANF Clinical Statements. Finally, we discuss the implications
      of ANF on data quality, clinical decision support, and ultimately, patient safety and
      outcomes. In the appendices, we explore current CIMI modeling efforts including illustrative
      examples for modeling CIMI clinical statements. We also compare and contrast ANF Clinical
      Statements and CIMI Clinical Statements in an appendix. </para>
    <note>
      <para>SNOMED CT is used as a representative example of a terminology system for the coded data
        elements in the ANF Reference Model. This ballot is focused on defining a Statement Model,
        not the underlying Terminology Knowledge layer described in the Knowledge Architecture.
        While the SNOMED CT examples are based on actual SNOMED CT definitions that are part of the
        SNOMED CT distribution, we recognize that there are inconsistencies within SNOMED CT that
        allow redundant representations. A first step in addressing the potential for redundant
        representation in the Terminology Layer is to define a separation of concerns between the
        Terminology and Statement layers, so that redundancies created by a poor separation of
        concerns between knowledge layers are eliminated. Subsequent efforts to improve the quality
        of the Terminology Layer can then be done independent of the Statement layer.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

-->


</section>
