<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">

	<title>Editorial Rules</title>

	<editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-performanceRequest" xreflabel="Performance versus request">
        <title>Performance versus request</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-performanceRequest-content">
                <listitem>
                    <para>ANF Statements must be either a Performance of an action or a Request for an action.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A Performance may include the passive observation of a phenomenon related to patients and their health status or family history, and may also include active interventions, such as providing education or administering medications or documenting that a patient is participating in exercise to improve their overall health status.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A Request may include requests for clinical testing, active interventions, future goals, or consultation with other providers.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-topicsAreActions" xreflabel="Topics are always an action">
        <title>Topics are always an action</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
        	<itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-topicsAreActions-content">
        		<listitem>
                    <para>The particulars of how topics—and other statement fields—are modeled
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190806T115233-0400" comment="Update: &quot;is&quot; to &quot;as&quot;  based on technical writer&apos;s review."?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20191009T120859-0600" comment="I think it should be changed back to &quot;is&quot;.  You are saying that the particulars of how topics are modeled is a terminology knowledge layer concern vs. a statement layer concern.  The way it&apos;s worded now doesn&apos;t make sense to me." mid="1"?>as<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="1"?>
                        a Terminology Knowledge layer concern, not a Statement Layer concern. The
                        Statement Layer does require that the Terminology Expression fields in a
                        statement are disjoint: There should be no confusion—or creation of false
                        dichotomies. There should be one, and only one, place to put each type of
                        information in a terminology expression. For example, the Statement Layer
                        defines a particular place to represent the subject of information.
                        Therefore, the terminology layer must not allow the subject of information
                        to be redundantly—and possibly contradictory—represented in a topic
                        expression (such as would be the case if "maternal history of diabetes"
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20191009T121334-0600" comment="I changed it from &quot;where&quot;, which is incorrect."?>were<?oxy_comment_end?>
                        an allowed topic expression). The Statement Layer requires that the topic
                        represent an Action as a code or expression according to the rules of the
                        terminology layer, and that the rules of the terminology layer enforce a
                        disjointness
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20191009T121126-0600" comment="I think &quot;of&quot; should be deleted, so it reads &quot;...enforce a disjointness between different types of terminology expressions.&quot;"?>of
                        <?oxy_comment_end?>between different types of terminology expressions. Here
                        we present a starting point for what the Terminology Layer editorial rules
                        may look like, based on current SNOMED CT practice. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SNOMED CT can accommodate this requirement for simple observations by
                        using Observation procedure to represent the topic (or other types of
                        procedures when appropriate, such as the administration of a medication). In
                        SNOMED CT examples, the Observation procedure specifies a Has focus
                        attribute linking it to the Clinical Finding or Disorder that it is being
                        observed. The observation procedure can also be further refined by adding
                        attributes in the terminology model, including Method, Procedure site -
                        Direct, (if appropriate) Laterality, and Using device.
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190806T115341-0400" comment="Imcomplete statement "?><!--We
                        expect --><?oxy_comment_end?></para>
                </listitem>
        		<listitem>
					<para>Medication administrations will use an Administration of substance concept to represent
                        the topic. All Administration of substance concepts will be refined with the
                        substance and dose form and strength being requested. If Route of
                        administration exists, then it will also be added. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Laboratory tests will use a Laboratory Procedure concept to represent the topic. These
                        concepts can be further refined. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Imaging Procedures
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20191009T121316-0600" comment="Change to &quot;will.&quot;  I believe I&apos;ve made this change before so not sure why it&apos;s still not changed."?>with<?oxy_comment_end?>
                        use an Imaging Procedure concept to represent the topic. These concepts will
                        be further refined with a Method, Procedure site and (if appropriate) a
                        laterality for those sites that are lateralizable. </para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-timing" xreflabel="Timing - past, present, or future">
        <title>Timing - past, present, or future</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-timing-content">
                <listitem>
        	       <para>For a Performance of Action, the Timing can represent a time in the past or a
                        current time. If a history of a performance of action is to be represented
                        in ANF, the Timing will be for a time in the past, prior to the statement.
                        Otherwise the Timing will be represented with the current time of the
                        statement. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>For a Request of Action, the Timing will always represent a future time. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-resultsRangedQuantity" xreflabel="Results are always a ranged quantity">
        <title>Results are always a ranged quantity</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-resultsRangedQuantity-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>Results are always a Measure, which is a
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20191009T121735-0600" comment="Do you want to clarify that this can include things like presence and absence?"?>ranged
                        quantity<?oxy_comment_end?>. Measure includes both a numeric interval along
                        with a Measure Semantic specified as a Logical Expression. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If a Result is intended to represent a numeric result then the upperBound and lowerBound would be populated with the appropriate numeric values and the Measure Semantic would indicate the unit of measure.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-presenceAbsence" xreflabel="Presence and absence are a countable quantity">
        <title>Presence and absence are a countable quantity</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-presenceAbsence-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>Any statement that represents the Presence or implies Presence of a Topic
                        will have a Result with an upperBound of infinite (inf), lowerBound of 1,
                        and Measure.semantic of "Countable quantity". </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Any statement that represents the Absence or implies Absence of a Topic
                        will have a Result with an upperBound of 0, lowerBound of 0, and
                        Measure.semantic of "Countable quantity". </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-separateCompoundTopics" xreflabel="Separate compound topics">
        <title>Separate compound topics</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-separateCompoundTopics-content">
                <listitem>
                    <para>For the purposes of ANF, a statement is a request or performance of an
                        action that should exist independently. Thus, if a compound topic contains
                        two topics that could each exist separately, then they should be divided
                        into separate ANF Statements. These independent ANF Statements can then be
                        associated with each other as associated statements. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>For example, "Negative screen for PTSD and depression", contains two
                        separate ANF Statements that would then be associated to each other.
                        However, if the narrative represents two or more actions that are performed
                        as a single activity at the same time without the need for stopping the
                        action, then a single topic would be used. For example, "Lumbar/Thoracic
                        Spine CT" would be represented with a single topic as it represents a single
                        activity that is performed at the same time even though a Lumbar CT and a
                        Thoracic CT could be done separately. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-techniques" xreflabel="Techniques are inseparable from the topic">
        <title>Techniques are inseparable from the topic</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-techniques-content">
                <listitem>
                    <para>A technique must be true within the duration of the performance.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                	<para>A technique is inseparable from the topic and cannot be expressed as a
                        stand-alone clinical statement.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A technique is a device used, a method applied, or a temporary state in
                        which the patient was actively placed during performance of the action. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-prerequisites" xreflabel="Prerequisites must be separated from the topic">
        <title>Prerequisites must be separated from the topic</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-prerequisites-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>A prerequisite is separable from the topic and can be expressed as a
                        stand-alone clinical statement </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A prerequisite is a state that must exist before something else can happen
                        or be done. Prerequisites are part of the details under which a procedure is
                        being performed. The state must exist prior to the performance of the
                        action. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-associatedStatement" xreflabel="Related statements should be associated">
        <title>Related statements should be associated</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-associatedStatement-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>Use an associated statement when it is important for the interpretation of
                        one statement that the other statements were observed, performed, or
                        requested. Also, if there is some implicitness that the two statements are
                        related (e.g. pleural empyema with fistula) or that they are unrelated (e.g.
                        Akinetic seizure without atonia) then the two statements should be
                        associated. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-subjectOfInformation" xreflabel="Subject of information is used to represent family and donor history">
        <title>Subject of information is used to represent family and donor history</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-subjectOfInformation-content">
                <listitem>
                    <para>The subjectOfInformation is used to represent who the statement is about.
                        This is normally the patient (Subject of record) unless explicitly stated
                        otherwise, for example Mother, Sibling, Donor, etc. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-status" xreflabel="Status indicates the state of a result">
        <title>Status indicates the state of a result</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-status-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>The status of a Performance of action can be specified with concepts such as
                        (on hold, needed, rejected, etc). </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-healthRisk" xreflabel="HealthRisk indicates the clinical risk of the result">
        <title>HealthRisk indicates the clinical risk of the result</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-healthRisk-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>In PerformanceCircumstance, healthRisk is used to flag a result with coded
                        values such as 'low', 'normal', high', and 'critical'. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-normalRange" xreflabel="Normal Range can be specified for a result">
        <title>Normal Range can be specified for a result</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-normalRange-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>In PerformanceCircumstance, normalRange is used to flag a result with coded
                        values such as 'low', 'normal', high', and 'critical'. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-participants" xreflabel="Participants can be specified or requested">
        <title>Participants can be specified or requested</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-participants-content">
                <listitem>
                    <para>A Performance of action can specify participants using participant in
                        PerformanceCircumstance. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                	<para>A Request for action can specify requested participants using
                        requestedParticipant in RequestCircumstance. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-purpose" xreflabel="Purpose indicates the reason for a request">
        <title>Purpose indicates the reason for a request</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-purpose-content">
                <listitem>
                    <para>The purpose is why an action was requested. The purpose of the topic is
                        typically some type of therapeutic intent, diagnostic intent, or both. There can be more than one therapeutic intent and diagnostic intent.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-priority" xreflabel="Priority defaults to routine for a request">
        <title>Priority defaults to routine for a request</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-priority-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>Priority is used to represent the priority for which a request is to be
                        carried out. By default a Request will be considered "routine" unless
                        otherwise specified. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-repetition" xreflabel="Repetition is used to request multiple occurences of a topic">
        <title>Repetition is used to request multiple occurrences of a topic</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-repetition-content">
                <listitem>
                	<para>Repetition is used to represent when an action is requested for more than a
                        single occurrence. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Repetition is an optional component for a RequestCircumstance and contains
                        five Measures that are used to further define the parameters of the
                        Repetition: </para>

                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>periodDuration:</emphasis> This required field is used
                                to represent how long a repetition should persist. If it is not
                                specified, a default value of [0,inf) will be used. e.g. for 3
                                weeks</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>periodStart:</emphasis> This required field is used to represent
                                when a repeated action should begin. If it is not specified, a default value
                                of [0,inf) will be used. e.g. NOW</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>eventSeparation:</emphasis> This required field is used
                                to represent how long between actions. If it is not specified, a
                                default value of [0,inf) will be used. e.g. for 2 weeks</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>eventFrequency:</emphasis> This required field is used
                                to represent how often the action should occur. If it is not
                                specified, a default value of [0,inf) will be used. e.g. 3 times per
                                week</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>eventDuration:</emphasis> This is an optional field that
                                is used to represent how long every action should last. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>

                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>

    <editorial-rule xml:id="anf-editorialrule-requestedResult" xreflabel="A desired result can be specified in a request">
        <title>A desired result can be specified in a request</title>                    
        <mathphrase>
            <itemizedlist xml:id="anf-editorialrule-requestedResult-content">
                <listitem>
                    <para>A desired result can be specified as a Measure using requestedResult in
                        RequestCircumstance. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If a requestedResult is specified, the appropriate upperBound and
                        lowerBound is specified with the correct Measure.semantic. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                	<para>If a requestedResult is not specified in the request, an upperBound and
                        lowerBound of 1 is used with a Measure.semantic of ISO 8601 after statement
                        time. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>


</section>
