<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<section xml:id="OpenEHR" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">

            <title>OpenEHR: An Example Framework for Clinical Statements</title>

            <para>In considering the appropriate design of statement models, it’s useful to review how such
                models will be used in practice within a Model Driven Development architecture.
                    OpenEHR<footnote xml:id="__FN3__">
                    <para>Demski H, Garde S, Hildebrand C. Open data models for smart health
                        interconnected applications: the example of openEHR. BMC Med Inform Decis
                        Mak. 2016 Oct 22;16(1):137. (available at <link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27770769">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27770769</link>).</para>
                </footnote><superscript>,</superscript><footnote xml:id="__FN4__">
                    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.openehr.org/what_is_openehr">http://www.openehr.org/what_is_openehr</link>.</para>
                </footnote> offers one such architecture that is relatively complete and mature, so
                it serves as a good example. <xref linkend="_Ref474334719" xrefstyle="select:label"/> illustrates the components of the OpenEHR architecture, which are further
                described below.</para>

            <figure xml:id="_Ref474334719">
                <title>OpenEHR architecture</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image4com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <section xml:id="_Ref474420488">
                <title>OpenEHR Reference Model</title>

                <para>The foundation of the OpenEHR architecture is a reference model that contains
                    only the most generic set of objects and data types needed to define the
                    contents of an EHR. These objects include organizing structures such as
                    “Folders”, “Compositions”, and “Sections”, as well as generic clinical data
                    objects such as “Entries”, “Clusters” of entries, and “Elements” that comprise
                    the entries. The reference model also includes several dozen data types that may
                    be used to populate the values of Elements, such as “Quantity”, “Text”, and
                    “Timed Event”. Collectively, these constructs define the general building blocks
                    available to construct more detailed models for representing clinical
                    observations, actions, and other data in EHRs. <xref linkend="_Ref474335678" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows the constructs of the OpenEHR reference
                    model and how they are hierarchically organized to create the “scaffolding” for
                    patient records.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474335678">
                    <title>OpenEHR Reference Model</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image5com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>Within the reference model, the “Observation” class is a specific sub-type of
                    the “Entry” object, and it is used to record information from a direct
                    observation or measurement on a patient or to record the perspective of the
                    patient, such as in history taking. The Observation class includes only a small
                    number of data elements that are inherited by all clinical observation models,
                    such as “Subject” (the person to whom the observation applies) and “Information
                    Provider” (the person or agent who generated the observation). Otherwise, all
                    Entries and Elements used to record actual observations are specified within
                    sub-types of the Observation class, which OpenEHR calls “Archetypes.”</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>OpenEHR Archetypes</title>

                <para>Archetypes are clinical object models that specify:</para>

                <orderedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The set of Elements that may be used to represent various kinds of
                            observations</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>The datatypes used to populate those Elements</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which Elements must be populated versus being optional, and</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Whether Elements can have only one or may have multiple values.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>The values of Elements, themselves, may be collections of other Elements
                    (“Clusters”) or instances of other Archetypes (effectively, nested Archetypes).
                        <xref linkend="_Ref474337532" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows the graphical
                    representation of an OpenEHR archetype.</para>

                <para>For primitive Elements, the Archetype may define further constraints that
                    define how the Element may be populated, as shown in the callouts of <xref linkend="_Ref474337532" xrefstyle="select:label"/>. For example, the value
                    of the “Systolic” Element in the Blood Pressure Artifact is specified to be a
                    “Quantity” datatype, to represent the property of “Pressure”, and to be recorded
                    using the units of measure “mm[Hg]”. Similarly, the “Position” Element is
                    specified to be a “Coded Text” datatype and to be populated by one of several
                    enumerated code values, with the code for “Sitting” being the default if no
                    other value is specified.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474337532">
                    <title>Example of an OpenEHR Archetype</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image6com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>OpenEHR Archetypes must be defined using only the constructs of the underlying
                    Reference Model, as shown in <xref linkend="_Ref474334719" xrefstyle="select:label"/>. This constraint ensures that the Archetypes may
                    be stored and processed by the underlying database and application
                    implementations, which are otherwise loosely bound to the specific structures of
                    the Archetypes themselves.</para>

                <para>The OpenEHR framework uses a specific structured language to define
                    Archetypes, the Archetype Definition Language (ADL). <xref linkend="_Ref474337532" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows the graphical
                    rendering of an Archetype, although the actual definition is specified using a
                    text-based ADL expression (not shown). Other Model-Driven Development
                    frameworks, of course, may use different languages for defining statement models and
                    different graphical rendering methods.</para>

                <para>Like structured data types and object classes in programming languages,
                    Archetypes specify and constrain in detail how instances of actual data
                    (clinical observations, in this case) may be represented within the information
                    system. These specifications govern how software modules must create instances
                    of those observations (i.e., modules such as graphical user interfaces or EDI
                    interface engines) and how software modules may retrieve and process instances
                    of those observations (i.e., modules such as user displays or decision-support
                    rule engines). Using conceptual-level Archetypes rather than low-level data
                    structures for these purposes allows domain experts to formally specify
                    Archetypes, and (in theory, at least) de-couples Archetype specifications from
                    low-level implementation dependencies.</para>

                <para>OpenEHR currently includes several hundred Archetypes<footnote xml:id="__FN5__">
                        <para>See <link xlink:href="http://www.openehr.org/ckm/">http://www.openehr.org/ckm/</link> for an online listing.</para>
                    </footnote>, including many for clinical observations. The framework, however,
                    remains very much a work in progress, and many Archetypes remain in draft
                    form.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>OpenEHR Templates</title>

                <para>To support specific use cases and system functions, OpenEHR allows Archetypes
                    to be combined and/or further constrained to create purpose-specific data
                    structures called “Templates”. Templates may then drive the automated generation
                    of computing artifacts used to collect, retrieve, or export clinical
                    observations (see <xref linkend="_Ref474334719" xrefstyle="select:label"/>).</para>

                <para><xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows an example
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190313T152535-0600" comment="Why are some items in the template below numbered while others are not?" id="z4q_w3l_fhb" flag="done" mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190326T122423-0500" comment="The numbering you notice in the image below comes directly from the OpenEHR template.  See https://www.openehr.org/ckm/#" parentID="z4q_w3l_fhb" flag="done"?>OpenEHR<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?>
                    Template that represents the information captured during an initial visit to a
                    heart failure clinic. Note that the template combines a number of Archetypes,
                    such as Blood Pressure, Pulse, and Full Blood Count, as well as adds
                    navigational and organizational nodes such as “Physical Exam.” The latter nodes
                    are also Archetypes, specifically sub-classes of the Section object specified in
                    the Reference Model.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474415737">
                    <title>Example of an OpenEHR Template</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image7com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>Although not shown in <xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/>, Templates may also include additional constraints applied to their
                    constituent Archetypes. Such constraints may entail the inclusion of only a
                    subset of the Archetype’s Elements, the allowance of only a subset of the coded
                    values specified for an Element, the designation of default values for Elements,
                    etc. The purpose of these constraints is to customize an Archetype for use in a
                    specific context, while ensuring that any data collected or retrieved using
                    Templates that contain the Archetype conform to the Archetype’s underlying
                    constraints.</para>

                <para>For example, <xref linkend="_Ref474416536" xrefstyle="select:label"/> shows a
                    graphical user interface (“Screen Form”) for data entry generated from the
                    heart-failure Template in <xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/>. Because the Template design constrained the Blood Pressure Archetype to
                    include only the “Systolic” and “Diastolic” Elements (as opposed to the full set
                    of Elements shown in <xref linkend="_Ref474337532" xrefstyle="select:label"/>),
                    the Screen Form displays only those two Elements. Note that the display includes
                    the units of measure and allowed value ranges specified for the “Systolic” and
                    “Diastolic” Elements, as derived from the complete Archetype. In this manner,
                    all data collected via Screen Forms generated from the Template in <xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/> will conform to the
                    constraints specified within the Archetypes that the Template includes. This
                    aspect of Model Driven Development allows the observation modeling features and
                    constraints that are formally specified in Archetypes to be uniformly and
                    automatically applied across various uses of the Archetypes (through Templates)
                    within and across information systems.</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474416536">
                    <title><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190313T152917-0600" comment="In the example, why does Pulse appear to be under Weight and BP under Height?" id="iyc_rjl_fhb" flag="done" mid="4"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190326T123023-0500" comment="They are not under Pulse and Height, but are different data types.  Weight and Height can only have one value whereas Pulse and BP can have multiple values as they can be taken multiple times during an encounter.  If you look closely you can see that Weight and Height have the constraint (1..1) and Pulse and BP have (0..*)" parentID="iyc_rjl_fhb" flag="done" mid="5"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190403T114103-0600" comment="Okay, thanks.  To my untrained eyes, and particularly because of the indenting under Weight and Height, it looked as though they were included under them." flag="done"?>Example<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="5"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="4"?>
                        of a Screen Form generated from an OpenEHR Template</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image8com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Querying OpenEHR Data</title>

                <para>Although OpenEHR Templates may combine and further constrain Archetypes to
                    enable purpose-specific data collection and data processing, the querying of
                    OpenEHR data need not consider the structure of any individual Templates that
                    were used to instantiate clinical observations. Rather, querying requires
                    knowledge of only the Archetypes, the underlying Reference Model, and any
                    controlled terminologies used in the definition of Archetypes (See
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190318T113916-0600" comment="In the figure, unless this is a reference to a source other than VA, recommend revising spelling of &quot;artefacts&quot; to &quot;artifacts.&quot;  Also, the oval for Terminology Bindings probably should be brought to the front so it&apos;s not cutoff by the rectangle currently in front of it." id="wtk_gpl_fhb" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190326T131257-0500" comment="This is how it is spelled in the OpenEHR documentation and this image is taken directly from there." parentID="wtk_gpl_fhb" flag="done" mid="7"?><xref linkend="_Ref474421318" xrefstyle="select:label"/><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="7"?> for a graphical representation
                    of these dependencies).</para>

                <figure xml:id="_Ref474421318">
                    <title>Architectural components used in querying of OpenEHR data.</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image9com.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>As discussed above, all persisted observation data must conform to the
                    constraints of the Archetypes used to collect them (even if those Archetypes are
                    combined and further constrained in Templates). Further, none of the
                    navigational elements of Templates (such as the grouping of Archetypes into a
                    “Physical Exam” category, as shown in <xref linkend="_Ref474415737" xrefstyle="select:label"/>) influence the semantics of the Archetype data
                    collected via Templates. Specifically, the semantics of a clinical observation
                    represented by an Archetype should exist independently of any encompassing
                    navigational or organizational category in which that Archetype may appear
                    within a Template (Archetypes must be carefully designed to confer this
                    property).</para>

                <para>At the same time, queries may reference sub-parts of an OpenEHR medical record
                    in which the Archetype instances were recorded. These named sub-parts of a
                    record, such as “Problem List” and “Medication Order List,” are also Archetypes
                    defined to specialize the “Section” class of the Reference Model (see <xref linkend="_Ref474420488" xrefstyle="select:label"/>).</para>

                <para>Finally, queries may also reference the terminology model from which specific
                    codes were drawn when defining clinical observation Archetypes. For example, a
                    query could seek to retrieve any patient with a diagnosis subsumed by the coded
                    concept “Cardiovascular Disease,” although no Archetype specifically references
                    that very general disease concept. Such a query would rely upon the hierarchical
                    subsumption relationships represented in the terminology model to associate the
                    general “Cardiovascular Disease” concept with the specific disease concepts
                    (such as “Atherosclerosis”) that are actually referenced in defined
                    Archetypes.</para>
            </section>
        

        
</section>
