<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Representing Statements</title>
    <blockquote>
        <attribution>Isaac Newton</attribution>
        <para>My Design in this Book is not to explain the
            Properties of Light by Hypotheses, but to propose and prove them by Reason and
            Experiments.</para>
    </blockquote>
    
    <para>The purpose of this document is: </para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>To define a clinical statement.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To define the types of clinical statements and their attributes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To provide a set of guidelines to model clinical statements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To provide a validation framework for inter-modeler reliability when applied in
                the field. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To provide information on how clinical statements will be modeled for the KBS
                Clinical Decision Support (CDS) Knowledge Artifact (KNART) project. Once the models
                are approved, model slots bound to terminologies will be identified for subsequent
                terminology binding definitions proposed by the VA Terminology Team. Modeling of
                clinical statements outside of the CDS KNART project is currently beyond the scope
                of this effort.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>KNART example: Consult request to Cardiology to evaluate chest pain.
                        Certain information must be collected and stored as structured data, such as
                        the reason for the consult.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>These modeling guidelines were derived from several documented use cases. The main goal of
        this effort is to provide a reproducible and a principled approach to the formal capture of
        clinical knowledge within Information Models and their references to underlying Terminology
        Models. Currently, the proposal and examples are independent of any specific
        terminology.</para>
    <para>These guidelines will be distributed to a variety of participants to contribute to a
        modeling exercise. After having read the guidelines, participants will be asked to access a
        survey where they will view a number of clinical statements and indicate how they would
        model them. <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>When attempting the modeling exercise, it will
            be important to model per the guidelines specified in this document regardless of
            how existing terminologies, such as SNOMED-CT, may model these
            concepts</emphasis></emphasis>. In the future, an exercise to reconcile approaches may
        be conducted but is out-of-scope at this time.</para>    
    <para>A statement is an expression of facts or plans. We will use a common—and misleadingly
        simple—statement topic: <emphasis>Blood Pressure</emphasis> or simply
            <emphasis>BP</emphasis> as an expository statement. If a patient told a clinician that
        their BP was 160/95, or a clinician told a patient that they should keep their BP below
        120/70, they would be mutually understood. The ability for the creator of the statement and
        the interpretor of the statement to each believe that they <emphasis>understand</emphasis>
        the statement is the first requirement. </para>
    
    <para>
        
        <para>A <emphasis>clinical statement</emphasis> represents an entry in the patient record
            that documents in a structured/computable manner clinical information about a subject of
            information, such as a patient or a relative of the patient, and that is asserted by a
            particular source, recorded, and potentially verified.</para>
        <para>Clinicians author clinical statements and enter them into their organization’s
            electronic health record (EHR). Clinicians typically input the information via a manner
            that we call here the <emphasis>clinical input form (CIF)</emphasis>. However, the CIF
            is not a literal form that clinicians select and enter data in. Rather, it refers to the
            manner in which information is presented to the clinicians and how they input the data,
            such as by constraining the information to allow only certain values to be entered, such
            as through a drop-down list or radio button, or breaking up large chunks of related
            information into smaller parts. For example, when a clinician orders a medication,
            rather than selecting this information all at once with a single item, they will choose
            the various parts of the medication order, such as:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Kind of drug and strength (e.g., Acetaminophen 150 mg)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Amount and how often the patient should take the medication (e.g., 1 tablet
                    twice daily)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Duration (2 days)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Any constraints (e.g., do not exceed a total daily dosage of 600 mg)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Ideally, the way the information is presented to clinicians is in a manner that is
            most efficient for the clinicians to use. However, what is an efficient way for
            clinicians to select and input data may not be the most efficient way for data analysts
            to use when they are querying data once it has been normalized and stored in a database,
            such as when creating a new CDS rule or compiling prevalence statistics. For this, the
            data is normalized using the <emphasis>analysis normal form (ANF)</emphasis> and stored
            in a database. Again, the ANF is not necessarily a physical structure, but is how a data
            analyst might see the data when they are looking at it in a database, and not as
            clinicians would see it in the user interface (i.e., CIF).</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Clinician collects data à Clinical Input Form</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Data is normalized à Transformation process from CIF to ANF à
                    Representable/storable in multiple types of databases, which <emphasis
                        role="underline">could</emphasis> include VistA but a separate process would
                    need to be performed to make that happen.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Data analyst who is using or querying the data (e.g., creating a CDS rule or
                    working on prevalence statistics) à ANF (it is how the data is represented or
                    stored in the database; must know enough about the data to know what is stored
                    in the topic vs. what is stored as a result or detail)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>        
        <table frame="topbot" rowsep="0" colsep="0"
            xml:id="table_f39f17ff-b1f9-4701-85db-324fb78b9f2b">
            <title>General Statement Model</title>
            <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="102.37pt"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="292.9pt"/>
                <thead>
                    <row rowsep="1">
                        <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Statement</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Narrative:</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Topic:</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Subject of information:</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Statement time:</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Act:</entry>
                        <entrytbl cols="3">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1.86*"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                            <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="6.48*"/>
                            <tbody>
                                <row rowsep="0">
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                </row>
                                <row rowsep="0">
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                    <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" namest="c2" nameend="c3"/>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </entrytbl>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </para>
    

    <para>
        
    </para>
    <editorial-rule>
        <title>Topic</title>
        <mathphrase>The <emphasis>topic</emphasis> is the center of interest or activity represented
            by the statement. A few examples of topics include <link
                xlink:href="#ge_solor_Insulin_dependent_diabetes_mellitus_type_1A_cc0759c3-623e-3417-badb-8dbad681e0f5"><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata>
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px" height="14px">
                                <text x="1" y="7"
                                    style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                        >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                        style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; "
                                        >&#xF2D8; </tspan>
                                    <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Insulin dependent diabetes mellitus type
                                    1A]</text>
                            </svg>
                        </imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></link>, 
            <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_Pulse_rate_1f621ed0-b2b9-37bf-ba99-cdcdc1a6e24a"><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata>
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px"
                                height="14px">
                                <text x="1" y="7"
                                    style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                    >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                        style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #5ec200; stroke: #5ec200; "
                                        >&#xF060; </tspan>
                                    <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Pulse rate]</text>
                            </svg>
                        </imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></link>,
            <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_Administration_of_medication_8a39a4e6-97c8-3ab1-b589-71edfe1f32ce"><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata>
                        <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px"
                            height="14px">
                            <text x="1" y="7"
                                style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                    style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #5ec200; stroke: #5ec200; "
                                    >&#xF12F; </tspan>
                                <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Administration of medication]</text>
                        </svg>
                    </imagedata>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></link> 
            
            . For each of these topics, the information that must
            be described is quite different, so CIMI describes topic types that contain the
            appropriate properties to describe the required information for the given topic. The
            number of topic types will change as CIMI progresses, but currently the allowable topic
            types are EvaluationResult, Assertion, and Procedure.</mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>
    
    <editorial-rule>
        <title>Subject of information</title>
        <mathphrase>The <emphasis>Subject of Information</emphasis> represents who or what the
            statement refers to. In most cases, the <emphasis>Subject of Information</emphasis>
            refers to who or what the record within which this statement is embedded is about. In
            such cases, the <emphasis>Subject of Information</emphasis> may be referred to as the
                <emphasis>Subject of Record</emphasis>. In other cases, the <emphasis>Subject of
                Information</emphasis> may refer to a relative of the <emphasis>Subject of
                Record</emphasis> (mother, father, uncle...), and would be recorded appropriately in
            such circumstance. </mathphrase>
        <para/>
    </editorial-rule>
    
    <editorial-rule>
        <title>Statement time</title>
        <mathphrase>The Statement time is the time the statement is made. The statement time is
            independent of the period of time that a statement refers to, which may be past,
            present, or future, and is represented separately as part of the act. </mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>
    
    <editorial-rule>
        <title>Act</title>
        <mathphrase>The Act is information that details the act related to the topic, either a
            request act, or a performance act.</mathphrase>
    </editorial-rule>
    
    <section xml:id="section_12d7f603-3acd-4e35-b9b8-3f4994aa2d70">
        <title>Understandable, Reproducible, and Useful</title>
        <para>Given a narrative, fill out the form </para>
        <example xml:id="example_dc87fd7a-561e-4335-ae79-9bde3fb1fc05">
            <title>Pulse observed to be 110</title>
            <para>A patient tells their health-care provider that they had a <link
                    xlink:href="#ge_solor_Pulse_rate_1f621ed0-b2b9-37bf-ba99-cdcdc1a6e24a"><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata>
                                <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px" height="14px">
                                    <text x="1" y="7"
                                        style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                            >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                            style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #5ec200; stroke: #5ec200; "
                                            >&#xF060; </tspan>
                                        <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Pulse rate]</text>
                                </svg>
                            </imagedata>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></link> on Monday, April 23rd at 9:15 am Pacific Standard Time. </para>
        </example>
        <example xml:id="example_7b0c38f2-acf3-48a8-a2d7-c06cf0e007cc">
            <title>Resting pulse requested to be less than 70</title>
            <para>A health-care provider tells a patient that they would like their resting pulse to
                be less than 70. </para>
        </example>
        <para>In the case of a human interpretor, they can often believe that they understand a
            statement, even when there is a great deal of information missing from the statement. In
            the above example, it was probably assumed that the units used to measure the blood
            pressure was mm/Hg, that the patient was at rest and seated, and that the pressure was
            measured from a brachial artery, either the brachial artery in the right arm, or the
            brachial artery in the left arm. </para>
        <para>In a face-to-face interaction, statements can often be clarified to confirm assumed
            content, and to ensure effective communication of information from the creator to the
            interpretor. When recording statements for future interpretation, such verification of
            assumed content cannot be performed. This inability to clarify statements after the fact
            requires that statements sufficiently record the circumstances necessary to reproducibly
            interpret the statement.</para>
        <para/>
        <para/>
        
        <editorial-rule>
            <title>Understandable</title>
            <mathphrase>Editorial rules must be understandable to an editor or user simply by reading the definition or rule. A statement must be understandable to the creator and the
                interpreter.</mathphrase>
        </editorial-rule>
        <editorial-rule>
            <title>Reproducible</title>
            <mathphrase>Independent observers encountering a topic and equivalent circumstances
                will record equivalent statements</mathphrase>
        </editorial-rule>
        <editorial-rule>
            <title>Useful</title>
            <mathphrase>The representation must be useful for the purposes that the modeling is intended to support. </mathphrase>
        </editorial-rule>
        <para/>
            
        
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_f73a5fd3-af2d-4e34-8a4b-3854a63e7ffd">
        <title>Structured Statement</title>
        <para>Narrative: Pulse observed to be 100 bpm on Monday, April 23rd at 9:15 am Pacific
            Standard Time</para>
        <para>Action Topic: Pulse</para>
        <para>Circumstance: facts or conditions relevant to an action; Two types of action: request,
            performance</para>
        <para>
            <table frame="topbot" rowsep="0" colsep="0"
                xml:id="table_9b08a484-6589-430a-bcb5-060703de35c3">
                <title>Patient pulse representation of narrative with Structured
                    Statement</title>
                <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="96.98pt"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="298.78pt"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row rowsep="1">
                            <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Performance Statement</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Narrative:</entry>
                            <entry>Pulse observed to be 100 bpm</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Topic:</entry>
                            <entry>Pulse</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Subject of information:</entry>
                            <entry>Patient of Record</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Statement time:</entry>
                            <entry>Monday, April 23rd 2018 at 9:15 am Pacific Standard Time</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Act:</entry>
                            <entrytbl cols="3">
                                <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1.86*"/>
                                <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                                <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="6.48*"/>
                                <tbody>
                                    <row rowsep="0">
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Circumstance:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Timing:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                    </row>
                                    <row rowsep="0">
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Result:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" namest="c2" nameend="c3"
                                            >120 beats per minute </entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </entrytbl>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="section_5307a5f5-3008-4c0c-948b-f0a13c3e059c">
            <title>Modeling Principles</title>
            <para>The modeling guidelines were developed in accordance with the principles shown below.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Separation of Concerns:</emphasis> As defined by
                        Wikipedia<footnote xml:id="__FN1__">
                            <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation_of_concerns"
                                >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation_of_concerns</link>
                            </para>
                        </footnote>: Separation of Concerns (SoC) is a design principle for separating a
                        computer program into distinct sections, such that each section addresses a
                        separate concern. A concern is a set of information that affects the code of a
                        computer program. A concern can be as general as the details of the hardware the
                        code is being optimized for, or as specific as the name of a class to
                        instantiate. A program that embodies SoC well is called a modular program.
                        Modularity, and hence separation of concerns, is achieved by encapsulating
                        information inside a section of code that has a well-defined interface.
                        Encapsulation is a means of information hiding. Layered designs in information
                        systems are another embodiment of separation of concerns (e.g., presentation
                        layer, business logic layer, data access layer, persistence layer). The value of
                        separation of concerns is simplifying development and maintenance of computer
                        programs. When concerns are well-separated, individual sections can be reused,
                        as well as developed and updated independently. Of special value is the ability
                        to later improve or modify one section of code without having to know the
                        details of the other sections, and without having to make corresponding changes
                        to those sections.</para>
                    <para>The use of immutable objects (see principle B Immutability below) is a
                        technique that fulfills the Separation of Concerns principle.</para>
                    <para>Attributes that describe specific semantic concepts should be grouped together
                        into a single class and not be spread across a number of classes. Doing the
                        latter leads to tight coupling between classes. Doing the former leads to better
                        decomposition of a potentially complex domain.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis> Attributes for a Role (e.g.,
                        Practitioner) should not be mixed with attributes for an Entity (e.g.,
                        Person). This allows a person to assume a number of roles over their
                        lifetime or to function in more than one role.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Immutability: </emphasis>An Immutable Object as defined
                        by Wikipedia<footnote xml:id="__FN2__">
                            <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/immutable_object"
                                >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/immutable_object</link>
                            </para>
                        </footnote>: Used in object-oriented and functional programming, an immutable
                        object is something that cannot be changed after it is created, in contrast to
                        mutable objects that can be changed after they are created. There are multiple
                        reasons for using immutable objects, including improved readability and runtime
                        efficiency and higher security.</para>
                    <para>Although building immutable objects…requires a bit more up-front complexity,
                        the downstream simplification forced by this abstraction easily offsets the
                        effort. One of the benefits of switching to a functional mindset is the
                        realization that tests exist to check that changes occur successfully in code.
                        In other words, testing’s real purpose is to validate mutation – and the more
                        mutation you have, the more testing is required to make sure you get it right.
                        If you isolate the places where changes occur by severely restricting mutation,
                        you create a much smaller space for errors to occur and have few plates to
                        test.</para>
                    <para>Finally, one of the best features of immutable classes is how well they fit
                        into the composition abstraction.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Composition Over Inheritance: </emphasis>Composition
                        over inheritance (or composite reuse principle) in object-oriented programming
                        is the principle that classes should achieve polymorphic behavior and code reuse
                        by their composition (by containing those instances of other classes that
                        implement the desired functionality) rather than inheritance from a base or
                        parent class.</para>
                    <para>To favor composition over inheritance is a design principle that gives the
                        design higher flexibility. It is more natural to build business-domain classes
                        out of various components than trying to find commonality between them and
                        creating a family tree.</para>
                    <para>Initial design is simplified by identifying system object behaviors in
                        separate interfaces instead of creating a hierarchical relationship to
                        distribute behaviors among business-domain classes via inheritance. This
                        approach more easily accommodates future requirements changes that would
                        otherwise require a complete restructuring of business-domain classes in the
                        inheritance model.</para>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Item for
                        Consideration:</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis> Should we say that we only
                            allow inheritance for a single concern, i.e., we can subtype measurement but
                            not subtype a combination of phenomenon type and measurement
                            type?</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Statement Model Stability:</emphasis> Stability
                        is different from immutability. Stable means that the model can still meet
                        unanticipated requirements without having to change. It is not acceptable to
                        change the model every time a new way to administer a drug or to treat a
                        condition is identified. By representing these types of potentially dynamic
                        concerns in the terminology expressions, as opposed to static fields in a class
                        structure, we do not have to change the model every time something new is
                        discovered. As Terry Winograd said, anticipating breakdowns, and providing a
                        space for action when they occur, is a design imperative.</para>
                    <para>In some regards, in this context “stable” means “not brittle.” A model easily
                        broken by changes that someone could anticipate is one possible definition of
                        brittle. A stable model is critical in the phase of a known changing landscape.
                        We do that by isolating areas of anticipated change into a dynamic data
                        structure. That dynamic data structure may also be immutable in an object that
                        represents a clinical statement.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Overall Model Simplicity: </emphasis>In cases where
                        different principles collide, we shall favor the enhancement of simplicity of
                        the entire system over simplicity in one area of the system.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Cohesion: </emphasis>Related classes should reside in
                        the same module or construction. The placement of a class in a module should
                        reduce the dependencies between modules.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reusability: </emphasis>Architectural patterns should
                        encourage class reusability where possible. Reusability may further refine
                        encapsulation when composition is considered.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Assumption-free: </emphasis>Implied semantics must be
                        surfaced explicitly in the model.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Example: </emphasis>Implicit in the statement,
                                “I order a book from Amazon” are: paying for the book, delivery of the
                                book to some location, and the transfer of ownership of the book from
                                the vendor to the client.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Design by Composition and/or Class Specialization:
                    </emphasis>The capture of additional model expressivity must be captured by
                        composition and/or by class specialization. The modeling approach should avoid
                        the use of design by constraint (except for terminology binding and attribute
                        type constraints) as it violates proper decoupling and encapsulation. An example
                        of design by constraint is to create a single procedure class containing all
                        attributes for all known procedures and constraining out irrelevant attributes
                        in a more specialized model. This approach is very difficult to implement and
                        violates numerous object-oriented best practices.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">No False Dichotomies: </emphasis>Dichotomies that are
                        not completely disjoint (mutually exclusive) lead to arbitrary classification
                        rules and result in ambiguity based on different assumptions about the domain.
                        These must be avoided.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Model Should Avoid Semantic Overloading (semantic
                        precision): </emphasis>Semantic overloading occurs when a model attribute’s
                        meaning changes entirely, depending on context. While the refinement of the
                        semantics of an attribute in a subclass is acceptable, a change of meaning is
                        problematic. For instance, in FHIR, the Composition class defines an attribute
                        called Subject. In some subclasses, the attribute may be the entity that this
                        composition refers to (e.g., the patient in a medical record). In other cases,
                        it is the topic being discussed by the composition (e.g., a medication orderable
                        catalog).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Convention Over Configuration: </emphasis>Convention
                        over configuration (also known as coding by convention) is a software design
                        paradigm used by software frameworks that attempt to decrease the number of
                        decisions that a developer using the framework is required to make without
                        necessarily losing flexibility.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Model Consistency:</emphasis> Patterns should allow the
                        consistent representation of information that is commonly shared across models.
                        For instance, attribution and participation information should be captured
                        consistently. Failure to do so forces implementers to develop heuristics to
                        capture and normalize attribution information that is represented or extended
                        differently in different classes (e.g., FHIR).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Model Symmetry: </emphasis>There should be symmetry in
                        the models wherever we can have it.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Iterative development and validation using use cases</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <para>
            <table frame="topbot" rowsep="0" colsep="0"
                >
                <title>Blood Pressure Measurement Statement</title>
                <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="96.98pt"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="298.78pt"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row rowsep="1">
                            <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Performance Statement</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Narrative:</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Topic:</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Subject of information:</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Statement time:</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Performance Act:</entry>
                            <entrytbl cols="3">
                                <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1.86*"/>
                                <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                                <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="6.48*"/>
                                <tbody>
                                    <row rowsep="0">
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Circumstance:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Timing:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">cde</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row rowsep="0">
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Result:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" namest="c2" nameend="c3">120 beats
                                            per minute </entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </entrytbl>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </para>
        <para>
            <table xml:id="table_7e8ac57c-08f8-4f1e-b1fc-af55f26c991d" colsep="0" rowsep="0" frame="topbot">
                <title>Pulse Request Statement</title>
                <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="96pt" colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="372.24pt" colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row rowsep="1">
                            <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Request Statement</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row rowsep="0">
                            <entry>Narrative:</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row rowsep="0">
                            <entry>Topic:</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Subject of information:</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Statement time:</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row rowsep="0">
                            <entry>Request Act:</entry>
                            <entrytbl cols="3">
                                <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="2.14*"/>
                                <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                                <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="6.35*"/>
                                <tbody>
                                    <row rowsep="0">
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Circumstance:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Timing:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">cde</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row rowsep="0">
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Repetition:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">cde</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row rowsep="0">
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Requested result:</entry>
                                        <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" namest="c2" nameend="c3">&lt; 70
                                            beats per minute</entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </entrytbl>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>    
        </para>
        <section xml:id="section_70b0a98c-07ee-461f-943d-56b055dabf64">
            <title>Measurement</title>
            <para>
                
                <figure>
                    <title>Measure UML</title>
                    <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image1.png" scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
                </figure>
                
                
                <editorial-rule>
                    <title>Measurement</title>
                    <mathphrase>Define measurement</mathphrase>
                </editorial-rule>
                
                <editorial-rule>
                    <title>Lower bound</title>
                    <mathphrase>The lower bound is the smallest reported value of the measurement. If only one value is reported, then the lower bound is the same as 
                        the upper bound.</mathphrase>
                </editorial-rule>
                <editorial-rule>
                    <title>Upper bound</title>
                    <mathphrase>The upper bound is the largest reported value of the measurement. If only one value is reported, then the upper bound is the same
                        as the lower bound. </mathphrase>
                </editorial-rule>
                <editorial-rule>
                    <title>Include lower bound</title>
                    <mathphrase>Indicate if the lower bound is within the interval represented by this measurement, or outside the interval represented by this measurement.</mathphrase>
                </editorial-rule>
                <editorial-rule>
                    <title>Include upper bound</title>
                    <mathphrase>Indicate if the upper bound is within the interval represented by this measurement, or outside the interval represented by this measurement.</mathphrase>
                </editorial-rule>
                <editorial-rule>
                    <title>Resolution</title>
                    <mathphrase>An optional numeric representation of the resolution of this measurement, using the same semantics as the measurement itself. </mathphrase>
                </editorial-rule>
                <editorial-rule>
                    <title>Measure semantic</title>
                    <mathphrase>A concept that defines the semantic interpretation of the upper and lower bounds of this measurement.  </mathphrase>
                </editorial-rule>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="section_b139fa1d-0462-42f7-bc7a-182d28e32efd">
        <title>Statement Types</title>
        <para>The types of clinical statements are listed and described below. The rationale for
            selecting these types is: Clinicians basically do two categories of things with a
            patient that need to be documented as clinical statements: </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Performance of action</emphasis>: Actions may include
                    passive observation of a phenomenon related to patients and their health status
                    or family history, and may also include active interventions, such as providing
                    education or administering medications or documenting that a patient is
                    participating in exercise to improve their overall health status.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Request for action</emphasis>: Requests for future
                    actions may include defining goals, consultation with other providers, or active
                    interventions.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE: </emphasis>Given that this work is not finalized yet, it
            is possible that additional clinical statement types may need to be added in the event
            during creation of the KNARTs there are clinical terminology artifacts identified that
            do not fit into any of the types listed above.</para>
        <para>Any statement that states or implies an “if/then” clause should be expressed and
            captured as an ECA rule</para>
        <para>Example: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>“Free-text reminder: Consider [ordering X procedure] for patients with
                    suspected pericarditis, myocarditis, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, or pulmonary
                    hypertension.”</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Implied “if/then” clause: <emphasis role="bold">IF</emphasis> pericarditis,
                    myocarditis, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, or pulmonary hypertension is suspected
                    – <emphasis role="bold">THEN</emphasis> consider ordering X procedure.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Rather than capturing the above statement as a free text reminder, building an
                    appropriate ECA rule should be considered.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section xml:id="section_e50dee69-daff-4b15-8e2b-a2eb6bc21b21">
            <title>Performance Statements</title>
            <para>An action statement describes an action that has previously been performed, and –
                if applicable - the results of that action. As shown in the examples below, this can
                range from documenting that a subject of record: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Was observed to have the presence or absence of a clinical
                        phenomenon</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Underwent a specific test/screening or procedure, and its resultant value,
                        if any</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Was administered a medication or other substance </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Was provided educational materials</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Has any other state or specific characteristic that is clinically
                        relevant</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>If the action statement:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Regards a measurement that was taken, all information about that
                        measurement will be included as part of the clinical statement, such as its
                        value and unit of measure and any details about how the measurement was
                        taken. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Results in an order(s) placed during the same encounter that was made to
                        learn more about the phenomenon or to monitor it, then a link will be made
                        to the order(s). </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Examples of Action clinical statements:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Systolic blood pressure of 120 mmHg taken from right brachial artery while
                        seated and no more than 30 minutes from when the patient last
                        urinated</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Diabetes mellitus is present</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Diabetes mellitus is not present</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Three dot blot hemorrhages</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Dot blot hemorrhage is present</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Patient taking one Acetaminophen 100 mg tablet by mouth daily as needed
                        for pain</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Positive screen for fall risk</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Negative screen for PTSD and depression</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Family history of colon cancer </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Patient provided educational materials on pre-diabetes diagnosis</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Patient counseled on the health risks of continuing smoking </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_3cd03dbb-48dd-4bdc-8f29-fa20bfd459c9">
            <title>Request Statements</title>
            <para>A Request clinical statement describes a request for an action made by a
                clinician. Most of the times, but not always, the object of the request (e.g., lab
                test, medication order) will be fulfilled by someone other than the clinician (e.g.,
                lab technician, pharmacist) making the request. All information about the request
                will be documented in this clinical statement, including information about details
                relating to the request, such as patient must fast for 12 hours before having a
                lipids blood test.</para>
            <para>Examples of Request clinical statements:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Lipids panel for patient Jane Doe. Patient must fast for 12 hours prior to
                        the blood test.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Head CT with contrast for patient John Doe. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cardiology referral for patient Mary Smith.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Penicillin medication for patient Michael Smith to be taken twice a day by
                        mouth with food for 10 days.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Advised to participate in group tobacco cessation counseling once a
                        week.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Advised to lose 15 pounds within 3 months.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Advised to exercise at least 3 times a week for 30 minutes per day for 3
                        months. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Advised to decrease the number of packs smoked per day from 3 to 2 within
                        6 months by using a nicotine patch.</para>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_1b4e6bff-3a99-465f-95ae-89b8ac23bc6e">
        <title>Statement Building Blocks</title>
        <para>The following components are used in multiple places within clinical statements. </para>
        <para/>
        <section xml:id="section_a4879816-b718-4def-80a1-926f2850f40e">
            <title>Stamp Coordinate</title>
            <para>The stamp coordinate represents the versions of the integrated terminology and
                statement model used to represent a clinical statement. </para>
        </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref493843805">
                <title>Phenomena and Interval Values</title>
                
                <para>In many representation models, such as SNOMED-CT and CIMI, a somewhat arbitrary
                    distinction exists between the modeling of “Findings” and “Observable Entities.” The
                    former typically document the presence or absence of some phenomenon in the patient
                    (such as whether the patient has a pressure ulcer), whereas the latter characterize
                    some feature of the patient or the patient’s condition (such as the number of
                    pressure ulcers a patient has). <xref
                        linkend="table_95d32b2d-0ebf-4caf-abb0-380bf1ff3551"/> shows an example of the
                    different representations for these two similar observations when modeled as
                    Findings versus Observable Entity.<table frame="topbot" rowsep="0" colsep="0"
                        xml:id="table_95d32b2d-0ebf-4caf-abb0-380bf1ff3551">
                        <title>An undesirable redundancy in representing clinical observations.</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="232.16pt"/>
                            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="229.22pt"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Pressure Ulcer as Finding</entry>
                                    <entry>Pressure Ulcer as Observable Entity</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>[Pressure Ulcer(s)]→(value)→[Present]</entry>
                                    <entry>[Pressure Ulcer(s)]→(value)→5</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>[Pressure Ulcer(s)]→(value)→[Absent]</entry>
                                    <entry>[Pressure Ulcer(s)]→(value)→0</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry/>
                                    <entry/>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table></para>
                <para>Because the observation of pressure ulcers in a patient could be correctly modeled
                    as either a Finding or Observable Entity, any subsequent query to determine whether
                    a patient had a pressure ulcer would need to test for the observation in two
                    different ways:</para>
                <para> Because the observation of pressure ulcers<link
                    xlink:href="#con_224b97e0-b703-39f6-ba4b-aa27f5dc15aa"><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata>
                                <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px" height="14px">
                                    <text x="1" y="7"
                                        style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                        >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                            style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; "
                                            >&#xF061; </tspan>
                                        <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Tetralogy of Fallot]</text>
                                </svg>
                            </imagedata>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></link> in a patient could be correctly modeled as either a
                    Finding or Observable Entity Text before. <link
                        xlink:href="#table_9b08a484-6589-430a-bcb5-060703de35c3"><inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata>
                                    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px" height="14px">
                                        <text x="1" y="7"
                                            style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                            >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                                style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; "
                                                >&#xF2D8; </tspan>
                                            <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Overriding structures]</text>
                                    </svg>
                                </imagedata>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></link> Text after. any subsequent query to determine
                    whether a patient had a pressure ulcer would need to test for the observation in two
                    different ways </para>
                <para><emphasis>IF EXISTS object WHERE object.conceptId = “3456_PressureUlcers” AND
                    (object.value = “Present” OR object.value &gt; 0)</emphasis></para>
                <para>This duality of representation complicates data querying and significantly
                    increases the possibility that data analysts will not be aware of and account for
                    all the ways that an observation may be represented, resulting in false-negative
                    query results.</para>
                <para>To resolve the arbitrary distinction between “Findings” and “Observable
                    Entities,” one must consolidate these redundant concepts types into the single
                    concept type “Phenomenon.” Further, one must introduce a new data type to
                    represent the values of Phenomena, one that can express both the “presence”
                    (present/absent/indeterminate) and numeric (integer, real) values that Findings
                    and Observable Entities can currently represent, respectively. This new data
                    type is an “interval value” </para>
                <para/>
                    <section xml:id="_Ref493848005">
                        <title>Confusion About Negation: “Absent” and “Not Present”</title>
                        <para>Negation as a logical concept is subject to many ambiguities and inconsistencies,
                            in healthcare applications and general usage<footnote xml:id="__EN4__">
                                <para>Horn L. A Natural History of Negation. University of Chicago Press,
                                    1989.</para>
                            </footnote>. For example, the semantic distinctions between the statements “he
                            didn’t say she was ill” and “he said she was not ill” are subtle and open to varying
                            interpretations. When such distinctions appear in medical records and are used as
                            the basis for inference or data retrieval, it’s important that a clear and formal
                            semantic exists that is shared by those who record the information, those who later
                            review the information and use it in medical decision making, and those who write
                            software that aggregates, abstracts, infers, or performs other logical computations
                            on the information.</para>
                        <para>One important distinction in medical documentation is that of a clinical
                            phenomenon being documented as “absent” versus the phenomenon not being documented
                            as “present.” For example, does the explicit documentation of “No abdominal
                            tenderness” mean the same thing as no documentation of “abdominal tenderness”? Would
                            the interpretation be different if the phenomenon were instead “jaundice” or “HIV”?
                            Would it matter if the presenting complaint at the time that observation were
                            documented were “vomiting” versus “ankle sprain”? Depending on the clinical context,
                            the specific phenomenon in question, and the assumptions of individuals using the
                            medical record, the interpretation of “absent” versus “not present” could be the
                            same or quite different. Today’s representation and inferencing models for
                            electronic health records do not provide enough clarity and control to safely
                            interpret negation in these situations.</para>
                        <para>Finally, current ontology-based models for representing clinical observations
                            sometimes result in gross errors when subsumption inferences are applied to negated
                            clinical concepts. For example, the SNOMED-CT model incorrectly infers that the
                            documentation of “No myocardial infarction” in a patient implies that the patient
                            has “No heart disease” whatsoever. A model that correctly handles subsumption
                            testing over negated clinical concepts is required to support correct (and safe)
                            inferencing in electronic health records.</para>
                    </section>
                <section>
                
                    <title>The Interval Value Data Type</title>
                    <para>An interval value data type (or “interval value”) formally represents a
                        numeric interval between two non-negative real numbers. The interval can be
                        open or closed. Examples of interval values are:</para>
                    <para>[5,5], [0,10), (0,∞], [0,0]</para>
                    <para>The formal syntax of interval values is represented by the following
                        grammar:</para>
                    <para>Interval :: [ ‘[‘ | ‘(‘ ] N1 ‘,’ N2 [ ‘]’ | ‘)’ ]</para>
                    <para>N1 :: Non-Negative Real Number</para>
                    <para>N2 :: [ Non-Negative Real Number | ∞ ]</para>
                    <para>The semantics of this grammar are as follows:</para>
                    <para>‘[‘ and ‘]’ : Inclusive boundary (i.e. &gt;= and &lt;= )</para>
                    <para>‘(‘ and ‘)’ : Exclusive boundary (i.e., &gt; and &lt; )</para>
                    <para>∞: infinity, is &gt; every Non-Negative Real Number</para>
                    <para>N1 &lt;= N2</para>
                    <para>The interval value data type provides a single way to represent both
                        “presence” values and numeric values for a phenomenon. In general, the
                        interval value represents the numeric range within which the observed value
                        of a phenomenon occurs. Note that this formalism allows both exact values
                        and ranges of values to be expressed.</para>
                    <para>In the special case that the beginning and end point of an interval are
                        the same number, <emphasis>n</emphasis>, the meaning is that the value of
                        the phenomenon is <emphasis>exactly n</emphasis>. </para>
                    <para>[5,5] : exactly 5 ; [0,0] : exactly 0</para>
                    <para>In the special case that the beginning of the interval is a number,
                            <emphasis>n</emphasis>, and the end point is ∞, the meaning is that the
                        value of the phenomenon is <emphasis>&gt; n </emphasis>or
                            <emphasis>&gt;=n</emphasis>, depending on whether the interval is open
                        or closed.</para>
                    <para>(0,∞] : &gt; 0 ; [10,∞] : &gt;= 10</para>
                    <para>The interval value also represents whether a phenomenon is “present”,
                        “absent”, or “indeterminate”. Specifically, any interval value that includes
                            <emphasis>only </emphasis>numbers that are &gt; 0 also denotes the value
                        “present”. Any interval value that includes only the number 0, itself,
                        denotes the value “absent”. Any interval value that includes
                            <emphasis>both</emphasis> the number 0 and at least one number &gt; 0
                        denotes the value “indeterminate”. Lastly, there are two interval values
                        that explicitly denote “present” and “absent,” respectively. These value may
                        be assigned to phenomena that would not otherwise take on a numeric value
                        (such as “nausea”):</para>
                    <para>Nausea value = (0,∞] : present</para>
                    <para>Nausea value = [0,0] : absent </para>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Ref493768774"/> lists a number of phenomena and how their
                        current values (as “Findings” or “Observable Entities”) would be represented
                        instead as interval values under the model proposed here.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493768774">
                        <title>The semantics of interval values assigned to phenomena, as shown
                            through examples.</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/interval-values-for-phenomena.png"
                                    width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Comparing Interval Values using IsWithin()</title>
                    <para>Phenomena that represent clinical observations must be assigned interval
                        values, so the querying of such phenomena for purposes of data retrieval and
                        data analysis requires the comparison of interval values. Specifically, one
                        must be able to test whether one interval value <emphasis>is
                            within</emphasis> (i.e., encompassed by) another interval value. For
                        example, if one wanted to retrieve only those patients who had between 1 and
                        5 pressure ulcers, one would test whether a patient had the phenomenon
                        “pressure ulcer” recorded with a value interval that was within the interval
                        [1,5]. Note that this test would retrieve patients who had pressure-ulcer
                        interval values, for example, of [1,1], [4,4], and [3,5], but not those who
                        had [0,0] or [1,10].</para>
                    <para>Formally, the comparison of two interval values is done using the
                        predicate <emphasis>IsWithin(
                            i</emphasis><subscript>1</subscript><emphasis>, i</emphasis><subscript>2
                            </subscript><emphasis>), </emphasis>where i<subscript>1</subscript>,
                            i<subscript>2 </subscript>are interval values. The values of the
                        IsWithin() predicate may be TRUE, FALSE, or UNKNOWN, determined as
                        follows:</para>
                    <para>TRUE =&gt; if a number is in i<subscript>1</subscript>, then it is
                        definitely in i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript>
                        “subsumes” i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para>FALSE =&gt; if a number is in i<subscript>1</subscript>, then it is
                        definitely NOT in i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript>
                            “i<subscript>1</subscript>is disjoint with”
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para>UNKNOWN =&gt; if a value is in, it may or may not be in
                            i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript> “overlaps”
                            i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para>Examples of interval-value comparisons:</para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin</emphasis>( [5,5], [0,10] ) =&gt; TRUE (interval
                            i<subscript>2</subscript> “subsumes” interval
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin</emphasis>( [15,20], [0,10] ) =&gt; FALSE (interval
                            i<subscript>2</subscript> “is disjoint with” interval
                            i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin</emphasis>( [5,15], [0,10] ) =&gt; UNKNOWN (interval
                            i<subscript>2</subscript> “overlaps” interval
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                    <para>Other useful examples:</para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [2,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                            TRUE</emphasis></para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [0,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt; UNKNOWN
                        </emphasis></para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( (0,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                            TRUE</emphasis></para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [0,0], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                            FALSE</emphasis></para>
                    <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [0,0], [0,0] ) =&gt; TRUE</emphasis></para>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Querying Phenomena Using Interval Values</title>
                <para>Based on the definition of the IsWithin() predicate, patient records may be
                    queried for the presence or the numeric value of clinical observations using a
                    single formalism.</para>
                <section>
                    <title>Basic Querying</title>
                    <para>The example query in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493771252"/> seeking to
                        determine whether a patient has a pressure ulcer may now be formulated more
                        simply and consistently (using pseudo-SQL to represent the logic):</para>
                    <para>IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode =
                        “3456_PressureUlcers” AND IsWithin(ph.value, (0,∞]) = TRUE</para>
                    <para>Note that, with pressure ulcers represented as Phenomena, the single
                        predicate “IsWithin(ph.value, (0,∞]) = TRUE” replaces the two expressions
                        previously required when pressure ulcers could be represented as either
                        Findings or Observable Entities (“object.value = “Present” OR object.value
                        &gt; 0”). The user formulating the query can reliably test for pressure
                        ulcers in the patient’s record without concern for how that clinical
                        observation is represented or what types of values it may have.</para>
                    <para>Similarly, to determine whether a patient has any test results within a
                        specific numeric range, a similar formulation may be used, simply
                        substituting the desired numeric reference interval in the IsWithin()
                        predicate:</para>
                    <para>IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode =
                        “2468_SerumPotassium” AND IsWithin( ph.value, [0, 3.7) ) = TRUE</para>
                    <para>The query above will evaluate to true if the patient 9876 has any serum
                        potassium values &lt; 3.7.</para>
                </section>
                <section xml:id="_Ref493859801">
                    <title>Querying with Negation</title>
                    <para>Querying for the absence of a clinical phenomenon for a specific patient
                        introduces certain complications because of variations in the way that the
                        phenomenon may or may not be represented in the medical record. For example,
                        if a data-retrieval or data-analysis function needed to determine whether a
                        patient did NOT have any pressure ulcers, the query could be formulated in
                        at least two ways.</para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Under the <emphasis>closed-world assumption
                                    </emphasis>(CWA)<emphasis>, </emphasis>which implies that all
                                information about the state of the patient is included in the
                                medical record. In this case, the absence of any information in the
                                medical record supporting the presence of a pressure ulcer would be
                                sufficient evidence that the patient had no pressure ulcers. The
                                specific formulation of the query under this assumption would be: IF
                                NOT (EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND
                                ph.conceptCode = “3456_PressureUlcers” AND IsWithin(ph.value, (0,∞])
                                = TRUE) (Note that the reference value in the IsWithin() predicate
                                is “(0,∞]” in this case.)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Under the <emphasis>open-world assumption </emphasis>(OWA). This
                                assumption implies that not all information about the patient’s
                                state is included in the medical record, so that the non-existence
                                of some patient state cannot be assumed based solely on a lack of
                                data asserting the presence of that state. In this case, the absence
                                of some phenomenon can only be inferred if the patient record
                                explicitly asserts such absence, or at least uncertainty about its
                                presence. A specific formulation of the query under this assumption
                                would be: IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND
                                ph.conceptCode = “3456_PressureUlcers” AND IsWithin(ph.value, (0,∞])
                                &lt; &gt; TRUE An alternative OWA formulation of the query with
                                slightly different semantics would be: IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE
                                ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode = “3456_PressureUlcers” AND
                                IsWithin(ph.value, [0,0]) = TRUE (Note the different formulations of
                                the IsWithin() predicates in these queries.)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <para>The semantic distinctions among these query formulations are significant,
                        in that they will generate different query responses for the same patient
                        data in certain cases. <xref linkend="_Ref493768774"/> shows the Boolean
                        value for each query given different patient data instances in the medical
                        record. Notably, the query values are different in the last two cases. Note
                        that in <xref linkend="_Ref493768774"/>, a Boolean value of TRUE indicates
                        that the patient does NOT have pressure ulcers, whereas a Boolean value of
                        FALSE indicates that the patient DOES have pressure ulcers (since the
                        queries are testing for the absence of that phenomenon).</para>
                    <figure>
                        <title>Example truth table of negated querying under closed-world and
                            open-world assumptions.</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/truth-table-of-negated-query.png"
                                    width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    <para>The potential variance in query responses depending on how a negation
                        query is formulated and how the absence of a phenomenon is represented in
                        the medical record is a problem for health-care applications that depend on
                        clear and consistent analysis of patient data. If data analysis of clinical
                        observations is subject to misinterpretation, then medical applications may
                        reach incorrect conclusions and/or provide incorrect advice, with adverse
                        patient-safety consequences.</para>
                    <para>To avoid ambiguity in the representation and analysis of clinical
                        observation data, a better formalized and more intuitive model for querying
                        is required.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Normalized Querying of Phenomena</title>
                <para>This section introduces a model for normalizing the querying of clinical
                    observations represented as phenomena so that the semantics of various query
                    formulations are more explicit and intuitive, especially when queries include
                    explicit negation. </para>
                <section xml:id="_Ref493847012">
                    <title>A Tri-Valued State of Knowledge: Present, Absent, and
                        Indeterminate</title>
                    <para>The initial step involves abstracting the possible states of a clinical
                        phenomenon as reflected in the medical record to three mutually exclusive
                        and exhaustive values: Present, Absent, and Indeterminate. The informal
                        definitions of these states are as follows:</para>
                    <para>Present”: The phenomenon is explicitly documented as present or can be
                        logically inferred to be present</para>
                    <para>“Absent”: The phenomenon is explicitly documented as absent or can be
                        logically inferred to be absent</para>
                    <para>“Indeterminate”: The phenomenon is neither “Present” nor “Absent”</para>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Ref493776756"/> illustrates this set of possible states
                        and their relationships to each other. </para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493776756">
                        <title>The space of value assignments in a tri-valued approach to
                            representing states of knowledge</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/tri-valued-approach.png" width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    <para>The implications of this conceptualization include the following logical
                        statements, some of which may seem counter-intuitive (note that the symbol
                        “” connotes logical equivalence, i.e. “if and only if”):</para>
                    <para>Absent NOT Present AND NOT Indeterminate (Note: Absent implies NOT
                        Present)</para>
                    <para>NOT Present  Absent OR Indeterminate (Note: NOT Present does not
                        necessarily imply Absent)</para>
                    <para>Indeterminate  NOT Present AND NOT Absent (Note: It does not imply
                        “Present OR Absent”) </para>
                    <para>It’s important to note that, in this conceptualization, Present, Absent,
                        and Indeterminate reflect the possible states<emphasis
                            > </emphasis>of<emphasis> knowledge </emphasis>about the clinical
                        phenomenon in a particular patient, not the states of the phenomenon itself.
                        For example, Absent does not indicate that the patient is necessarily free
                        of the phenomenon, but only that the medical record indicates that the
                        patient does not have it. Similarly, Indeterminate does not indicate that
                        the patient is in some intermediate state between having and not having the
                        phenomenon or that it is impossible to determine whether the patient has the
                        phenomenon, but rather that, based on the information in the medical record,
                        it cannot be known whether the patient does or does not have the
                        phenomenon.</para>
                    <para>AXIOMS:</para>
                    <para>Based on this conceptualization, the three states of knowledge with
                        respect to any phenomenon, ph, are formally defined via the following
                        axioms, which use the prior definitions of “interval value” and the
                        “IsWithin()” predicate:</para>
                    <para>Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  <emphasis>ph</emphasis> where
                        IsWithin( <emphasis>ph</emphasis>.value, (0,∞] ) = TRUE</para>
                    <para>Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  <emphasis>ph</emphasis> where
                        IsWithin( <emphasis>ph</emphasis>.value, [0,0] ) = TRUE</para>
                    <para>Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  NOT
                            Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) and NOT
                        Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)</para>
                    <para>Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR
                            Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) </para>
                    <para>NOT ( Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)
                        )</para>
                    <para>NOT ( Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                            Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                    <para>NOT ( Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                            Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Ref493768774"/> shows several examples of how these axioms
                        generate the appropriate value of Present, Absent, or Indeterminate for
                        certain phenomena based on how those phenomena are documented in the patient
                        record. Note that each row in the table represents a distinct state of the
                        patient’s medical record (i.e., they are not present in the record at the
                        same time). In fact, the presence of certain of the rows in the record at
                        the same time would be inconsistent with the logical model defined
                        above.</para>
                    <figure>
                        <title>Example assignments of present, absent, and indeterminate based on
                            various interval values</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/assignment-of-tri-value.png"
                                    width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section xml:id="_Ref493858870">
                    <title>Assigning Values to Phenomena That Include Refining Attributes</title>
                    <para>In contemporary models for representing clinical observations, such as
                        SNOMED-CT, OpenEHR, and CIMI, observation instances can consist of
                        post-coordinated concept expressions, i.e., a general concept that is
                        further described and refined by a set of associated attribute/value pairs.
                        Collectively, the concept and its refining attribute/value pairs
                        characterize the distinct phenomenon that was observed. For example, <xref
                            linkend="_Ref493843663"/> shows such a post-coordinated expression
                        comprising an observed phenomenon.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493843663">
                        <title>A sample post-coordinated phenomenon. </title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/post-coordinated-phenomenon.png"
                                    width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    <para>When such a phenomenon is documented in the medical record and assigned an
                        interval value, per the model specified in Section <xref
                            linkend="_Ref493843805"/>, it is essential that the interval value
                        corresponds to the conceptual entirety of the phenomenon. If interval values
                        are not clearly assigned to the entirety of documented phenomena at the time
                        the phenomena are captured and stored, then inconsistent and incorrect
                        interpretations of the data may result. </para>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Ref493845221"/> illustrates the correct assignment of
                        interval values to two phenomena, the first of which documents that two
                        pressure ulcers were present in the patient’s left leg on a specific date,
                        and the second of which documents that pressure ulcers were absent in the
                        patient’s right leg on the same date. The presence of both of these
                        phenomena in the patient record at the same time is intuitively possible,
                        and is consistent with the axioms of the model in Section <xref
                            linkend="_Ref493847012"/>.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493845221">
                        <title>The correct assignment of interval values to post-coordinated
                            phenomena. </title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/assignment-of-interval-value.png"
                                    width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Ref493845589"/> illustrates the problems that may occur
                        when interval values are erroneously assigned to just a subset of the
                        post-coordinated expressions used to document phenomena. In this case, the
                        interval values are assigned just to the general concept of a pressure
                        ulcer, omitting the refining attributes from the scope of the assignment.
                        This results in the representation that the patient both had and did not
                        have pressure ulcers at the same time. Because the full set of refining
                        attributes were not included in the scope of the interval-value assignment,
                        an incorrect representation is created that is intuitively non-sensical and
                        violates the axioms of Section <xref linkend="_Ref493847012"/>. Such
                        representations can lead to incorrect data-retrieval, data-analysis, and
                        inferencing results if used by automated processes later. This is
                        underscored in the discussion of subsumption testing involving phenomena in
                        Section <xref linkend="_Ref493846313"/>.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493845589">
                        <title>The incorrect assignment of interval values to post-coordinated
                            phenomena. </title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata
                                    fileref="images/incorrect-assignment-of-interval-value.png"
                                    width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref493846313">
                <title>Normalized Querying using Subsumption Relationships Among Phenomena</title>
                <para>As mentioned in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493848005"/>, ontology-based
                    representation models may produce incorrect results when performing subsumption
                    testing over negated concepts. The root cause of these errors is that negation
                    changes the basic rules of logical subsumption testing and must be explicitly
                    handled as a special case. This section presents a formal model for handling
                    subsumption over negated concepts when such concepts are represented as
                    phenomena with assigned interval values.</para>
                <section>
                    <title>Theoretical Foundation</title>
                    <para>The semantics of logical subsumption are based on set membership. The
                        definitions of concepts (or phenomena) describe the characteristics of
                        certain sets or types of instances in the real world. We say that phenomenon
                        A <emphasis>subsumes</emphasis> phenomenon B if and only if any instance of
                        phenomenon B is <emphasis>necessarily</emphasis> an instance of phenomenon
                        A. In other words, if set A subsumes set B, the instances of set B are a
                        subset of the instances of set A. Equivalently, membership in set B
                            <emphasis>implies </emphasis>membership in set A for any instance,
                            <emphasis>I</emphasis>, which can be represented by the logical
                        statement</para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>IF Member-Set-B(<emphasis>i</emphasis>) THEN
                                    Member-Set-A(<emphasis>i</emphasis>)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <para>These relationships can be seen graphically in <xref
                            linkend="_Ref493852417"/>. Note that subsumption does not necessarily
                        imply that Set B is a proper subset of Set A – Set A and Set B could be the
                        same.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493852417">
                        <title>Set-theoretic view of the subsumption relationship. </title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/set-theoretic-view.png" width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Ref493851545"/> shows how subsumption relationships can
                        apply to clinical observations. Specifically, the figure shows a subsumption
                        hierarchy involving various types of pressure ulcer phenomena in which each
                        parent phenomenon subsumes its child phenomena, given their respective
                        definitions. In set-theoretic terms, any clinical observation that is an
                        instance of (member-of) a child phenomenon is necessarily an instance of its
                        parent phenomenon (and, indeed, any ancestors of that parent). For example,
                        we would say that, if a patient has a stage-4 pressure ulcer in the left
                        leg, then it’s necessarily true that the patient has a pressure ulcer (of
                        some kind) in the left leg and also that the patient has a pressure ulcer
                        (somewhere on her body).</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493851545">
                        <title>An example subsumption hierarchy for post-coordinated phenomena in
                            the clinical domain. </title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/subsumption-hierarchy.png" width="5.5in"
                                />
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    <para>Per classical logic, statement (1) also implies the
                        contra-positive:</para>
                    <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>IF NOT Member-Set-A(<emphasis>i</emphasis>) THEN NOT
                                    Member-Set-B(<emphasis>i</emphasis>)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <para>which makes intuitive sense if one considers that an instance cannot be a
                        member of any subset of set A if it is not a member of set A to begin with.
                        In the medical context, it’s clear that a patient who does not have a
                        pressure ulcer on the right leg cannot have a stage-2 pressure ulcer on the
                        right leg.</para>
                    <para>Lastly, one should note that statement (1) does <emphasis role="underline"
                            >NOT</emphasis> imply the following statements:</para>
                    <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>IF Member-Set-A(i) THEN Member-Set-B(i)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>IF NOT Member-Set-B(i) THEN NOT Member-Set-A(i)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <para>This can be seen clearly by inspection of <xref linkend="_Ref493852417"/>.
                        Note specifically that membership in Set A does not
                            <emphasis>preclude</emphasis> membership in Set B. It just does not
                        necessarily imply it, i.e., it simply provides no definitive information
                        either way. Similarly, lack of membership in Set B provides no definitive
                        information as to lack of membership in Set A.</para>
                    <para>Extending this reasoning to the clinical domain, one can stipulate the
                        inferences shown in <xref linkend="_Ref493853493"/> when interval values are
                        assigned to certain of the phenomena in the subsumption hierarchy.
                        Specifically, the documented presence of a pressure ulcer in the left leg
                        necessarily implies the presence of a pressure ulcer somewhere, but it does
                        not provide definitive information about the presence of a stage-4 pressure
                        ulcer in the left leg (e.g., it could be stage 3). Similarly, the absence of
                        a pressure ulcer in the right leg necessarily implies the absence of a
                        stage-2 pressure ulcer in the right leg, but it provides no definitive
                        information about the absence of a pressure ulcer in general (e.g., there
                        could be one in the left leg).</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493853493">
                        <title>Examples of correct subsumption inferences with respect to
                            post-coordinated phenomena.</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/correct-subsumption.png" width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section xml:id="_Ref493866647">
                    <title>A Formal Model of Negation with Subsumption Relationships</title>
                    <para>Using these precepts of classical logic, one can generalize the set of
                        axioms introduced in <xref linkend="_Ref493847012"/> to incorporate
                        subsumption inference into the determination of whether a specified
                        phenomenon is Present, Absent, or Indeterminate, based on the state of a
                        patient’s medical record. The axioms below should replace those introduced
                        earlier.</para>
                    <para>Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  <emphasis>ph’</emphasis> where
                            Is-A(<emphasis>ph’</emphasis>, <emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                            IsWithin(<emphasis>ph’</emphasis>.value, (0,∞] ) = TRUE</para>
                    <para>Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  ph’ where
                            Is-A(<emphasis>ph’</emphasis>, ph’) AND
                            IsWithin(<emphasis>ph’</emphasis>.value, [0,0] ) = TRUE</para>
                    <para>Indeterminate(ph)  NOT Present(ph) AND NOT Absent(ph)</para>
                    <para>Is-A(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>, <emphasis>ph’</emphasis>)  IF an instance
                        satisfies all properties of <emphasis>ph</emphasis>, then it necessarily
                        satisfies all properties of <emphasis>ph’</emphasis>, i.e. <emphasis>ph’
                        </emphasis>subsumes <emphasis>ph</emphasis></para>
                    <para>Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR
                            Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) </para>
                    <para>NOT ( Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)
                        )</para>
                    <para>NOT ( Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                            Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) </para>
                    <para>NOT ( Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                            Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                    <para>Again, for these axioms to hold and be mutually consistent, the scope of
                        any interval value assigned to a phenomenon must include all of its refining
                        attributes, as described in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493858870"/>.</para>
                    <para>Applying standard logical operators, the axioms above also imply the
                        following logical statements:</para>
                    <para>NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) NOT (  ph’ where Is-A(ph’,
                            <emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND IsWithin( ph’.value, (0,∞] ) = TRUE
                        )</para>
                    <para>NOT Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) NOT (  ph’ where
                            Is-A(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>, ph’) AND IsWithin( ph’.value, [0,0] ) =
                        TRUE )</para>
                    <para>Is-A(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>, <emphasis>ph</emphasis>) (allows degenerate
                        case when present/absent are explicitly documented for a phenomenon)</para>
                    <para>NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR
                            Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) </para>
                    <para> (Note: NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) does not necessarily imply
                            Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                    <para>Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                        NOT Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)</para>
                    <para> (Note: Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) does imply NOT
                            Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                    <para>Returning to the original example of negation given in Section <xref
                            linkend="_Ref493859801"/>, one can now explicitly specify the
                        closed-world assumption or the open-world assumption in the manner that the
                        query predicate is formulated based on the logical definitions of “Present”
                        and “Absent”. Specifically, the query may be formulated as</para>
                    <para>IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode =
                        “3456_PressureUlcers” AND <emphasis> &lt;predicate&gt;</emphasis></para>
                    <para>where <emphasis>&lt;predicate&gt;</emphasis> is either “NOT Present(ph)”
                        (closed-world assumption) or “Absent(ph)” (open-world assumption). The
                        ability to formulate the predicate using the higher-level abstractions
                        “Present”, “NOT Present”, “Absent”, or “NOT Absent” allows data analysts to
                        abstract away from the detailed, technical use of the IsWithin() predicate
                        in the queries of Section <xref linkend="_Ref493859801"/>. It also obviates
                        data analysts from understanding and correctly applying the logic of
                        subsumption when negated phenomenon appear in the medical record. The
                        complete truth table for the query above based on a number of potential
                        values in the patient record are shown in <xref linkend="_Ref493946553"
                        />.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="_Ref493946553">
                        <title>Complete truth table for querying using interval values and the
                            tri-valued model of knowledge</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/complete-truth-table.png" width="5.5in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Practical examples</title>
                    <para>Two practical examples help to illustrate the applicability and utility of
                        the models presented above. They represent differing clinical contexts in
                        which the closed-world assumption or the open-world assumption are
                        appropriate, and can be explicitly made in the formulation of data
                        queries.</para>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: Medication
                        prescription.</emphasis></para>
                    <para>A decision support rule concludes that a patient meets the clinical
                        criteria to be on an antihypertensive, but must determine whether the
                        patient is already taking such a medication before recommending its
                        prescription. The logic is best formulated as</para>
                    <para>IF NOT Present(prescription for antihypertensive) THEN recommend
                        prescribing an antihypertensive</para>
                    <para>In this case, the closed-world assumption is appropriate in formulating
                        the query because (a) medication prescriptions are likely to be documented
                        in the medical record and (b) the explicit absence of a medication
                        prescription is not likely to be explicitly document (otherwise, all of the
                        medications that a patient were not taking would need to be
                        documented).</para>
                    <para>Note also that, were a prescription for a specific antihypertensive agent,
                        such as “Captopril” explicitly documented in the patient record, the axioms
                        presented in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> would correctly infer
                        that the predicate “NOT Present(prescription for antihypertensive)” was
                        false, because Is-A(prescription for Captopril, prescription for
                        antihypertensive).</para>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: Drug allergy.</emphasis></para>
                    <para>A different decision support rule concludes that a patient meets the
                        clinical criteria to be prescribed penicillin, but must determine whether
                        the patient is allergic to that drug before recommending such a
                        prescription. Here, the logic is best formulated as</para>
                    <para>IF Absent(allergy to penicillin) THEN recommend prescribing a
                        penicillin</para>
                    <para>In this case, the open-world assumption is more appropriate because (a)
                        it’s important to be certain that no allergy exists, and (b) the presence of
                        allergies is likely to be explicitly documented in the medical record. Note
                        also the following implications of formulating the query in this way:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The explicit assignment of the interval value “[0,0]” to the
                                phenomenon “Allergy to a drug” (i.e., the documentation of “NKDA”)
                                in the medical record will result in the predicate “Absent(allergy
                                to penicillin)” evaluating to true per the axioms presented in
                                Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> (because
                                Is-A(penicillin,drug) ). This is the desired behavior.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The explicit assignment of the interval value “(0,∞]” to the
                                phenomenon “Allergy to Amoxicillin” (i.e., the documentation of an
                                allergy to Amoxicillin) in the medical record will result in the
                                predicate “Absent(allergy to penicillin)” evaluating to false per
                                the axioms presented in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/>
                                (because Is-A(Amoxicillin, penicillin) ). Again, this is the desired
                                behavior.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If no phenomena related to drug allergies are documented in the
                                medical record at all, the phenomenon “allergy to penicillin” will
                                be indeterminate per the axioms presented in Section <xref
                                    linkend="_Ref493866647"/>, which will imply that the predicate
                                “Absent(allergy to penicillin)” is false, again per the axioms. This
                                is also the desired behavior.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>These examples show that the model specified in this paper for querying
                        with negation works in a manner that is clinically appropriate in at least
                        these two important cases.</para>
                </section>
            </section>


        <section xml:id="section_4ba31e20-94ae-4d32-86a6-0d16fe45b3a9">
            <title>UUID</title>
            <para>The UUID is the means by which all clinical statement items that require unique
                identifiers are identified. </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_a90e0e13-e26f-4e0f-95a1-bd3d6884c6fa">
            <title>Logical Expression</title>
            <section xml:id="section_d77f3cb2-b433-4811-acee-39c70e475f67">
                <title>Stamp Coordinate</title>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_55e57c1b-49ed-47b3-8e74-b443103c0af8">
        <title>Encoded Statement</title>
        <para/>
        <section>
            <title>Procedures</title>
            <para>
                
                <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_Peripheral_pulse_taking_8a07a847-abb7-3cae-997a-649205922577"><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata>
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px"
                                height="14px">
                                <text x="1" y="7"
                                    style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                    >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                        style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; "
                                        >&#xF061; </tspan>
                                    <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Peripheral pulse taking]</text>
                            </svg>
                        </imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
                </link> 
                
            </para>
            <para>
                
                <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_Pulse_rate_1f621ed0-b2b9-37bf-ba99-cdcdc1a6e24a"><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata>
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px"
                                height="14px">
                                <text x="1" y="7"
                                    style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                    >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                        style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #5ec200; stroke: #5ec200; "
                                        >&#xF060; </tspan>
                                    <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Pulse rate]</text>
                            </svg>
                        </imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></link> 
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_Blood_pressure_taking_215fd598-e21d-3e27-a0a2-8e23b1b36dfc"><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata>
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px"
                                height="14px">
                                <text x="1" y="7"
                                    style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                    >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                        style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; "
                                        >&#xF2D8; </tspan>
                                    <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Blood pressure taking]</text>
                            </svg>
                        </imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></link> 
                
            </para>
            
            <para>
                
                <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_Measurement_of_blood_pressure_using_cuff_method_74374092-8c3a-328c-9370-ba1ecba7a0d0"><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata>
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px"
                                height="14px">
                                <text x="1" y="7"
                                    style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                    >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                        style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; "
                                        >&#xF2D8; </tspan>
                                    <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Measurement of blood pressure using cuff method]</text>
                            </svg>
                        </imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></link> 
                
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Finding, Observation, and Phenomenon</title>
           <para>
                
                <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_O_AND_OR_E___pulse_rate_5aa42d0d-682d-35ad-be48-2ad2542db16e"><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata>
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px"
                                height="14px">
                                <text x="1" y="7"
                                    style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                    >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                        style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #FF4E08; stroke: #FF4E08; "
                                        >&#xF061; </tspan>
                                    <tspan dy="-1.5"/>O/E - pulse rate]</text>
                            </svg>
                        </imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></link> 
                
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <link xlink:href="#ge_solor_Pulse_rate_1f621ed0-b2b9-37bf-ba99-cdcdc1a6e24a"><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata>
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="126px"
                                height="14px">
                                <text x="1" y="7"
                                    style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Open Sans Condensed Light, Symbol, Material Design Icons; baseline-shift: sub;"
                                    >[<tspan dy="1.5"
                                        style="font-family: Material Design Icons; fill: #5ec200; stroke: #5ec200; "
                                        >&#xF060; </tspan>
                                    <tspan dy="-1.5"/>Pulse rate]</text>
                            </svg>
                        </imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></link> 
                
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_897a7f9b-481b-4028-af57-be1159e7557d">
        <title>Statement Models</title>
        <para/>
        <section>
            <title>Clinical Input Form Statements</title>
         <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Analisis Normal Form Statements</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
