<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Concepts and Codes</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Terminology systems are increasingly critical components for achieving
            interoperability across applications in the healthcare domain.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T131526-0600" comment="I recommend moving this up so it&apos;s the 2nd sentence in this paragraph." flag="done"?>A
            standard terminology is one that has wide industry acceptance or use.<?oxy_comment_end?>
            The role of standard terminologies in achieving interoperability for the purposes of
            advancing patient care is well documented. Ideally, these clinical terminology standards
            intend to provide rules to allow for the exchange, integration, and management of
            electronic clinical information. The federal government recognizes the benefit of
            standard terminologies and promotes their development and use. The <emphasis
                role="italic">Federal Health IT Strategic Plan 2015-2020</emphasis> set a strategy
            to encourage consistent terminology standards implementation in Electronic Health
            Records (EHRs) and encourage use through federal payment policies. </para>
        <para>Standards are obtained from a variety of efforts, cover different domains of clinical
            and nonclinical content relevant to the EHR, and serve various purposes. Currently, no
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T131701-0600" comment="Recommend revising to &quot;single&quot; for readability purposes." flag="done"?>single<?oxy_comment_end?>
            terminology or classification system contains everything that is needed for the medical
            record. </para>
        <para>The scope of content covered in terminologies varies from focusing on a very specific
            domain to covering multiple domains. The main terminologies supported in Solor (i.e.,
            SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm) all follow very structured and persistent code practices.
            They never delete codes but in some cases (i.e., RxNorm) they are moved to a separate
            table. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>SNOMED CT Concepts</title>
        <para>Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine-Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT®) is a comprehensive
            clinical terminology, maintained by SNOMED International representing over 300,000
            concepts including disorders (22%), procedures (17%), body structures (11%), clinical
            findings other than disorders (10%), and organisms (10%).</para>
        <para>SNOMED CT concepts span multiple domains, from findings and disorders to procedures
            and pharmaceutical and biological products. SNOMED CT concepts exist at multiple levels
            of granularity, and mechanisms exist to add missing content to ensure that information
            is coded at the most granular level possible. SNOMED CT concepts are identified with a
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T132125-0600" comment="Does this go against the desiderata of a meaningless identifer, as mentioned in the terminology-intro.xml section?  If yes, should it be acknowledged?" id="wvs_slw_lhb" mid="4"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190806T153923-0500" comment="No.  They have structure but no meaning behind the structure.  The desiderata of a meaningless identifier is broken when you add meaning to an identifier.  For example, ICD has a meaning to the code in that (I50.32 is a subtype of I50.3 which is a subtype of I50).  The SCTID doesn&apos;t have that structure to it.  It only gives you information about what type of identifier it is (Concept, Description, Relationship) and that would never change." parentID="wvs_slw_lhb" mid="3"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T132602-0600" comment="It&apos;s still in the current version of the SIA book." flag="done"?>6-
            to 18-digit integer that has some structure that describes where the identifier
            originated (the original creator of the identifier) and what type of identifier it is.
            <?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="3"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="4"?></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T204727-0500" comment="Can we legally add examples here to the documentation?
"?>LOINC
            Codes</title><?oxy_comment_end?>
        <para>Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC®) is a terminology
            representing about 50,000 clinical and laboratory observations, health measurements, and
            documents, developed and maintained by the Regenstrief Institute.</para>
        <para>LOINC codes are used to identify laboratory and clinical measurements, observations
            and documents. Each named concept in LOINC is given a LOINC code which has no structure
            other than a check digit appended to the end. In addition, all of the components that
            make up the LOINC name are assigned LOINC Part Codes (LP) to them in the LOINC Database.
            LOINC Parts do not follow the same policies and maintenance practices as LOINC terms and
            are not intended to be used as a standalone terminology. Some LOINC codes are also
            associated with answers (LA) and answer lists (LL) in the LOINC Database. </para>
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190717T161420-0600" comment="The line formatting for this in the PDF is strange. The justification type is putting a lot of white space between each word.  I think maybe a hard return needs to be inserted before the graphic?  You&apos;ll have to view in the PDF probably to see what I mean."?>The
            screenshot from Komet below exemplifies the 6 LOINC parts: Component, Method, Property,
            Scale, System, and Timing.<?oxy_comment_end?>
            <figure>
                <title>LOINC Code Example</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/LOINC_komet.png" scale="20"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>RxNorm</title>
        <para>RxNorm is a terminology for human clinical drugs in the U.S., representing drug
            properties such as ingredient, strength, and dose form, maintained by the National
            Library of Medicine (NLM) and distributed via the Unified Medical Language System
            (UMLS).</para>
        <para>RxNorm provides normalized clinical drug names and relationships between those names
            and common drug vocabularies for the purpose of easing the exchange of clinical drug
            information between systems that use different drug vocabularies. Every concept in
            RxNorm is given a unique RXCUI. The names and codes from the common drug vocabularies
            are then linked to that RXCUI.</para>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/RxNorm.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>UMLS</title>
        <para>Terminology systems typically consist of the following elements: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Coded Concepts – the discrete units of knowledge managed within the
                    terminology. They typically consist of numeric codes and textual preferred
                    names, synonyms, and descriptions. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept Hierarchies – the logical organization of concepts into parent-child
                    and ancestor-descendant relationships that express the semantics of
                    generalization and specialization. The hierarchical organization of a
                    terminology may be explicitly expressed through stored parent-child and
                    ancestor-descendant links, or it may be implicitly expressed through the logical
                    definitions of individual concepts that a computer can use to infer parent-child
                    and ancestor-descendant relationships. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Value Sets – named lists of individual concepts that represent more abstract
                    categories useful in decision-support logic.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>New applications and new medical knowledge constantly call for expansion and
            enhancement of existing terminologies. However, since terminology systems are often
            non-static, incomplete and under specified, inconsistencies may be introduced. </para>
        <para>While many of these challenges are related to terminology evolution, others may be
            related to the design of the standard clinical terminologies themselves. Cimino notably
            described the challenges of concept orientation, completeness, correctness, currency,
            granularity, and redundancy when designing re-usable medical terminologies. Today, 20
            years later, a menagerie of inconsistent and overlapping terminology models hinders
            efforts that try to store and analyze encoded clinical data. Several efforts aim to
            assist. The National Library of Medicine (NLM) integrates terms and codes from over 150
            source vocabularies by concept, attribute, and meaning in the Unified Medical Language
            System ® (UMLS) Metathesaurus. The NLM, also, in collaboration with the Office of the
            National Coordinator for Health Information Technology and Centers for Medicare &amp;
            Medicaid Services, hosts the Value Set Authority Center (VSAC). The VSAC aims to provide
            lists of values, codes, and names (i.e., value sets) from standard clinical
            terminologies to represent clinical concepts. </para>
        <para>These tools, while helpful, have gaps.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T141242-0600" comment="Did you want to include a link to this reference?  Same for all citations in this paragraph." id="syq_1mw_lhb" flag="done" mid="7"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190418T125814-0400" comment="Proper documentation of references needs to be an overarching task that is done for the entire SIA book. " parentID="syq_1mw_lhb" flag="done" mid="8"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T124300-0600" comment="Okay, thanks." flag="done"?>Raje
            et al.
            <?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="8"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="7"?>highlighted
            issues with completeness, correctness, and redundancy when they found gaps in the UMLS
            Metathesaurus’ coverage of disease concepts. <citation>Raje</citation> Similarly,
            Winnenburg et al. highlighted duplicate value sets in the VSAC, and showed that 19% of
            value sets in 2011 contained invalid codes. <citation>Winnenburg</citation> In
            subsequent work, they highlighted issues related to granularity by evaluating over 1,000
            value sets and found that value sets varied vastly in size with some only containing one
            code, while other value sets included over 20,000 codes.
                <citation>Winnenburg2</citation> Similarly, Bahr et al. showed issues with concept
            orientation by analyzing medication value sets and found extraneous and missing
            ingredients in both the value sets and drug classes.<citation>Bahr</citation>
        </para>
        <para>These issues related to integrating clinical content have a direct impact on patient
            safety and point to the need to be able to consistently represent and encode clinical
            data and observations. Therefore, quality assurance is an indispensable part of the
            terminology management lifecycle. A central limitation of integrating controlled medical
            terminologies is that they often lack any formal model to denote the relationships among
            constituent data elements. </para>
        <para>Recently, however, development teams for SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm have partnered
            to promote interoperability. Developers can now leverage SNOMED CT’s representation
            model for the building blocks of LOINC, and a new drug model in SNOMED CT facilitates
            extensions and consistency to RxNorm. Bodenreider et al. wrote about the recent
            collaboration: “while this evolution leads to greater compatibility and
            interoperability, integration of SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm still requires mappings
            among the three terminologies. Moreover, these three terminologies use different
            formalisms and tools for their representation, have their own release cycles and
            versioning mechanisms, which makes their seamless integration non trivial, if at all
            possible.” </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Solor</title>
        <para>Solor integrates the content from its native format into a common Solor format. Once
            the content is in Solor, there is a step where equivalency is determined through various
            methods where concepts of the same idea are aggregated. For example, Gentamycin from
            SNOMED is the same as Gentamycin from LOINC, and is also the same Gentamycin from
            RxNorm. The end result from this process is the creation of a Solor concept that is
            devoid of any source information (but will have traceability). This end result is what
            will be exposed to the user to view and use. In the Gentamycin example, a user will find
            this concept that is devoid of any source information and will not need to know if this
            is the SNOMED/LOINC/RxNorm Gentamycin that needs to be selected. Solor concepts are
            identified using a Universally Unique Identifier (UUID).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Interoperability by Mapping</title>
        <para>Today's health care terminology standards encompass methods, terminologies, and
            specifications for the exchange, storage, and retrieval of information associated with
            health care systems. These standards contain terminologies and concepts that are used in
            medical records to describe patient symptoms, lab results, prescription medications,
            etc. In today's health care industry, the standard approach to integrating multiple
            disparate health data sources is to conduct mapping, a manual process that attempts to
            associate data to different systems for exchanging patient information and other data.
            Mapping, while pragmatically actionable, is prone to information loss and errors.</para>
        <para>Preserving the meaning of information when exchanging electronic health record data
            (i.e., semantic interoperability) is critical for delivering safe patient care and
            leveraging standards-based clinical decision support. Given that individuals often
            receive health care from more than one health system, integration of data from multiple
            sources is needed to ‘view’ a patient’s complete health record and avoid erroneous
            clinical decisions based on incomplete or inaccurate information, such as decisions that
            lead to performing unnecessary tests or giving a patient a drug to which they are known
            to be allergic. To date, the strategy for achieving semantic interoperability between
            the clinical systems of the Department of Defense (DoD) and the Veterans Administration
            (VA) has been to ‘map’ millions of data elements used in the respective EHRs to standard
            terminologies (e.g., SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm). However, ‘round trip testing’ of the
            mapped concepts has identified problems with the quality of the mappings for
            bidirectional use. New strategies are required to achieve semantic interoperability to
            support safe patient care, both before and after the two organizations start using a
            single vendor for their electronic health record systems. The use of logical definitions
            and terminology system extensions to manage concepts used in the delivery of care can
            overcome key challenges with the mapping strategy.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Mapping is Operational, but Incomplete</title>
            <para>Despite the fact that mapping is plagued by challenges (e.g., being out of date,
                not scalable, inconsistent, overly complex, incoherent, unstandardized), it still
                serves an operational need. Current data standards hinder true interoperability, so
                mapping allows disparate organizations to share and use at least some of their
                clinical data across health systems. In this section, we will highlight some of the
                immediate benefits that mapping provides from an operational perspective.
                Subsequently, we will discuss the challenges associated with mapping. These
                challenges may ultimately compromise patient safety and clinical decisions. </para>
            <para>Here’s how terminology mapping accomplishes partial interoperability at the
                semantic level <citation>HL</citation>:<orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Makes Data Exchange Possible</emphasis>:
                            Terminology mapping enables semantic interoperability, helping the
                            healthcare sector reach the objective of fluent machine-to-machine
                            communication. This function lets IT systems, such as EHRs, map
                            different terms to a shared semantics, or meaning.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Provides a Trusted Source</emphasis>: Adopts a
                            unified approach for managing terminology so that a single source of
                            terminology can be leveraged across health systems. Mapping can help
                            achieve a partially normalized data set that allows departmental systems
                            to operate.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Incorporates Terminology into
                                Applications</emphasis>: Terminology mapping also provides a method
                            for incorporating standard clinical terminology within healthcare apps,
                            thereby promoting semantic interoperability among organizations.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Manages a Range of Terminology Value
                                Sets</emphasis>: A structured approach to mapping terminology can
                            help an organization monitor the multitude of groupers and value sets
                            that are required for use for different purposes. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Challenges with Mapping</title>
            <para>The current lack of highly reliable, consistent, and complete semantic
                interoperability limits healthcare organizations’ ability to exchange information
                and pursue collaborative care. The standard approach to integrating multiple
                disparate health data sources is to conduct mapping, a manual process that
                is:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Out of date</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Not scalable using local terminology</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inconsistent and loses information at each transformation</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Unnecessarily complex and incoherent</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Lacking a standard approach and structure</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <section>
                <title>Summary of Solor white paper - "From retrospective mapping to prospective
                    standardization" </title>
                <para>Methods: To describe the current mapping approach, we reviewed reports
                    submitted by a consulting terminology expert who evaluated the process and
                    outcomes from the multi-year mapping efforts, summarized key features of the
                    mapping methods that threaten quality, and identified examples to illustrate
                    mapping challenges. To describe the new approach, we explain the strategy for
                    representing concepts required for interoperability, internal use, or
                    integration of historical data, and we present basic models for representing
                    concepts and managing requests for new concepts. Finally, we applied the new
                    approach to the problems identified from the mapping strategy and discussed
                    strengths and limitations.<citation>MappingPaper</citation>
                </para>
                <para>Results: A major threat to quality concerned the requirement that local source
                    terms be mapped to a single standardized terminology element; no creation of
                    logical expressions was allowed to represent target concepts. The quality of the
                    mappings were also impacted by incomplete and different mapping rules used by
                    the two organizations. Ongoing resources are required to assess and maintain
                    mappings over time. <citation>MappingPaper</citation>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example of Challenges due to Mapping</title>
                <para>Mapping is an approach to share data; unfortunately, mapping at each step in
                    the data exchange process creates additional opportunities for error and for
                    loss of information that may lead to a patient’s harm. SNOMED CT and other
                    meaningful use standards are frequently used as targets of this mapping, and
                    their use is mandated as part of the Meaningful Use regulations. Tables 1 and 2
                    below show how equivalent concepts in two different care settings leads to
                    information loss when they are mapped to SNOMED CT because SNOMED CT does not
                    represent the equivalent meaning. In Tables 1 and 2, the Local Concept column
                    represents the concept created by Hospital A during the care of a patient, the
                    Map Type column specifies broader than or narrower than or equivalent, and the
                    SNOMED CT Concept column represents the concept to which the local concept has
                    been mapped. The Meaning Lost column describes the information lost due to
                    mapping because an equivalent match of the local concept is not found in SNOMED
                    CT. In Table 1 below, the SNOMED CT Concept is broader than the local concept,
                    causing important tumor morphology information to be lost during mapping. In
                    Table 2, the SNOMED CT Concept is also broader than the local concept, causing
                    important tumor location information to be lost in the mapping process.</para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Mapping.png" scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Solor Solution</title>
            <para>What’s needed is a semantically normalized information model (i.e., Solor) with an
                appropriate separation of concerns in regard to the informatics architectural
                layers. Such a model is critical for the success of a number of forward-thinking
                healthcare initiatives. Solor does not map one terminology system to another.
                Rather, Solor integrates specific terminologies such as – but not limited to –
                SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm. These three terminologies form the foundation of Solor
                because they are meaningful use standards, where when integrated together, they
                represent the breadth of information necessary for clinical data
                representation.</para>
            <para>The new approach to data integration involves the use of description logic to
                model and manage concepts from standard terminologies to support clinical care.
                Instead of mapping an existing local code or term to a standard code with the goal
                of creating semantic equivalence, challenges created by mapping were avoided by
                directly representing concepts using standard codes or logical expressions that
                conform to a description logic model. We described the strategy for representing
                ‘things’ (i.e. meanings) about patient care using existing single SNOMED, LOINC, and
                RxNorm concepts, computable logical expressions based on SNOMED CT, LOINC, or RxNorm
                that are added to extensions managed by an organization, organization specific
                identifiers to support specific local needs, and by adding ‘names’ (i.e., new
                dialect-specific synonyms) to already-existing ‘things’. Finally, ‘alternate
                identifiers’ for SNOMED, LOINC or RxNorm concepts are useful for integrating
                historical data so source terms (linked to alternative identifiers) are accurately
                represented using standard concepts defined using description logic.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Design Features - Understandable, Reproducible and Useful</title>
                <para>Content in Solor aims to adhere to design features for concept
                    validity:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Understandable: The meaning of a concept can be understood, without
                            reference to private or inaccessible information.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Reproducible: Multiple users can apply the concept to the same
                            situations.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Useful: The concept has a practical value to users that is
                            self-evident or can be readily explained.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Licensing and Solor</title>
                <para>Solor is not intended to compete with existing standards and processes, and
                    does not redistribute content. It enables the community of Solor to integrate
                    terminologies – their own terminology and others’ terminology. Those who are
                    distributing terminology must have a license to distribute these terminologies.
                    For example: If organization A is distributing SNOMED CT, LOINC and its curated
                    terminology, then organization A needs to ensure it has a license to
                    redistribute SNOMED CT and LOINC. Solor’s transformation processes and
                    architectural foundation are available under the Apache 2 Open Source License. </para>
                <para>SNOMED CT, LOINC and RXNorm are foundational terminologies in Solor. Solor
                    fully supports and relies on these standards and their organizations. Solor’s
                    intent is to complement these standards. Organizations are free to integrate
                    Solor content into their standards.</para>
                <section>
                    <title>LOINC License</title>
                    <para>The LOINC database can be obtained from the Regenstrief LOINC website
                            (<link xlink:href="http://www.regenstrief.org/loinc/"
                            >http://www.regenstrief.org/loinc/</link>), as a PDF report sorted
                        alphabetically by class, as a tab-delimited ASCII text file, and/or as an
                        Access database. The LOINC database and associated documents and programs
                        are copyrighted, but the copyright permits all commercial and noncommercial
                        uses in perpetuity at no cost. If the LOINC database or its contents are
                        distributed as a database, such distributions must include all parts of the
                        formal LOINC term, the LOINC short name, the LOINC code, the deprecated
                        flag, and the copyright. The copyright notice is needed to prevent variants,
                        which would defeat the purpose of this standard. No such notice is required
                        when LOINC codes are used in messages to report test results.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>SNOMED CT License</title>
                    <para>Use of SNOMED CT is subject to the SNOMED International Affiliate license
                        provisions and is free in Member territories including the United States, in
                        low income countries, and for Qualifying Research Projects in any country.
                        To learn more, please see the SNOMED CT and Licensing page. Users should
                        carefully read the license agreement before re-distributing any content in
                        any type of application as there may be additional restrictions, permissions
                        or copyright considerations imposed by the content providers. Users must
                        contact the vocabulary content providers regarding any use that is not
                        covered by the license. The content providers may charge fees for these
                        additional uses of their content. Appendix 1 of the license agreement lists
                        contact information for each content provider. The SNOMED CT® Affiliate
                        License Agreement is included as Appendix 2 of the UMLS Metathesaurus
                        License and outlines possible costs. NLM is a member of SNOMED International
                        and there is no charge for SNOMED CT use in the United States and other
                        Member territories. For information about fees in non-member countries, see
                        the SNOMED International website.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T211931-0500" comment="How does this relate to the SNOMED CT Integration efforts?
"?>
        <title>Solor Integration - Integrating LOINC Method Attributes and SNOMED CT
            Concepts<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
        <para>The collaborative agreement between LOINC and SNOMED CT developers has enabled
            informaticists to leverage SNOMED CT for the representation of the building blocks of
            LOINC (e.g., method) and for a more consistent representation of clinical and laboratory
            observations in SNOMED CT. We utilized the derivative works from this collaborative
            effort to represent LOINC and SNOMED CT in Solor, an open-source ecosystem for
            integrating disparate medical terminologies in a common model. </para>
        <para>Seamless integration of LOINC and SNOMED CT is non-trivial because LOINC and SNOMED CT
            have different semantics models, and use different formalisms and tools for their
            representation, have separate release cycles, and different versioning mechanisms.
            Furthermore, the initial collaboration between LOINC and SNOMED CT provided equivalent
            concepts between LOINC laboratory concepts and SNOMED CT concepts but did not include
            many clinical concepts from LOINC. In this work, our objectives are: (1) to assess the
            extent to which LOINC method attributes can be represented by concepts in SNOMED CT, (2)
            to describe how to integrate equivalent LOINC method attributes and SNOMED CT concepts
            in the Solor common model, and (3) to explore the benefits and challenges of integrating
            LOINC and SNOMED CT in the Solor common model. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Methods:</emphasis> We sought to identify the overlaps and gaps
            between method attributes in LOINC and concepts in SNOMED CT, and integrated the
            equivalent concepts in Solor – an integrated common model for medical terminologies.
            First, we gathered the list of method attributes from LOINC version 2.63 and mapped each
            to a concept unique identifier (CUI) from the UMLS (using the UMLS API). For CUIs
            representing a LOINC method attribute, we retrieved associated atoms from SNOMED CT in
            the
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T125835-0600" comment="Is this correct?  What is UMLS.2?  Is it supposed to be a reference?" flag="done"?>UMLS.
                <citation>Cholan_NLM</citation><?oxy_comment_end?>Next, we imported each LOINC
            identifier and attached description logic defining whether there was equivalency of the
            method attribute to SNOMED CT concepts. When there was an overlap, a Solor-navigation
            concept was created which facilitated an inferred taxonomy representation with semantic
            context from SNOMED CT attached to the right LOINC method attribute. Finally, we
            evaluated the alignments obtained between LOINC method attributes and SNOMED CT concepts
            to determine what method attributes in LOINC were not covered by concepts in SNOMED CT. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Results: </emphasis><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis
                    role="underline">Semantic profile of LOINC method
                attributes</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> –</emphasis> The method
            axis of LOINC is used to specify methods used for particular clinical observations and
            measurements. The distribution of the most prevalent semantic groups found in LOINC
            method attributes include procedures (58%), concepts/ideas (14%), living beings (13%),
            occupations (8%), and disorders (2%). Whereas, SNOMED CT concepts represent disorders
            (22%), procedures (17%), body structures (11%), clinical findings other than disorders
            (10%), and organisms (10%).<citation>Bodenreider_Solor</citation>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T130256-0600" comment="Is this supposed to be a reference?" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?></para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">Coverage of LOINC method attributes
                    by the UMLS and SNOMED CT</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> –
            </emphasis>Of the 1702 LOINC methods, 1688 (99%) were mapped to a UMLS CUI. Sampling the
            1% not mapped implies provisional codes added to a LOINC version update that were not
            yet added to the UMLS version release. We computed the coverage of LOINC method
            attributes by SNOMED CT by analyzing the count of LOINC method attributes that shared at
            least 1 UMLS CUI with a corresponding SNOMED CT concept. Of the 1688 CUIs that
            represented LOINC method attributes, 383 (23%) were associated with a SNOMED CT
            concept.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">Solor
                Transformation</emphasis></emphasis> –Solor is an ecosystem that allows users to
            import, transform, view, and export content from disparate medical terminologies, all in
            one common model. Users can navigate and search Solor content, view details of the data
            elements, and select specific concepts to view more information. Solor has two
            fundamental building blocks: concepts and semantics. A concept is defined as an idea or
            a general notion and is represented by a universally unique identifier (UUID). A
            semantic is attached to a concept to provide contextual meaning and semantic data to the
            concept’s content. </para>
        <para> Integrating LOINC method attributes into Solor required a transformation process in
            which the LOINC data was transformed into Solor components using these defining
            relationships to create OWL EL++ description logic definitions. The LOINC identifier was
            used to create a Type 5 UUID for a Solor concept, so that the identifiers used in Solor
            are idempotent, and are derivable directly from the LOINC data. Additionally, the
            original LOINC identifier for this concept is properly represented, as are the other
            data elements required by the LOINC license. These Solor concepts integrate SNOMED CT
            and LOINC semantics; the LOINC Method semantic and SNOMED CT semantic are grouped under
            the same Solor concept. The
            f<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T131130-0600" comment="In the PDF, it&apos;s actually Figure 3.1.  Also, in the figure, while the SNOMED CT name is displayed, there isn&apos;t anything that states that.  Should there be?" flag="done"?>igure
            <?oxy_comment_end?>below exemplifies the integration: the LOINC method attribute is
            “AUDIT”, and the SNOMED CT concept is displayed as “Alcohol use disorders identification
            test”.</para>
        <figure>
            <title><emphasis role="bold">Solor Editor: Representation of LOINC and SNOMED CT in a
                    common model</emphasis></title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/Komet_LOINC_Int.png" scalefit="1" width="100%"
                        contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Conclusion</emphasis>: LOINC method attributes include concepts
            ranging from procedures, administrative concepts, occupations, and a small number of
            disorders and phenomena. Only about 23% of LOINC method attributes can be directly
            represented by a SNOMED CT concept. The overall interoperability between LOINC method
            attributes and SNOMED CT concepts was limited at best. Interestingly, there were a
            number of procedures and specimen source details in LOINC method attributes with little
            or no coverage by SNOMED CT. One suggestion is for developers of LOINC and SNOMED CT to
            review these gaps and include better coverage in future versions, if appropriate. </para>
        <para>Solor may assist in providing a collaborative ecosystem to host local extensions for
            SNOMED CT to represent LOINC method attributes. Currently, implementers of LOINC and
            SNOMED CT must traverse the distinct hierarchies of each source terminology and version.
            Integrating the terminology content of LOINC and SNOMED CT into the Solor common model
            may have a beneficial impact on the usability (i.e., reduced burden) for implementers in
            both traversing distinct formalisms and maintaining version control. It may be helpful
            to communicate more specific details about LOINC method attributes by leveraging the
            right SNOMED CT concepts for additional details about the method attributes. Next steps
            include conducting a formative evaluation with a purposive sample of experts in standard
            clinical terminologies to assess the benefits and challenges of integrating and
            representing overlapping LOINC and SNOMED CT content in Solor’s common model. We aim to
            have this evaluation completed by Summer 2019 and will include these updated results if
            accepted. Solor’s integration of disparate medical terminology content may help
            implementers and authors of medical terminologies with orienting concepts and traversing
            relationships between disparate standards. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Evaluating the impact of implementing Solor</title>
        <para>Electronic clinical quality measures (eCQMs) and clinical decision support (CDS)
            alerts are triggered by clinical data that is encoded by standards based clinical
            terminologies. Because these measures and alerts intend to promote evidence-based
            clinical processes, variations in data caused by having inaccurate or antiquated
            implementations of underlying terminology standards may impact the ability of clinicians
            to assess care and improve quality. Jean-Jacques et al. showed that health information
            technology-supported quality improvement (QI) initiatives can decrease disparities for
            some chronic disease management and preventive measures <citation>QI</citation>.
            Data-driven QI efforts rely heavily on patient-level data generated by eCQM reports or
            CDS alerts, which are dependent upon standards-based encoded EHR data. If clinicians
            rely on inaccurate implementations of eCQMs and CDS, then they may have lists/alerts
            with patients intended to be excluded from a measure/alert, and may therefore, target
            inappropriate patients for therapies, such as recommending aspirin use for someone at
            high-risk for a fatal bleeding event. Furthermore, their lists/alerts will not include
            the
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T135639-0600" comment="I didn&apos;t make the connection of how newly added patients can lead to inaccurate results or recommendations." id="bsj_b4d_vhb" flag="done" mid="16"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190521T163713-0400" comment="This is explained below in the paragraph with Number-needed-to-treat statistics. If this needs additional clarification I can add text here. " parentID="bsj_b4d_vhb" flag="done" mid="17"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T133425-0600" comment="Okay." flag="done"?>newly
            added patients
            <?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="17"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="16"?>who may need
            certain therapies to improve outcomes. Having accurate eCQMs/CDS may translate into
            potential lives saved, and avoidable harms. Furthermore, the comparability of clinical
            quality performance scores between healthcare organizations is negatively impacted by
            the vast variation in standards-based terminology implementations. Value-based payment
            programs rely on standardized implementations of standards-based data that generate eCQM
            data to be able to benchmark scores effectively, and administer value-based payments
            accordingly. In the current ecosystem, eCQM data and their underlying standards-based
            encoded clinical data may not be implemented in a standardized way, and therefore the
            ability to increase value, and enhance population health, may be hindered. </para>
        <para>For official eCQMs endorsed by CMS, regular updates occur at least annually, and
            sometimes two to three times per year. These updates to eCQM definitions may result in
            changes to measure logic or to the official sets of included and excluded codes in the
            standards-based terminologies (i.e. value set vocabularies). In previous work, we found
            that clinics often lag behind in implementing the most updated, and accurate, versions
            of official eCQM as outlined by value set specifications. When older and newer versions
            of eCQMs were implemented against the same clinical data, we found changes in
            measurement of quality of up to 5% difference in overall performance score, and up to
            28% difference in the number of patients included in a measure’s denominator.
                <citation>Cholan_shift</citation> Similarly, in other work, we showed that
            implementations of the same eCQM using distinct value set specifications also led to
            variations in the calculated prevalence of patients at risk for key conditions, and in
            some cases led to variations in CQM performance
                percentages.<citation>concepts</citation>
        </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Proposed Study to Evaluate the Impact
                    of Solor</emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Purpose</emphasis></para>
        <para>Solor provides an easier way to verify that value sets are up to date and covered.
            Solor can also suggest and add additional codes based on Solor concepts to value set
            specifications. In this study, our objective is to use Solor to identify codes from eCQM
            value sets, to better understand the usage of these codes against clinical data, and to
            assess the impact of the pre and post Solor codes on eCQM performance. </para>
        <para/>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Methods</emphasis></para>
        <para>First, we will identify differences in the coverage of vocabulary specifications –
            unique identifiers, concepts, code groups, and coding systems – between what is covered
            in VSAC value sets and what is intended to be covered in value sets according to Solor
            to define global concepts in measures. After this, we will query clinical data at xxx to
            determine the frequency of patients for whom the new Solor codes are used. Finally, we
            will implement the measures in a quality measure calculation registry and CDS
            environment to estimate the performance differences before and after Solor’s mapping of
            non-covered value set codes. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Evaluation</emphasis></para>
        <para>We will compute the frequency of patients who use any of the codes contained in CQM
            value sets, stratified by measure. We will compare the change in frequencies before and
            after Solor’s addition of equivalent codes. We will use Fisher’s exact test to compare
            aggregate-CQM performance rates between the original versions of measures and the
            versions of measures after Solor value sets are implemented. We will use the Jaccard
            similarity index to assess the similarity between the patients included in the original
            versions of the measures, and the versions including complete value set coverage. Number
            Needed to Treat and Number Needed to Harm Statistics can be used to calculate the
            potential harms avoided, and harms causes based on pre and post Solor encoded data. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Goals</emphasis></para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Assess VSAC value sets before and after the use of Solor.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Understand the frequency of patients that are impacted by newly added Solor
                    value set concepts. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Understand how increasing value set code coverage impacts CQM performance
                    estimates, and the patients included in measure populations, and implications on
                    population health. </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="underline">Example Results</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                    role="underline">s</emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T212054-0500" comment="Convert to SVG?
"?>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/NNT.png" scale="50"/><?oxy_comment_end?>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
        <para> Assuming that the Solor value set specifications of a measure represent “perfect”
            inclusion, then every newly included patient can be thought of as needing the
            evidence-based therapy (such as aspirin for secondary prevention of heart attacks) in
            order to avoid bad outcomes. Under the same assumption, every dropped patient between
            value set versions of a measure can be thought of as avoiding potential harm caused by
            the promoted therapy. For aspirin use, Number-Needed-to- Treat (NNT) statistics show
            that of patients with known cardiovascular risk who took aspirin, 1.3% were helped by
            preventing a non-fatal heart attack, and 0.25% were harmed by a major bleeding
                event.<citation>Aspirin</citation>, <citation>antiplatelet</citation> In the Cholan
            et al study <citation>Cholan_shift</citation>, 121 (92%) of the patients dropped in the
            Solor version of the Aspirin measure were also taking an anticoagulant medication, so
            the Number-Needed-to-Harm (NNH) statistic for this subset of patients is likely much
            higher, and for these clinics, 1 to 2 people may have been harmed if the pre-Solor
            definition persisted, as Hansen et. al showed that patients with combinations of
            aspirin, warfarin, and clopidogrel are associated with up to a three-fold higher risk of
            bleeding for patients on dual therapy and triple therapy.<citation>Hansen</citation>
            With another measure for statin therapy, 1 in 21 people have a repeat heart attack,
            stroke or death avoided, so even 10 missed people have significant risk of events.
            Similarly, 10% are harmed by muscle damage or pain, or ~1 of the 14 inappropriately
                included.<citation>efficacy</citation> Even in this small study, failure to include
            or exclude patients could have led to real harm. With eCQM implementation and QI
            infrastructure increasing, the problem of having, and using, antiquated CQM versions of
            value sets could have significant potential negative impact on population health by not
            avoiding events, and avoiding harms for patients.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
