<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Concepts and Codes</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>The scope of content covered in terminologies varies from focusing on a very specific
            domain to covering multiple domains.  The main terminologies supported in Solor (SNOMED
            CT, LOINC, and RxNorm) all follow very structured and persistent code practices.  They
            never delete codes but in some cases (RxNorm) they are moved to a separate table.  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>SNOMED CT Concepts</title>
        <para>SNOMED CT concepts span multiple domains, from findings and disorders to procedures
            and pharmaceutical and biological products.  SNOMED CT concepts exist at multiple levels
            of granularity and mechanisms exist to add missing content to ensure that information is
            coded at the most granular level possible.  SNOMED CT Concepts are identified with a 6
            to 18 digit integer that has some structure that describes where the identifier
            originated (the original creator of the identifier) and what type of identifier it is.  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>LOINC Codes</title>
        <para>LOINC codes are used to identify laboratory and clinical measurements, observations
            and documents.  Each named concept in LOINC is given a LOINC code which has no structure
            other than a check digit appended to the end.  In addition, all of the components that
            make up the LOINC name are assigned LOINC Part Codes (LP) to them in the LOINC Database.
            LOINC Parts do not follow the same policies and maintenance practices as LOINC terms and
            are not intended to be used as a standalone terminology.  Some LOINC codes are also
            associated with answers (LA) and answer lists (LL) in the LOINC Database.  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>RxNorm</title>
        <para>RxNorm provides normalized clinical drug names and relationships between those names
            and common drug vocabularies for the purpose of easing the exchange of clinical drug
            information between systems that use different drug vocabularies.  Every concept in
            RxNorm is given a unique RXCUI.  The names and codes from the common drug vocabularies
            are then linked to that RXCUI.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Solor</title>
        <para>Solor integrates the content from its native format into a common Solor format.  Once
            the content is in Solor, there is a step where equivalency is determined through various
            methods where concepts of the same idea are aggregated. For example, Gentamycin from
            SNOMED is the same as Gentamycin from LOINC, and is also the same Gentamycin from
            RxNorm. The end result from this process is the creation of a Solor concept that is
            devoid of any source information (but will have traceability). This end result is what
            will be exposed to the user to view and use. In the Gentamycin example, a user will find
            this concept that is devoid of any source information and will not need to know if this
            is the SNOMED/LOINC/RxNorm Gentamycin that needs to be selected.  Solor concepts are
            identified using a Univerally Unique Identifier (UUID).</para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>

