<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Concepts and Codes</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Terminology systems are increasingly critical components for achieving
            interoperability across applications in the healthcare domain.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T131526-0600" comment="I recommend moving this up so it&apos;s the 2nd sentence in this paragraph." flag="done"?>A
            standard terminology is one that has wide industry acceptance or
            use.<?oxy_comment_end?>The role of standard terminologies in achieving interoperability
            for the purposes of advancing patient care is well documented. Ideally, these clinical
            terminology standards intend to provide rules to allow for the exchange, integration,
            and management of electronic clinical information. The federal government recognizes the
            benefit of standard terminologies and promotes their development and use. The <emphasis
                role="italic">Federal Health IT Strategic Plan 2015-2020</emphasis> set a strategy
            to encourage consistent terminology standards implementation in Electronic Health
            Records (EHRs) and encourage use through federal payment policies. </para>
        <para>Standards are obtained from a variety of efforts, cover different domains of clinical
            and nonclinical content relevant to the EHR, and serve various purposes. Currently, no
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T131701-0600" comment="Recommend revising to &quot;single&quot; for readability purposes." flag="done"?>single<?oxy_comment_end?>
            terminology or classification system contains everything that is needed for the medical
            record. </para>
        <para>The scope of content covered in terminologies varies from focusing on a very specific
            domain to covering multiple domains. The main terminologies supported in Solor (i.e.,
            SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm) all follow very structured and persistent code practices.
            They never delete codes but in some cases (i.e., RxNorm) they are moved to a separate
            table. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>SNOMED CT Concepts</title>
        <para>Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine-Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT®) is a comprehensive
            clinical terminology, maintained by the International Health Terminology Standards
            Development Organization (IHTSDO) representing over 300,000 concepts including disorders
            (22%), procedures (17%), body structures (11%), clinical findings other than disorders
            (10%), and organisms (10%).</para>
        <para>SNOMED CT concepts span multiple domains, from findings and disorders to procedures
            and pharmaceutical and biological products. SNOMED CT concepts exist at multiple levels
            of granularity, and mechanisms exist to add missing content to ensure that information
            is coded at the most granular level possible. SNOMED CT concepts are identified with a
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T132125-0600" comment="Does this go against the desiderata of a meaningless identifer, as mentioned in the terminology-intro.xml section?  If yes, should it be acknowledged?" id="wvs_slw_lhb" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190418T125555-0400" comment="terminology-intro.xml is not rendered in the SIA pdf any longer so I do not think we need to address this. " parentID="wvs_slw_lhb" flag="done" mid="3"?>6-
            to 18-digit integer that has some structure that describes where the identifier
            originated (the original creator of the identifier) and what type of identifier it is.
            <?oxy_comment_end mid="3"?><?oxy_comment_end?></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T204727-0500" comment="Can we legally add examples here to the documentation?
"?>LOINC
            Codes</title><?oxy_comment_end?>
        <para>Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC®) is a terminology
            representing about 50,000 clinical and laboratory observations, health measurements, and
            documents, developed and maintained by the Regenstrief Institute.</para>
        <para>LOINC codes are used to identify laboratory and clinical measurements, observations
            and documents. Each named concept in LOINC is given a LOINC code which has no structure
            other than a check digit appended to the end. In addition, all of the components that
            make up the LOINC name are assigned LOINC Part Codes (LP) to them in the LOINC Database.
            LOINC Parts do not follow the same policies and maintenance practices as LOINC terms and
            are not intended to be used as a standalone terminology. Some LOINC codes are also
            associated with answers (LA) and answer lists (LL) in the LOINC Database. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>RxNorm</title>
        <para>RxNorm is a terminology for human clinical drugs in the U.S., representing drug
            properties such as ingredient, strength, and dose form, maintained by the National
            Library of Medicine (NLM) and distributed via the Unified Medical Language System
            (UMLS).</para>
        <para>RxNorm provides normalized clinical drug names and relationships between those names
            and common drug vocabularies for the purpose of easing the exchange of clinical drug
            information between systems that use different drug vocabularies.  Every concept in
            RxNorm is given a unique RXCUI.  The names and codes from the common drug vocabularies
            are then linked to that RXCUI.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>UMLS</title>
        <para>Terminology systems typically consist of the following elements: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Coded Concepts – the discrete units of knowledge managed within the
                    terminology. They typically consist of numeric codes and textual preferred
                    names, synonyms, and descriptions. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept Hierarchies – the logical organization of concepts into parent-child
                    and ancestor-descendant relationships that express the semantics of
                    generalization and specialization. The hierarchical organization of a
                    terminology may be explicitly expressed through stored parent-child and
                    ancestor-descendant links, or it may be implicitly expressed through the logical
                    definitions of individual concepts that a computer can use to infer parent-child
                    and ancestor-descendant relationships. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Value Sets – named lists of individual concepts that represent more abstract
                    categories useful in decision-support logic.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
                <para>New applications and new medical knowledge constantly call for expansion and
                    enhancement of existing terminologies. However, since terminology systems are
                    often non-static, incomplete and under specified, inconsistencies may be
                    introduced. </para>
                <para>While many of these challenges are related to terminology evolution, others
                    may be related to the design of the standard clinical terminologies themselves.
                    Cimino notably described the challenges of concept orientation, completeness,
                    correctness, currency, granularity, and redundancy when designing re-usable
                    medical terminologies. Today, 20 years later, a menagerie of inconsistent and
                    overlapping terminology models hinders efforts that try to store and analyze
                    encoded clinical data. Several efforts aim to assist. The National Library of
                    Medicine (NLM) integrates terms and codes from over 150 source vocabularies by
                    concept, attribute, and meaning in the Unified Medical Language System ® (UMLS)
                    Metathesaurus. The NLM, also, in collaboration with the Office of the National
                    Coordinator for Health Information Technology and Centers for Medicare &amp;
                    Medicaid Services, hosts the Value Set Authority Center (VSAC). The VSAC aims to
                    provide lists of values, codes, and names (i.e., value sets) from standard
                    clinical terminologies to represent clinical concepts. </para>
                <para>These tools, while helpful, have gaps.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T141242-0600" comment="Did you want to include a link to this reference?  Same for all citations in this paragraph." id="syq_1mw_lhb" mid="6"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190418T125814-0400" comment="Proper documentation of references needs to be an overarching task that is done for the entire SIA book. " parentID="syq_1mw_lhb"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T124300-0600" comment="Okay, thanks." mid="7"?>Raje
            et al.
            <?oxy_comment_end mid="7"?><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="6"?>highlighted
            issues with completeness, correctness, and redundancy when they found gaps in the UMLS
            Metathesaurus’ coverage of disease concepts. Similarly, Winnenburg et al. highlighted
            duplicate value sets in the VSAC, and showed that 19% of value sets in 2011 contained
            invalid codes. In subsequent work, they highlighted issues related to granularity by
            evaluating over 1,000 value sets and found that value sets varied vastly in size with
            some only containing one code, while other value sets included over 20,000 codes.
            Similarly, Bahr et al. showed issues with concept orientation by analyzing medication
            value sets and found extraneous and missing ingredients in both the value sets and drug
            classes. </para>
                <para>These issues related to integrating clinical content have a direct impact on
            patient safety and point to the need to be able to consistently represent and encode
            clinical data and observations. Therefore, quality assurance is an indispensable part of
            the terminology management lifecycle. A central limitation of integrating controlled
            medical terminologies is that they often lack any formal model to denote the
            relationships among constituent data elements. </para>
                <para>Recently, however, development teams for SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm have
                    partnered to promote interoperability. Developers can now leverage SNOMED CT’s
                    representation model for the building blocks of LOINC, and a new drug model in
                    SNOMED CT facilitates extensions and consistency to RxNorm. Bodenreider et al.
                    wrote about the recent collaboration: “while this evolution leads to greater
                    compatibility and interoperability, integration of SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm
                    still requires mappings among the three terminologies. Moreover, these three
                    terminologies use different formalisms and tools for their representation, have
                    their own release cycles and versioning mechanisms, which makes their seamless
                    integration non trivial, if at all possible.” </para>
          
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Solor</title>
        <para>Solor integrates the content from its native format into a common Solor format.  Once
            the content is in Solor, there is a step where equivalency is determined through various
            methods where concepts of the same idea are aggregated. For example, Gentamycin from
            SNOMED is the same as Gentamycin from LOINC, and is also the same Gentamycin from
            RxNorm. The end result from this process is the creation of a Solor concept that is
            devoid of any source information (but will have traceability). This end result is what
            will be exposed to the user to view and use. In the Gentamycin example, a user will find
            this concept that is devoid of any source information and will not need to know if this
            is the SNOMED/LOINC/RxNorm Gentamycin that needs to be selected.  Solor concepts are
            identified using a Univerally Unique Identifier (UUID).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T211931-0500" comment="How does this relate to the SNOMED CT Integration efforts?
"?>
        <title>Solor Integration - Integrating LOINC Method Attributes and SNOMED CT
            Concepts<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
        <para>The collaborative agreement between LOINC and SNOMED CT developers has enabled
            informaticists to leverage SNOMED CT for the representation of the building blocks of
            LOINC (e.g., method) and for a more consistent representation of clinical and laboratory
            observations in SNOMED CT. We utilized the derivative works from this collaborative
            effort to represent LOINC and SNOMED CT in Solor, an open-source ecosystem for
            integrating disparate medical terminologies in a common model. </para>
        <para>Seamless integration of LOINC and SNOMED CT is non-trivial because LOINC and SNOMED CT
            have different semantics models, and use different formalisms and tools for their
            representation, have separate release cycles, and different versioning mechanisms.
            Furthermore, the initial collaboration between LOINC and SNOMED CT provided equivalent
            concepts between LOINC laboratory concepts and SNOMED CT concepts but did not include
            many clinical concepts from LOINC. In this work, our objectives are: (1) to assess the
            extent to which LOINC method attributes can be represented by concepts in SNOMED CT, (2)
            to describe how to integrate equivalent LOINC method attributes and SNOMED CT concepts
            in the Solor common model, and (3) to explore the benefits and challenges of integrating
            LOINC and SNOMED CT in the Solor common model. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Methods:</emphasis> We sought to identify the overlaps and gaps
            between method attributes in LOINC and concepts in SNOMED CT, and integrated the
            equivalent concepts in Solor – an integrated common model for medical terminologies.
            First, we gathered the list of method attributes from LOINC version 2.63 and mapped each
            to a concept unique identifier (CUI) from the UMLS (using the UMLS API). For CUIs
            representing a LOINC method attribute, we retrieved associated atoms from SNOMED CT in
            the
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T125835-0600" comment="Is this correct?  What is UMLS.2?  Is it supposed to be a reference?"?>UMLS.2
            <?oxy_comment_end?>Next, we imported each LOINC identifier and attached description
            logic defining whether there was equivalency of the method attribute to SNOMED CT
            concepts. When there was an overlap, a Solor-navigation concept was created which
            facilitated an inferred taxonomy representation with semantic context from SNOMED CT
            attached to the right LOINC method attribute. Finally, we evaluated the alignments
            obtained between LOINC method attributes and SNOMED CT concepts to determine what method
            attributes in LOINC were not covered by concepts in SNOMED CT. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Results: </emphasis><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis
                    role="underline">Semantic profile of LOINC method
                attributes</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> –</emphasis> The method
            axis of LOINC is used to specify methods used for particular clinical observations and
            measurements. The distribution of the most prevalent semantic groups found in LOINC
            method attributes include procedures (58%), concepts/ideas (14%), living beings (13%),
            occupations (8%), and disorders (2%). Whereas, SNOMED CT concepts represent disorders
            (22%), procedures (17%), body structures (11%), clinical findings other than disorders
            (10%), and organisms
            (10%).<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T130256-0600" comment="Is this supposed to be a reference?"?>1<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">Coverage of LOINC method attributes
                    by the UMLS and SNOMED CT</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> –
            </emphasis>Of the 1702 LOINC methods, 1688 (99%) were mapped to a UMLS CUI. Sampling the
            1% not mapped implies provisional codes added to a LOINC version update that were not
            yet added to the UMLS version release. We computed the coverage of LOINC method
            attributes by SNOMED CT by analyzing the count of LOINC method attributes that shared at
            least 1 UMLS CUI with a corresponding SNOMED CT concept. Of the 1688 CUIs that
            represented LOINC method attributes, 383 (23%) were associated with a SNOMED CT
            concept.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">Solor
                Transformation</emphasis></emphasis> –Solor is an ecosystem that allows users to
            import, transform, view, and export content from disparate medical terminologies, all in
            one common model. Users can navigate and search Solor content, view details of the data
            elements, and select specific concepts to view more information. Solor has two
            fundamental building blocks: concepts and semantics. A concept is defined as an idea or
            a general notion and is represented by a universally unique identifier (UUID). A
            semantic is attached to a concept to provide contextual meaning and semantic data to the
            concept’s content. </para>
        <para> Integrating LOINC method attributes into Solor required a transformation process in
            which the LOINC data was transformed into Solor components using these defining
            relationships to create OWL EL++ description logic definitions. The LOINC identifier was
            used to create a Type 5 UUID for a Solor concept, so that the identifiers used in Solor
            are idempotent, and are derivable directly from the LOINC data. Additionally, the
            original LOINC identifier for this concept is properly represented, as are the other
            data elements required by the LOINC license. These Solor concepts integrate SNOMED CT
            and LOINC semantics; the LOINC Method semantic and SNOMED CT semantic are grouped under
            the same Solor concept.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T131130-0600" comment="In the PDF, it&apos;s actually Figure 3.1.  Also, in the figure, while the SNOMED CT name is displayed, there isn&apos;t anything that states that.  Should there be?"?>Figure
            1<?oxy_comment_end?> exemplifies the integration: the LOINC method attribute is “AUDIT”,
            and the SNOMED CT concept is “Alcohol use disorders identification test”.</para>
        <figure>
            <title><emphasis role="bold">Solor Editor: Representation of LOINC and SNOMED CT in a
                    common model</emphasis></title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/Komet_LOINC_Int.png" scalefit="1" width="100%"
                        contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Conclusion</emphasis>: LOINC method attributes include concepts
            ranging from procedures, administrative concepts, occupations, and a small number of
            disorders and phenomena. Only about 23% of LOINC method attributes can be directly
            represented by a SNOMED CT concept. The overall interoperability between LOINC method
            attributes and SNOMED CT concepts was limited at best. Interestingly, there were a
            number of procedures and specimen source details in LOINC method attributes with little
            or no coverage by SNOMED CT. One suggestion is for developers of LOINC and SNOMED CT to
            review these gaps and include better coverage in future versions, if appropriate. </para>
        <para>Solor may assist in providing a collaborative ecosystem to host local extensions for
            SNOMED CT to represent LOINC method attributes. Currently, implementers of LOINC and
            SNOMED CT must traverse the distinct hierarchies of each source terminology and version.
            Integrating the terminology content of LOINC and SNOMED CT into the Solor common model
            may have a beneficial impact on the usability (i.e., reduced burden) for implementers in
            both traversing distinct formalisms and maintaining version control. It may be helpful
            to communicate more specific details about LOINC method attributes by leveraging the
            right SNOMED CT concepts for additional details about the method attributes. Next steps
            include conducting a formative evaluation with a purposive sample of experts in standard
            clinical terminologies to assess the benefits and challenges of integrating and
            representing overlapping LOINC and SNOMED CT content in Solor’s common model. We aim to
            have this evaluation completed by Summer 2019 and will include these updated results if
            accepted. Solor’s integration of disparate medical terminology content may help
            implementers and authors of medical terminologies with orienting concepts and traversing
            relationships between disparate standards. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Evaluating the impact of implementing Solor</title>
       
        <para>Electronic clinical quality measures (eCQMs) and clinical decision support (CDS)
            alerts are triggered by clinical data that is encoded by standards based clinical
            terminologies. Because these measures and alerts intend to promote evidence-based
            clinical processes, variations in data caused by having inaccurate or antiquated
            implementations of underlying terminology standards may impact the ability of clinicians
            to assess care and improve quality. Jean-Jacques et al. showed that health information
            technology-supported quality improvement (QI) initiatives can decrease disparities for
            some chronic disease management and preventive measures;(ref12_ms). Data-driven QI
            efforts rely heavily on patient-level data generated by eCQM reports or CDS alerts,
            which are dependent upon standards-based encoded EHR data. If clinicians rely on
            inaccurate implementations of eCQMs and CDS, then they may have lists/alerts with
            patients intended to be excluded from a measure/alert, and may therefore, target
            inappropriate patients for therapies, such as recommending aspirin use for someone at
            high-risk for a fatal bleeding event. Furthermore, their lists/alerts will not include
            the
            <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190508T135639-0600" comment="I didn&apos;t make the connection of how newly added patients can lead to inaccurate results or recommendations."?>newly
            added patients <?oxy_comment_end?>who may need certain therapies to improve outcomes.
            Having accurate eCQMs/CDS may translate into potential lives saved, and avoidable harms.
            Furthermore, the comparability of clinical quality performance scores between healthcare
            organizations is negatively impacted by the vast variation in standards-based
            terminology implementations. Value-based payment programs rely on standardized
            implementations of standards-based data that generate eCQM data to be able to benchmark
            scores effectively, and administer value-based payments accordingly. In the current
            ecosystem, eCQM data and their underlying standards-based encoded clinical data may not
            be implemented in a standardized way, and therefore the ability to increase value, and
            enhance population health, may be hindered. </para>
        <para>For official eCQMs endorsed by CMS, regular updates occur at least annually, and
            sometimes two to three times per year. These updates to eCQM definitions may result in
            changes to measure logic or to the official sets of included and excluded codes in the
            standards-based terminologies (i.e. value set vocabularies). In previous work, we found
            that clinics often lag behind in implementing the most updated, and accurate, versions
            of official eCQM as outlined by value set specifications. When older and newer versions
            of eCQMs were implemented against the same clinical data, we found changes in
            measurement of quality of up to 5% difference in overall performance score, and up to
            28% difference in the number of patients included in a measure’s denominator. (ref_ms10)
            Similarly, in other work, we showed that implementations of the same eCQM using distinct
            value set specifications also led to variations in the calculated prevalence of patients
            at risk for key conditions, and in some cases led to variations in CQM performance
            percentages.(ref_ms11)</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Proposed Study to Evaluate the Impact
                    of Solor</emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Purpose</emphasis></para>
        <para>Solor provides an easier way to verify that value sets are up to date and covered.
            Solor can also suggest and add additional codes based on Solor concepts to value set
            specifications. In this study, our objective is to use Solor to identify codes from eCQM
            value sets, to better understand the usage of these codes against clinical data, and to
            assess the impact of the pre and post Solor codes on eCQM performance. </para>
        <para/>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Methods</emphasis></para>
        <para>First, we will identify differences in the coverage of vocabulary specifications –
            unique identifiers, concepts, code groups, and coding systems – between what is covered
            in VSAC value sets and what is intended to be covered in value sets according to Solor
            to define global concepts in measures. After this, we will query clinical data at xxx to
            determine the frequency of patients for whom the new Solor codes are used. Finally, we
            will implement the measures in a quality measure calculation registry and CDS
            environment to estimate the performance differences before and after Solor’s mapping of
            non-covered value set codes. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Evaluation</emphasis></para>
        <para>We will compute the frequency of patients who use any of the codes contained in CQM
            value sets, stratified by measure. We will compare the change in frequencies before and
            after Solor’s addition of equivalent codes. We will use Fisher’s exact test to compare
            aggregate-CQM performance rates between the original versions of measures and the
            versions of measures after Solor value sets are implemented. We will use the Jaccard
            similarity index to assess the similarity between the patients included in the original
            versions of the measures, and the versions including complete value set coverage. Number
            Needed to Treat and Number Needed to Harm Statistics can be used to calculate the
            potential harms avoided, and harms causes based on pre and post Solor encoded data. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Goals</emphasis></para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Assess VSAC value sets before and after the use of Solor.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Understand the frequency of patients that are impacted by newly added Solor
                    value set concepts. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Understand how increasing value set code coverage impacts CQM performance
                    estimates, and the patients included in measure populations, and implications on
                    population health. </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="underline">Example Results</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                    role="underline">s</emphasis></emphasis></para>
               <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T212054-0500" comment="Convert to SVG?
"?>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/NNT.png" scale="50"/><?oxy_comment_end?>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
        <para> Assuming that the Solor value set specifications of a measure represent “perfect”
            inclusion, then every newly included patient can be thought of as needing the
            evidence-based therapy (such as aspirin for secondary prevention of heart attacks) in
            order to avoid bad outcomes. Under the same assumption, every dropped patient between
            value set versions of a measure can be thought of as avoiding potential harm caused by
            the promoted therapy. For aspirin use, Number-Needed-to- Treat (NNT) statistics show
            that of patients with known cardiovascular risk who took aspirin, 1.3% were helped by
            preventing a non-fatal heart attack, and 0.25% were harmed by a major bleeding
                event.<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5977609/#r26-2730131"
                xml:id="__tag_704405666">26</link>, <link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5977609/#r27-2730131"
                xml:id="__tag_704405665">27</link> In xxx study, 121 (92%) of the patients dropped
            in the Solor version of the Aspirin measure were also taking an anticoagulant
            medication, so the Number-Needed-to-Harm (NNH) statistic for this subset of patients is
            likely much higher, and for these clinics, 1 to 2 people may have been harmed if the
            pre-Solor definition persisted, as Hansen et. al showed that patients with combinations
            of aspirin, warfarin, and clopidogrel are associated with up to a three-fold higher risk
            of bleeding for patients on dual therapy and triple therapy.<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5977609/#r28-2730131"
                xml:id="__tag_703754501">28</link>With another measure for statin therapy, 1 in 21
            people have a repeat heart attack, stroke or death avoided, so even 10 missed people
            have significant risk of events. Similarly, 10% are harmed by muscle damage or pain, or
            ~1 of the 14 inappropriately included.<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5977609/#r29-2730131"
                xml:id="__tag_704405667">29</link> Even in this small study, failure to include or
            exclude patients could have led to real harm. With eCQM implementation and QI
            infrastructure increasing, the problem of having, and using, antiquated CQM versions of
            value sets could have significant potential negative impact on population health by not
            avoiding events, and avoiding harms for patients.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
