<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<glossary xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Terms Glossary</title>
    
    <glossentry xml:id="concept">
        <glossterm>concept</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A clinical idea</para><para>The concept of a broken femur bone</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="CONCEPT">
        <glossterm>Concept</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A clinical idea to which a unique SNOMED ConceptId has been
            assigned</para><para>Fracture of Femur (SNOMED ConceptID = 71620000)</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry xml:id="RELATIONSHIP">
        <glossterm>Relationship</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>An association between two Concepts </para><para>Fracture of Femur : Finding Site = Bone Structure of Femur
        </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry xml:id="CONCEPT_DEFINITION">
        <glossterm>Concept Definition</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A collection of Relationships that logically defines the
            meaning of a Concept in SNOMED</para><para>Fracture of Femur : IS-A = Injury of Thigh, Finding Site = Bone
                Structure of Femur, Morphology = Fracture</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry xml:id="PRE_COORDINATED_CONCEPT">
        <glossterm>Pre-coordinated concept</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A concept that is pre-defined as a Concept in
            SNOMED</para><para>Fracture of Femur (SNOMED ConceptID = 71620000) : IS-A = Injury
                of Thigh, Finding Site = Bone Structure of Femur, Morphology =
                Fracture</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry xml:id="EXPRESSION">
        <glossterm>Expression</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A collection of references to one or more Concepts used to
            express an instance of a clinical idea (i.e., in a particular
            patient)</para><para>An expression may consist of a single ConceptID
                or a large collection of related Concepts</para><para>Fracture of Femur </para><para> OR</para><para>Fracture of
                    Femur : Finding Site = Structure of Head of Femur : Laterality =
                    Left, Morphology = Spiral Fracture</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry xml:id="POST_COORDINATED_EXPRESSION">
        <glossterm>Post-coordinated Expression</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>An expression created to represent an instance of a clinical
            idea that does not exist as a pre-defined Concept in
            SNOMED</para><para>Fracture of Femur : Finding Site = Structure of Head of Femur :
                Laterality = Left, Morphology = Spiral
                Fracture</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry xml:id="REFINEMENT">
        <glossterm>Refinement</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The further specification or addition of Relationships to a
            predefined Concept to express a more specific concept</para><para><emphasis role="underline">Pre-defined Concept</emphasis>
                Fracture of Femur : IS-A = Injury of Thigh, Finding Site = Bone
                Structure of Femur, Morphology = Fracture</para><para><emphasis
                    role="underline">Refinement</emphasis> Fracture of Femur :
                    Finding Site = Structure of Head of Femur : Laterality = Left,
                    Morphology = Spiral Fracture, Severity = Severe</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    
    <glossentry xml:id="FOCUS_CONCEPT">
        <glossterm>Focus Concept</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The core concept that is refined in a post-coordinated
            expression</para><para>Fracture of Femur (SNOMED ConceptID = 71620000) </para><para>
                IN</para><para>Fracture of Femur : Finding Site = Structure of Head
                    of Femur : Laterality = Left, Morphology = Spiral Fracture, Severity
                    = Severe</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    
    <glossentry xml:id="SUBSUMPTION_TESTING">
        <glossterm>Subsumption Testing</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The logical determination of whether a concept (as represented
            by an Expression) is more specific than another concept (also
            represented by an Expression). If so, the more specific concept
            <emphasis>is subsumed by</emphasis> the more general concept,
            and the more general concept <emphasis>subsumes</emphasis> the more
            specific concept.</para><para>Fracture of Femur (see Concept Definition above)</para><para>
                SUBSUMES</para><para>Fracture : Finding Site = Structure of Head of
                    Femur : Laterality = Left, Morphology = Spiral
                    Fracture</para><para>(the head of the femur is a part of the femur,
                        and a spiral fracture is a kind of fracture)</para><para>Fracture of
                            Femur (see Concept Definition above)</para><para> DOES NOT
                                SUBSUME</para><para>Fracture : Finding Site = Bone Structure of
                                    Shaft of Fibula Morphology = Transverse Fracture</para><para>(the
                                        shaft of the fibula is not a part of the femur)</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    

    <glossentry  xml:id="EQUIVALENCE_TESTING">
        <glossterm>Equivalence Testing</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>
            The logical determination of whether a concept (as represented
            by an Expression) is exactly the same as another concept (also
            represented by an Expression). If so, the two concepts are
            <emphasis>equivalent.</emphasis>            
        </para>
            <para>Fracture of Femur (see Concept Definition above)</para><para>
                IS EQUIVALENT TO</para><para>Traumatic Injury : Finding Site = Bone
                    Structure of Femur Morphology = Fracture</para><para>Fracture of
                        Femur (see Concept Definition above)</para><para> IS NOT EQUIVALENT
                            TO</para><para>Traumatic Injury : Finding Site = Structure of Head
                                of Femur : Laterality = Left, Morphology = Spiral
                                Fracture</para><para>(the second concept is more specific than
                                    “Fracture of Femur”; although it is subsumed by it, it is not
                                    equivalent to it)</para>        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="PREDICATE_EXPRESSION">
        <glossterm>Predicate Expression</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>
            The Expression that is being tested as the <emphasis>more
                general </emphasis>concept in a subsumption test. This is
            typically the expression that appears in a query. <emphasis role="underline">Fracture of Femur</emphasis> in the
            subsumption tests above.
        </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry xml:id="CANDIDATE_EXPRESSION">
        <glossterm>Candidate Expression</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>
            The Expression that is being tested as the <emphasis>more
                specific </emphasis>concept in a subsumption test. This is
            typically the expression that appears in the patient
            record. The Post-coordinated Expressions in the subsumption tests
            above             
        </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="ISAAC">
        <glossterm>Informatics [Agile|Analytic] Architecture</glossterm>
        <acronym>ISAAC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The underlying architecture - which we call ISAAC - is a logical
                architecture, not an implementation. It describes the logical informatics
                architecture that will be reflected in the systems architecture of VHA clinical
                systems. In addition, it is an integrative architecture, which deliberately builds
                upon selected, compatible elements of its underlying components to build a coherent
                system. It builds primarily upon SNOMED CT, RxNORM, and LOINC by integrating their
                content and semantics, and normalizing the means to identify and version components,
                lexically search, logically define, semantically retrieve, and collaboratively
                extend.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="snomedctus">
        <glossterm>SNOMED CT-US extension</glossterm>
        <acronym>SNOMED CT-US</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Integrated SNOMED CT product, containing the US extension of terminology.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="snomedctusva">
        <glossterm>SNOMED CT-US-VA extension</glossterm>
        <acronym>SNOMED CT-US-VA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Integrated SNOMED CT product, containing the US extension as well as the
                terminology from the VA extension.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="lsb">
        <glossterm>SNOMED CT-US-VA extension</glossterm>
        <acronym>LSB</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_Standard_Base">Linux
                    Standard Base</link> (LSB) is a joint project by several Linux distributions
                under the organizational structure of the Linux Foundation to standardize the
                software system structure, including the filesystem hierarchy used in the Linux
                operating system. The LSB is based on the POSIX specification, the Single UNIX
                Specification (SUS), and several other open standards, but extends them in certain
                areas.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="npm">
        <glossterm>Node package manager</glossterm>
        <acronym>npm</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para><link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Npm_(software)">npm </link>is the
                default package manager for the JavaScript runtime environment Node.js.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="msa">
        <glossterm>MSA</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para><link xlink:href="https://smartbear.com/learn/api-design/what-are-microservices/"
                    >Microservice architecture</link> is a method of developing software
                applications as a suite of independently deployable, small, modular services in
                which each service runs a unique process and communicates through a well-defined,
                lightweight mechanism to serve a business goal.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="soa">
        <glossterm>SOA</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Service-oriented_architecture"
                    >service-oriented architecture</link> (SOA) is a style of software design where
                services are provided to the other components by application components, through a
                communication protocol over a network. The basic principles of service oriented
                architecture are independent of vendors, products and technologies.[1] A service is
                a discrete unit of functionality that can be accessed remotely and acted upon and
                updated independently, such as retrieving a credit card statement online.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="isaac">
        <glossterm>Informatics Standards Architecture ACceleration</glossterm>
        <acronym>ISAAC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para> The VA ISAAC (InformaticS Architecture ACceleration) effort seeks a holistic
                approach to architecture that supports novelty within a rigorous—and vertically
                integrated—deployment pipeline that enables knowledge engineers, developers,
                testers, build managers, and operations personnel to work together effectively to
                deliver assets to the points of care and analysis. This technology stack must
                support integrated delivery of iterative revisions of specifications, services, and
                content which are today delivered by isolated silo organizations who place the
                implementation burden upon their consumers. This pipeline will be built from
                existing software-based best practices, and will embrace DevOps culture and practice
                by emphasizing collaboration and communication while automating the process of
                product delivery. ISAAC will promote standards and clarify the interoperability of
                terminologies for the workbench and Opentooling framework.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="komet">
        <glossterm>KnOwledge Management EnvironmenT</glossterm>
        <acronym>KOMET</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para> The VA ISAAC’s KnOwledge Management EnvironmenT (KOMET) realizes the informatics
                architecture within a DevOps environment that integrates development, testing,
                publication, and delivery of specifications, content, and services into a vertically
                integrated environment that supports continuous delivery. </para>
            <glossseealso otherterm="isaac">ISAAC</glossseealso>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="solor">
        <glossterm>Semantic Operability using SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm </glossterm>
        <acronym>Solor</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A single comprehensive terminology structure, populated with normalized content
                from SNOMED CT, LOINC and RxNORM terminologies. A single, integrated terminology
                will simplify the development and implementation of higher order models. The single
                terminology model is based on the data structures of the SNOMED RF2 model, which
                features comprehensive and consistent version representation, modularity of content
                with defined dependencies between modules, standardized processes for promoting
                content from one module to another, and standardized processes and structures for
                extending the provided content to meet system requirements.</para>
            <glossseealso otherterm="snomedct">SNOMED CT</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="loinc">LOINC</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="rxnorm">RxNorm</glossseealso>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="prisme">
        <glossterm>Project Information System and Management Environment </glossterm>
        <acronym>PRISME</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para> Environment to support common functionality required for project management,
                workflow, and system integration. For example, issue tracking, artifact versioning,
                and so forth. </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="lego">
        <glossterm>Lightweight Expression of Granular Objects</glossterm>
        <acronym>LEGO</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Lightweight Expression of Granular Objects are reusable standards-based clinical
                data objects designed to protect clinicians from complex codes. LEGOs accurately
                capture clinical meaning and preserve clinical meaning between systems. </para>
            <para> They are looseley based on the IHTSDO Observables Model concept and comprised of
                self-contained units of knowledge, LEGOs transform patient data into a normalized
                consumable form. Ultimately, LEGO models can provide a foundation for the
                large-scale exchange of computer-processible medical information </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="vha">
        <glossterm>Veterans Health Administration</glossterm>
        <acronym>VHA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Veterans Health Administration is America’s largest integrated health care
                system with over 1,700 sites of care, serving 8.76 million Veterans each
                year.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="va">
        <glossterm>U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs</glossterm>
        <acronym>VA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The US Department of Veterans Affairs provides patient care and federal benefits
                (financial, education, and so forth) to veterans and their dependents.
                (http://www.va.gov/) . There are three major administrative areas: Veterans Benefits
                Administration (VBA), Veterans Health Administration (VHA), and National Cemetery
                Administration (NCA). </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ahrq">
        <glossterm>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</glossterm>
        <acronym>AHRQ</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) (formerly known as the
                Agency for Health Care Policy and Research) is an agency of the Department of Health
                and Human Services (HHS) whose mission is to produce evidence to make health care
                safer, higher quality, more accessible, equitable, and affordable, and to work to
                make sure that the evidence is understood and used. AHRQ's priority areas of focus
                are to: * Improve health care quality by accelerating implementation of
                patient-centered outcomes research (PCOR). * Make health care safer. * Increase
                accessibility by evaluating Affordable Care Act (ACA) coverage expansions. * Improve
                health care affordability, efficiency, and cost transparency.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="arra">
        <glossterm>American Recovery and Reinvestment Act</glossterm>
        <acronym>ARRA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (ARRA) (Public Law 111–5),
                commonly referred to as the Stimulus or The Recovery Act, was an economic stimulus
                package acted in the spring of 2009. While the primary purpose of ARRA was to
                stimulate the economy, it included the enactment of the Health Information
                Technology for Economic and Clinical Health Act, also known as the HITECH Act, which
                among other things codified the Office of the National Coordinator for Health
                Information Technology (ONC), and provided for health information technology
                investments and incentive payments meant to encourage the Meaningful Use of EHRs.
                This is important to VA as ONC has sponsored the development of standards which are
                then named in regulation as being necessary for Meaningful Use certification.</para>
            <glossseealso otherterm="hitech">HITECH Act</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="mu">Meaningful Use</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="onc">ONC</glossseealso>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ascx12">
        <glossterm>Accredited Standards Committee X12</glossterm>
        <acronym>ASC X12</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Accredited Standards Committee X12 (ASC X12), is a Standards Development
                Organization (SDO) chartered by the American National Standards Institute (ANSI) in
                1979. [The name "X12" is a sequential designator assigned by ANSI at the time of
                accreditation]. ASC X12 develops Electronic Data Interchange (EDI) standards for
                multiple industries. Of interest to the VA is the Insurance industry standards which
                includes healthcare eligibility and billing standards. These healthcare eligibility
                and billing standards are widely used, and their use is mandated by the Health
                Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA).</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="astm">
        <glossterm>American Society for Testing and Materials</glossterm>
        <acronym>ASTM International</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>ASTM International, known until 2001 as the American Society for Testing and
                Materials (ASTM), is an international standards organization that develops and
                publishes voluntary consensus technical standards for a wide range of materials,
                products, systems, and services. While ASTM is generally not involved in Healthcare
                IT standards, they developed a Continuity of Care Record (CCR) standard, which was
                included in Stage 1 of Meaningful Use.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="hipaa">
        <glossterm>Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act</glossterm>
        <acronym>HIPAA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA) (Public
                Law 104–191) contains two sections, the second of which directly affects the VA.
                Title I protects health insurance coverage for workers and their families when they
                change or lose their jobs. Title II, known as the Administrative Simplification (AS)
                provisions, requires the establishment of national standards for electronic health
                care transactions and national identifiers for providers, health insurance plans,
                and employers. The AS provisions also address the security and privacy of health
                data. The standards are meant to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of the
                nation's health care system by encouraging the widespread use of electronic data
                interchange in the U.S. health care system. The HIPAA AS provisions mandate, among
                other things, the use of ASC X12, HL7, and NCPDP messaging standards. Note that the
                HIPAA privacy provisions were strengthened in the ARRA legislation.</para>
            <glossseealso otherterm="arra">ARRA</glossseealso>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="hitech">
        <glossterm>Health Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health Act</glossterm>
        <acronym>HITECH Act</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Health Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health Act,
                abbreviated HITECH Act, was enacted under Title XIII of the American Recovery and
                Reinvestment Act of 2009. The HITECH Act provides funding to promote and expand the
                adoption of health information technology, including the creation of a nationwide
                network of electronic health records. The HITECH Act set meaningful use of
                interoperable EHR adoption in the health care system as a critical national goal and
                incentivized EHR adoption, and provides incentives for adoption of MU-certified EHR
                systems, which later become penalties for non-use of such systems. The Act
                officially established the Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information
                Technology (ONC), (which already existed under Executive Order 13335); as well as
                the The HIT Policy Committee which recommends a policy framework for the development
                and adoption of a nationwide health information technology infrastructure that
                permits the electronic exchange and use of health information; and the HIT Standards
                Committee which recommends to the National Coordinator standards, implementation
                specifications, and certification criteria. The activities of these organizations
                are important to VA as they deal with the development of standards which are then
                named in regulation as being necessary for Meaningful Use certification and
                implemented in the Nationwide Health Information Network.</para>
            <glossseealso otherterm="arra">ARRA</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="hitpc">HITPC</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="hitsc">HITSC</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="mu">Meaningful Use</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="onc">ONC</glossseealso>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="hitpc">
        <glossterm>Health Information Technology Policy Committee</glossterm>
        <acronym>HITPC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A committee which will make recommendations to the National Coordinator for Health
                IT on a policy framework for the development and adoption of a nationwide health
                information infrastructure, including standards for the exchange of patient medical
                information. </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="hitsc">
        <glossterm>Health Information Technology Standards Committee</glossterm>
        <acronym>HITSC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A committee which is charged with making recommendations to the National
                Coordinator for Health IT on standards, implementation specifications, and
                certification criteria for the electronic exchange and use of health
                information.</para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.healthit.gov/policy-researchers-implementers/health-it-standards-committee</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="hitsp">
        <glossterm>Health Information Technology Standards Panel</glossterm>
        <acronym>HITSP</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A cooperative partnership between the public and private sectors for the purpose
                of harmonizing and integrating standards that will meet clinical and business needs
                for sharing information among organizations and systems.</para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.hitsp.org/</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ihtsdo">
        <glossterm>International Health Terminology Standards Development Organisation</glossterm>
        <acronym>IHTSDO</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The International Health Terminology Standards Development Organisation (IHTSDO)
                is an international non-profit standards development organization. Its mission is to
                develop, maintain, promote and deliver medical terminology products in order to
                improve the health in a global scale through the development and application of
                appropriately standardized clinical terminologies in general. In particular, the
                IHTSDO maintains and promotes SNOMED CT to ensure safe, precise and effective
                exchange of clinical and health related information.</para>
            <glossseealso otherterm="snomedct">SNOMED CT</glossseealso>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="loinc">
        <glossterm>Logical Observation Identifiers Names and Codes</glossterm>
        <acronym>LOINC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Logical Observation Identifiers Names and Codes (LOINC) is a standard for
                identifying medical laboratory observations. It was developed and is maintained by
                the Regenstrief Institute. LOINC was created in response to the demand for an
                electronic database for clinical care and management and is publicly available at no
                cost. LOINC applies universal code names and identifiers to medical terminology
                related to electronic health records. The purpose is to assist in the electronic
                exchange and gathering of clinical results (such as laboratory tests, clinical
                observations, outcomes management and research). LOINC has two main parts:
                laboratory LOINC and clinical LOINC. Clinical LOINC contains a subdomain of Document
                Ontology which captures types of clinical reports and documents. It is noted that
                there is some overlap between LOINC and SNOMED-CT. Recently LOINC and IHTSDO agreed
                to harmonize the two standards.</para>
            <glossseealso otherterm="ihtsdo">IHTSDO</glossseealso>
            <glossseealso otherterm="snomedct">SNOMED CT</glossseealso>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="onc">
        <glossterm>Office of the National Coordinator For Health Information Technology</glossterm>
        <acronym>ONC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para> A resource to the entire health system to support the adoption of health
                information technology and the promotion of a nationwide health information exchange
                to improve health care.</para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.healthit.gov/newsroom/about-onc</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="rxnorm">
        <glossterm>RxNorm</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>RxNorm, produced by the National Library of Medicine, provides normalized names
                for clinical drugs and links its names to many of the drug vocabularies commonly
                used in pharmacy management and drug interaction software, including those of First
                Databank, Micromedex, MediSpan, Gold Standard, and Multum. By providing links
                between these vocabularies, RxNorm can mediate messages between systems not using
                the same software and vocabulary.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="snomedct">
        <glossterm>Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine: Clinical Terms</glossterm>
        <acronym>SNOMED CT</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine: Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT) is the most
                comprehensive, multilingual clinical terminology in the world. It is a vital
                component for safe and effective communication and reuse of meaningful health
                information.</para>
            <glossseealso otherterm="ihtsdo">IHTSDO</glossseealso>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ahima">
        <glossterm>American Health Information Management Association</glossterm>
        <acronym>AHIMA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A professional organization for the field of medical record management.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ahlta">
        <glossterm>Armed Forces Health Longitudinal Technology Application</glossterm>
        <acronym>AHLTA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The clinical documentation engine used by DoD Physicians to write their notes,
                input orders, document procedures performed and provide the basis of medical coding
                information.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="arb">
        <glossterm>Architecture Review Board (HL7)</glossterm>
        <acronym>ARB</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The HL7 Architecture Review Board seeks to define a coherent architecture for HL7
                work that defines the relationships among the HL7 work products and how they relate
                to other standards and components of local implementations. This architecture
                includes the Business Architecture by which these work products are produced and
                managed through their life cycle, the governance that will be enacted on these work
                products, and the scope of the standardization effort itself.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="bhie">
        <glossterm>Bi-directional Health Information Exchange</glossterm>
        <acronym>BHIE</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A series of communications protocols developed by the VA used to exchange
                healthcare information between VA healthcare facilities nationwide and between VA
                healthcare facilities and DoD healthcare facilities.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="cac">
        <glossterm>Clinical Application Coordinator</glossterm>
        <acronym>CAC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Clinical Application Coordinator (CAC) as a part of the Resource and Patient
                Management System (RPMS)-EHR implementation team provides ongoing operational
                support for certain RPMS packages that comprise and/or interface with the Electronic
                Health Record.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="capri">
        <glossterm>Compensation and Pension Record Interchange</glossterm>
        <acronym>CAPRI</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>CAPRI software was designed to promote efficient communications between VHA and
                VBA. It offers VBA Rating Veteran Service Representatives and Decision Review
                Officers help in building the rating decision documentation through on-line access
                to medical data.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ccd">
        <glossterm>Continuity of Care Document</glossterm>
        <acronym>CCD</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An XML-based markup standard/specification intended to specify the encoding,
                structure, and semantics of a patient summary clinical document for exchange. The
                CCD is a constraint on the HL7 Clinical Document Architecture (CDA) standard
                specifying that the content of documents consist of a mandatory textual part for
                human interpretation and optional structured parts for software processing.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ccda">
        <glossterm>Consolidated Clinical Document Architecture</glossterm>
        <acronym>C-CDA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An ANSI-certified standard from Health Level Seven (HL7), which specifies the
                syntax and supplies a framework for specifying the full semantics of a clinical
                document. C-CDA defines a clinical document as having six characteristics;
                Persistence, Stewardship, Potential for Authentication, Context, Wholeness, and
                Human Readability.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ccdi">
        <glossterm>Critical Care Data Interface</glossterm>
        <acronym>CCDI</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Interfaces which exchange information between VistA, the VA's computerized patient
                record and information system, and GE's QS(R) Critical Care Clinical Information
                System. These interfaces will enable VA Medical Centers nationwide to improve
                efficiency and accuracy by reducing duplicate data entry. In addition, they will
                support a national research data repository for patients treated in critical care
                and operating room environments.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ccdss">
        <glossterm>Clinical Care Delivery Support System</glossterm>
        <acronym>CCDSS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A system that provides clinicians, staff, patients or other individuals with
                knowledge and person-specific information, intelligently filtered or presented at
                appropriate times, to enhance health and health care. </para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.healthit.gov/policy-researchers-implementers/clinical-decision-support-cds</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ccow">
        <glossterm>Clinical Context Object Workgroup</glossterm>
        <acronym>CCOW</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A vendor independent HL7 standard protocol designed to enable disparate
                applications to synchronize in real time at the user-interface level, which allows
                applications to present information at the desktop and/or portal level in a unified
                way.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="cds">
        <glossterm>Clinical Decision Support</glossterm>
        <acronym>CDS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Provision of pertinent knowledge and person-specific information to clinical
                decision makers to enhance health and health care.1 A required component of
                Meaningful Use. For further detail, review the CDS Content Delivery Roadmap.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="cem">
        <glossterm>Clinical Element Model</glossterm>
        <acronym>CEM</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A small reusable representation of clinical information that is bound to a
                terminology system for its meaning. The CEM approach and repository of models was
                developed by Intermountain Healthcare and is used within their clinical
                systems.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="chcs">
        <glossterm>Composite Health Care System</glossterm>
        <acronym>CHCS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A module-based medical informatics system designed by Science Applications
                International Corporation (SAIC) and used by all DoD health care centers. Modules
                include RAD (radiology), LAB (Laboratory), PHR (Pharmacy), PAS (Patient Appointing
                and Scheduling), MCP (Managed Care Program; used to support TRICARE enrollees by
                enrolling them to Primary Care Managers), PAD (Patient Administration): MRT (Medical
                Records Tracking), MSA (Medical Service Accounting) medical billing, WAM (Workload
                Assignment Module), DTS (Dietetics), CLN (CLinical: Nursing, Physician, and Allied
                Health), DAA (Database Administration), ADM (Ambulatory Data Module) Medical Coding
                of outpatient visits, and TOOLS (FileMan).</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="chdr">
        <glossterm>Clinical/Health Data Repository</glossterm>
        <acronym>CHDR</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Department of Defense (DoD) and the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) in
                partnership, designed and implemented a Clinical Data Repository/Health Data
                Repository (CHDR) system that generates standards-based, computable electronic
                health records that can be exchanged and shared between the two agencies healthcare
                systems.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="cimi">
        <glossterm>Clinical Information Modeling Initiative</glossterm>
        <acronym>CIMI</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An initiative established to improve the interoperability of healthcare
                information systems through shared implementable clinical information models</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="cprs">
        <glossterm>Computerized Patient Record System</glossterm>
        <acronym>CPRS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A graphical user interface (GUI) for VistA.
                http://www.ehealth.va.gov/EHEALTH/CPRS_Demo.asp</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="cqm">
        <glossterm>Clinical Quality Measure</glossterm>
        <acronym>CQM</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>CQMs are tools that help many stakeholders, including CMS and health care
                providers themselves, measure and track the quality of health care services provided
                by eligible professionals, eligible hospitals, and CAHs within our health care
                system. They measure many aspects of patient care including health outcomes,
                clinical processes, patient safety, efficient use of healthcare resources, care
                coordination, patient engagement, and population and public health.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="dbq">
        <glossterm>Disability Benefits Questionnaire</glossterm>
        <acronym>DBQ</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>DBQs are downloadable forms created for Veterans' use in the evaluation process
                for disability benefits. DBQs will help speed the processing of Veterans' disability
                compensation and pension claims. DBQs allow Veterans and Service members to have
                more control over the disability claims process by giving them the option of
                visiting a primary care provider in their community, at their expense, instead of
                completing an evaluation at a Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) facility. The
                streamlined forms use check boxes and standardized language so that the disability
                rating can be made accurately and quickly.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="edi">
        <glossterm>Electronic Data Interchange</glossterm>
        <acronym>EDI</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The transfer of structured data, by agreed message standards, from one computer
                system to another without human intervention. EDI relies on primarily older
                technologies and point-to-point messaging.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ehr">
        <glossterm>Electronic Health Record</glossterm>
        <acronym>EHR</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A systematic collection of electronic health information about individual patients
                or populations. See also Interagency EHR (iEHR)</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="fhim">
        <glossterm>Federal Health Information Model</glossterm>
        <acronym>FHIM</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A coordination of several partner agencies with the development of electronic
                medical records, information and terminology standards, including the coordination
                of agency efforts at relevant Standards Development Organizations (SDOs).</para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.fhims.org/</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="fhir">
        <glossterm>Fast Health Information Resources</glossterm>
        <acronym>FHIR</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR, pronounced "Fire") defines a set
                of "Resources" that represent granular clinical concepts. The resources can be
                managed in isolation, or aggregated into complex documents. Technically, FHIR is
                designed for the web; the resources are based on simple XML or JSON structures, with
                an http-based RESTful protocol where each resource has predictable URL. Where
                possible, open internet standards are used for data representation. </para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=FHIR</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="haig">
        <glossterm>Health Architecture Interagency Group</glossterm>
        <acronym>HAIG</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A component of the VA/DoD IPO structure.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="harb">
        <glossterm>Health Architecture Review Board</glossterm>
        <acronym>HARB</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Serves as an advisory working sub-group to the VA/DoD Health Executive Council
                (HEC) that provides architecture oversight and approval due diligence for joint
                DoD/VA health programs to facilitate interagency cooperation and foster
                collaboration on enterprise architecture for interagency Health Information
                Technology (HIT) initiatives; activities that were previously the responsibility of
                the HEC IM/IT WG.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="hl7">
        <glossterm>Health Level 7</glossterm>
        <acronym>HL7</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A non-profit organization involved in the development of international healthcare
                informatics interoperability standards. The name "Health Level-7" is a reference to
                the seventh layer of the ISO OSI Reference model also known as the application
                layer, indicating that HL7 focuses on application layer protocols for the health
                care domain, independent of lower layers.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="hmp">
        <glossterm>Health Management Platform</glossterm>
        <acronym>HMP</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An IT platform for browser-based, clinical (nurse and physician) user-interface
                modules that are healthcare team-driven and enable functionality which decrease
                cognitive load, managing relationships between conditions, interventions and
                observations, acquire data (including documentation) as a by-product of workflow and
                support higher quality, safe patient care and clinician satisfaction.</para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.osehra.org/document/va-health-informatics-initiative-health-management-platform-virtual-patient-record</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="icd">
        <glossterm>International Classification of Diseases</glossterm>
        <acronym>ICD</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>UN-sponsored WHO standard diagnostic tool for epidemiology, health management and
                clinical purposes.2 The ICD is revised periodically and is currently in its tenth
                revision. (ICD-10)</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="iehr">
        <glossterm>Interagency Electronic Health Record</glossterm>
        <acronym>iEHR</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A healthcare IT system currently under development which will integrate the Health
                IT resources of both the VA and the DoD to acquire next generation EHR capabilities
                for both departments.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ihc">
        <glossterm>Intermountain Healthcare</glossterm>
        <acronym>IHC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A non-profit healthcare system based in Salt Lake City, UT., which is the largest
                healthcare provider in the Intermountain West.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ihe">
        <glossterm>Integrating the Healthcare Enterprise</glossterm>
        <acronym>IHE</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Associated with Patient Care Devices (PCD) and Pulse Oximetry (POI)</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ipo">
        <glossterm>Interagency Program Office</glossterm>
        <acronym>IPO</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>IPO will act as a single point of accountability in the development and
                implementation of electronic health records systems or capabilities as well as
                accelerating the exchange of health care information to support the delivery of
                health care by both Departments. The IPO will also have responsibility for oversight
                and management of personnel and benefits electronic data sharing between the
                Departments.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="irdc">
        <glossterm>Informatics Research and Design Center</glossterm>
        <acronym>IRDC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A VA facility and operations base for the Knowledge Based Systems group, located
                in Nashville, TN</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>



    <glossentry xml:id="jic">
        <glossterm>Joint Initiative Council</glossterm>
        <acronym>JIC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Formed to enable common, timely health informatics standards by addressing and
                resolving issues of gaps, overlaps, and counterproductive standardization efforts
                for international standardization needs.</para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.jointinitiativecouncil.org/</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="json">
        <glossterm>Javascript Object Notation</glossterm>
        <acronym>JSON</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A text-based open standard designed for human-readable data interchange, used
                primarily to transmit data between a server and web application, serving as an
                alternative to XML.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="kbs">
        <glossterm>Knowledge Based Systems</glossterm>
        <acronym>KBS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Office that extends past VA informatics by infusing clinical informatics expertise
                into VHA healthcare decision making, strategic planning, and delivery.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>


    <glossentry xml:id="mdht">
        <glossterm>Model Driven Health Tools</glossterm>
        <acronym>MDHT</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An open source tooling project initiated and lead by VHA within the Open Health
                Tools (OHT) organization. VA is also one of the founding members of OHT.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="mdws">
        <glossterm>Medical Domain Web Services</glossterm>
        <acronym>MDWS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A suite of Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) middle-tier web services that
                exposes medical domain functionality, Medical Domain Objects (MDO). MDWS is equipped
                with the capacity to virtualize any legacy Veterans Health Information Systems and
                Technology Architecture (VistA) Remote Procedure Call (RPC) as a web service. A web
                service is an Application Programming Interface (API), which uses Simple Object
                Access Protocol (SOAP), the standardized protocol to communicate with subscribed
                client applications. http://osehra.org/group/mdws The MDWS Group at OSEHRA is
                intended to coordinate the further development and maintenance of MDWS as an Open
                Source project.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="mu">
        <glossterm>Meaningful Use</glossterm>
        <acronym>MU</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An incentive-based program to be rolled out in 3 planned stages over the period of
                approximately 2010 through 2016, which is designed to insure that providers show the
                use of certified EHR technology in ways that can be measured significantly in
                quality and quantity. The three core MU requirements for a certified EHR are: use in
                a meaningful manner, such as e-prescribing; the electronic exchange of health
                information to improve quality of health care; and utilization in submitting
                clinical quality and other measures.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ncpdp">
        <glossterm>National Council for Prescription Drug Programs</glossterm>
        <acronym>NCPDP</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A not-for-profit, ANSI-accredited, standards development organization representing
                most sectors of the pharmacy services industry. The membership provides healthcare
                business solutions through education and standards focused on improving
                communication within the pharmacy industry.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ndfrt">
        <glossterm>National Drug File - Reference Terminology</glossterm>
        <acronym>NDF-RT</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The National Drug File - Reference Terminology (NDF-RT) is produced by the U.S.
                Department of Veterans Affairs, Veterans Health Administration (VHA). NDF-RT is an
                extension of the VHA National Drug File (NDF). It organizes the drug list into a
                formal representation. NDF-RT is used for modeling drug characteristics including
                ingredients, chemical structure, dose form, physiologic effect, mechanism of action,
                pharmacokinetics, and related diseases. </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="niem">
        <glossterm>National Information Exchange Model</glossterm>
        <acronym>NIEM</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An XML-based information exchange framework representing a collaborative
                partnership of agencies and organizations across all levels of the U.S. government
                (federal, state, tribal, and local), as well as private industry. NIEM is designed
                to develop, disseminate, and support enterprise-wide information exchange standards
                and processes to enable automated information sharing.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="nlm">
        <glossterm>National Library of Medicine</glossterm>
        <acronym>NLM</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A division of the National Institutes of Health (NIH), representing the world's
                largest medical library. The NLM includes more than seven million books, journals,
                technical reports, manuscripts, microfilms, photographs and images on medicine and
                related sciences including some of the world's oldest and rarest works.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="nprm">
        <glossterm>Notices of Proposed Rule Making</glossterm>
        <acronym>NPRM</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A notice of proposed rule making (NPRM) is a public notice issued by law when one
                of the independent agencies of the United States government wishes to add, remove,
                or change a rule or regulation as part of the rulemaking process. It is an important
                part of United States administrative law which facilitates government by typically
                creating a process of taking of public comment.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="oia">
        <glossterm>Office of Information and Analytics</glossterm>
        <acronym>OIA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An office that provides strategy and technical direction, guidance, and policy to
                ensure that IT resources are acquired and managed for the VA in a manner that
                implements various Federal laws and regulations.</para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.oit.va.gov/About_the_Office_of_OI_T.asp</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="oit">
        <glossterm>Office of Information and Technology</glossterm>
        <acronym>OIT</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>OIT delivers available adaptable, secure and cost effective technology services to
                the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) and acts as a steward for all VA's IT assets
                and resources.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="omg">
        <glossterm>Object Management Group</glossterm>
        <acronym>OMG</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An international, open membership, non-profit computer industry standards
                consortium focused on modeling (programs, systems and business processes) and
                model-based standards. http://www.omg.org/</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="pcast">
        <glossterm>President's Council of Advisors on Science and Technology.</glossterm>
        <acronym>PCAST</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An advisory group of the nation's leading scientists and engineers who directly
                advise the President and the Executive Office of the President. PCAST makes policy
                recommendations in the many areas where understanding of science, technology, and
                innovation is key to strengthening our economy and forming policy that works for the
                American people. PCAST periodically produces reports on a number of technology
                subject areas, one of which is Networking and Information Technology Research and
                Development. Under this category, on December 8, 20, a "PCAST report was published
                titled "Realizing the Full Potential of Health Information Technology to Improve
                Healthcare for Americans: The Path Forward."
                http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/microsites/ostp/pcast-health-it-report.pdf</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="pcd">
        <glossterm>Patient Care Devices</glossterm>
        <acronym>PCD</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A medical device used in the process of diagnosing, monitoring, treating, or
                preventing disease. </para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://www.ihe.net/resources/upload/ihe_pcd_user_handbook_2011_edition.pdf</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="po">
        <glossterm>Pulse Oximetry</glossterm>
        <acronym>PO</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Pulse Oximetry is a non-invasive method for monitoring a patient's O2 saturation
                using a pulse oximeter device.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="poi">
        <glossterm>IHE Patient Care Device Technical Framework Supplement - Pulse Oximetry
            Integration.</glossterm>
        <acronym>POI</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>This supplement builds on existing integration profiles (i.e., PCD, DEC) and
                transactions (i.e., PCD-01) and specifies content constrained for exchanging pulse
                oximetry data</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="raem">
        <glossterm>Requirements Analysis and Engineering Management</glossterm>
        <acronym>RAEM</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Management of those tasks that encompass determining the needs or conditions to be
                met for a new or altered product, including conflicting requirements of various
                stakeholders, analyzing, documenting, validating and managing software or system
                requirements.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="rest">
        <glossterm>Representational State Transfer</glossterm>
        <acronym>REST</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An architectural style that abstracts the architectural elements within a
                distributed hypermedia system. REST ignores the details of component implementation
                and protocol syntax in order to focus on the roles of components, the constraints
                upon their interaction with other components, and their interpretation of
                significant data elements.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ri">
        <glossterm>Regenstreif Institute</glossterm>
        <acronym>RI</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A private, non-profit research organization founded in 1969, heavily involved in
                the field of medical informatics and health services research, which is affiliated
                with the Indiana University School of Medicine and based in Indianapolis.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="samhsa">
        <glossterm>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration</glossterm>
        <acronym>SAMHSA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A branch of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, headquartered in
                Rockville, MD., charged with improving the quality and availability of prevention,
                treatment, and rehabilitative services in order to reduce illness, death,
                disability, and cost to society resulting from substance abuse and mental
                illnesses.3 www.samhsa.gov</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="scr">
        <glossterm>Standards Collaboration Roadmap</glossterm>
        <acronym>SCR</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A guide identifying the strategic partners, priorities, established objectives and
                evaluation criteria for interagency collaboration and joint standards architecture
                engagement. The roadmap will include both internal VA programs and external agency
                partner collaboration activities. The SCR is a revision-controlled document, updated
                as needed to reflect the dynamic nature of the healthcare IT environment.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="sdl">
        <glossterm>Standards Development Lifecycle</glossterm>
        <acronym>SDL</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A 6-step cycle used to define the process steps and stakeholders involved within
                the development and adoption of standards.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="sdo">
        <glossterm>Standards Development Organization</glossterm>
        <acronym>SDO</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An organization whose primary activities are developing, coordinating,
                promulgating, revising, amending, reissuing, interpreting, or otherwise producing
                technical standards that are intended to address the needs of a relatively wide base
                of affected adopters (e.g. Health IT). SDOs may be governmental, quasi-governmental
                or non-governmental entities. Quasi- and non-governmental standards organizations
                are often non-profit organizations.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="smart">
        <glossterm>System for the Mechanical Analysis and Retrieval of Text</glossterm>
        <acronym>SMART</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An information retrieval system used within documentation and forms. The SMART
                (System for the Mechanical Analysis and Retrieval of Text) Information Retrieval
                System is an information retrieval system developed at Cornell University in the
                1960s. Many important concepts in information retrieval were developed as part of
                research on the SMART system, including the vector space model, relevance feedback,
                and Rocchio classification. </para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SMART_Information_Retrieval_System</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="smarthealthit">
        <glossterm>Substitutable Medical Applications, Reusable Technologies (SMART)
            Platforms</glossterm>
        <acronym>SMART on FHIR</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>SMART Health IT is an open, standards based technology platform that enables
                innovators to create apps that seamlessly and securely run across the healthcare
                system. Using an electronic health record (EHR) system or data warehouse that
                supports the SMART standard, patients, doctors, and healthcare practitioners can
                draw on this library of apps to improve clinical care, research, and public health.
                The SMART platform is composed of open standards, open source tools for developers
                building apps and a publicly accessible app gallery. To date, dozens of clinical
                applications have been built on this platform, and SMART applications are being used
                to provide clinical care at healthcare institutions, including Boston Children’s
                Hospital and Duke Medicine. The project is run out of the not-for-profit
                institutions, Boston Children’s Hospital Computational Health Informatics Program
                and the Harvard Medical School Department for Biomedical Informatics.</para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc>http://smarthealthit.org/smart-on-fhir/</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="sme">
        <glossterm>Subject Matter Expert</glossterm>
        <acronym>SME</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An individual who is broadly accepted as an expert in a particular area or
                topic.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="sparql">
        <glossterm>A recursive acronym for SPARQL Protocol and RDF Query Language</glossterm>
        <acronym>SPARQL</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A query language for databases, able to retrieve and manipulate data stored in
                Resource Description Framework format, which was made a standard by the RDF Data
                Access Working Group (DAWG) of the World Wide Web Consortium, and is recognized as
                one of the key technologies of the semantic web. SPARQL v1.1 was released in March,
                2013.4 </para>
            <bibliography>
                <title>Source</title>
                <bibliomisc> http://www.w3.org/TR/sparql11-overview/</bibliomisc>
            </bibliography>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="sro">
        <glossterm>Standards Related Organization</glossterm>
        <acronym>SRO</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An organization whose primary activities are directly inter-related or critically
                affected by the development, coordination, promulgation, revision, amendment,
                reissuance, interpretation, or production of technical standards.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="ssc">
        <glossterm>Standards Steering Committee</glossterm>
        <acronym>SSC</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A committee representing multiple organizations within VHA, chartered to refine
                and vet the Standards Life Cycle Process document and establish/maintain a
                governance process for prioritization and validation of standards and
                standards-related activities.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="sts">
        <glossterm>Standards and Terminology Service</glossterm>
        <acronym>STS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>To prepare standards specifying principles and methods for the preparation and
                management of language resources within the framework of standardization and related
                activities.5 (See also ISO/TC 37)</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="uml">
        <glossterm>Unified Modeling Language</glossterm>
        <acronym>UML</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A standardized general-purpose modeling language in the field of object-oriented
                software engineering. UML was added to the list of OMG adopted technologies in
                1997.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="vbms">
        <glossterm>Veterans Benefit Management System</glossterm>
        <acronym>VBMS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The VA's web-based, electronic claims processing solution. The first Generation of
                VBMS was deployed in January 2013. The integration of VBMS with the online portal
                eBenefits, provides an end-to-end digital filing capability.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="vehu">
        <glossterm>VHA eHealth University</glossterm>
        <acronym>VEHU</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The online presence and training platform for the Office of Training Strategy.
                VeHU is used to promote collaboration of clinical staff, developers, and informatics
                staff to ensure VA resources are utilized in every possible capacity.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="visn">
        <glossterm>Veterans Integrated Service Networks</glossterm>
        <acronym>VISN</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>22 geographic based VA operating units or networks, allowing networks to manage
                themselves and adapt to the specific demographics of their location.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="vista">
        <glossterm>Veterans Information Systems and Technology Architecture</glossterm>
        <acronym>VistA</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An enterprise-wide information system consisting of a range of over 150 integrated
                software modules designed for the support of clinical care, financial functions, and
                infrastructure management. A GUI developed for clinician use, Computerized Patient
                Record System (CPRS), provides a client-server interface that allows health care
                providers to review and update a patient's electronic medical record.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="who">
        <glossterm>World Health Organization</glossterm>
        <acronym>WHO</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A specialized agency of the United Nations (UN) that is concerned with
                international public health, established on 7 April 1948, and headquartered in
                Geneva, Switzerland.8</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry xml:id="xml">
        <glossterm>eXtensible Markup Language</glossterm>
        <acronym>XML</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A markup language that defines a set of rules for encoding documents in a format
                that is both human-readable and machine-readable. The design goals of XML emphasize
                simplicity, generality, and usability over the Internet.9</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>


    <glossentry xml:id="means">
        <glossterm>Multi-Enterprise Architecture of Networked Services</glossterm>
        <acronym>MEANS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>See HITSP 08 N 345 MEANS - A Multi-Enterprise Architecture of Networked Services
                standard. Note that this standard may be obsolete.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
</glossary>
