<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Application of Terminology Layer</title>
    <para>Terminology is used throughout the architectural layers.  In this section we will give
        examples of how terminology should best be used in the various architectural layers.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Analysis Normal Form Terminology Usage</title>
        <para>The Statement Layer requires that the Terminology Expression fields in a statement are
            disjoint: There should be no confusion—or creation of false dichotomies. There should be
            one, and only one, place to put each type of information in a terminology expression.
            For example, the Statement Layer defines a particular place to represent the subject of
            information. Therefore, the terminology layer must not allow the subject of information
            to be redundantly—and possibly contradictory—represented in a topic expression (such as
            would be the case if "maternal history of diabetes" where an allowed topic
            expression).</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">topic:</emphasis> The particulars of how topics—and other
            statement fields—are modeled as a Terminology Knowledge layer concern, not a Statement
            Layer concern.  The Statement Layer requires that the topic represent an Action as a
            code or expression according to the rules of the terminology layer, and that the rules
            of the terminology layer enforce a disjointness of between different types of
            terminology expressions. Here we present a starting point for what the Terminology Layer
            editorial rules may look like, based on current SNOMED CT practice.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>SNOMED CT can accommodate this requirement for simple observations by using
                    Observation procedure to represent the topic (or other types of procedures when
                    appropriate, such as the administration of a medication). In SNOMED CT examples,
                    the Observation procedure specifies a Has focus attribute linking it to the
                    Clinical Finding or Disorder that it is being observed. The observation
                    procedure can also be further refined by adding attributes in the terminology
                    model, including Method, Procedure site - Direct, (if appropriate) Laterality,
                    and Using device.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Medication administrations will use an Administration of substance concept to
                    represent the topic. All Administration of substance concepts will be refined
                    with the substance and dose form and strength being requested. If Route of
                    administration exists, then it will also be added.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Laboratory tests will use a Laboratory Procedure concept to represent the
                    topic. These concepts can be further refined.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Imaging Procedures with use an Imaging Procedure concept to represent the
                    topic. These concepts will be further refined with a Method, Procedure site and
                    (if appropriate) a laterality for those sites that are lateralizable.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">purpose:</emphasis> The purpose is why an action was requested.
            The purpose of the topic is typically some type of therapeutic intent, diagnostic
            intent, or both. There can be more than one therapeutic intent and diagnostic
            intent.</para>
    </section>
</section>
