<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190823T110530-0500" comment="Add ISO 1087, and Chute et al requirements as well."?>Terminology
        Intro<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
    <para>The desiderata for the design of a controlled
        healthcare<?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190516T104634-0700" comment="We need to be consistent in our use of language. Interchanging Terminology and Vocabulary can be confusing to those that are not used to blocking out the distinctions. I recommend we stick with terminology, and not include the title of Jim&apos;s paper in the text. Just say someting like Cimino published criterion upon which terminologies should be evaluated in 1989." flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
        terminology
        <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190516T104401-0700" comment="I&apos;d be very cautious about the phrasing of &quot;first published&quot; implying that no one else published anything prior.  " flag="done"?>was
        published in 1989<?oxy_comment_end?> with seven items and was expanded in 1998 to a list of
        twelve desiderata in the paper by JJ Cimino.<citation>desiderata</citation> These desiderata are used to describe desirable
        characteristics of controlled medical terminologies. They are:<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Content</para>
                <para>While missing content is expected, formally stated processes for requesting
                    and adding content is required. SNOMED CT, LOINC and RxNorm all have formal
                    processes in place for requesting changes to the terminologies either through
                    the organization that maintains them or through a national release center in the
                    case of SNOMED CT. While content can be added using these formal processes,
                    there is usually a delay before a formal
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20191016T103843-0600" comment="Should this be &quot;edition&quot; instead?"?>addition<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    is available for use. In addition to the formal processes available through the
                    standards development organizations (SDOs), SNOMED CT includes formal mechanisms
                    for users to extend the terminology and add missing content locally.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept orientation</para>
                <para>The most granular piece of a terminology must be a concept with a single
                    coherent meaning. Terms associated with a code should represent a single
                    concept.</para>
                <para>In the 1998 paper <citation>Representing Thoughts, Words, and Things in the
                        UMLS</citation> the authors describe that the Ogden Richards' semiotic
                        triangle<quote> shows that, although written or spoken symbols (words)
                        cannot completely capture the essence of a reference (thought) or of a
                        referent (thing), there is a correspondence among them. Either a word or an
                        object can inspire a thought, and people may endeavor to express their
                        thoughts with words or by identifying objects in the world. The relationship
                        between a word and a thing is indirect, however. The link can be completed
                        only when an interpreter (usually a person) processes the word, which
                        invokes a corresponding thought, and then links that thought to a thing in
                        the world (the “referent”). This diagram is seductive in its
                        simplicity.</quote></para>
                <para><quote>By implying a one-to-one relationship between each pair of members in
                        the triangle, this simple diagram masks hidden complexity. Ogden and
                        Richards alluded to this complexity by the dotted line between a symbol and
                        a referent, indicating that the link between a symbol and a referent can
                        only be made indirectly through an interpreter, but the notion that a symbol
                        does—or could—refer to a single thought and that a thought does—or
                        could—refer to a single referent is a fallacy. Thus, it has been
                        historically recognized that multiple terms may refer to the same object or
                        idea, a single term may refer ambiguously to more than one object or idea,
                        and terms may be confusing because they are out of date. It is within this
                        context that we seek solutions to improve our ability to communicate about
                        biomedical concepts.</quote></para>
                <para>
                    <figure>
                        <title>Ogden and Richards semiotic triangle</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T200411-0500" comment="Convert image to svg"?>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/terminology_semiotictriangle.jpg"/><?oxy_comment_end?>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept permanence</para>
                <para>A concept's meaning cannot change, and concepts cannot be deleted after they
                    have been released. Once added to a terminology, concepts and their identifiers
                    should persist. However, a mechanism to make concepts inactive when they are
                    deemed to be duplicate or erroneous should be available. Terminologies like
                    SNOMED CT and LOINC both have mechanisms for inactivating concepts after they
                    have been deemed to be in error.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Meaningless concept identifiers</para>
                <para>Concepts should use unique identifiers that do not contain any contextual
                    information about a concept. Identifiers should not include any hierarchical
                    information that would prevent changes in the concepts hierarchy without
                    retirement.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Polyhierarchy</para>
                <para>In traditional classification systems, categories are only allowed to exist in
                    a single monohierarchical representation. For example, in ICD-10 A39.0
                    Meningococcal meningitis only exists as a subtype of A39 Meningococcal
                    infection.  In this representation you can easily find all meningococcal
                    infections, but if you need to find all types of meningitis you are required to
                    know all the various codes that represent the different classifications of meningitis.<figure>
                        <title><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190903T155353-0600" comment="Can you center the text in the boxes below and fix the first box where the text is cutoff?" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20191016T113247-0600" comment="This is still a problem - the text is cutoff." mid="6"?>Monohierarchy
                            Example<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="6"?></title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/meningitis_monohierarchy.svg"
                                    scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
                <para>In a well designed terminology, concepts should be allowed to exist in
                    multiple hierarchies if multiple parent concepts are appropriate. For example,
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T201423-0500" comment="Add image representing the polyhierarchy" id="m3l_gb2_xhb" flag="done" mid="4"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190528T215454-0400" comment="Adding initial image. Will re-create." parentID="m3l_gb2_xhb" flag="done" mid="5"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190806T085004-0600" comment="Recommend removing most of the white space around the image that isn&apos;t needed and is forcing &quot;hierarchies&quot; to be hyphenated and shown before and after the image." flag="done"?>Bacterial
                    meningitis is both a subtype of Bacterial Meningitis and Meningococcal
                    infectious disease and should exist in both hierarchies.<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="5"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="4"?>
                    <figure>
                        <title>Polyhierarchy Example</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/meningitis_polyhierarchy.svg"
                                    scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T201919-0500" comment="Should we add a comparison of stated vs inferred definitions here?
" flag="done" mid="7"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190507T163331-0600" comment="I think that would be helpful." id="p3x_b22_xhb" flag="done" mid="8"?><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190528T221625-0400" comment="Added some draft explanation. Need example to help." parentID="p3x_b22_xhb" flag="done" mid="9"?><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190812T161629-0600" comment="I think it needs to be more &quot;in your face,&quot; where you have the each term of stated and inferred, followed by their own definitions." flag="done"?>Formal
                    definitions<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="9"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="8"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="7"?></para>
                <para>While hierarchical information is paramount, the inclusion of additional
                    definitional knowledge can help maintain and correctly place concepts within the
                    appropriate hierarchy. Allowing computers to use this additional information can
                    aid in properly placing concepts in hierarchies that developers did not
                    originally add to a concept.</para>
                <para>When content modelers add new content to a terminology, the relationships they
                    create are sometimes called stated relationships. These stated relationships
                    help to give concepts a formal definition and can be used to correctly place a
                    concept in new hierarchies the content modeler did not originally assign. In
                    large terminologies, correctly adding all the possible valid hierarchical
                    relationships can be difficult as it requires the content modeler to think of
                    all the possible parents. By adding the additional information, like Finding
                    Site in the example below, additional hierarchical relationships can be inferred.<figure>
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190903T164307-0600" comment="Need to fix the text in circles to make it fit fully and not be cutoff, as it currently is.  With the text being white on a white background, the cutoff text cannot be read outside of the circles.  Same for the second diagram for inferred below." flag="done"?>
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20191016T113507-0600" comment="Still not fixed.  I think it needs to be fixed; otherwise, it appears as sloppy work." mid="15"?>
                        <title>Relationships Stated by a Content
                            Modeler<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="15"?></title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/stated_relationships.svg" scalefit="1"
                                    width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
                <para>DL ontologies can be classified (i.e., some relationships between concepts are
                    inferred from the asserted class descriptions) using a DL classifier and a new
                    set of inferred relationships is created for concepts. Solor provides both views
                    of stated and inferred relationships, and allow users to compare the
                    differences. Solor has blocks of necessary &amp; sufficient, necessary, and
                    inherited (i.e., inferred) relationships. <figure>
                        <title>Inferred Relationships by DL Classifier</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/inferred_relationships.svg" scalefit="1"
                                    width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>No residual categories (Reject "Not Elsewhere Classified")</para>
                <para>Since terminologies will never be completely finished, it is easy to reject
                    the concept orientation desiderata and begin to create or use concepts as
                    grouper categories for missing content. Doing so introduces a "semantic drift"
                    that will cause problems with properly identifying historical data. By assigning
                    meaning to a category or using a less specific concept to represent your
                    intended meaning, information is lost. Rejecting these categories requires the
                    capability to extend content as described in the first desiderata.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Multiple granularities</para>
                <para>The ability to represent meaning occurs at various levels, depending on the
                    setting of care and users of the terminology. As care progresses, a more finer
                    grained concept may be required to more accurately represent the diagnosis.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Multiple consistent views</para>
                <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T202611-0500" comment="Insert Cranial Nerve example here" id="bwk_122_xhb" flag="done" mid="14"?>
                <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190528T221559-0400" comment="Inserting initial image. Will re-create." parentID="bwk_122_xhb" flag="done" mid="16"?>
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190806T085156-0600" comment="Recommend removing most of the white space around the image that isn&apos;t needed and is forcing &quot;usable&quot; to be hyphenated and shown before and after the image." flag="done"?>
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190903T164556-0600" comment="There is still a lot of unnecessary white space above/below the diagram that should be deleted." mid="15"?>
                <para>In addition to representing meaning at various levels, the display of the
                    concepts that are relevant to certain users should be able to be customized.
                    Allowing users to view concepts in a way that is intuitive will support the
                    adoption of terminologies by making the terminology more usable.<?oxy_comment_end mid="15"?><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="16"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="14"?>
                    <figure>
                        <title>Multiple Consistent Views</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T132412-0600" comment="In the PDF, the &quot;After&quot; image is not shown, only the before image.  Either need to resize or move the &quot;After&quot; image below the &quot;Before&quot; image." flag="done"?>
                                <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190814T134943-0500" comment="convert to SVG" mid="18"?>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/CranialNerves.svg" scalefit="1"
                                    width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
                                ><?oxy_comment_end?></imagedata><?oxy_comment_end mid="18"?>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Representing context</para>
                <para>Terminologies should allow for the representation of the context in which the
                    concepts should be used. While some contextual information should not be
                    supported in the terminology (like date, time, names, etc), other contextual
                    information should be supported (for example severity and laterality).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Graceful evolution</para>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190402T125215-0600" comment="This sentence reads awkwardly to me, specifically re: the last part about testing.  Recommend revising it." flag="done"?>Change
                    in terminologies is inevitable but should not be done radically or without clear
                    documented reasons for the change. Changes should be carefully tested and vetted
                    by end-users. <?oxy_comment_end?></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Recognize redundancy</para>
                <para>Duplicate concepts should not exist in the terminology and processes should be
                    in place to both prevent and detect them. With large terminologies, it is
                    inevitable that duplicate and erroneous concepts are added. Robust terminologies
                    need processes and procedures in place to identify and retire duplicate and
                    erroneous concepts. Multiple processes can be utilized to ensure redundant
                    concepts are not added to terminologies. For example:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Standardized naming conventions should be in place to eliminate
                                the possibility of creating redundant concepts</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Description Logic classifiers that utilize formal concept
                                definitions to detect equivalent concepts</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    
</chapter>
