<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Concepts and Codes</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>The scope of content covered in terminologies varies from focusing on a very specific
            domain to covering multiple domains.  The main terminologies supported in Solor (SNOMED
            CT, LOINC, and RxNorm) all follow very structured and persistent code practices.  They
            never delete codes but in some cases (RxNorm) they are moved to a separate table.  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>SNOMED CT Concepts</title>
        <para>SNOMED CT concepts span multiple domains, from findings and disorders to procedures
            and pharmaceutical and biological products.  SNOMED CT concepts exist at multiple levels
            of granularity and mechanisms exist to add missing content to ensure that information is
            coded at the most granular level possible.  SNOMED CT Concepts are identified with a 6
            to 18 digit integer that has some structure that describes where the identifier
            originated (the original creator of the identifier) and what type of identifier it is.  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>LOINC Codes</title>
        <para>LOINC codes are used to identify laboratory and clinical measurements, observations
            and documents.  Each named concept in LOINC is given a LOINC code which has no structure
            other than a check digit appended to the end.  In addition, all of the components that
            make up the LOINC name are assigned LOINC Part Codes (LP) to them in the LOINC Database.
            LOINC Parts do not follow the same policies and maintenance practices as LOINC terms and
            are not intended to be used as a standalone terminology.  Some LOINC codes are also
            associated with answers (LA) and answer lists (LL) in the LOINC Database.  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>RxNorm</title>
        <para>RxNorm provides normalized clinical drug names and relationships between those names
            and common drug vocabularies for the purpose of easing the exchange of clinical drug
            information between systems that use different drug vocabularies.  Every concept in
            RxNorm is given a unique RXCUI.  The names and codes from the common drug vocabularies
            are then linked to that RXCUI.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Solor</title>
        <para>Solor integrates the content from its native format into a common Solor format.  Once
            the content is in Solor, there is a step where equivalency is determined through various
            methods where concepts of the same idea are aggregated. For example, Gentamycin from
            SNOMED is the same as Gentamycin from LOINC, and is also the same Gentamycin from
            RxNorm. The end result from this process is the creation of a Solor concept that is
            devoid of any source information (but will have traceability). This end result is what
            will be exposed to the user to view and use. In the Gentamycin example, a user will find
            this concept that is devoid of any source information and will not need to know if this
            is the SNOMED/LOINC/RxNorm Gentamycin that needs to be selected.  Solor concepts are
            identified using a Univerally Unique Identifier (UUID).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Solor Integration - Integrating LOINC Method Attributes and SNOMED CT
            Concepts</title>
        <para>The collaborative agreement between LOINC and SNOMED CT developers has enabled
            informaticists to leverage SNOMED CT for the representation of the building blocks of
            LOINC (e.g., method) and for a more consistent representation of clinical and laboratory
            observations in SNOMED CT. We utilized the derivative works from this collaborative
            effort to represent LOINC and SNOMED CT in Solor, an open-source ecosystem for
            integrating disparate medical terminologies in a common model. </para>
        <para>Seamless integration of LOINC and SNOMED CT is non-trivial because LOINC and SNOMED CT
            have different semantics models, and use different formalisms and tools for their
            representation, have separate release cycles, and different versioning mechanisms.
            Furthermore, the initial collaboration between LOINC and SNOMED CT provided equivalent
            concepts between LOINC laboratory concepts and SNOMED CT concepts but did not include
            many clinical concepts from LOINC. In this work, our objectives are (1) to assess the
            extent to which LOINC method attributes can be represented by concepts in SNOMED CT, (2)
            to describe how to integrate equivalent LOINC method attributes and SNOMED CT concepts
            in the Solor common model, and (3) to explore the benefits and challenges of integrating
            LOINC and SNOMED CT in the Solor common model. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Methods:</emphasis> We sought to identify the overlaps and gaps
            between method attributes in LOINC and concepts in SNOMED CT, and integrated the
            equivalent concepts in Solor – an integrated common model for medical terminologies.
            First, we gathered the list of method attributes from LOINC version 2.63 and mapped each
            to a concept unique identifier (CUI) from the UMLS(using the UMLS API). For CUIs
            representing a LOINC method attribute, we retrieved associated atoms from SNOMED CT in
            the UMLS.2 Next, we imported each LOINC identifier and attached description logic
            defining whether there was equivalency of the method attribute to SNOMED CT concepts.
            When there was an overlap, a Solor-navigation concept was created which facilitated an
            inferred taxonomy representation with semantic context from SNOMED CT attached to the
            right LOINC method attribute. Finally, we evaluated the alignments obtained between
            LOINC method attributes and SNOMED CT concepts to determine what method attributes in
            LOINC were not covered by concepts in SNOMED CT. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Results: </emphasis><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis
                    role="underline">Semantic profile of LOINC method
                attributes</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> –</emphasis> The method
            axis of LOINC is used to specify methods used for particular clinical observations and
            measurements. The distribution of the most prevalent semantic groups found in LOINC
            method attributes include procedures (58%), concepts/ideas (14%), living beings (13%),
            occupations (8%), and disorders (2%). Whereas, SNOMED CT concepts represent disorders
            (22%), procedures (17%), body structures (11%), clinical findings other than disorders
            (10%), and organisms (10%).1</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">Coverage of LOINC method attributes
                    by the UMLS and SNOMED CT</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> –
            </emphasis>Of the 1702 LOINC methods, 1688 (99%) were mapped to a UMLS CUI. Sampling the
            1% not mapped implies provisional codes added to a LOINC version update that were not
            yet added to the UMLS version release. We computed the coverage of LOINC method
            attributes by SNOMED CT by analyzing the count of LOINC method attributes that shared at
            least 1 UMLS CUI with a corresponding SNOMED CT concept. Of the 1688 CUIs that
            represented LOINC method attributes, 383 (23%) were associated with a SNOMED CT
            concept.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">Solor
                Transformation</emphasis></emphasis> –Solor is an ecosystem that allows users to
            import, transform, view, and export content from disparate medical terminologies, all in
            one common model. Users can navigate and search Solor content, view details of the data
            elements, and select specific concepts to view more information. Solor has two
            fundamental building blocks: concepts and semantics. A concept is defined as an idea or
            a general notion and is represented by a universally unique identifier (UUID). A
            semantic is attached to a concept to provide contextual meaning and semantic data to the
            concept’s content. </para>
        <para> Integrating LOINC method attributes into Solor required a transformation process in
            which the LOINC data was transformed into Solor components using these defining
            relationships to create OWL EL++ description logic definitions. The LOINC identifier was
            used to create a Type 5 UUID for a Solor concept, so that the identifiers used in Solor
            are idempotent, and are derivable directly from the LOINC data. Additionally, the
            original LOINC identifier for this concept is properly represented, as are the other
            data elements required by the LOINC license. These Solor concepts integrate SNOMED CT
            and LOINC semantics; the LOINC Method semantic and SNOMED CT semantic are grouped under
            the same Solor concept. Figure 1 exemplifies the integration: the LOINC method attribute
            is “AUDIT”, and the SNOMED CT concept is “Alcohol use disorders identification
            test”.</para>
        <figure>
            <title><emphasis role="bold">Solor Editor: Representation of LOINC and SNOMED CT in a
                common model</emphasis></title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/Komet_LOINC_Int.png" scalefit="1"
                        width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Conclusion</emphasis>: LOINC method attributes include concepts
            ranging from procedures, administrative concepts, occupations, and a small number of
            disorders and phenomena. Only about 23% of LOINC method attributes can be directly
            represented by a SNOMED CT concept. The overall interoperability between LOINC method
            attributes and SNOMED CT concepts was limited at best. Interestingly, there were a
            number of procedures and specimen source details in LOINC method attributes with little
            or no coverage by SNOMED CT. One suggestion is for developers of LOINC and SNOMED CT to
            review these gaps and include better coverage in future versions, if appropriate. </para>
        <para>Solor may assist in providing a collaborative ecosystem to host local extensions for
            SNOMED CT to represent LOINC method attributes. Currently, implementers of LOINC and
            SNOMED CT must traverse the distinct hierarchies of each source terminology and version.
            Integrating the terminology content of LOINC and SNOMED CT into the Solor common model
            may have a beneficial impact on the usability (i.e., reduced burden) for implementers in
            both traversing distinct formalisms and maintaining version control. It may be helpful
            to communicate more specific details about LOINC method attributes by leveraging the
            right SNOMED CT concepts for additional details about the method attributes. Next steps
            include conducting a formative evaluation with a purposive sample of experts in standard
            clinical terminologies to assess the benefits and challenges of integrating and
            representing overlapping LOINC and SNOMED CT content in Solor’s common model. We aim to
            have this evaluation completed by Summer 2019 and will include these updated results if
            accepted. Solor’s integration of disparate medical terminology content may help
            implementers and authors of medical terminologies with orienting concepts and traversing
            relationships between disparate standards. </para>
        
    </section>
    
</chapter>

