<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Application of Terminology Knowledge Layer</title>
    <para>Terminology is used throughout the architectural layers.  In this section we will give
        examples of how terminology should best be used in the various architectural layers.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Analysis Normal Form Terminology Usage</title>
        <para>The Statement Layer requires that the Terminology Expression fields in a statement are
            disjoint: There should be no confusion—or creation of false dichotomies. There should be
            one, and only one, place to put each type of information in a terminology expression.
            For example, the Statement Layer defines a particular place to represent the subject of
            information. Therefore, the terminology layer must not allow the subject of information
            to be redundantly—and possibly contradictory—represented in a topic expression (such as
            would be the case if "maternal history of diabetes" were an allowed topic
            expression).</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">topic:</emphasis> The particulars of how topics—and other
            statement fields—are modeled as a Terminology Knowledge Layer concern, not a Statement
            Layer concern. The Statement Layer requires that the topic represent an Action as a code
            or expression according to the rules of the
            T<?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190903T121300-0600" comment="Recommend being consistent with capitalization and the terms you are using when referring to the various layers..  In this one paragraph for this layer, you have:

 - Terminology Knowledge layer
 - Terminology Layer
 - terminology layer" flag="done"?>erminology
            Knowledge Layer<?oxy_comment_end?>, and that the rules of the Terminology Knowledge
            Layer enforce a disjointness between different types of terminology expressions. Here we
            present a starting point for what the Terminology Knowledge Layer editorial rules may
            look like, based on current SNOMED CT practice.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>SNOMED CT can accommodate this requirement for simple observations by using
                    Observation procedures to represent the topic (or other types of procedures when
                    appropriate, such as the administration of a medication). In SNOMED CT examples,
                    the Observation procedure specifies a Has focus attribute linking it to the
                    Clinical Finding or Disorder that it is being observed. The Observation
                    procedure can also be further refined by adding attributes in the terminology
                    model, including Method, Procedure site - Direct, and
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190903T121959-0600" comment="If this is referring to Laterality, recommend putting it aftward, not before." id="ads_f3d_z3b"?><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190905T211040-0500" comment="Does this new wording work?" parentID="ads_f3d_z3b" mid="2"?>if
                    appropriate <?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_end?>Laterality and Using
                    device. For example:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Diabetes Mellitus Type 2 Present = [Observation procedure]-(Has
                                focus) [Diabetes mellitus type 2]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Pulse Rate 68 bpm, Taken by Pulse Oximeter = [Observation
                                procedure]-(Method) [Examination - action]-(Has focus) On
                                examination - pulse rate]-(Using device) [Pulse oximeter];</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Medication administrations will use an Administration of substance concept to
                    represent the topic. All Administration of substance concepts will be refined
                    with the substance, dose form and strength being requested. If Route of
                    administration exists, then it will also be added.  For example:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Patient Took One Acetaminophen 500 mg Tablet by Mouth for Pain =
                                [Administration of substance]-(Method) [Administration -
                                action]-(Direct substance) [Product containing precisely paracetamol
                                500 milligram/1 each conventional release oral tablet]-(Route of
                                administration) [Oral]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Ribavirin 200 mg Capsule Oral, Take 2 Capsules Every Morning =
                                [Administration]-(Method)[Administration - action]-(Direct
                                substance)[Ribavirin 200 MG Oral Capsule]-(Route of
                                administration)[Oral]</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Laboratory tests will use a Laboratory Procedure concept to represent the
                    topic. These concepts can be further refined. For example:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Rheumatoid Factor 1 Time Routine = Rheumatoid factor
                                measurement</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Imaging Procedures will use an Imaging Procedure concept to represent the
                    topic. These concepts will be further refined with a Method, Procedure site, and
                    a laterality for those sites that are lateralizable. For example:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>X-ray Chest to Evaluate for Heart Failure = Plain chest
                                X-ray</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">purpose:</emphasis> The purpose is why an action was requested.
            The purpose of the topic is typically some type of therapeutic intent, diagnostic
            intent, or both. There can be more than one therapeutic intent and diagnostic intent and
            therefore there can be more than one purpose.  The purpose is represented as a
            post-coordinated expression, based on two possible procedures:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>386053000 |Evaluation procedure|</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>277132007 |Therapeutic procedure|</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>The procedure is then refined by post-coordinating with a “363702006 |Has focus
            (attribute)|” attribute and identifying a finding/disorder or procedure concept as the
            value for the attribute.  For example: Request for administration of Ibuprofen 400 mg
            tablet oral every 6 hours as needed for back pain has a purpose of [Therapeutic
            procedure]-(Has focus)[Backache]</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">subjectofInformation:</emphasis> The subjectOfInformation is
            used to represent who the statement is about. This is normally the patient (Subject of
            record) unless explicitly stated otherwise, for example Mother, Sibling, Donor,
            etc.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">associationSemantic:</emphasis> A logical expression to capture
            how the target statement is associated (e.g. a precondition, an interpretation, a
            component).</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">measureSemantic:</emphasis> Measure semantic represents a unit
            of measure or scale specified by the interval values. It is described using a logical
            expression using standard-based terminology (i.e. SNOMED CT). For systolic blood
            pressure, the unit of measure is millimeters of mercury, and thus the measure semantic
            is a SNOMED CT concept: 259018001 |Millimeter of mercury|. For blood glucose measurement
            daily for 2 weeks, the measure semantic would be 258705008 |week|. For quantity/count
            measure values, the measure semantic to express a number of findings or phenomena
            described in the ANFStatement.topic "3 dot-and-blot hemorrhages" would be 30766002
            |Quantitative|. If Measure is used to represent date or time:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Date/time using Unix Epoch time: [762636008] Duration, [257997001]
                    Seconds</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Duration using Unix Epoch time start time and end time: [762636008] Duration,
                    [257997001] Seconds</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">status:</emphasis> This is a coded value used with a Performance
            of action representing the current status of the intervention (e.g. completed, on hold,
            needed, rejected, etc). This data element is not intended as a substitute for workflow
            specification.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">healthRisk:</emphasis> In PerformanceCircumstance, healthRisk is
            used to flag a result with coded values such as 'low', 'normal', high', and
            'critical'.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">participantRole:</emphasis> Participants can be specified or
            requested.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>A Performance of action can specify participants using participant in
                    PerformanceCircumstance.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>A Request for action can specify requested participants using
                    requestedParticipant in RequestCircumstance.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
