<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <title>Architectural Challenges</title>
    </info>
    <epigraph>
        <para>Defining guidelines for an evolutionary architecture for the next decade is not an
            easy task.<citation>30</citation></para>
    </epigraph>

    <para>How did we end up with a menagerie instead of a productive ecosystem? Before we embark on
        our next adventure, we should spend time to understand how we got where we are, and how we
        may avoid making the same mistakes. There are several antipatterns that are pervasive in
        health IT systems. These antipatterns include <emphasis role="italic">accidental
            complexity</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">design by committee</emphasis>, and
            <emphasis role="italic">stovepipe</emphasis>. These antipatterns are discussed in the
        following sections. </para>
    <para/>
    <section>
        <title>Accidental complexity</title>
        <para>Accidental (or incidental) complexity is complexity that arises in computer programs
            or their development process that is non-essential to the problem to be solved. While
            essential complexity is inherent and unavoidable, accidental complexity is caused by the
            approach chosen to solve the problem.<citation>49</citation></para>
        <para>Some examples of accidental complexity as they relate to informatics are described in
            the following sections. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Semantic-laden identifiers</title>
            <para>Solving a distributed identifier allocation problem by using namespaces that are
                assigned to organizations (or committees in the case of HL7), semantics are often
                introduced into the identifier, which some developers used to identify what
                organization created the components that where associated with those identifiers. </para>
            <para> Exposing derivable semantics in the identifier can lead to complexity when
                users/developers demand that the semantics be maintained, which may result in
                unnecessary retirement as described in the next section. </para>
            <para> Reliance on UUIDs rather than on identifiers with derivable semantics would
                eliminate this complexity. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Unnecessary retirement</title>
            <para>An unintended side effect of using identified namespaces as part of distributed
                identifier assignment, is an increase in the complexity of transferring
                responsibility for a component from one organization to another. This complexity
                includes an elaborate sequence of marking a component for retirement in one release,
                actually retiring it in a subsequent release, and creating an essentially identical
                component with an identifier derived from the new organizations namespace, and the
                need for creation of mapping solutions to keep historical relationships between
                components retired for these reasons to the current concepts that replace
                them.</para>
            <para> Again, reliance on UUIDs rather than on identifiers with derivable semantics
                would eliminate this complexity. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Thingey which has a property called TypeOfThingey inside it</title>
            <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
            <para> --FIX -add here --<?oxy_custom_end?>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Post-coordination</title>
            <para>Terminology models sometimes make it necessary to require post-coordination to provide domain
                coverage at the point of care, however, the information models we use in healthcare
                typically can’t handle post-coordination well. Reliance on the information model to
                represent post-coordination has introduced complexity that might be avoided if we
                used a dynamic means to assign unique identifiers to post-coordinated expressions.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Accidental complexity solutions</title>
            <para>Accidental complexity must be minimized in any good architecture, design, and
                implementation. Working in short iterations with ongoing design reviews may help
                reduce accidental complexity.</para>
            <para>We must also develop an example implementation in parallel with the architecture,
                so that complexity can be identified early, and evaluated critically with respect to
                the essential or accidental nature of that complexity. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Design by committee</title>
        <section>
            <title>No unifying vision</title>
            <para>Design by committee is the result of having many contributors to a project, but no
                unifying vision.</para>
            <para>A complex software design is the product of a committee process. The design has so
                many features and variations that it is infeasible for any group of developers to
                realize the specifications in a reasonable time frame.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Interoperability at the expense of operability</title>
            <para>Interoperability provides an illusion of operability between disparate systems,
                and therefore there is no need to standardize. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Design by committee solutions</title>
            <para>A solution to design by committee is to articulate a set of architectural
                principles to which architectural components will be evaluated against, and to have
                the committee be advisory to an architect that provides the unifying vision.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Stovepipe</title>
        <para>The Stovepipe Enterprise antipattern is characterized by a lack of coordination and
            planning across a set of systems.<citation>36</citation></para>
        <para>If every subsystem has a unique interface, then the system is overly complex. Absence
            of common multisystem conventions is a key problem for systems. For example, currently,
            essentially no terminology systems are the same with regard to their representation and
            semantics, despite the requirement that they must work together.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Overlapping and unreconciled models</title>
            <para>SNOMED CT and LOINC are classic examples of two terminologies that are proposed
                for common use in health IT, but that are not well coordinated, and have
                unreconciled content (content that is not made consistent or compatible).</para>
            <para>As an example of unreconciled content, SNOMED CT and LOINC all have
                representations for Amoxicillin. In LOINC, Amoxicillin is a textual value in the
                has-component field of the concept:</para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>
AMOXICILLIN [MASS/VOLUME] IN SERUM OR PLASMA
		HAS-COMPONENT: AMOXICILLIN
                </programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>While SNOMED CT has the concept: </para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>
AMOXICILLIN MEASUREMENT (PROCEDURE)
	COMPONENT: AMOXICILLIN (SUBSTANCE)
                </programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            <para>In SNOMED CT, Amoxicillin is also a concept, rather than just a text value. </para>
            <para> From an end-users perspective, the artificial separation and uncoordinated
                development of these important systems has been a burden. RxNorm may help bridge the
                medication components of the overlap, but there are other overlapping domains
                (method, type of scale, system, time aspect, and non-pharmaceutical components) that
                RxNorm does not cover. The UMLS may help us formally reconcile some of these other
                domains, but if coordination and reconciliation can be part of the development
                processes for these sources, rather than a cleanup exercise for implementers, we can
                allocate resources to solving more compelling problems. </para>
            <para> We hope that the newly announced cooperative agreement between IHTSDO (owners of
                SNOMED CT) and the Regenstrief Institute (owners of LOINC) will change the
                coordination of these two systems in a significantly helpful way. </para>
            <para> Although SNOMED CT and LOINC are classic examples of overlapping and unreconciled
                models, there are many other examples. The UMLS Source Release Documentation
                identifies 169 sources, most of which are uncoordinated, and have independent
                models. These overlapping and unreconciled models create an unnecessary burden for
                the implementer. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Uncoordinated development</title>
            <para> Today, related components from different organizations do not share their work
                prior to a release. The result of this lack of sharing is that dependent components
                are always out of date with the latest release of the underlying standard. For
                example, how can you keep a mapping of SNOMED CT to ICD-9-CM components up to date,
                when it takes 6 months after the release of SNOMED CT to update and quality assure
                the map? As an implementer, does that mean you should wait 6 months for the map to
                be updated before deploying the latest SNOMED CT release? What if the new SNOMED CT
                release contains new content that may improve the diagnosis, treatment, or
                prevention of disease? Is it really acceptable to delay implementation of the latest
                SNOMED CT release by 6 months while waiting for dependent system components to be
                updated after the fact? </para>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Stovepipe solutions</title>
            <para> The primary solution for the stovepipe systems we are working with is to break
                down the barriers that prevent collaborative development of content, tools,
                processes, and ultimately architecture. </para>
            <para> Today, deployment delay is not a significant issue because clinical decision
                support is nascent, and pharmacy, laboratory, and clinical systems are poorly
                integrated. However, if we successfully create compelling decision support on an
                integrated platform, coordination of development and release cycles among clinical
                terminologies, logical representation, clinical facts, and clinical knowledge bases
                will become increasingly important. We must prepare for success and work to better
                coordinate development among dependent components. </para>
            <para> In<?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?> [new
                reference]<?oxy_custom_end?> Architectural opportunities we outlined many
                opportunities that are helping to break down those barriers. Here we propose
                leveraging those opportunities. Those opportunities include acquisition and
                development of open-source tooling. Improvements in open-source tooling will help
                break down collaborative barriers significantly. Such improvement is a fundamental
                focus of our architecture effort. </para>
            <para> The solution to the stovepipe antipattern is effective collaboration without
                barriers of proprietary concern. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>A collaborative path forward</title>
        <para> The Health Information Technology Standards Committee (HITSC) is a federal advisory
            committee which provides recommendations on health IT standards. They have identified
            SNOMED CT, RxNorm, and LOINC as key clinical vocabularies for Meaningful Use and for
            HIPAA transactions. </para>
        <para> We plan to collaborate closely with these systems—indeed we plan to found the entire
            architecture on top of them—rather than treat them as an architectural afterthought. As
            these systems are foundational, we plan to collaborate closely and directly contributie
            to SNOMED CT, RxNorm, and LOINC when possible. </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
