<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <title>The Menagerie</title>
    </info>
    <epigraph>
        <attribution>Grady Booch</attribution>
        <para>All architecture is design but not all design is architecture. Architecture represents
            the significant design decisions that shape a system, where significant is measured by
            cost of change.</para>

    </epigraph>
    <para>Health Informatics Architecture is a clinical and technical discipline that is concerned
        with the representation of clinical knowledge, clinical organizational information and
        patient-specific clinical data within health information systems and with the technical
        methodologies used to process that data for patient care, quality assurance, and other
        secondary uses. </para>
    <para>The importance of defining informatics architecture is in part illustrated by the current
        state of affairs surrounding informatics architecture. Today, a menagerie of inconsistent
        and overlapping terminology, information, and messaging models hinders Clinical Decision
        Support efforts that try to store and analyze encoded clinical data. The current complexity
        encountered when trying to integrate these models—and the lack of coherence between (and
        sometimes within) the models themselves—must be overcome to build a foundation for scalable
        and extensible clinical decision-support architecture. </para>
    <para> We believe that defining—and validating—a coherent informatics architecture is a first
        step to enable implementation of meaningful clinical decision support that can be shared
        between organizations. </para>
    <section>
        <title>Architectural opportunities</title>
        <para>While our current state of affairs is less than desired, there has been tremendous
            work and good progress over the last 25 years. Our challenge today is to leverage these
            works to form the coherent architecture we seek. In the following subsections, we
            describe the an incomplete inventory of systems that provide architectural opportunities
            we hope to leverage. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Unified Medical Language System</title>
            <para>In 1986, the National Library of Medicine (NLM) began a long-term research and
                development project to build the Unified Medical Language System (UMLS®). The
                purpose of the UMLS is to aid the development of systems that help health
                professionals and researchers retrieve and integrate electronic biomedical
                information from a variety of sources.
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>REF-UMLS
                FIX<?oxy_custom_end?>.</para>
            <para>The UMLS efforts have been instrumental in focusing attention on issues
                surrounding clinical terminology, as well as providing means of interoperation
                between different terminology systems. We hope to leverage knowledge gained via the
                UMLS experience&#8212;as well as content developed and curated as part of UMLS
                efforts&#8212;to bootstrap our efforts. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED&#160;RT support for description logic</title>

            <para>Kaiser Permanente developed SNOMED RT (Reference Terminology) and donated its work
                to the College of American Pathologists in the hope that a robust standard for
                encoding clinical data would evolve. SNOMED RT was first released in 2000.</para>

            <para>&#160;SNOMED&#160;RT was the first clinical terminology outside of a research
                environment to use description-logic as its knowledge representation foundation.
                This effort made a distinction between reference uses of terminology (uses related
                to knowledge representation and retrieval) and interface uses of terminology (uses
                related to correctness and efficiency of user data input). </para>

            <para>SNOMED RT was designed to complement the broad coverage of medical concepts in
                SNOMED RT with a set of enhanced features that significantly increases its value as
                a reference terminology for representing clinical data. SNOMED RT represented
                multiple hierarchies and incorporates description logic.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED&#160;CT support for user interface customization</title>

            <para>SNOMED&#160;CT (Clinical Terms) was first released in 2002. A distributed team
                within the US and the United Kingdom integrated SNOMED RT and the UK's Clinical
                Terms Version 3 (formerly known as the Read Codes) into a single terminology.
                SNOMED&#160;CT has become the most comprehensive, multilingual clinical healthcare
                terminology in the world. </para>

            <para>SNOMED&#160;CT introduced expanded dialect support that allows language
                customization to be represented as a core component of SNOMED&#160;CT. This
                integrated approach eliminates the expensive and error-prone approach of mapping
                interface terminologies to reference terminologies. </para>

            <para>In addition to the expanded dialect support, SNOMED&#160;CT introduced reference
                extensions&#8212;a standard means to extend terminology content by referencing
                component identifiers. These reference extensions provide means to specify
                alternative taxonomy navigation, ordering of items in taxonomy lists, and other
                essential features of interface terminology. </para>

            <para>This new SNOMED&#160;CT framework created a means by which an integrated
                terminology system could provide for interface and reference needs of clinical
                systems. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Standard extension model</title>

            <para>SNOMED&#160;CT does not cover all the concepts required for representation of
                clinical concepts in the informatics architecture. Therefore, we must have a
                standard model to extend resources, and to contribute the extensions to responsible
                organizations when appropriate. </para>

            <para>The SNOMED&#160;CT extension model provides such a standard model for extension
                that we can build upon. Organizations are currently using this standard extension
                model with success.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Spanish extension</title>

                <para>The Spanish extension of the International Release is updated each year in
                    April and October. Although Spanish is the first language extension to
                    SNOMED&#160;CT, it is not the only language extension. SNOMED&#160;CT is
                    currently available in American English, British English, Spanish, Danish and
                    Swedish, with other translations under way or nearly completed in French and
                    Dutch.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>United Kingdom SNOMED CT extension</title>

                <para>The British National Health Service produces 2 extensions to SNOMED&#160;CT.
                    The UK Clinical Extension, and the UK Drug Extension. </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>United States SNOMED CT extension</title>

                <para>The US Extension to SNOMED&#160;CT® is a listing of the concepts,
                    descriptions, relationships and their history for terminology content accepted
                    by the NLM as a formal extension to the SNOMED&#160;CT International
                    Release.</para>

                <para>The main purposes of the US Extension to SNOMED&#160;CT are to:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Provide “rapid” access to concept IDs for use by implementers, pending
                            action by IHTSDO on content submissions likely to be added to the
                            SNOMED&#160;CT International Release.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Provide standard terminology needed for US clinical use cases, but not
                            generally useful in other countries, e.g., regulatory or legislatively
                            mandated terms specific to the US.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>The US Extension includes both active and inactive content that is harmonized
                    with the most recently published version of the SNOMED&#160;CT International
                    Release. As the content of the extension grows and undergoes consistent review,
                    realignment and harmonization with the International Release, users should
                    expect changes to the US Extension related to all future releases of
                    SNOMED&#160;CT.</para>

                <para>The US Extension is being developed to facilitate the use of SNOMED&#160;CT as
                    the primary coding terminology for clinical information in electronic health
                    records, research data bases and clinical trials databases, except in the
                    domains of medications and laboratory tests, which are covered by RxNorm and
                    LOINC respectively. As local vocabularies often provide variable ways of
                    representing commonly used concepts, the use of a common set of SNOMED&#160;CT
                    concepts will maximize data interoperability among institutions. Users unable to
                    find terms they think are appropriate should contact the NLM to request
                    additional content to the US Extension. Content suitable for inclusion in the
                    International Release may be submitted by NLM to the IHTSDO contemporaneously
                    with its evaluation, modeling and ID assignment in the US Extension. If accepted
                    into the International Release, the corresponding US Extension entries will be
                    linked to the International Release content and labeled as “retired” in the US
                    Extension.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Australian SNOMED CT extension</title>

                <para>SNOMED CT Australian Release (SNOMED CT-AU) is the Australian extension to
                    SNOMED CT, providing local variations and customizations of terms relevant to
                    the Australian healthcare community. It includes the international resources
                    along with all Australian developed terminology and documentation for
                    implementation in Australian clinical IT systems.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Canadian SNOMED CT extension</title>

                <para>Canada Health Infoway’s Standards Collaborative is developing and maintaining
                    a Canadian Extension that encompasses English and French components.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Other extensions</title>

                <para>Many other organizations are developing extensions to SNOMED CT. The IHTSDO is
                    currently comprised of Australia, Belgium, Brunei, Canada, Czech Republic,
                    Denmark, Estonia, Hong Kong, China, Iceland, Israel, Lithuania, Malaysia, Malta,
                    Netherlands, New Zealand, Poland, Singapore, Slovak Republic, Slovenia, Spain,
                    Sweden, United Kingdom, United States, and Uruguay. Many of these members are
                    either currently developing extensions to SNOMED&#160;CT, or are planning to.
                    Healthcare organizations, knowledge base vendors, and other organizations may
                    also create extensions to SNOMED&#160;CT as may be required to meet their
                    operational and organizational needs. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>RxNorm</title>

            <para>Pharmacy related matters are of massive importance in our health care system. For
                example, adverse drug events (ADEs) comprise the largest single category of adverse
                events experienced by hospitalized patients, accounting for about 19 percent of all
                injuries. Clinical information systems can play a critical role in preventing such
                injuries, and in ensuring proper prescribing practices. </para>

            <para>RxNorm was created to provide a means of interoperability between one pharmacy
                information system and another. First released in 2005, RxNorm includes the VA’s
                NDF-RT, which codes clinical drug properties, including mechanism of action,
                physiologic effect, and therapeutic category.</para>

            <para>RxNorm is the official HITSP standard for exchanging information on clinical
                drugs, using the combination ingredient + strength + dose form. RxNorm is freely
                available, and part of the UMLS, and can form a foundational component of an
                informatics architecture. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED&#160;CT transition to the IHTSDO</title>

            <para>In 2007,&#160;the SNOMED&#160;CT intellectual property
                rights&#160;were&#160;transferred from the College of American Pathologists to the
                SNOMED SDO® in the&#160;formal creation of the International Health Terminology
                Standards Development Organization (IHTSDO). The IHTSDO is a not-for-profit
                association that is owned and governed by its national Members. In January 2012
                eighteen countries were Members of IHTSDO, more countries are joining every
                year.</para>

            <para>SNOMED&#160;CT is now owned, maintained and distributed by the IHTSDO. Historic
                commercial proprietary concerns surrounding SNOMED&#160;CT licensing have been
                eliminated, enabling SNOMED&#160;CT to serve as a foundation for open informatics
                architecture. </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>IHTSDO open-source tooling</title>

            <para>In 2009, the IHTSDO made a software workbench open source. This open-source
                framework validated many architectural ideas, including change-set configuration
                management to support distributed development. </para>

            <para>The IHTSDO workbench validated a temporal model of </para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A time period datatype, including the ability to represent time periods
                        with no end (infinity or forever)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>System-maintained transaction time</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Temporal queries at current time, time points in the past or future, or
                        over durations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Predicates for querying time periods</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>


            <para>This open source environment includes a description-logic classifier, and
                distributed editing capabilities that can be leveraged in a architectural
                implementation that can be used to validate the architecture. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED CT Release Format 2</title>

            <para>In January 2012, SNOMED CT's RF2 format officially replaced the RF1 format. The
                new format has better features for configuration management of and reference
                extensions to SNOMED CT’s contents. This new format will accommodate evolving
                requirements without the need for further fundamental change in the foreseeable
                future.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>IHTSDO and GMDNA</title>

            <para>In 2012, the IHTSDO and the Global Medical Device Nomenclature Agency (GMDNA)
                responsible for the international naming system for medical devices (GMDN) signed a
                Cooperation Agreement with the IHTSDO, resulting in the use of GMDN as the medical
                device component in SNOMED&#160;CT.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED&#160;CT and LOINC agreement</title>

            <para>In 2013, the IHTSDO and the Regenstrief Institute agreed that they would work
                together to link SNOMED&#160;CT and LOINC. This agreement means that LOINC can be
                integrated into SNOMED&#160;CT by means of SNOMED description logic statements that
                define LOINC codes, and that these description logic statements will be a part of
                future SNOMED&#160;CT releases. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>VA interagency agreement with NLM</title>

            <para>In September of 2013, the VA and the National Library of Medicine (NLM) entered
                into an interagency agreement (IAA) to accelerate the pace of clinical terminology
                standards development and integration in areas that support Veterans health care and
                benefits determination. The VA has a long history of successful use of health
                information technology to support its mission and of effective collaboration with
                other federal agencies to promote the development and use of health data standards.
                VA seeks to accelerate the enhancement of clinical terminology standards and related
                infrastructure for internal uses such as clinical decision support, quality
                improvement, research and business processes and for external data sharing with key
                partners including the Department of Defense and VA academic affiliates across the
                country.</para>

            <para>Under the IAA, NLM will work with the VA to make specific enhancements to SNOMED
                CT, LOINC, and RxNorm in order to: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Modify and add to SNOMED CT and/or the US Extension to SNOMED CT, to
                            LOINC, and to RxNorm so they evolve more rapidly and effectively to
                            support current and emerging priority use cases for the VA and its
                            federal and private sector partners.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Coordinate enhancements to the IHTSDO Workbench/Open Tooling Framework
                            so that NLM and VA development efforts are mutually beneficial and
                            support more rapid improvements to SNOMED CT and more effective
                            integration of SNOMED CT with other relevant health IT standards.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Expand the content and capabilities of the NLM Value Set Authority
                            Center as needed to support more effective authoring, validation,
                            maintenance, and use of vocabulary value sets for clinical decision
                            support and other high priority VA use cases, as well as for clinical
                            quality measures.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Allow predicates for querying time periods</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>


            <para>The initial set of high priority tasks to be addressed by the VA and NLM under the
                IAA include: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Establish principled relationships between LOINC and SNOMED CT so that
                            they form an interlocking set to support effective integrated use by the
                            VA and other US health care providers.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Finalize specific rules and parameters for relating and connecting
                            LOINC and SNOMED CT content in the laboratory test domain.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Initiate analysis for other domains of interest to the VA.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Determine the magnitude and prioritize the changes that must be made
                            to LOINC and SNOMED CT to instantiate these relationships and
                            connections in light of the VHA’s priority use cases.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED CT, RxNorm, and LOINC</title>

            <para>Today, thanks to all the prior efforts of many individuals and organizations, we
                have an opportunity to leverage the combination of SNOMED&#160;CT, RxNorm, and LOINC
                as a coherent foundation for informatics architecture. There is still work to be
                done, as the integration of LOINC and SNOMED CT is only beginning, and how best to
                utilize RxNORM will require careful consideration. But the opportunity is
                compelling; we must take advantage of it. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Architectural Aspects</title>
        <para>Informatics Architecture is a clinical and technical discipline that is concerned with
            the <emphasis>representation</emphasis> of clinical knowledge, organization-specific
            clinical information, and patient-specific clinical data. Successful representation
            concerns a) the foundation of the architecture, b) how the representation is presented
            to&#8212;and manipulated by&#8212;the user, and c) how the representation is made
            interoperable with other environments. To meets these needs, we describe three aspects
            of informatics architecture: <emphasis>foundational architecture</emphasis>,
                <emphasis>interaction architecture</emphasis> and <emphasis> semantic
                interoperability architecture</emphasis>, respectively. </para>

        <para>Note that the role of the Informatics Architect differs from the role of other types
            of business and technical architects involved in the field of enterprise architecture
            (e.g., data architect, solution architect, enterprise architect, etc). More details are
            available here: <link
                xlink:href="http://blog.prabasiva.com/2008/08/21/different-types-of-architects/"
                >Different types of architects (available from:
                https://blog.prabasiva.com/2008/08/21/different-types-of-architects/)</link></para>
        </section>

    <section>
            <title>Foundational architecture</title>
            <para><emphasis>The foundational informatics architecture is the primary focus of this document</emphasis></para>
            <para>The foundational architecture is concerned with the taxonomy, classification, and declarative and procedural search of an information pool. This architecture lives
                within the logical architecture of the enterprise, but does not try to define the
                overall systems architecture, or the physical architecture that supports the
                foundational architecture.</para>
        </section>
<!-- ADDIN EN.CITE
&lt;EndNote&gt;&lt;Cite&gt;&lt;Author&gt;Gent&lt;/Author&gt;&lt;Year&gt;2007&lt;/Year&gt;&lt;RecNum&gt;35&lt;/RecNum&gt;&lt;DisplayText&gt;&lt;style
face=&quot;superscript&quot;
size=&quot;10&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/DisplayText&gt;&lt;record&gt;&lt;rec-number&gt;35&lt;/rec-number&gt;&lt;foreign-keys&gt;&lt;key
app=&quot;EN&quot; db-id=&quot;fzfdxe9z3a0rd9ewv5cx5w5ivesaftr2dpz5&quot;
timestamp=&quot;1378667225&quot;&gt;35&lt;/key&gt;&lt;/foreign-keys&gt;&lt;ref-type
name=&quot;Blog&quot;&gt;56&lt;/ref-type&gt;&lt;contributors&gt;&lt;authors&gt;&lt;author&gt;Andrew
Gent&lt;/author&gt;&lt;/authors&gt;&lt;/contributors&gt;&lt;titles&gt;&lt;title&gt;What
is Information Architecture?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;secondary-title&gt;Incredibly
Dull&lt;/secondary-title&gt;&lt;/titles&gt;&lt;volume&gt;2013&lt;/volume&gt;&lt;number&gt;6/27/2007&lt;/number&gt;&lt;dates&gt;&lt;year&gt;2007&lt;/year&gt;&lt;/dates&gt;&lt;urls&gt;&lt;related-urls&gt;&lt;url&gt;http://incrediblydull.blogspot.com/2007/06/what-is-information-architecture.html&lt;/url&gt;&lt;/related-urls&gt;&lt;/urls&gt;&lt;/record&gt;&lt;/Cite&gt;&lt;/EndNote&gt;<span
style='mso-element:field-separator'></span>< [endif]--><!--[if supportFields]><span
style='mso-element:field-end'></span>< [endif]-->
                
        <section>
            <title>Interaction architecture</title>
            <para>The interaction architecture is concerned with navigation, interface layout and
                functionality, and other aspects of the user’s information access experience. This
                document will only address the interaction architecture aspects of the authoring
                environment. The interaction architecture for end user applications, such as patient
                record systems or other clinical applications, is beyond the scope of this document. </para>

<!-- NEED TO FIX THIS: ADDIN EN.CITE
&lt;EndNote&gt;&lt;Cite&gt;&lt;Author&gt;Gent&lt;/Author&gt;&lt;Year&gt;2007&lt;/Year&gt;&lt;RecNum&gt;35&lt;/RecNum&gt;&lt;DisplayText&gt;&lt;style
face=&quot;superscript&quot;
size=&quot;10&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/DisplayText&gt;&lt;record&gt;&lt;rec-number&gt;35&lt;/rec-number&gt;&lt;foreign-keys&gt;&lt;key
app=&quot;EN&quot; db-id=&quot;fzfdxe9z3a0rd9ewv5cx5w5ivesaftr2dpz5&quot; timestamp=&quot;1378667225&quot;&gt;35&lt;/key&gt;&lt;/foreign-keys&gt;&lt;ref-type
name=&quot;Blog&quot;&gt;56&lt;/ref-type&gt;&lt;contributors&gt;&lt;authors&gt;&lt;author&gt;Andrew
Gent&lt;/author&gt;&lt;/authors&gt;&lt;/contributors&gt;&lt;titles&gt;&lt;title&gt;What
is Information Architecture?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;secondary-title&gt;Incredibly
Dull&lt;/secondary-title&gt;&lt;/titles&gt;&lt;volume&gt;2013&lt;/volume&gt;&lt;number&gt;6/27/2007&lt;/number&gt;&lt;dates&gt;&lt;year&gt;2007&lt;/year&gt;&lt;/dates&gt;&lt;urls&gt;&lt;related-urls&gt;&lt;url&gt;http://incrediblydull.blogspot.com/2007/06/what-is-information-architecture.html&lt;/url&gt;&lt;/related-urls&gt;&lt;/urls&gt;&lt;/record&gt;&lt;/Cite&gt;&lt;/EndNote&gt;<span
style='mso-element:field-separator'></span>< [endif]--><!--[if supportFields]><span
style='mso-element:field-end'></span>< [endif]-->
        </section>
    
    
        <section>
            <title>Semantic interoperability architecture</title>
            <para>The semantic interoperability architecture is concerned with the export and import
                of knowledge and data from this architecture to another that does not share the same
                semantic foundation. This <emphasis>semantic interoperability architecture</emphasis> would not be necessary if all systems shared the same
                foundational architecture, but such homogeneity is unrealistic at this time.
                Defining the semantic interoperability architecture will be a follow-on activity
                after the basics of the foundational architecture are defined and validated. As
                such, the semantic interoperability architecture is not a focus of this document at
                this time. </para>
            <para>While defining the particulars of the semantic interoperability architecture is
                not the current focus, we are concerned with builidng a foundation that will support
                semantic interoperability. We achieve this foundation in two ways: <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of SNOMED&#160;CT, RxNorm, and LOINC as the primary building
                            blocks for the foundational architecture.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Enablement of <emphasis>semantic operability</emphasis> within the
                            foundational architecture through normalization of representation and
                            achieving coherence within and among the primary building blocks of the
                            architecture.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist> Semantic interoperability of systems that do not share a common
                foundation may be challenging or unattainable. Although we may seek
                interoperability, it may be far easier to obtain <emphasis>semantic
                    operability</emphasis> through shared coherent architecture. The more common the
                foundations of systems that attempt to interoperate, the more likely successful
                interoperability may be achieved. </para>
        </section>

    <section>
        <title>Not all design is architecture</title>

        <para>As previously highlighted at the beginning of this document:</para>
        <blockquote>

            <attribution>Grady Booch</attribution>
            <para>All architecture is design but not all design is architecture. Architecture
                represents the significant design decisions that shape a system, where significant
                is measured by cost of change.</para>

        </blockquote>

        <para>The goal of defining the informatics architecture is not to specify all aspects of the
            system as they relate to representation or display of clinical information. Rather the
            goal is to provide an architectural foundation upon which higher-level designs can be
            safely based. Support for evolutionary change is a critical feature of informatics
            architecture&#8212;as support for changes in knowledge over time is a critical component
            of health informatics. Without this architectural foundation, we cannot advance beyond
            the circus of the menagerie. </para>

        <para>In the next section, we discuss the challenges that contributed to our current state
            of affairs, and present proposed solutions that may allow us to open the menagerie’s
            cages. </para>
    </section>

</chapter>
