<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <title>Operability</title>
    <para xml:id="para_t4z_wsk_dbb">The essential challenge of informatics practice within the
        healthcare enterprise, is to quickly deliver a high-fidelity reasoned interpretation of
        principles and facts to the point of care—and then to quickly aggregate these point of care
        experiences for analytic analysis so that new principles and facts can be formulated and
        validated as part of a continuous optimization of healthcare knowledge and delivery. To
        effectively answer this challenge, we must focus on simplification and integration of
        knowledge assets, and on build, test, deploy, and release processes for delivering these
        assets to the points of care and analysis. This focus on perhaps mundane topics is not
        because we think that novelty has no place in our work; rather, that without a focus on
        aspects of our delivery challenge that are often treated as peripheral to the overall
        problem, we cannot achieve reliable, rapid, low-risk knowledge-asset development and
        delivery in an efficient manner. </para>
  
    <para xml:id="para_w4z_wsk_dbb">The Veteran’s Administration ISAAC (InformaticS Architecture
        ACceleration) effort seeks a holistic approach to architecture that supports novelty within
        a rigorous—and vertically integrated—deployment pipeline that enables knowledge engineers,
        developers, testers, build managers, and operations personnel to work together effectively
        to deliver assets to the points of care and analysis. This pipeline must support integrated
        delivery of iterative revisions of specifications, services, and content which are today
        delivered by isolated silo organizations who place the implementation burden upon their
        consumers. This pipeline will be built from existing software-based best practices, and will
        embrace DevOps culture and practice by emphasizing collaboration and communication while
        automating the process of product delivery. ISAAC’s KOMET (KnOwledge Management EnvironmenT)
        realizes ISAAC’s architecture within a DevOps environment that integrates development,
        testing, publication, and delivery of specifications, content, and services into a
        vertically integrated environment that supports continuous delivery. </para>
    
    <figure xml:id="de117c5e-5b71-457b-88f9-1bb939f7ba72">
        <title>Overview of KOMET's domains of concern</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/content-services-specifications.svg"
                    align="center" format="svg" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <section>
        <title>Modularity</title>
        <para xml:id="para_ty5_lcy_dbb">KOMET defines a modular system and a service platform for
            clinical knowledge management that implements a complete and dynamic component model.
            KOMET provides an environment for the modularization of knowledge resources into
            bundles. Each bundle is a tightly coupled, dynamically loadable collection of
            terminology, terminological knowledge assertions, A-Box assertions regarding rules,
            transformation, and files that explicitly declare their external dependencies (if any).
                <link
                xlink:href="http://www.mkbergman.com/489/ontology-best-practices-for-data-driven-applications-part-2"
            />
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
