<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <title>Principia</title>
    <section>
        <title>Observation</title>
        <para>Definition: Observation is the active acquisition of information from a primary
            source. In living beings, observation employs the senses. In science, observation can
            also involve the recording of data via the use of instruments. The term may also refer
            to any data collected during the scientific activity. The human mind, and modern
            scientific instruments can extensively process "observations" before they are
            consciously surfaced to the observer. This unconscious or automated pre-processing of
            data makes answering the question as to where in the data processing chain "observing"
            ends and "drawing conclusions” begins difficult. For our purposes, we do not try to draw
            a line between “observing” and “drawing conclusions” because for our analysis purposes,
            the distinction is immaterial.  <link
                xlink:href="https://www.revolvy.com/main/index.php?s=Qualitative%20property&amp;item_type=topic"
            /></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Anatomy</title>
        <para>Definition: Standard (anatomy)…</para>
        <para>Definition: Measurement consists of using observation to compare the phenomenon being
            observed to a standard [not a normal range]. Measurement asserts something. These
            standards can be qualitative, that is, only the absence or presence of a property is
            noted, or quantitative if a numerical value is attached to the
            observed phenomenon by counting or measuring. The standard of comparison can be an
            artifact, process, or definition which can be duplicated or shared by all observers, if
            not by direct measurement then by counting the number of aspects or properties of the
            object that are comparable to the standard. Measurement reduces an observation to a
            number which can be recorded, and two observations which result in the same number are
            equal within the resolution of the process.</para>
        <para>Technique: Transform qualitative values to quantitative properties Function(x). </para>
        <para>[Age more than 40 years] scalar, [african american]:non-disjoint [male]:disjoint
            classs</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Concerns</title>
        <section>
            <title>Concern 1:</title>
            <para> Observation measurement</para>
            <para>We need a simple, and universally applicable way to represent  </para>
            <para> Technique 1.1: A quantitative approach (limit to Analysis Normal Form) </para>
            <para>As we’ve discussed: </para>
            <para>[0,0] absent [0,3] possibly present, but no more than 3 [0,∞] unknown [1,∞]
                present [4-6] 4-6 </para>
        </section>
       <section> <title>Concern 2:</title> <para> Identification of equivalent Observation Results is imperative to enable data analytics,
                decision support, and other secondary uses of data. </para>
        <para>Technique 2.05: Quantitative/Qualitative Concepts A transform function that will
            normalize a qualitative observation to a quantitative observation. </para>
        <para>Define F(qual) -> quant</para>
        <para>Technique 2.1 Inverse concepts Concepts which are considered opposites of another.
            Loosely based on the idea of a multiplicative inverse. Cooperative = 1/Uncooperative.
            Define Cooperative as the LEft Inverse Form (<acronym>LEIF</acronym>),
            and Uncooperative as the Right Inverse Form (<acronym>RIF</acronym>). We create
            editorial guidelines as to what constitutes a <acronym>LEIF</acronym> vs a
                <acronym>RIF</acronym> concept. We start out with a straw man rule that “Concepts
            that assert the positive are <acronym>LEIF</acronym> concepts, Concepts that are the
            inverse of a <acronym>LEIF</acronym> concept are <acronym>RIF</acronym> concepts.” By
            generically stating right and left hand sides of the inverse function Cooperative
            inverse Uncooperative -> <acronym>LEIF</acronym> inverse <acronym>RIF</acronym>, we have
            a semantically unburdened categorization, so <acronym>RIF</acronym> concepts are not
            required to negate something… And we are not bound specifically to our first straw-man
            rule of “asserting the positive” if we find better discriminators. </para>
        <para>F(<acronym>RIF</acronym>) -> <acronym>LEIF</acronym></para>
        <para>We then work to move RIF concepts to a set of RIF extensions. <acronym>RIF</acronym>
            concepts will be excluded from the normalized form, and must be converted to
                <acronym>LEIF</acronym> concepts as part of the normalization process. </para>
        <para>The Inverse function will apply specifically to an Observation Result. We won’t try to
            apply it to an expression for the purposes of using that expression in
            classification. </para>
        <para>Technique 2.2 <acronym>OWL EL</acronym> profile definitions and classification of
            normalized form</para>
        <para><acronym>OWL EL</acronym> profile with concrete domains supports multiple sufficient
            sets, and necessary conditions, and an ability to include concrete domains, such as
            ingredient strength, Concepts which have provably equivalent definitions by an
            appropriate classifier are considered equivalent.  </para>
        <para>Technique 2.3 Equivalence by generalization and subsumption </para>
        <para>Technique 2.4 Equivalence among post-coordinated and pre-coordinated expressions
             </para>
        <para>All post-coordinated expressions are converted to concepts with a single identifiers,
            and the equivalence of the post-coordinated and pre-coordinated expressions is
            determined through the classifier's computation of logical equality, and through use of
            the is-a taxonomy the classifier computes  </para>
        <para>Technique 2.5: Multiple sufficient sets, independent of the necessary sets</para>
        <para>Technique 2.6: Concrete domains</para>
        <para>Technique 2.v: Volume (hypo/hyper) Technique 2.w: Pressure (hypo/hyper) Technique 2.y:
            temperature (hypo/hyper) </para></section>
       <section> <title>Concern 3:</title><para> Identification of logical inconsistencies</para>
        <para/></section>
    </section>
</chapter>
