<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <title>Tools</title>
    </info>
    <para> Web tools vs desktop tools</para>
    <section xml:id="section_27598222-cf41-4802-a09c-11be0085c9a7">
        <title xml:id="title_e9c7df67-915b-4025-81b4-3c23af98c911">Knowledge Management Tools</title>
        <para xml:id="para_14f1329a-f9be-4f8e-813f-39a8c814b8a9">
            <link xlink:href="http://www.knowledge-management-tools.net/knowledge-creation.html"
                >Knowledge Management Tools</link></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>Web tools vs desktop tools</title>
        </info>
        <para>
            <blockquote xml:id="blockquote_63866628-6ded-4f8a-b815-dc33e63ed58e">
                <attribution>
                    <link
                        xlink:href="https://jaxenter.com/eclipse-oxygen-photon-ide-interview-135242.html"
                        >Interview with Mickael Istria, ‎Eclipse developer at the ‎Eclipse Foundation</link>
                </attribution>
                <para xml:id="para_f8fffc1c-f2fa-4095-945e-65d5b288c779">Some believe that web IDEs
                    will take over everything. While I agree about their upcoming success, I have a
                    more tempered opinion. I think as long as there will be trained developers and
                    workstations, classic desktop IDEs will remain because they’ll still be more
                    productive for many use-cases; just like Office suites are still there despite
                    Google Docs.</para>
                <para xml:id="para_5df3df0b-5227-49e4-a4e4-b4848abaf50f">I don’t believe the cloud
                    offering can easily fit all the needs of all the real experts of the software
                    development domain. They can for sure help newcomers or “amateur” developers,
                    but there will always be people more productive with a workstation and a desktop
                    IDE. Those developers are the target of Eclipse IDE, it’s important to keep in
                    mind who’s the target and to focus on serving this target. I see Desktop and Web
                    IDEs completing each other rather than competing one versus the other.</para>
                <para xml:id="para_5d8cd7e3-37f7-4b84-8ceb-5bc51ff167ef">However, latest IDEs have
                    brought innovation in term of internal architecture by improving separation of
                    concerns: VSCode has clarified the idea Language Server, Eclipse Che has created
                    the concept of full developer workspace (as a container). Those —initially
                    internal— architecture choices are important milestones in the world of dev
                    tools because they make a lot of sense for everyone.</para>
            </blockquote>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
