<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article version="5.1" xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <info>
<!--        <title>An Architecture for Managing Clinical Decision Support Knowledge Artifacts With Implications for Patient Safety</title> -->
        <title>Architecture for Managing Knowledge Artifacts</title>
        <subtitle>Principles, Tools and Processes</subtitle>
        <author>
            <personname>Walter Sujansky</personname>
        </author>
        <date>2017-07-05</date>
    </info>

    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>This report specifies an envisioned “future state” for the tools and processes used by
            the Veterans Health Administration (VHA) to manage knowledge artifacts in its clinical
            decision support (CDS) systems. A prior report<footnote xml:id="__EN1__">
                <para> Processes for the Management of Clinical Decision Support Knowledge Artifacts
                    With Implications for Patient Safety - Background, Best Practices, and Current
                    State. VA Knowledge Based Systems Group. March 31, 2017. </para>
            </footnote> described the current state of the tools and processes used by VHA for this
            purpose and identified certain gaps between VHA’s current practices and industry best
            practices for the management of software used in safety-critical medical devices and
            healthcare applications. As described in the prior report, the application of industry
            best practices is important to prevent errors and failures in CDS systems that can
            result in serious patient-safety risks. </para>
        <para xml:id="_Ref487113442">This report draws on industry best practices, as specified in
            the IEC-62304 Standard for Medical Device Software Lifecycle Processes<footnote
                xml:id="__EN2__">
                <para>
                    <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="https://www.iso.org/standard/38421.html"
                        >https://www.iso.org/standard/38421.html</link>. Accessed July 5,
                    2017.</para>
            </footnote>, as well as on software-development tools that have long been available and
            are commonly used in industry. The result is a consolidated “future state” architecture
            consisting of both processes and tools for the management of knowledge artifacts. </para>
        <para>Note that the prescribed architecture is not necessarily defined relative to the
            existing technologies, processes, and tools used for CDS at VHA facilities (i.e., Vista
            and CPRS). Rather, it reflects the general requirements of a system to manage knowledge
            artifacts in a safe and reliable manner, which could be applied to any number of
            specific software infrastructures, including commercial off-the-shelf systems.</para>
        <para><xref linkend="_Ref486590485" xrefstyle="select: label"/> of this report provides background and
            definitions that are relevant to the remainder of the document. <xref
                linkend="_Ref486442222" xrefstyle="select: label"/> characterizes the specific tools that are needed to manage
            knowledge artifacts in a safe and reliable manner consistent with industry best
            practices. <xref linkend="_Toc478715575" xrefstyle="select: label"/> specifies the processes for managing
            knowledge artifacts as prescribed by the IEC-62304 standard, and relates each process to
            the corresponding tools described in <xref linkend="_Ref486442222" xrefstyle="select: label"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="_Ref486590485">
        <title>Background and Definitions</title>
        <para>Knowledge artifacts<footnote xml:id="__FN1__">
                <para>The term “knowledge artifact” was introduced by HL7 in its specification of a
                    standard format for sharing and distributing decision-support rules, order sets,
                    and documentation templates (see <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Knowledge_Artifact_Specification"
                        >http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Knowledge_Artifact_Specification</link>).
                    The term is used more generally here, including but not limited to those types
                    of artifacts.</para>
            </footnote> are configurable units of biomedical knowledge (declarative or procedural)
            that are machine readable and can be processed by a knowledge engine to analyze data,
            facilitate clinical documentation, or support medical decision making. Examples include
            clinical alert rules, order sets, and documentation templates, as well as the smaller
            units of knowledge that these artifacts may depend upon, such as value sets, data-access
            functions, and orderable items. Knowledge artifacts also include the
                <emphasis>interfaces</emphasis> to EHRs, messaging applications, and other resources
            external to the CDS system that knowledge artifacts directly reference. The major types
            of knowledge artifacts are listed and described in <xref linkend="_Toc486430915" xrefstyle="select: label"
            />. </para>
        <para>Notably, knowledge artifacts do not include knowledge engines, i.e., the hard-coded
            software components that actually execute rules, order sets, and documentation
            templates. Nor do knowledge artifacts include the hardcoded software components external
            to the knowledge engine that store patient data or deliver messages on behalf of rules,
            order sets, and documentation templates. These components are also critical to the
            functioning of a CDS system, but are typically managed within the core
            software-engineering lifecycle of the EHR.</para>
        <para>Like other software artifacts, knowledge artifacts undergo a natural lifecycle in
            which they are designed, implemented, tested, released, used, and (when necessary)
            modified and re-released. Unlike many other software artifacts, however, knowledge
            artifacts are highly modular and configurable components that get added and changed
            frequently within a CDS system to meet the frequently changing requirements of clinical
            decision support. The fluid nature of knowledge artifacts within a CDS system, the
            significant degree of interdependence among these artifacts, and the patient-safety
            implications of introducing errors into the artifacts necessitate a highly rigorous
            process for their management.</para>
        <section xml:id="_Toc486430915">
            <title>Types of Knowledge Artifacts</title>
            <para>The major types of knowledge artifacts that determine the correct functioning of
                CDS systems is listed in <xref linkend="_Ref486590586" xrefstyle="template:Table %n"/>. The list includes any
                modular software object that could be independently managed and released and that
                may interact with other software objects in a CDS system. Note that the contents of
                <xref linkend="_Ref486590586"  xrefstyle="template:Table %n"/> may not be exhaustive.</para>
            <table xml:id="_Ref486590586">
                <title>Types of knowledge artifacts used in CDS systems.</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="31*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="69*"/>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center"><para><emphasis role="bold">Knowledge
                                        Artifact</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry align="center"><para><emphasis role="bold"
                                    >Description</emphasis></para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Clinical Alert Rule</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>An “Event-Condition-Action” rule. Upon the occurrence of
                                    some discrete triggering event (such as the refilling of a
                                    medication prescription), the rule evaluates whether some
                                    condition related to the patient is true (such as the patient
                                    having no recent lab tests that screen for a side-effect of the
                                    medication) and if it is true, automatically invokes some action
                                    (such as notifying a physician or ordering the required lab test
                                    directly).</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Order Set</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A collection of orders for medications, diagnostic tests,
                                    imaging studies, nursing interventions, etc. that should all be
                                    placed together in a particular clinical situation.
                                </para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Documentation Template</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A prescribed framework for documenting clinical
                                    observations or interventions in a particular context. These
                                    templates may specify the types of items that should be
                                    documented, provide pick lists, data-entry controls, or
                                    boilerplate text to facilitate the documentation of these items,
                                    and automatically retrieve certain patient data from the EHR and
                                    add it to the documentation.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Data Access Function</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A modular query command that automatically retrieves a
                                    specified set of data about a patient from the EHR and makes it
                                    available to the knowledge engine. For example, a query command
                                    to retrieve all of the lab tests performed on a patient in the
                                    preceding six months.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Data Manipulation
                                Function</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A modular algorithm that takes one or more data objects as
                                    input, analyzes or manipulates these objects, and generates a
                                    resulting data object as output. For example, a function that
                                    takes as input a set of lab tests and returns as output a
                                    Boolean value indicating whether at least one of the tests
                                    measures the blood glucose level. </para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Coded Clinical Concept</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A symbol representing a semantic concept in the realm of
                                    biomedicine that can be stored and manipulated by a computer
                                    system. Coded clinical concepts may include text
                                    descriptions/labels, as well as logical definitions with respect
                                    to other coded clinical concepts.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Controlled Terminology</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A collection of coded clinical concepts and certain
                                    semantic relationships among them, such as hierarchical
                                    subsumption (is-a), partonomy (part-of), association
                                    (caused-by), etc. </para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Value Set</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>An enumerated set of coded clinical concepts, such as all
                                    of the SNOMED codes that indicate a diagnosis of diabetes
                                    mellitus or all of the RxNorm codes for antibiotics that could
                                    be used to treat pneumococcal pneumonia. </para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Clinical Concept
                                Mapping</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>The representation of equivalence or subsumption among a
                                    set of coded clinical concepts from different controlled
                                    terminologies. For example, a mapping between the ICD-10 code
                                    and the SNOMED code for Type-2 Diabetes Mellitus.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Data Entry Control</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A user-interface control and related data model for
                                    recording a specific type of clinical observation, such as a
                                    blood pressure reading or smoking history.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Orderable Item</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A data model representing a specific type of orderable
                                    intervention (medication, imaging study, procedure, diet, etc.),
                                    including the set of modifiers for the intervention that
                                    must/may be specified (such as available dosage forms for the
                                    medication or imaging views for an x-ray). Orderable items may
                                    be included in order sets or ordered
                                individually.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>External System
                                Interface</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A machine-processible representation of the commands and
                                    the data objects that a knowledge artifact may use to interact
                                    with an external computing resource, such as an EHR, messaging
                                    system, terminology server, etc. Examples of external system
                                    interfaces include the database schema and data dictionary of an
                                    EHR or the application programming interface (API) for a
                                    messaging and notification system.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Ref486589560">
            <title>Terminology and Definitions Related to Knowledge Artifact Management</title>
            <para>Before describing the specific tools and processes of the future-state
                architecture, it is useful to define certain terms relevant to the management of
                knowledge artifacts in general. <xref linkend="_Ref204323820" xrefstyle="template:Table %n"/> lists a number of
                the terms that figure prominently in the specification of the future-state
                architecture that follows in <xref linkend="_Ref486442222" xrefstyle="select: label"/> and <xref
                    linkend="_Toc478715575" xrefstyle="select: label"/>. Note that certain of these terms may be entirely new
                or may be defined differently than in prior use or alternative contexts.</para>
            <table xml:id="_Ref204323820">
                <title>Terms and concepts relevant to the management of knowledge artifacts in CDS
                    systems.</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="29*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="71*"/>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center"><para><emphasis role="bold"
                                >Term</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry align="center"><para><emphasis role="bold"
                                    >Definition</emphasis></para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Knowledge Artifact</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>See <xref linkend="_Toc486430915" xrefstyle="select: label"/>.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Sub- Artifacts and
                                        </emphasis></para><para><emphasis>Parent
                                        Artifacts</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A sub-artifact is a knowledge artifact that another
                                    (parent) knowledge artifact directly uses and depends upon to
                                    perform its function. For example, a rule may depend on a
                                    data-access function to retrieve relevant patient data and on a
                                    value set to determine whether that data meets a specific
                                    clinical criterion. In this case, the rule is the parent
                                    artifact, and the data-access function and value set are the
                                    sub-artifacts. Note that sub-artifacts may, themselves, be
                                    parent artifacts with respect to other knowledge artifacts. For
                                    example, a value set used by a rule itself depends upon a set of
                                    coded clinical concepts from a controlled terminology. Note also
                                    that a sub-artifact may be used (shared) by multiple parent
                                    artifacts, creating the potential for many-to-many dependency
                                    relationships among parent and sub-artifacts.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>High-Level Artifacts</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>Knowledge artifacts that a knowledge engine can use
                                    directly to provide useful CDS functionality. For example, a
                                    complete alert rule, order set, or documentation template is a
                                    high-level artifact. Such artifacts may be comprised of
                                    sub-artifacts, i.e., other knowledge artifacts that are integral
                                    to their functioning. For example, an alert rule may include one
                                    or more data-access functions, and an order set may reference
                                    multiple orderable items. Note that certain high-level artifacts
                                    may also be sub-artifacts, such as a rule that is called by
                                    another rule or an order set that is contained within another
                                    order set. On the other hand, a single clinical concept or data
                                    access function would not be a high-level artifact, since it
                                    does not provide decision support outside of its inclusion in a
                                    rule, order set, or documentation template. High-level artifacts
                                    are distinct from other knowledge artifacts in that they require
                                    a safety-class designation (as discussed in <xref
                                        linkend="_Ref487105785" xrefstyle="select: label"/>).</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Source Artifact</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A collection of <emphasis>source objects</emphasis> (see
                                    below) that specify and describe a single knowledge artifact.
                                    The source objects that comprise a source artifact must remain
                                    mutually consistent and be managed as a coherent
                                whole.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Source Object</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A unit of information that is related to a specific
                                    knowledge artifact, that can be directly inspected and edited by
                                    a knowledge engineer, and that may be managed under version
                                    control. Source objects include the source code files for the
                                    artifacts, themselves (e.g., rules), configuration files listing
                                    other knowledge artifacts that the rules depend upon (such as
                                    value sets), documentation files describing the intent of the
                                    rules, test plan files describing verification processes, etc.
                                    Source objects are typically individual files, but could also be
                                    database rows or other persisted objects to which versioning
                                    meta-data are attached. </para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Compiled Artifact</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A source artifact transformed and packaged into a
                                    representation that can be directly loaded into and used by a
                                    knowledge engine. Compiled artifacts include an executable
                                    representation of the knowledge artifact, as well as meta data
                                    that may be useful when the artifact is combined with other
                                    artifacts in a functioning system, such as copies of or links to
                                    configuration information, documentation, source code, and other
                                    source objects. Note that certain source artifacts may be
                                    directly executable by a knowledge engine, such that the source
                                    artifact and compiled artifact are
                                        identical<emphasis>.</emphasis></para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Knowledge Module</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>A collection of one or more compiled knowledge artifacts
                                    that are released and made available as a unit for deployment in
                                    a CDS system. A knowledge module could comprise a single rule,
                                    several dozen value sets, or an entire controlled terminology
                                    consisting of thousands of concepts and relationships. The
                                    “granularity” with which compiled knowledge artifacts are
                                    combined into knowledge modules and released together depends on
                                    several factors, including the frequency with which artifacts
                                    are added or updated as well as the number of mutual
                                    dependencies among artifacts. Typically, greater frequency of
                                    updates calls for fewer artifacts in each released module,
                                    whereas greater dependency among artifacts calls for more
                                    artifacts in each released module.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Dependency Management</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>The representation and analysis of dependencies among
                                    knowledge artifacts. A complete depiction of such dependencies
                                    allows knowledge engineers to predict the effects of changing an
                                    artifact on other artifacts, enabling the sharing and re-use of
                                    sub-artifacts without risking inadvertent and harmful
                                    consequences when they are modified. Dependency management also
                                    helps to maintain a sound architecture within a corpus of
                                    knowledge artifacts (e.g., avoiding unnecessary dependencies,
                                    circular dependencies, etc.)</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Configuration
                                Management</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>The representation and analysis of dependencies among
                                    knowledge modules (i.e., compiled and packaged knowledge
                                    artifacts). A depiction of such dependencies enables knowledge
                                    engineers to ensure that the correct set of modules and versions
                                    of modules are used when testing knowledge artifacts and
                                    deploying knowledge artifacts into production environments.
                                    Rigorous configuration management helps to avoid, for example,
                                    testing a new parent artifact in an environment that uses one
                                    version of a sub-artifact and deploying it in a production
                                    environment that used a different version.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><para><emphasis>Release Management</emphasis></para></entry>
                            <entry><para>The orderly transition of knowledge artifacts from a
                                    development/testing environment into a production environment.
                                    Release management ensures that all testing, documentation, and
                                    approvals that serve as pre-conditions to releasing new or
                                    updated knowledge artifacts have been completed. It also ensures
                                    that all of the knowledge modules in a CDS system that were
                                    updated are released at the same time (including documentation).
                                    Lastly, release management ensures that the versions of the
                                    knowledge modules that were tested and approved are the same
                                    versions that are release to production.</para></entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="_Ref486442222">
        <title> Tools for the Management of Knowledge Artifacts in CDS Systems</title>
        <para>The complexity of knowledge engineering for CDS systems exceeds the capabilities of
            the unaided mind and demands robust tools to aid personnel in maintaining quality,
            avoiding errors, and quickly detecting and addressing problems. Today, most
            knowledge-engineering teams lack the full complement of tools they need for these tasks,
            although such tools are available and commonly used in other software-engineering
            domains. The envisioned future-state architecture for managing knowledge artifacts
            includes many of these tools, integrated into a coherent whole and specifically crafted
            to support best practices for knowledge engineering in CDS systems. </para>
        <section>
            <title>A CDS Knowledge-Management Architecture</title>
            <para>The architecture of the envisioned CDS knowledge-engineering environment is
                depicted in <xref linkend="_Ref486576210" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/>. The environment includes the following
                tools, which are described in the sections that follow:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Toc486430917" xrefstyle="select:  labelnumber title"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Toc486430918" xrefstyle="select:  labelnumber title"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Toc486430922" xrefstyle="select:  labelnumber title"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Toc486430925" xrefstyle="select:  labelnumber title"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Toc486430926" xrefstyle="select:  labelnumber title"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Toc486430927" xrefstyle="select:  labelnumber title"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><xref linkend="_Toc486430928" xrefstyle="select:  labelnumber title"/></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Note that each tool may consist of a <emphasis>repository</emphasis> (for storing
                knowledge artifacts in various states of development), an
                    <emphasis>engine</emphasis> (for performing certain “headless” operations on
                knowledge artifacts and related resources), and/or an
                    <emphasis>application</emphasis> (for providing display and data-entry
                capabilities for users). A variety of machine interfaces also exist among the tools
                within the architecture, as depicted by the arrows in <xref linkend="_Ref486576210" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"
                />.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref486576210">
                <title>An architecture for managing CDS knowledge artifacts. </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/image2.png"
                             />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Toc486430917">
            <title>Version Control Tools</title>
            <para>Version control tools<footnote xml:id="__EN3__">
                    <para> Kaur P, Singh H. A layered structure for uniform version management in
                        component based systems. ACM SIGSOFT Software Engineering Notes. Volume 34
                        Issue 6, November 2009. Pages 1-7.</para>
                </footnote> record all versions of software source files as they are created and
                undergo changes. They serve several purposes: They provide a shared repository of
                all the current and prior versions of each file, they communicate file changes
                across all the members of a software-development team, and they enable sets of files
                to be developed and tested concurrently in separate “branches” of the repository
                before they are incorporated into the overall software system. </para>
            <para>Version-control systems should serve similar purposes in the creation and
                maintenance of knowledge artifacts, which can be represented as sets of files under
                version control. Such files include alert rules, data-access routines,
                data-manipulation functions, coded concepts, value sets, information-model
                definitions, order sets, individual orders, documentation templates, and data-entry
                controls. Important meta data related to knowledge artifacts, such as requirements,
                documentation, configuration, and test cases, should also be maintained under
                version control, associated with the artifacts. Collectively, all of these files are
                    <emphasis>source objects</emphasis> that may change over time and, hence, should
                managed under version control.</para>
            <para>A variety of version-controlled systems exist for software objects, such as
                    Subversion<footnote xml:id="__EN4__">
                    <para>
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://subversion.apache.org/"
                            >https://subversion.apache.org/</link>. Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote> or Git<footnote xml:id="__EN5__">
                    <para>
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://git-scm.com/">https://git-scm.com/</link>. Accessed
                        July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>. Most such tools have similar data models and capabilities, as well as
                application programming interfaces that enable integration into larger software
                development environments. Whichever existing system is used within the CDS
                management environment, it should have the following features:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Unique object identification</emphasis>. Every
                        object under version control must have a unique identifier, and the
                        identifier must remain unchanged as the object is modified and different
                        versions of it are created and saved. Knowledge artifacts developed at
                        different VHA facilities should be assigned identifiers in different
                        namespaces to maintain global uniqueness among them all.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Version history retention</emphasis>. Each version
                        of an object must be persisted as the object changes over time, along with
                        meta-data indicating its version identifier, time of creation, creating
                        author, and branch of the version control system on which it was created
                        (see below). Further, every version of each object must remain available for
                        retrieval and inspection.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Version comparison</emphasis>. It must be easy to
                        compare two versions of the same object and identify all differences between
                        them. Among other things, this capability is important to determine whether
                        updates to a sub-artifact have changed its semantics in a way that may
                        affect the behavior of one or more of its parent artifacts. Ready comparison
                        is also important when merging two or more concurrent development efforts
                        involving the same knowledge artifacts (see below).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Branching capabilities</emphasis>. It must be
                        possible to create a virtual copy of the entire version-control repository
                        in a new “branch,” such that changes made to objects in this branch do not
                        appear in the original repository. This capability allows individual
                        knowledge engineers to make and test changes to knowledge artifacts without
                        affecting the work of other knowledge engineers or the integrity of
                        knowledge artifacts currently in production. This facility is critical to
                        the orderly and safe management of a clinical decision support system (see
                        example below).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Merging capabilities. </emphasis>It must be possible
                        to incorporate all of the changes made on one branch of the version-control
                        repository into another branch, such that any conflicts between different
                        versions of the same objects are detected and resolved. This capability is
                        important to enable work done by multiple knowledge engineers concurrently
                        to be combined and incorporated into the main branch of the repository. The
                        merging capability is also important to allow knowledge engineers to update
                        their local branches of the repository with changes that may have been made
                        by others to the main branch, enabling them to ensure that their own changes
                        will remain compatible with the latest version of the system.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>For example, <xref linkend="_Ref486583915" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> illustrates the process by which a
                set of knowledge artifacts could be edited concurrently by two different knowledge
                engineers, each working in a separate branch of the version-control repository.
                Engineer 1 working creates Branch 1 and makes changes to her copy of the knowledge
                artifacts entirely independently of the changes made concurrently by engineer 2
                working on Branch 2. Engineer 1 tests her changes, merges them back into the main
                (Trunk) branch of the repository, and releases a version of the system that includes
                her changes. Meanwhile, engineer 2 has continued working on his own project, unaware
                and undistracted by any of the changes engineer 1 made. At some point, he updates
                his branch with the new version of the Trunk (via a merge operation), thereby
                becoming aware of and reconciling his work with engineer 1’s own changes. After
                testing his updated changes, he merges them back into the Trunk and releases a new
                version of the system that includes both his and engineer 1’s changes. In this
                manner, the ability to branch versions of the source objects enabled engineer 1 and
                engineer 2 to work concurrently on their projects and to ultimately
                combine/reconcile their work in an orderly and safe manner.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref486583915">
                <title>Example of branching and merging in a version control tool, enabling
                    concurrent work. </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image3.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para><xref linkend="_Ref486584141" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows an example of tooling support to compare two
                versions of the same source object at the time they are merged, in this case a value
                set whose members differ. Note that the identifier of the value set is the same for
                both versions (“valueset_id103_amiodarone”), whereas the unique version identifiers
                differ (“dad5f3s” versus “1046bf0”). The comparison shows that the two versions are
                different, and the exact discrepancies between them, to enable
                reconciliation.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref486584141">
                <title>Comparing conflicting versions of a knowledge artifact in a version-control
                    system </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image4.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Toc486430918">
            <title>Compilation and Automated Validation Tools</title>
            <para>Before source artifacts under version control can deployed to and executed in a
                runtime environment, they must undergo certain transformation and processing steps.
                In the general software-engineering lifecycle, these steps are referred to as the
                “build” process<footnote xml:id="__EN6__">
                    <para> Smith, P. Software Build Systems: Principles and Experience.
                        Addison-Wesley, 2011.</para>
                </footnote>. A number of open-source and commercial tools exist to automate and
                facilitate the build process, such as Maven<footnote xml:id="__EN7__">
                    <para>
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://maven.apache.org/">https://maven.apache.org/</link>.
                        Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>, Gradle<footnote xml:id="__EN8__">
                    <para>
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://gradle.org/">https://gradle.org/</link>. Accessed
                        July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>, and Ant<footnote xml:id="__EN9__">
                    <para>
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://ant.apache.org/">http://ant.apache.org/</link>.
                        Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>.</para>
            <para>The build process for knowledge artifacts performs three functions: </para>
            <para>(1) It translates the artifacts into a form that can be directly executed by a
                knowledge engine.</para>
            <para>(2) It performs a number of automated validation steps to check that the compiled
                artifacts will function properly in the expected runtime environment (which may
                include other knowledge artifacts on which they depend). </para>
            <para>(3) It packages the artifacts into knowledge modules that contains one or more
                compiled artifacts, as well as meta-data needed to manage those artifacts.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Compilation</title>
                <para>Compilation is typically needed to convert source objects that can be directly
                    edited by knowledge engineers into alternative representations that can be more
                    efficiently executed by knowledge engines. The representations required by
                    knowledge engines can range from machine code to interpretable byte code to the
                    source code itself (the latter form requiring no transformation at all from the
                    source version). </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref486412590">
                <title>Validation</title>
                <para>The compilation process performs certain basic validations of syntactic
                    correctness and consistency, primarily to identify errors that would prevent
                    parsing or translation of the editable (source) form into a computable
                    (compiled) form. However, other important validation steps should also be
                    performed during the automated build process for knowledge artifacts.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Consistency checking with respect to sub-artifacts.
                    </emphasis>A configuration file associated with the knowledge artifact should
                    contain the unique identifiers and version numbers of all the sub-artifacts on
                    which the knowledge artifact depends. This configuration file, which is further
                    described in <xref linkend="_Toc486430923" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, should be accessible to
                    the build engine, as well as visible to knowledge engineers. During the build
                    process, consistency between the artifact being built and its sub-artifacts
                    should be validated by checking that any references to the sub-artifacts are
                    valid and correctly formulated. For example, if an artifact calls a data access
                    function to retrieve a patient’s lab results over a specific date range, a
                    validation check should confirm that the date parameters in the call are in the
                    correct format recognized by the data access function. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Automated Unit testing. </emphasis>Not all errors in an
                    artifact can be caught by the compilation and validation steps. For example, a
                    rule may inadvertently specify the wrong data access function, albeit with
                    correctly formatted date parameters. Alternatively, a rule may specify the wrong
                    combination of Boolean expressions for a complex alert condition, although the
                    expressions are syntactically correct. For these types of errors, automated unit
                    testing is a valuable additional part of the build process. As described in
                    <xref linkend="_Toc486430925" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, an automated testing framework enables
                    a set of tests cases specific to the knowledge artifact to be programmed and
                    automatically executed each time the artifact is built. For example, the test
                    cases for a clinical alert rule might use various combinations of patient data
                    to confirm that the rule fires or does not fire correctly in each case.</para>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref486584826" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows the results of an automated unit test
                    executed during the build process for an alert rule. In this case, the rule
                    compiled and executed correctly, but it referenced the wrong value set,
                    resulting in the failure of one of the unit test cases. The display shows which
                    specific test case failed and what test data were used in that case,
                    facilitating the debugging process.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref486584826">
                    <title>The displayed results from the automated testing of a clinical alert
                        rule, indicating a failure and the details of the failed test case.</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image5.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Packaging</title>
                <para>Upon successful compilation and validation, a knowledge artifact is ready for
                    use in a runtime knowledge engine. Artifacts in this state are stored in a
                    library or repository, from which they may be loaded into a runtime environment
                    for integration testing or production use. To facilitate the management of
                    knowledge artifacts in such repositories, it is helpful to package them into
                    knowledge modules consisting of one or more artifacts and containing a set of
                    related information for each artifact. This information should include:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The compiled knowledge artifact, itself, in a form ready for loading
                            into a runtime environment</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The unique identifier of the artifact and its version number, for
                            organizing the artifact in the repository and for referencing the
                            artifact from the configuration files of other artifacts that may depend
                            on it.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The configuration file that was used to build the artifact, containing
                            the identifiers and version numbers of any sub-artifacts on which the
                            artifact depends and with respect to which it was previously validated
                            and tested. This information helps to determine the environments in
                            which the artifact is known to function correctly.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Copies of or links to the source objects from which the knowledge
                            artifact was built. Access to these source objects allows knowledge
                            engineers to determine the specific contents or behavior of a knowledge
                            artifact within a specific knowledge module, as well as whether and how
                            the artifact was changed from a previous version of the module. This
                            information allows engineers to effectively and safely combine knowledge
                            artifacts from a knowledge module repository when those artifacts may
                            have been created or maintained independently of each other. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Toc486430922">
            <title>Configuration and Dependency Management Tools</title>
            <para>Clinical decision support systems are complex assemblies of knowledge artifacts,
                along with knowledge engines that execute the artifacts and EHRs, messaging systems,
                terminology servers, etc. with which the artifacts interoperate. Typically, numerous
                interdependencies exist among these components and even small changes to any one of
                them can undermine the integrity of the system and lead to software failures. It is
                therefore imperative to have tools that assist knowledge engineers to maintain
                consistency among the components as changes are made over time. </para>
            <section xml:id="_Toc486430923">
                <title>Configuration Management</title>
                <para>Configuration management tools<footnote xml:id="__EN10__">
                        <para>
                            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="http://www.sei.cmu.edu/productlines/frame_report/config.man.htm"
                                >http://www.sei.cmu.edu/productlines/frame_report/config.man.htm</link>.
                            Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                    </footnote> define the combination of knowledge modules that are mutually
                    consistent and must be deployed together in a runtime system to ensure reliable
                    functioning. As mentioned, a knowledge module is a particular version of a
                    particular package of knowledge artifacts that has been built and is ready for
                    runtime use. Configuration management files specify, for each knowledge module,
                    what other knowledge modules it depends upon. </para>
                <para>Based on the configuration files of all the knowledge modules to be used in
                    the CDS system, it is possible to determine the overall combination of knowledge
                    modules that must be available for the system to function correctly. Over time,
                    these configurations change as knowledge artifacts are added to or changed
                    within the system (i.e., new knowledge modules are added to the configuration,
                    or the version numbers of existing knowledge modules changed).</para>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref486585395" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows the configuration files (in the
                    “dependencies” pane) for two knowledge modules to be used in a particular system
                    – valueset.id104 and rulefunction.id8642. Each configuration file indicates the
                    set of other knowledge modules (including version numbers) that the displayed
                    module depends upon. </para>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref486585743" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows the configuration file for the entire
                    CDS system, which results from analyzing and reconciling the configuration files
                    for each of the knowledge modules that make up the system. By analyzing the
                    configuration files of each knowledge module and reconciling any discrepancies,
                    it is possible (and necessary) to arrive at a configuration of knowledge modules
                    that will allow all of the knowledge artifacts in the CDS system to function
                    correctly. Configuration management tools enable this process at any point in
                    time, and as individual knowledge modules get added or updated.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref486585395">
                    <title>The contents of configuration files (“dependencies”) for two knowledge
                        modules. </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image6.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref486585743">
                    <title>The contents of the configuration file for an entire CDS system.</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image7.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Dependency Management</title>
                <para>Dependency-management tools discover and display dependencies among the
                    knowledge artifacts that comprise a CDS system, down to a highly granular level.
                    These tools have some similarities to configuration-management tools, but go
                    further. Whereas configuration-management tools represent and manage the
                    dependencies between a knowledge module and all of the other knowledge modules
                    it depends upon, dependency-management tools can analyze dependencies among
                    individual knowledge artifacts within these knowledge modules. </para>
                <para>Most dependency management tools build a directed graph of dependencies among
                    all of the knowledge artifacts in an entire CDS system, which enables the
                    subsequent inspection and rules-based processing of the dependencies to assist
                    knowledge engineers. This capability enables knowledge engineers to better
                    predict, track, and manage the effects of even small changes to knowledge
                    artifacts. </para>
                <para>For example, <xref linkend="_Ref486585896" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows the dependencies that are
                    represented in the configuration-management files of four knowledge modules. At
                    this level, it’s only apparent that all three rule modules have dependencies on
                    the module that contains a library of data access objects (daos) for querying
                    the EHR. If a change were required to one of the knowledge artifacts (daos) in
                    the library, this information would only inform knowledge engineers that the
                    change could affect any one of the rules. </para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref486585896">
                    <title>A dependency graph among 4 knowledge modules. </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image8.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>In contrast, <xref linkend="_Ref486586057" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> and <xref linkend="_Ref486586412"
                    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> show how a dependency management tool can drill inside the dao library module
                    to identify and display dependencies between specific dao knowledge artifacts
                    and the rule artifacts that depend on them. The latter knowledge allows
                    knowledge engineers to determine which specific rules would be affected by
                    changes to a specific dao artifact, and therefore focus on only those rules when
                    evaluating the effects of the change.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref486586057">
                    <title>A dependency graph showing the relationship(s) among a set of rules and
                        one specific data access function within a knowledge module</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image9.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref486586412">
                    <title>A dependency graph showing the relationship(s) among a set of rules and a
                        different data access function within the knowledge module </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image10.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>At least one dependency-management tool (Semedy<footnote xml:id="__EN11__">
                        <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="http://www.semedy.com/">http://www.semedy.com/</link>.
                            Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                    </footnote>), exists that is specifically designed for managing knowledge
                    artifacts for clinical decision-support systems. Other existing open-source
                    tools (such as depan<footnote xml:id="__EN12__">
                        <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="https://github.com/google/depan"
                                >https://github.com/google/depan</link>. Accessed July 6,
                            2017.</para>
                    </footnote>) and commercial tools (such as Structure101<footnote
                        xml:id="__EN13__">
                        <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="http://structure101.com/"
                                >http://structure101.com/</link>. Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                    </footnote>) are designed for managing dependencies among the components of
                    conventional programming languages, such as Java and C++, but certain of these
                    tools may be configurable or extensible to also manage knowledge
                    artifacts</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Toc486430925">
            <title>Automated Testing Tools</title>
            <para>As discussed in  <xref linkend="_Ref486412590" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, automated testing is an
                important part of validating knowledge artifacts in complex and frequently changing
                CDS systems. Critically, automated testing allows knowledge engineers to quickly and
                reliably test and re-test knowledge artifacts as changes are made to them or to the
                other knowledge artifacts on which they depend. Although automated test cases are,
                themselves, small software programs that must be created and maintained by knowledge
                engineers, the effort is worthwhile in safety-critical systems because automated
                testing enables more frequent and more thorough re-testing of such systems as
                changes are made to their components. </para>
            <para>In the absence of automated testing, additions of or changes to knowledge
                artifacts must either (1) be bundled into large, infrequent releases to allow time
                for the slow, manual regression testing otherwise needed, or (2) be released without
                thorough regression testing, risking runtime failure of the new/updated knowledge
                artifacts or the failure of other knowledge artifacts that depend on them. Neither
                alternative is acceptable in a CDS system.</para>
            <para>A variety of frameworks exist to support automated unit testing of software code,
                including JUnit<footnote xml:id="__EN14__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JUnit"
                            >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JUnit</link>. Accessed July 6,
                        2017.</para>
                </footnote>, Mockito<footnote xml:id="__EN15__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://site.mockito.org/">http://site.mockito.org/</link>.
                        Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>, and TestNG<footnote xml:id="__EN16__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://testng.org/doc/">http://testng.org/doc/</link>.
                        Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>, and many of these systems are readily integrated with common
                configuration-management and build tools, such as Maven and Ant. Such frameworks
                would be valuable in automatically testing alert rules by introducing various sets
                of patient data into a test EHR, automatically executing the rules, and determining
                whether they fired or did not fire correctly (see  <xref
                    linkend="_Ref486412590" xrefstyle="select: label"/> and <xref linkend="_Ref486584826"  xrefstyle="select: label"/> for an example).
                When any configuration changes are made to any part of the CDS system, the test
                suites for all of the alert rules could be re-run to check whether the changes
                adversely affect the rule base. </para>
            <para>Other tools exist for automating integration testing of complete applications
                through simulation of the human use of graphical user interfaces. These tools, such
                as Selenium<footnote xml:id="__EN17__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://www.seleniumhq.org/"
                            >http://www.seleniumhq.org/</link>. Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>, AutoIt<footnote xml:id="__EN18__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://www.autoitscript.com/site/autoit/"
                            >https://www.autoitscript.com/site/autoit/</link>. Accessed July 6,
                        2017.</para>
                </footnote>, and TestComplete<footnote xml:id="__EN19__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://smartbear.com/product/testcomplete/overview/"
                            >https://smartbear.com/product/testcomplete/overview/</link>. Accessed
                        July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>, would be valuable in also automating certain testing of documentation
                templates or order sets to ensure their correct behavior. </para>
            <para>It is possible that customized versions of existing testing frameworks or
                customized interfaces to them may be needed to incorporate these tools into an
                environment specifically for managing knowledge artifacts. However, certain of these
                tools are open-source or highly configurable, likely allowing such customizations
                and interfacing.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Toc486430926">
            <title>Issue Tracking and Workflow Tools</title>
            <para>The creation and maintenance of knowledge artifacts for a CDS system is a complex
                undertaking that must be done carefully, reliably, and efficiently. The avoidance of
                errors and oversights requires a systematic and reproducible process, and adherence
                to a process requires appropriate software tools. Such tools must support the
                following general functions:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Issue Tracking</emphasis>: The recording and
                        prioritization of discrete issues that concern knowledge artifacts and need
                        to be addressed, including bug reports, change orders, and requests for new
                        capabilities. The formal tracking of such issues as they are addressed and
                        resolved, including their transition across various states (“submitted”,
                        “evaluated”, “implemented”, “tested”, “released”, “closed”, etc.). Note:
                        “Issue” is a generic term in the context of these tools’ capabilities, and
                        may encompass problems, tasks, or entire projects.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Communication and Sharing</emphasis>: The assignment
                        of issues to specific personnel during the course of their resolution. The
                        ability for personnel to seek review and receive approval of their work on
                        an issue. The ability to share with other personnel information or assets
                        related to an issue (such as software code or requirements documents), as
                        well as comments related to the resolution of an issue (questions, problems,
                        completion status, code snippets, etc.).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Workflow Support</emphasis>: The ability to define
                        and enforce specific workflows for certain types of issues. These workflows
                        specify the states that an issue may move through during its resolution, the
                        specific requirements for transitioning from one state to the next (such as
                        approval of a design or completion of testing) , and types of personnel
                        allowed to perform various tasks in the workflow (such as approving
                        requirements or performing testing).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Documentation</emphasis>: The ability to associate
                        relevant documents with a specific issue, such as requirements documents,
                        risk-analysis documents, design documents, test plans, release plans, etc.
                        The ability to maintain a change history for these documents as they are
                        updated during the course of resolving the issue. The ability to maintain an
                        audit trail of all activity related to an issue from its creation to its
                        resolution, including assignments, approvals, state transitions,
                        communications, and documents.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reporting</emphasis>:<emphasis role="bold"
                        > </emphasis>The ability to generate dashboards and reports based on current
                        issue-tracking data and past audit-trail data. The ability to track and
                        report metrics related to the knowledge engineering process, including types
                        of issues, average resolution time, personnel productivity, and conformance
                        to prescribed workflows.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Numerous commercial and open-source tools exist for issue tracking, such as
                    JIRA<footnote xml:id="__EN20__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira"
                            >https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira</link>. Accessed July 6,
                        2017.</para>
                </footnote>, Bugzilla<footnote xml:id="__EN21__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/"
                            >https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/</link>. Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>, and Trac<footnote xml:id="__EN22__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://trac.edgewall.org/"
                            >https://trac.edgewall.org/</link>. Accessed July 6, 2017.</para>
                </footnote>, which could be readily applied to the task of managing lifecycle
                processes for knowledge artifacts. </para>
            <para>For example, <xref linkend="_Ref486586067" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows a possible workflow for the
                creation of new clinical alert rules, modeled in the Jira issue-tracking system. The
                workflow specifies each of the states that the rule-creation process must pass
                through, and the gating criteria for transitioning from one state to another. Given
                the specification of such a workflow, the Jira system then enforces that each
                rule-creation project (“issue”) passes through each of these states, and each
                transition takes place only as allowed. For example, <xref linkend="_Ref486587526" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/>
                shows how the transition from “New Rule Requested” to “Request Approved” can only be
                performed by a staff member who has the “Administer Projects” permission enabled for
                her account. </para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref486586067">
                <title>A sample workflow for the creation of new clinical alert rules. </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image11.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref486587526">
                <title>A constraint in the workflow that specifies which users may approve new rule
                    requests.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image12.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Adherence to formal processes enforced by tools may take more effort in the short
                run, as it entails additional documentation, waiting for approvals, etc. However, in
                the long run, it saves effort by avoiding oversights, re-work, and low-priority
                distractions. More importantly, it maximizes the chances that all CDS knowledge
                artifacts released to production will function in a correct and safe manner. </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Toc486430927">
            <title>Performance Tracking and Analysis Tools</title>
            <para>Even with careful version control, configuration management, validation, testing,
                and adherence to rigorous development processes, knowledge artifacts containing
                errors may be released to the production environment. No amount of tooling or
                process can prevent all software errors. However, given the safety implications of
                errors within CDS systems, it is important to perform ongoing surveillance of the
                knowledge artifacts used in production to detect residual errors as quickly as
                possible. </para>
            <para>Tools that track and analyze the behavior of knowledge artifacts in use can
                greatly assist such surveillance activities. These tools should be able to perform
                the following functions:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Collection of feedback from clinician end-users and testers regarding
                        perceived problems or bugs in the CDS system; the means to submit such
                        reports as “trouble tickets” to the issue-tracking system used by CDS
                        knowledge engineers.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Automated and detailed logging of CDS events, in particular the invocation
                        and behavior of CDS alert rules and the circumstances in which they
                        executed; ability to review these logs and “drill down” on individual
                        events, including the specific patient data evaluated by the CDS
                        logic.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Automated detection of statistically significant changes in the rates that
                        CDS alerts fire; automated notification of the appropriate personnel when
                        such aberrations occur, with sufficient information to enable them to be
                        investigated and resolved by the knowledge engineering team.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Automated logging of rule overrides by users; statistical analysis to
                        detect changes in the rate of overrides or to identify rules that are
                        getting overridden an inordinate percentage of time (suggesting their logic
                        may be incorrect or insufficiently specific).</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The ability to automatically detect statistically significant changes in the
                behavior of alert rules is particularly important for identifying subtle errors. In
                the absence of such capabilities, the failure of an alert rule to fire in all
                applicable circumstances could go unnoticed for a long period of time. In these
                cases, only automated surveillance involving statistical analysis may detect such
                errors. </para>
            <para>For example<footnote xml:id="__FN2__">
                    <para>This example was originally published in the following paper and is used
                        here with permission of the author: Wright A, et. al. Analysis of clinical
                        decision support system malfunctions: a case series and survey. J Am Med
                        Inform Assoc. 2016 Nov;23(6):1068-1076.</para>
            </footnote>, <xref linkend="_Ref486588257" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows a scatter plot of the frequency
                with which a rule fired that alerted clinicians to the need for thyroid testing in
                patients taking the medication Amiodarone (a required screening test for such
                patients). Although not apparent from even inspecting the scatter plot, the rate of
                firing steadily decreased in 2011 and 2012 to a statistically significant degree
                (the time period indicated by the blue bar). In this case, a change made by the
                pharmacy in 2012 to the clinical code used in new prescriptions for Amiodarone was
                not properly reflected in the alert rule. This inadvertent discrepancy caused the
                rule to miss the increasing number of patients who were issued new prescriptions
                using the updated code (patients started on the medication prior to 2012 still
                triggered the rule). With the aid of statistical analysis, the discrepancy was
                discovered and corrected, resulting in the rate of rule firing to return to its
                correct levels in 2013.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref486588257">
                <title>A visual display of subtle errors in alert rules that may go unnoticed in the
                    absence of automated surveillance and statistical analysis. </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image13.png"
                            width="2.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Toc486430928">
            <title>Integrated Development Environment for Knowledge Engineering</title>
            <para>To maximize the convenience, and therefore actual use, of the tools described
                above, knowledge engineers should have access to them from an integrated development
                environment (IDE). This environment should share and link the relevant underlying
                data (such as the version-control repository, knowledge-module repository, and
                issue-tracking database), and enable knowledge engineers to view information from
                and issue commands to all of the tools from a single user interface. Note that
                certain of the tools may also offer alternative interfaces for use by personnel
                outside of the development team, such as the issue-tracking, performance analysis,
                and testing tools.</para>
            <para>The development of an appropriate IDE for managing knowledge artifacts will
                require the integration of tools with varying capabilities and (possibly) from
                various sources. However, there already exist examples of IDE frameworks for general
                software engineering, which can seamlessly integrate various tools and capabilities
                using a “plug-in” architecture (notably, the Eclipse IDE). It may possible to extend
                these frameworks to both customize them for the authoring/editing of CDS knowledge
                artifacts and to integrate them with existing tools that provide the types of
                version control, configuration management, automated testing, and issue tracking
                capabilities described above.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="_Toc478715575">
        <title>Processes for the Safe and Reliable Management of Knowledge Artifacts</title>
        <para>Availability of the tools and architecture described in  <xref
            linkend="_Ref486442222" xrefstyle="select: label"/> enables knowledge engineers to follow best practices for
            developing and managing knowledge artifacts used in CDS systems. This section describes
            those best practices and how the tools specifically support them.</para>
        <para>In 2006, the International Electrotechnical Commission (IEC) published a set of
            standard processes specifically for developing software used in medical devices and
            clinical processes. The “International Standard 62304: Medical Dev ice Software
            Lifecycle Processes” (IEC-62304)<xref linkend="_Ref487113442"/> applies not only to
            software embedded in medical devices, but to any software used in the “diagnosis,
            prevention, monitoring, treatment or alleviation of disease.” Hence, the IEC-62304
            standard provides an appropriate benchmark for the software lifecycle processes used to
            develop and maintain CDS systems, including the knowledge artifacts that drive the
            behavior of CDS alert rules, order sets, and documentation templates</para>
        <para>IEC-62304 address two complementary sets of processes, and both should be applied in
            the future for developing and maintaining knowledge artifacts:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Processes to characterize the risks associated with a knowledge
                    artifact</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Processes to achieve an appropriately low level of failure in the artifact,
                    given those risks</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <section xml:id="_Ref487105785">
            <title>Risk-Assessment Processes</title>
            <para>The risk model used by IEC-62304 is based on the proposition that a
                    <emphasis>software failure</emphasis> in a medical device or application may
                contribute to a patient-safety <emphasis>hazard</emphasis>, which may cause actual
                patient <emphasis>harm</emphasis>. </para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/image15.png"
                        width="3.0in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject> 
            </mediaobject>
            <para>In CDS systems, software failures result in knowledge artifacts <emphasis>failing
                    to</emphasis>
                <emphasis>prevent</emphasis> hazards and harms, rather than directly causing them.
                Nevertheless, the same risk model applies, and the IEC-62304 standard requires that
                a software safety class be assigned to knowledge artifacts based on the degree of
                harm that may result from their failure to function correctly.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Software Safety Classes</title>
                <para>IEC-62304 specifies three software safety classes:</para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="36*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="64*"/>
                        <tbody valign="top">
                            <row>
                                <entry align="center"><para><emphasis role="bold">Software Safety
                                            Class</emphasis></para></entry>
                                <entry align="center"><para><emphasis role="bold">Potential Harm
                                            From Software Failure</emphasis></para></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry align="center"><para>A</para></entry>
                                <entry><para>No injury or damage to health is
                                    possible</para></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry align="center"><para>B</para></entry>
                                <entry><para>Non-serious injury is possible</para></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry align="center"><para>C</para></entry>
                                <entry><para>Death or serious injury is possible</para></entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                <para>For purposes of this classification, IEC-62304 defines “serious injury” as “an
                    injury or illness that directly or indirectly (a) is life threatening, (b)
                    results in permanent impairment of a body function or permanent damage to a body
                    structure, or (c) necessitates medical or surgical intervention to prevent
                    permanent impairment of a body function or permanent damage to a body
                    structure.</para>
                <para>Note that safety classes are assigned based on <emphasis>possible</emphasis>
                    harm resulting from a software failure, regardless of the probability of the
                    failure occurring or the probability of the failure causing the harm. In other
                    words, a software system should be assigned a safety class corresponding to the
                    highest level of harm that the failure of system could conceivably cause. </para>
                <para>The purpose of assigning software safety classes is to guide which specific
                    software-lifecycle processes should be used in the development and maintenance
                    of specific software systems. The greater the potential harm that may result
                    from a software failure, the more rigorous the processes that one should employ. </para>
                <para>The IEC-62304 model for assigning and using software safety classes
                    specifically to knowledge artifacts raises two important practical
                    questions:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">In CDS systems, what specific components
                                should be assigned a safety class?</emphasis> One option is to
                            assign a single safety class to all of the components of an entire CDS
                            modality, such as the alert-rule modality or the documentation-template
                            modality. This approach would indicate that the lifecycle for all
                            individual rules or all individual documentation templates should be
                            managed using the same set of processes. A better option, however, is to
                            assign a separate safety class to each high-level artifact (i.e.,
                            individual alert rule, documentation template, and order set) based on
                            its specific contents, and subsequently apply only the workflow
                            appropriate for that safety class when creating and maintaining the
                            artifact. For example, an alert rule that advises a physician to
                            substitute a generic medication for an equivalent brand-name medication
                            might be assigned a safety class of “A”, whereas a rule that reminds a
                            physician to order monitoring tests when prescribing a potentially toxic
                            medication would be assigned a safety class of “C”. The approach of
                            assigning safety classes to individual high-level knowledge artifacts is
                            more efficient, in that it avoids the application of the most rigorous
                            processes for knowledge artifacts that have minimal patient-safety
                            implications. Note that sub-artifacts, such as value sets, individual
                            coded concepts, and data-access functions, will not be assigned safety
                            classes of their own, because they only function in the context of
                            high-level artifacts (see  <xref linkend="_Ref486589560" xrefstyle="select: label"/>), such
                            as rules and order sets. Therefore, sub-artifacts will automatically
                            inherit the safety class of the high-level artifacts that depend on
                            them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="underline">What safety classes should be assigned to
                                sub-artifacts that may be shared by multiple high-level
                                artifacts?</emphasis> Certain knowledge artifacts, such as value
                            sets and coded concepts, may be shared by multiple alert rules or
                            documentation templates, each with potentially different safety classes.
                            IEC-62304 specifies that, if a software system depends on the correct
                            functioning of a software component, then the component should inherit
                            the same software safety class as the overall system. Applied to
                            knowledge artifacts, this policy implies that sub-artifacts used by one
                            or more high-level artifacts should be assigned the
                                <emphasis>highest</emphasis> software safety class among those
                            high-level artifacts. <xref linkend="_Ref478710366" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows an example
                            of the correct application of this policy to the hierarchy of
                            sub-artifacts used by two rules with different software safety classes.
                            An effective dependency-management system is required to resolve such
                            inheritance relationships across many artifacts and lengthy chains of
                            dependencies to ensure that each artifact and sub-artifact is assigned
                            the appropriate patient safety class. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref478710366">
                    <title>Example of appropriate assignment of patient safety classes to
                        sub-artifacts. </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image14.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>Based on the safety class that a knowledge artifact is assigned or inherits,
                    it should be managed using the appropriate software-lifecycle processes
                    specified by the IEC-62304 standard. The specified processes fall into three
                    categories, as addressed below: Development processes, maintenance processes,
                    and cross-cutting processes that apply to both development and
                    maintenance.</para>
                <para>The sections below summarize each of the IEC-62304 processes that apply to
                    knowledge artifacts, and indicate which of the tools described in  <xref
                        linkend="_Ref486442222" xrefstyle="select: label"/> should be used in each process.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Toc478715576">
            <title>Development Processes</title>
            <para>The initial development of knowledge artifacts must conform to a careful and
                well-documented process to minimize the potential for error and failure when the
                artifacts are initially released to production.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Development Plan</title>
                <para>Specification and documentation of the processes that will be employed in the
                    development of each type of knowledge artifact (rule, documentation template,
                    data access object, value set, etc.) in each software safety class. Each type of
                    knowledge artifact with a given software safety class will follow the same
                    development workflow, which will include the required development phases,
                    approvals, testing processes, and documentation. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Workflow-definition feature of the issue-tracking and workflow tool.
                    Three distinct workflow processes will be defined for each type of artifact, one
                    corresponding to each safety class.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Requirements Analysis</title>
                <para>Determination and documentation of the <emphasis>clinical</emphasis>
                    requirements of the knowledge artifact, including the clinical purpose of the
                    artifact, the logic it will apply, the contents it should include, and the
                    actions that it should produce. The requirements-analysis process should include
                    a verification step to ensure that the requirements have been expressed fully,
                    consistently, unambiguously, and in a manner that enables the definition of test
                    criteria/test cases to evaluate correct functioning with respect to
                    requirements. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue tracking tool, especially its ability to associate requirements
                    documents with a tracked development project (“issue”), manage changes to the
                    requirements document, share the requirements documents with clinician experts
                    to solicit their review and approval, and require the approval of a clinician
                    expert before the next phase of development can be initiated. </para>
                <para>Assessment of patient-safety risks inherent in the new artifact (see Section
                    <xref linkend="_Ref486443481" xrefstyle="select: label"/>).</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Architectural Design and Detailed Design</title>
                <para>Specification of how the contents or logic of the artifact will be encoded.
                    Specification of how the knowledge artifact will be divided into sub-artifacts
                    (if applicable), and/or use any existing sub-artifacts. Specification of any
                    required interfaces among the sub-artifacts or between the knowledge artifact
                    and any required external resources. Design of any new sub-artifacts or of
                    existing sub-artifacts that must be modified. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue-tracking tool, especially its ability to associate design
                    documents with a tracked issue, manage changes to the design documents, share
                    the design documents with supervisors or other knowledge engineers to solicit
                    review, verification, and approval; IDE to inspect the existing available
                    sub-artifacts to use in the newly created artifact.</para>
                <para>Assessment of the effects of any required changes to existing artifacts based
                    on the configuration and dependency relationships of the overall system (see
                     <xref linkend="_Ref486443646" xrefstyle="select: label"/>).</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Unit Implementation and Unit Testing</title>
                <para>Implementation of new artifacts and required modifications to existing
                    artifacts. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Version-control system; IDE’s capabilities to browse the set of
                    released knowledge modules and associate the compiled artifacts within them with
                    their corresponding source artifacts in the version-control system; IDE’s
                    capabilities to author/edit knowledge artifacts and other source objects; </para>
                <para>Validation and testing of the implemented knowledge artifact (e.g., rule,
                    order set, etc.). If existing sub-artifacts needed to be modified or new
                    sub-artifacts implemented, independent validation and unit testing of these
                    artifacts. These testing processes should include clear acceptance criteria. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Compilation and automated validation tools; issue-tracking tool to
                    store the test plan and to document the test results associated with the
                    artifact; IDE to execute automated unit testing.</para>
                <para>If a sub-artifact is modified that is shared among multiple knowledge
                    artifacts, all of the affected knowledge artifacts should undergo regression
                    testing. For example, if a shared value set is updated, all CDS alert rules that
                    use the value set should be regression tested. Similarly, if many changes are
                    made to the data repository’s information model or to the contents of the
                    terminology, then many or all CDS alert rules may need to be regression tested. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Configuration and dependency analysis tools to identify any dependent
                    knowledge artifacts; Compilation and automated validation tools to perform
                    regression testing of those artifacts.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Integration and Integration Testing</title>
                <para>All components and sub-artifacts of the knowledge artifact under design should
                    be assembled and tested in a complete runtime environment. The results of this
                    testing should be documented. The rigor of integration testing and the level of
                    detail of the documentation associated with integration testing should be
                    commensurate with the risk associated with the knowledge artifact. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Automated testing tools; issue-tracking tool to store the test plan
                    and document the test results associated with the artifact.</para>
                <para>Integration testing should be conducted in an appropriate test environment
                    that simulates the target production environment as closely as possible,
                    including with respect to external runtime components, such as the data
                    repository and terminology server. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Configuration management tool to specify a runtime environment that
                    simulates the production environment accurately; repository of released
                    knowledge modules to provide the modules currently used by the runtime
                    environment; compilation and validation tool to build a runtime environment that
                    includes the new and updated knowledge modules from the development environment,
                    along with the released knowledge modules currently used in the production
                    system.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Release</title>
                <para>Assurance that all prescribed processes have been completed and documented.
                    Assurance that the version of the knowledge artifact that has been developed and
                    tested is the same as the version that is being released, particularly with
                    regards to any shared sub-artifacts or external resources whose versions could
                    differ in the test and production environments. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue tracking and workflow to ensure that all prescribed steps in
                    preparing a release have been completed and approved; configuration management
                    tool to ensure that the released artifact(s) are consistent with other artifacts
                    and components of the production environment; automated testing tools to execute
                    final testing in an environment identical to the target production environment;
                    IDE. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Maintenance Processes</title>
            <para>Appropriate change-management and artifact-update processes are at least as
                important as the initial development processes, because many errors in production
                CDS systems are related to modifications of knowledge artifacts that have unintended
                consequences.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Maintenance Plan</title>
                <para>Specification and documentation of the processes and workflow that will be
                    employed in the maintenance of each type of knowledge artifact. Each type of
                    knowledge artifact with a given software safety class will follow the same
                    modification workflow, which will include the required development phases,
                    approvals, testing processes, and documentation. . </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue tracking and workflow tools to guide and track adherence to the
                    prescribed processes, as well as to store the associated requirements documents,
                    test plans, etc.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Collection and Analysis of Data on Performance</title>
                <para>Monitoring of feedback regarding the use and behavior of the knowledge
                    artifact, including review of end-user reports and change requests, as well as
                    the active collection and analysis of log data to support automated
                    surveillance. Careful consideration of the patient-safety impacts of collected
                    feedback. For identified defects, creation and tracking of problem reports per
                    the problem-resolution process (see <xref linkend="_Ref478711911" xrefstyle="select: label"/>). </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Performance tracking and analysis tools; issue tracking tools to
                    collect the manually submitted or automatically generated trouble tickets on
                    behalf of the knowledge-engineering team.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Implementation of Needed and Requested Modifications</title>
                <para>Use of similar development process as for initial creation of knowledge
                    artifacts (see  <xref linkend="_Toc478715576" xrefstyle="select: label"/>), including requirements
                    analysis, solution design, dependency analysis, implementation, and testing.
                    Regression testing is a critical component of this process if any shared
                    knowledge artifacts or external resources were modified as part of implementing
                    the bug-fix or requested change. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue-tracking tool; Version control tool; configuration and
                    dependency analysis tools; compilation and validation tools; automated testing
                    tools; IDE.</para>
                <para>Release of modified knowledge artifact, either individually or part of a
                    wholesale version release of an entire CDA modality. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Configuration management tools; IDE.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Cross-Cutting Processes</title>
            <para>Several categories of processes apply to both the software development and
                software maintenance phases.</para>
            <section xml:id="_Ref486443481">
                <title>Software Risk-Management Processes</title>
                <para>Identification of each component of a knowledge artifact that could lead to a
                    hazardous situation were it to malfunction. Assignment of appropriate safety
                    classes to knowledge artifacts. Analysis of potential ways that failures in
                    knowledge artifacts could contribute to hazardous situations, including through
                    incorrect requirements or specifications, implementation defects, or reasonably
                    foreseeable misuse. Consideration of how changes to a knowledge artifact, its
                    sub-artifacts, or any external resources could result in artifact failures and
                    hazardous situations. Inclusion of 3<superscript>rd</superscript>-party software
                    components in this risk analysis.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue tracking tools, including document-management capabilities to
                    associate risk analyses with development and maintenance projects;
                    performance-tracking and analysis tools to identify historical risks associated
                    with certain knowledge artifacts.</para>
                <para>Planning and execution of risk-control measures, including appropriate
                    verification and testing processes. Documentation of trace-ability between each
                    potential hazard that could result from the software’s failure and the
                    risk-control measures implemented to reduce its probability.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue tracking and workflow tools; configuration and dependency
                    analysis tools; automated testing tools; integrated development
                    environment.</para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref486443646">
                <title>Software Configuration-Management Process</title>
                <para>Establishment of a scheme for the unique identification of configuration items
                    and their versions, such as alert rules, order sets, documentation templates,
                    data-access routines, value sets, information models, and terminologies.
                    Documentation of the set of configuration items and their versions that comprise
                    every knowledge artifact, which should be generated automatically from the
                    specification of the artifacts, not needed to be maintained actively by
                    personnel, which will be prone to error and quickly become outdated over
                    time.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Version control tools; configuration management tools; compilation
                    and validation tools; IDE.</para>
                <para>Explicit approval for any changes in the set of configuration items for a
                    knowledge artifact, and appropriate testing of such changes, including
                    regression testing (i.e., of other affected artifacts). Documented trace-ability
                    of any changes to configuration items with respect to the problem reports and
                    change requests that engendered such changes.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue-tracking tools; configuration and dependency analysis tools;
                    automated testing tools.</para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref478711911">
                <title>Software Problem-Resolution Processes</title>
                <para>Preparation of formal problem reports for each problem or failure detected in
                    a knowledge artifact. Investigation of each problem to identify its causes and
                    evaluate its relevance to patient safety, using the risk-management process.
                    Notification of user community regarding identified problems in CDS
                    system.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Performance tracking tools; issue tracking tools; test
                    environment.</para>
                <para>Characterization of the type of modification(s) needed (including urgency) and
                    preparation of a change request to implement the modification(s). Use of
                    software-maintenance processes to implement the modification(s).</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue tracking and workflow tools; tools for version control,
                    configuration management, testing, etc.</para>
                <para>Tracking and verification of the problem’s resolution, culminating in the
                    closing of the problem report. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tools:</emphasis> Issue tracking and workflow tools.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Summary and Next Steps</title>
        <para>The future-state architecture and processes described in this document are an
            ambitious vision for the management of CDS knowledge artifacts in a manner that
            minimizes software defects and maximizes patient safety. Although similar tools and
            processes have been implemented in mission-critical software systems in other domains,
            they have yet to all be applied for the management of CDS systems in healthcare
            settings. The implementation of this vision will require the careful assessment of
            available tools, desired workflows, and the manner in which they may be combined to
            optimize the management of CDS knowledge artifacts. </para>
        <para>The next phase of this work will lay out a roadmap for implementing the vision
            described above in a way that is consistent with the VHA’s current environment as well
            as its planned future health I.T. infrastructure.</para>
    </section>
</article>
