<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Use cases</title>
    <section>
        <title>Angina 1: ED Care</title>
        <para>This use case was created to evaluate the ontology created by the VistA Evolution GUI
            Research project. It includes common assessments, observations, interventions, and
            cognitive goals that arise while caring for a patient in this scenario to ensure that
            the ontology can accommodate these concepts. All clinical data in this use case is
            synthetic. Data was created to support the flow of this use case and provide examples of
            clinical observations that are documented throughout the interaction. Clinical decision
            making in this use case is based, primarily, on VA/DoD Clinical Practice Guidelines for
            the Management of Ischemic Heart Disease, available at:
            http://www.healthquality.va.gov/guidelines/CD/ihd/ Additional clinical resources are
            listed below in the Reference section. The intent of this use case is to capture actions
            that commonly occur when a patient presents with unstable angina. Many of the steps in
            this use case occur concurrently in an emergent case. In similar scenarios, the same
            actions may occur in slightly different order. Cognitive goals are included in some
            ‘Actions’ to provide insight on the Provider or healthcare professional’s mental process
            at that point of the encounter. Hyperlinks are included to provide examples of the data
            fields and values that may be entered by the EHR user during this step of the use case.
            Hyperlinks suggest standardized terminologies that may be used to capture data in this
            step of the use case.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Actors</title>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Patient</title>
                <para>A person receiving or registered to receive medical treatment</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Provider</title>
                <para>Physician, physician assistant (PA), or nurse practitioner (NP). All are
                    skilled health-care professionals trained and licensed to diagnose and treat
                    patients within their defined scope of practice. </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Registration Clerk (Reg. Clerk)</title>
                <para>A hospital employee that collects demographic, insurance and “reason for
                    visit” information from a new patient and enters this information in to the
                    Admission/Discharge/Transfer (ADT) system and/or the electronic health record
                    (EHR). </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Triage Nurse (Triage RN)</title>
                <para>A licensed nurse that assesses symptoms, health-related complaints, and vital
                    signs to determine the degree of urgency for care.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Unit Clerk (UC)</title>
                <para>A hospital employee that performs administrative duties to facilitate workflow
                    and patient care in the emergency department (ED) or a nursing unit.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Emergency Department Technician (ED Tech)</title>
                <para>A hospital employee that is trained to provide basic tasks such as vital signs
                    and laboratory draws under the supervision of an RN or Provider.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Registered Nurse (RN)</title>
                <para>A licensed healthcare professional that is trained to provide nursing care to
                    patients in inpatient and outpatient settings, within their defined scope of
                    practice.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Licensed Social Worker (LSW)</title>
                <para>A licensed healthcare professional that assists patients to improve their
                    quality of life and social needs, and facilitates care after discharge.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Nurse’s Aide/Assistant (NA)</title>
                <para>A trained healthcare worker that provides assistance with patient care, under
                    the supervision of an RN.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Clinical Pharmacist</title>
                <para>A licensed healthcare professional that often collaborates with physicians and
                    other healthcare professionals to coordinate pharmaceutical interventions and
                    promote health and disease prevention within their scope of practice.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Dispensing Pharmacist</title>
                <para>A licensed healthcare professional that dispenses medications, monitors
                    medication parameters and potential drug interactions, and provides information
                    about medications, within their scope of practice.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Radiology Technician (Rad Tech)</title>
                <para>A licensed radiography professional that performs diagnostic imaging exams on
                    patients to help physicians assess illness and injury.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Radiologist</title>
                <para>A licensed physician that specializes in diagnosing and treating diseases and
                    injuries by using medical imaging.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>EKG Technician (EKG Tech)</title>
                <para>A cardiology technologist that administers basic electrocardiogram tests to
                    patients. The results are then read by a cardiologist or other licensed
                    physician.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Respiratory Therapist (RT)</title>
                <para>A licensed healthcare practitioner that provides care and treatment to
                    patients requiring breathing and oxygenation support.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Charge RN</title>
                <para>A registered nurse that is responsible for the efficient management of a
                    nursing unit or department, including admissions, discharges, and the oversight
                    of all nursing and support staff.</para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Description</title>
            <para>53 year old white male presents to the ED with chest pain and is diagnosed as
                having a ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI)</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Trigger</title>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patient is brought to the ED by their family member</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patient is experiencing crushing chest pain (radiating to their jaw
                            and neck), shortness of breath (dyspnea), nausea, and sweating
                            (diaphoresis) after attempting to shovel their front walkway.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Preconditions</title>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Patient has a history of stable angina that is usually relieved by rest, however the above symptoms worsened with rest.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Patient has taken one sublingual (SL) nitroglycerin (NTG) tablet, without relief.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Postconditions</title>
            <section>
                <title>Minimal guarantees</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Data fields required to support this clinical workflow will be present in the EHR. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Data entered will be stored utilizing the appropriate clinical terminology.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Success guarantees</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>EHR supports patient-centered care, guided by goals set by the patient</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patient receives evidence-based care based on the health concerns that are noted during the outpatient visit.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patient will achieve improved outcomes and satisfaction as a result of care facilitated by EHR functionality.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Normal flow</title>
            <para>To be input</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Data fields required</title>
            <para>To be input</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>References for Clinical Management of Ischemic Heart Disease </title>
            <para>To be input</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Additional References</title>
            <para>To be input</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Angina 2: Telemetry Care</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>CHF: ED</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>CHF: IMC</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Depression: Outpaitent follow-up</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>DM 1: Diagnosis of diabetes</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>DM 2: Follow-up outpatient visit</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>DM 3: Referral for annual podiatry screening</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>DM 4: Care coordinator telephone follow-up</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </section>

</appendix>
