<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

    
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

  <title>Appendix A - Glossary</title>

  <table frame='all' xml:id="cimi_glossary_0135">
    <title>Glossary</title>
    <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="2*"/>
      <colspec colname='c2' />
      <colspec colname='c3' colwidth="5*" />
      <thead>
        <row>
          <!-- <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2" align="center">Horizontal Span</entry> -->

          <entry align="center">Term</entry>
          <entry align="center">Acronym</entry>
          <entry align="center">Definition</entry>

        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>Archetype</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>A re-usable, formal model of a concept expressed as a computable constraint model defined in ADL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Archetype Definition Language</entry>
          <entry>ADL</entry>
          <entry>ADL is a formal language for expressing archetypes. It provides a formal, textual syntax for describing constraints on any domain entity whose data is described by an information model</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Attribute</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>A field in any class</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Clinical Information Modelling Initiative</entry>
          <entry>CIMI</entry>
          <entry>An initiative established to improve the interoperability of healthcare information systems through shared implementable clinical information models</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Clinical Statement</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>Structured electronic communication made about a patient typically documented as an 'entry' in the patient record</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Complex Clinical Statement</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>A statement that is composed of parts where each part can only be fully understood in the context of its parent</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Compound Clinical Statement</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>A clinical statement composed of one or more clinical statements that may exist outside of the containing parent statement</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Constraint Model</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>A formal specification used for describing constraints on an Underlying Reference Model. The Constraint Model is used to express clinical information models (i.e. archetypes)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Context</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>The circumstances that form the setting in which the ‘topic’ should be evaluated</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Detailed Clinical Model</entry>
          <entry>DCM</entry>
          <entry>A relatively small, standalone information model designed to express a precise clinical concept in a standardized and reusable manner</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Governance</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>The use of a set of processes, customs, policies, laws and institutions to direct the way people administer </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Isosemantic Models</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>A model that, while different in structure, represents the same semantic content as a second model</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Key</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>The main concept of interest in a clinical statement, about which the other attributes and relationships provide additional information </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Meta</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>Attribution information relating to the statement itself such as who authored, verified, recorded, or signed the statement. Meta includes the who, where, why and when information</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Terminology Binding</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>The assertion of a relationship between the information model and the terminology</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Topic</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>The clinical entity described by the Clinical Statement e.g. clinical assertions, evaluations results, and procedures</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Topic Pattern</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>Attributes required to fully describe a clinical entity</entry>
        </row>

      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

</section>
  

