<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

    
    
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <sect2>
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>
            The Clinical Information Modeling Initiative (CIMI) is an HL7 group that is defining a library of detailed clinical information models using a common modeling formalism. CIMI was established to improve the interoperability of healthcare information systems through shared implementable clinical information models that can be used to generate platform-specific model specifications such as FHIR profiles or CDA templates. These models are grouped into semantically equivalent (or ‘isosemantic’) families of clinical models, which capture the same clinical meaning using different combinations of concept pre-coordination and corresponding information model structure.
        </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
    
        <title>Purpose</title>

        <para>
            The purpose of the CIMI Modeling and Style Guide is to allow the reader to understand the big picture behind the CIMI Models and to enlighten interested CIMI stakeholders regarding CIMI model terms, models, representations, and approaches among CIMI participants.  In this document we begin with broad-brush stroke description of the basics of the CIMI models and follow with the more technical aspects of CIMI modeling including the modeling patterns. 
        </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
    
        <title>Scope</title>

        <para>
            This document presents the specification of the Clinical Statement Pattern and the Topic/Context Pattern that are used to create detailed clinical models (DCMs). The CIMI models consist of computer processable language syntaxes structured as high level patterns that are either complete or under development and include:


        </para>
    

        <itemizedlist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Structured Data (Clusters).
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The Clinical Statement Pattern.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Topic Patterns.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Context Patterns.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Terminology Bindings.
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>

 
        <title>Audience</title>

        <para>
            The intended audience for this document is anyone trying to understand, develop, and/or use CIMI models. This includes:

            
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Modelers creating new models.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Modelers who have developed models in a different format and are transforming their existing models into CIMI models.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                FHIR profile developers who are transforming CIMI models into FHIR profiles.
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  

</section>