<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

  
    
  <title>Metadata</title>

  <para>
    The final division of the Clinical Statement pattern is the metadata which is a collection of attribution/provenance information regarding the topic/context being described by the clinical statement.
  </para>

           
  <sect2>
    <title>The CIMI Attribution/Provenance patterns</title>

    <para>
        In the CIMI model, provenance information is represented by the Attribution class shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_attibution_0135"/>. The Attribution class provides a pattern for the capture of provenance information such as the what, who, when, where, why, and how associated with a particular activity – e.g., provenance attributes about the verification of a clinical statement (e.g. the provider performing the surgery in O.R. suite 6).
    </para>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_attibution_0135">
                <title>Attribution Class</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/attribution.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="40%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

    <para> 
        CIMI currently includes two attribution patterns:
    </para>

    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Attribution information as a part of the clinical statement – In this pattern, the ClinicalStatement pattern contains a number of attributes of type Attribution (e.g., ClinicalStatement.authored and ClinicalStatement.verified). This pattern provides a consistent way to capture attribution information that extends beyond simply the agent of an activity (e.g., the author). When attribution is part of the ClinicalStatement model, any change to the attribution for an activity will result in a version change.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Attribution information external to the clinical statement - CIMI allows the capture of provenance information external to the clinical statement through the Provenance class. The provenance class contains the Attribution class and provides pointers to one or more clinical statements (e.g., the Provenance.target attribute). This pattern allows the addition and modification of provenance information associated with a clinical statement without impacting its version.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>


 </sect2>
   
    

</section>