<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<section version="5.1" xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>FHIR Implementation for Patient Safety</title>
  <synopsis> </synopsis>
  <para>This chapter identifies a set of options involving FHIR implementation constructs and
    approaches that can leverage to improve the semantic precision of FHIR resources using
    Solor-based semantic constraints.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Background</title>
    <para> Similar to other interoperability standards, HL7 Fast Healthcare Interoperability
      Resources (FHIR) provide a great of flexibility to implementers: a choice of services,
      optional data elements, minimal terminology constraints, and extensions – including modifiers
      – are wide open. However, while flexibility is useful to promote standards adoption, it leads
      to ambiguity, lack of semantic consistency, and poor patient outcomes. Therefore, successful
      standards implementations that support patient safety require rigorous conformance using
      profiles organized into implementation guides. </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>FHIR Conformance Methodology</title>
    <para> The concept of “profiling” a standard for a use case and to address specific requirements
      it used broadly standards like DICOM, NCPDP, and HL7 message, document, resources.
      Best-practices over the past decades define a profile (or template) as an unambiguous
      specification of a standard structure that has been analyzed for particular set of
      requirements. It prescribes a set of precise constraints upon the standard thus ensuring the
      implementation is testable and the semantics are precise. The constraints affect the presence,
      occurrences, and meaning of the data elements. Since FHIR is also a standard-based Application
      Programming Interface and a Data Services standards, conformance also describes the services
      supported by a FHIR server. FHIR conformance is documented using FHIR several definitional
      resources: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><citation>ImplementationGuide</citation>: this resource is used todescribe an
            implementation guide and references any profiles including extensions required by to
            meet the purpose of the implementation guide.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citation> StructureDefinition</citation>: this resurce to describe profiles of FHIR
            resources that contain how data elements, references, and extensions are supposed to
            instantiated. Profiles provide terminology bindings for coded data elements – using
            ValueSet resources. Conformance predicates to validate FHIR based on CIMI models and
            Solor could be created using FHIRPath. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><citation>ValueSet</citation>: this resources is used to describe a value set. Value
            sets reference concepts specified <citation>CodeSystem</citation> including external
            code systems like SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm, etc. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para> Profiling FHIR can more effective a family of a profiles are derived from a common set of
      base profiles as seen in <xref linkend="Profiling_method"/> . This methodology ensures that
      organizations and vendors are able to adopt common/national requirements. Similarly, an
      organization like VA could create a set of profiles derived from national profiles. Project
      and application may create further specializations of organization profiles that inherit the
      base profiles specifications. FHIR allows implementation guides to redefine what it means to
      support a data element. It allows VA to create profiles and implementation guides that are
      explicitly intended to promote patient safety. </para>
    <figure xml:id="Profiling_method">
      <title>FHIR Profiling Methodology</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/profiling_method.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="95%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>The US Core Implementation Guide introduces a reusable set of profiles that address
      national regulatory requirements (i.e. Meaningful Use 2015). US implementers can use them as
      the starting point for additional constraints or extensions. For instance, the VA may create
      extension specific to military service, Veteran care to ensure interoperability with DoD and
      other community providers. The only way to accomplish this level of patient-centered
      information exchange is to create precise implementation guides that leverage Solor. Since
      standards represent a union of data and interoperability requirements, implementers need to
      constrain or extend a standard consistent with their requirements. The more constrained and
      precise a profile, the more likely it is that resources that conform to those profiles will be
      semantically interoperable. such that the source and consuming system interpret the data in
      same way and present it to clinicians in the same context. Common meaning requires common
      semantics, assumptions, and data elements. Profiles are therefore the must-have element of
      successful implementation.</para>
    <para>FHIR conformance concepts and resources that were approved as Normative in FHIR Release 5
      (January 2019). This fact provides a stable foundation for creating implementation guides,
      profile, and value sets that illustrate best practices for semantic interoperability. Such
      example profiles and resources can guide a next generation of application developers and
      integrators. FHIR is an emerging a specification information exchange and for application
      development and systems built from the ground up on standard-based concepts. </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>HL7 engagement: FHIR implementations using Solor</title>
    <para>Based on an analysis of FHIR Release 4 and considering the roadmap for Release 5, there
      several important options to employ Solor in FHIR implementation guide development: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>FHIR conformance provides a mechanism to eliminate ambiguity, increase precision,
            and manage extensions. Filter-based, enumerated, and aggregated value sets are support
            by Terminology Servers. Solor assemblages could become the basis for FHIR ValueSets that
            use rigorous versioning based on globally-unique canonical identifiers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>All the resources needed to implement FHIR have reached Normative status in Release
            4. Only two business-related resource have reached that status: Observation and Patient.
            Other resources are still in “Trial Use” and will reach Normative status after 2020. The
            VA could leverage Solor to propose value set bindings that improve the clarity of FHIR
            resources and US-realm profiles managed by the US Realm Taskforce.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> The VA will also be responsible for managing/governance of VA-specific profiles and
            implementation guides. Solor assemblages may be used to provide precise vocabulary
            bindings for coded data elements needed to address VA-specific requirements. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Solor and CIMI models may be used to specify FHIR profile and data validation
            predicates using FHIRPath: standard-based, platform-neutral navigation and data
            validation language using syntax-generator(ANTLR) grammar. FHIRPath is standard-based
            notation already used to specify invariant for FHIR resources. It is also applicable to
            conformance predicates, logical expressions, and filters. It can be used to express
            additinal contrainst on data capture and validation rules can be specified and processed
            are runtime. <figure>
              <title>FHIR Resource Invariant</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/FHIRPath_resource_invariants.jpg" align="center"
                    format="jpg" width="95%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Future work to produce SNOMED CT value sets using Solor assemblages is permitted
            under the agreement HL7 and IHTSDO. Publishing best-practices as value sets,
            implementation guides, and profiles will improve the quality treatment data such that
            it’s can be shared among provider to improve outcomes and promote patient safety.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
