<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article version="5.0" xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <info>
        <title>“Data Element” Modeling and Its Relationship to Clinical Domain Models and SOLOR</title>
        <author>
            <personname>Walter Sujansky</personname>
        </author>
        <date>2017-10-23</date>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Recently, there has been lively discussion regarding the appropriate role of “clinical
            data elements” and forms-based data collection as a data-representation system for EHRs.
            This white paper attempts to characterize the “data-element” model for representing
            clinical data, and assess its strengths and weaknesses relative to alternative models,
            particularly with regards to supporting data retrieval and analysis. The paper also
            provides general recommendations for retaining the advantages of data elements for data
            collection, while mitigating their limitations for data analysis.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Data Elements</title>
        <para>“Data element” is a longstanding concept used in information technology and data
                modeling<footnote xml:id="__EN1__">
                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_element"
                        >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_element</link>. </para>
            </footnote>. Recently, the definition and use of data elements has been proposed as the
            basis for structured data capture within EHRs and other clinical applications.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Context for Recent Consideration of Data Elements: Structured Data
                Capture</title>
            <para>In 2013, the Office of the National Coordinator (ONC) Standards &amp;
                Interoperability (S&amp;I) Framework launched an initiative to develop “Structured
                Data Capture” standards for EHRs<footnote xml:id="__EN2__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://oncprojectracking.healthit.gov/wiki/display/TechLabSC/SDC+Home"
                            >https://oncprojectracking.healthit.gov/wiki/display/TechLabSC/SDC+Home</link>.
                    </para>
                </footnote>. The purpose of structured data capture (SDC) in the context of this
                initiative was to enable the collection of structured data within EHRs <emphasis>to
                    supplement data collected for other purposes, including clinical research,
                    adverse event reporting, and public health reporting</emphasis>. In other words,
                SDC was not intended as a model for primary data entry into EHRs, but rather as a
                mechanism to collect data from EHRs and/or from the users of EHRs for secondary
                purposes, such as research and specific reporting needs. </para>
            <para><xref linkend="_Ref493845583"/> illustrates the envisioned model for such data
                collection. The model entails an EHR user selecting a “form” or “template” from a
                forms repository that is external to the EHR (steps 1 and 2). This form, which
                specifies the exact data elements needed for the intended research or reporting
                purpose, becomes the artifact used to collect the requisite structured data. The EHR
                “auto-populates” whichever of the form’s data elements it can from the EHR’s own
                database - via mappings specified within the form – (step 3), and then prompts the
                user to enter manually values for the remaining data elements (step 4). The
                completed form is then locally saved (step 5), as well as transmitted to an external
                data repository (step 6), from which it can be accessed for its intended research,
                reporting, and analytical purposes (step 7).</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref493845583">
                <title>Envisioned model for structured data capture (SDC) using data
                    elements.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image2.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Within this model, “data elements” comprise the individual units of information
                that are collected when each “question/answer” pair in a form is populated. Examples
                range from simple concepts, such as a patient’s height, to complex concepts, such as
                the severity of a medication adverse event. In all cases, the precise meaning,
                allowable values, and other attributes of the data elements are carefully
                defined.</para>
            <para>“Common data elements” (CDEs) are data elements that are shared across a community
                of interest. The standardized and mutually agreed-upon definitions of CDEs enable
                their re-use in different contexts and aide in the exchange and repurposing of
                clinical data. The SDC model envisions the definition of many CDEs for use in
                various data-collection use cases.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Attributes of Data Elements</title>
            <para>The ONC S&amp;I SDC initiative did not actually define common data elements that
                may be used in forms, but only standardize the set of <emphasis>defining</emphasis>
                <emphasis>attributes</emphasis> that may be used to specify such data elements
                (leaving it to others to actually define the elements). The standardized attributes
                defined by S&amp;I number approximately 75, and the full set is available in a
                document from the ONC S&amp;I web site<footnote xml:id="__EN3__">
                    <para>See (“SDC Data Element Attributes” tab in <link
                            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://oncprojectracking.healthit.gov/wiki/download/attachments/16123327/SDC%20SWG%20Data%20Element%20Mapping%20Templatev4%20%282%29.xlsx?version=1&amp;modificationDate=1489605858000&amp;api=v2"
                            >https://oncprojectracking.healthit.gov/wiki/download/attachments/16123327/SDC%20SWG%20Data%20Element%20Mapping%20Templatev4%20%282%29.xlsx?version=1&amp;modificationDate=1489605858000&amp;api=v2</link>
                    </para>
                </footnote>.</para>
            <para>The most important required attributes for each data element include:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Data Element Unique Identifier</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Data Element Name</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Text definition</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Datatype of permitted values</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Set of permitted values when enumerated (including display text and code,
                        if coded)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Notably, coded values from standard terminologies must be
                    <emphasis>pre-coordinated</emphasis> (i.e., the SDC standard does not allow
                post-coordinated expressions as the values of data elements). </para>
            <para>Other relevant attributes include the units of measure and high/low ranges for
                numerically-valued data elements, as well as mappings to corresponding data elements
                in standardized clinical data representations, such as C/CDA (to facilitate the
                automated population of data elements from EHR contents). </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Data Element Examples</title>
            <para>Although the ONC S&amp;I SDC initiative did not define any specific data elements,
                other similar initiatives have produced libraries of defined data elements that
                serve as good examples of the concept. Notable among these libraries is the NIH
                Common Data Element (CDE) repository<footnote xml:id="__EN4__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://cde.nlm.nih.gov/form/search"
                            >https://cde.nlm.nih.gov/form/search</link>.</para>
                </footnote>. The repository contains data elements that have been recommended or
                required by NIH Institutes and Centers and other organizations, including the NCI,
                NLM, and AHRQ.</para>
            <para>The repository also contains libraries of structured data collection forms in
                which the specified data elements appear. Together, the forms and the CDEs exemplify
                the envisioned role of data elements in capturing and representing clinical
                information. Among examples of defined data elements in the repository are the
                following (with their definitions and allowable values):</para>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image3-1.jpg"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></para>
            <para>As evident from these examples, CDEs may represent simple, familiar clinical
                concepts, or complex esoteric concepts. Complexity can arise from either the
                definition of a CDE (as with the “Tissue Donor Sex Behavior” example), and/or from
                the definitions of its allowable values (as with the “Adverse Event Severity Grade”
                example). In either case, complex CDEs can pack a lot of clinical semantics into
                concise, atomic representations.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Limitations of Data Elements</title>
        <para>The model of forms and data elements prescribed by the S&amp;I SDC initiative has
            certain advantages with respect to standardizing data collection for secondary purposes.
            If different parties within a community do, indeed, use the same forms containing the
            same common data elements when collecting data, those data will be more uniform and
            amenable to aggregation, exchange, and pooled analysis. </para>
        <para>However, if a community creates and uses forms and data elements in a
            less-than-disciplined fashion, the resulting data sets will lack uniform semantics,
            preventing pooled analysis or (worse) generating incorrect analytical results. Given the
            inherent limitations of common data elements as a paradigm for modeling clinical
            semantics, there is a real danger of this occurring.</para>
        <para>The primary limitation of common data elements is that they are defined and used
            independently of any information model representing the context in which they are
            populated or the relationship among their populated values. The context of and
            relationships among populated data elements are represented only by the structure of the
            forms in which they are populated. These forms, however, lack any formal model to, for
            example, denote the relationships among their constituent data elements. Further, the
            same data elements can appear in different forms, such that the context in which the
            data elements are populated (and, hence, the complete semantics of the collected data)
            can vary depending on the form in which they appear. </para>
        <para>For example, a form may include the data element “Adverse event name,” followed by the
            data element “Adverse event severity”. The value of the latter is meaningless for
            purposes of data analysis unless associated with the value of the former (in particular,
            if multiple adverse events were present, with differing severities). Other than the
            sequence of the two data elements, however, forms have no way to formally represent this
            association. Also, “Adverse event severity” could appear in a different form, following
            the data element “Past adverse event name”. In this case, the semantics and implications
            of the value of “Adverse event severity” would be different than if it were associated
            with a currently experienced adverse event (for example, if it were “life threatening”).
            None of these contexts of and associations between data elements are formally
            represented, however. The result is that the values of data elements cannot be reliably
            aggregated or analyzed without access to the form(s) in which each the values was
            collected and a manual assessment of the semantics of the values when collected via each
            such form. Lastly, in the absence of a uniform information model, data analysts would
            have trouble determining the set of attributes that could have been populated to
            describe a particular clinical event, such as an adverse event, diagnosis, or treatment. </para>
        <para>The independent creation of common data elements in the absence of an information
            model also increases the chances that duplicative or overlapping data elements may be
            created by a community if great care and coordination are not exercised, with no
            guaranteed means of subsequent reconciliation or mapping. For example, the following two
            data elements could be defined and used by different parties within the same
            community:</para>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/image4-1.jpg"
                        width="5.5in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para>In this case, a data analyst searching a pooled data set for all instances of
            life-threatening adverse events would have to know that both of these data elements
            existed, and would have to query for instances of the first data element with a value of
            “Life-threatening” or “Death”, and instances of the second data element with a value of
            “Present”. Many other such situations could arise, because of the variable ways that the
            same or similar clinical concepts can be modeled as data elements.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Recommendations and Relationship to SOLOR</title>
        <para>To enable the consistent analysis of populated data elements without requiring
            detailed knowledge of the myriad forms used to collect those values, it is important to
            specify a clinical data model that exists independently of the forms. This data model
            should consist of (1) an <emphasis>information model</emphasis> (a.k.a., “clinical
            domain model”) to represent the context of and relationships among individual data
            elements, akin to a relational or object-oriented schema, and (2) a
                <emphasis>terminology model</emphasis> to represent the discrete clinical concepts
            represented by individual data elements and their allowed values. </para>
        <para>For example, the information model would specify <emphasis>Adverse Event</emphasis> as
            a clinical object type, which could be instantiated and further described by a set of
            explicitly related attributes, such as “AE Name”, “AE Code”, “AE Manifestation”, “AE
            Severity”, and “AE Start Date”. Any enumerated value sets for these attributes would be
            specified by reference to the terminology model or to other objects of the information
            model. For example, the values of the “AE Manifestation” attribute could be constrained
            to any concept in the terminology that was an Observation or a Disease. Together, the
            information model and terminology model would specify a clinical data model that
            represented the scope, structure, and semantics of any collected data and that supported
            data aggregation and analysis regardless of the specific data-entry instruments
            (including forms) that were used for data collection. </para>
        <para>Examples of information models consistent with this approach include OpenEHR<footnote
                xml:id="__EN5__">
                <para>Demski H, Garde S, Hildebrand C. Open data models for smart health
                    interconnected applications: the example of openEHR. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak.
                    2016 Oct 22;16(1):137. (available at <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27770769"
                        >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27770769</link>).</para>
            </footnote><superscript>,</superscript><footnote xml:id="__EN6__">
                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.openehr.org/what_is_openehr"
                        >http://www.openehr.org/what_is_openehr</link>. </para>
            </footnote> and CIMI<footnote xml:id="__EN7__">
                <para>Goossen, W. Detailed Clinical Models: Representing Knowledge, Data and
                    Semantics in Healthcare Information Technology. Healthc Inform Res. 2014 Jul;
                    20(3): 163–172.</para>
            </footnote><superscript>,</superscript><footnote xml:id="__EN8__">
                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Detailed_Clinical_Models"
                        >http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Detailed_Clinical_Models</link>.
                </para>
            </footnote>. Examples of applicable terminology models include SNOMED-CT<footnote
                xml:id="__EN9__">
                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.snomed.org/snomed-ct"
                        >http://www.snomed.org/snomed-ct</link>. </para>
            </footnote> and SOLOR<footnote xml:id="__EN10__">
                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.solor.io/">http://www.solor.io/</link>. </para>
            </footnote>. </para>
        <para>The specification of a clinical data model, as described above, still allows for the
            use of common data elements and standardized forms for data collection, as defined by
            the S&amp;I SDC model. However, achieving the benefits of both forms-based data entry
            and model-based data analysis requires the <emphasis>mapping </emphasis> of data
            elements that appear in forms to semantically equivalent representations that are
            consist with the clinical data model. These mappings allow data collected via forms to
            be transformed to equivalent data that conform to the clinical data model, which can
            then serve as a single, uniform point of reference for querying and analyzing the data.
            In this manner, clinicians can use familiar forms and data elements to enter data
            (without requiring any knowledge of the more complex underlying data model), and
            analysts can use the clinical data model to query and analyze the collected data
            (without requiring any knowledge of the data-collection forms that were used to enter
            them). <xref linkend="_Ref493941874"/> illustrates this approach to collecting and
            analyzing clinical data.</para>
        <figure xml:id="_Ref493941874">
            <title>Proposed model for the collection and analysis of structured data.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/image5.png"
                        width="5.5in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Importantly, the forms and data elements that will be used by clinicians must be
            created and maintained in coordination with the clinical data model that will be used by
            analysts. Such coordination is required to ensure that the former remains consistent
            with and can be reliably mapped to the latter as both evolve over time.</para>
        <para>Also, transformation between the forms-based view of collected data and the
            clinical-model-based view can occur in real time, as the forms are completed and their
            data stored. Alternatively, the transformation could occur later, when data are moved
            from an initial (forms-based) data store to a secondary (model-based) data store. The
            appropriate strategy will depend on the intended uses of the collected data and how
            promptly data analysis will follow data collection. </para>
        <para>Lastly, the SOLOR terminology plays an important role in both the forms-based model
            and the clinical data model. As mentioned, a terminology model, such as SOLOR, is needed
            as part of the clinical data model to rigorously represent the individual clinical
            concepts within the model. However, the definition of common data elements and
            data-collection forms in the forms-based model must also take into account the content
            of SOLOR, because the common data elements and their values will need to map to SOLOR
            concepts (to support the transformations described above). In practice, it is much
            better to consider such mappings at the time that the common data elements and forms are
            defined, rather than define them independently and hope that a mapping to SOLOR is
            possible at a later time.</para>
    </section>
</article>
