<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../CSS/SOLOR-css.css"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Task 5.10 Identify Solor Content that Requires Special Handling White Paper</title>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>The original Reference Set of 50,000 SNOMED concepts completed in the first iteration,
            and described in Section 2 below, was evaluated to determine if they meet the following
            criteria:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept includes laterality</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept is an inverse of a concept</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept is a primitive concept versus those that should be fully
                    defined</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>This review resulted in eight additional RefSets that identify the concepts that meet
            and those that do not meet the criteria above.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Laterality Correct: Clinical Findings, Observable Entities, Specimens and
                    Procedures where the Finding and Procedure Site attributes use the correct body
                    structure concept that involves laterality.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Laterality Incorrect: Clinical Findings, Observable Entities, Specimens and
                    Procedures where the Finding and Procedure Site attributes do not use the
                    correct body structure concept that involves laterality.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Doesn’t Include Laterality: Clinical Findings, Observable Entities, Specimens
                    and Procedures where the Fully Specified Name (FSN) doesn’t involve
                    laterality.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ambiguous: Any of the 50,000 concepts where the FSN was ambiguous as to
                    whether it contained laterality.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Is Inverse: Concepts that currently have or could have an inverse or opposite
                    concept in SNOMED CT. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Is Not Inverse: Concepts that were not considered as inverse or opposite
                    concepts.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Can Be Fully Defined: Concepts that can be fully defined now but are not being
                    fully modeled and/or specified as fully defined.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Cannot Be Fully Defined: Concepts that will always remain primitive or would
                    require major changes to the concept model to be fully defined.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para> </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Approach to Identify Content for 50,000 SNOMED Concepts RefSet</title>
        <para>The below approach was used to identify the first RefSet, which included 50,000 SNOMED
            concepts:</para>
        <para> </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>To identify content that would need to be evaluated for laterality
                    concepts:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Set 1: Find all concepts with “right”, “left”, or “bilateral” in an
                            active term. This identifies all concepts that could potentially
                            represent a lateralized concept based on a term.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Find all concepts where Set 1 is used as a destinationId for a
                            defining relationship in the Relationship table. This identifies
                            concepts that use the concepts from Set 1 as a value for a defining
                            relationship, which would include both children of concepts in Set 1 and
                            those that use them for other defining relationships.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Set 2: Find all concepts with a laterality defining attribute. This
                            would identify all Body Structures that use a Laterality
                            Attribute.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Find all concepts where Set 2 is used as a destinationId for a
                            defining relationship in the Relationship table. This query would
                            identify those concepts that do not have a term with “right”, “left”, or
                            “bilateral” but do use a Body Structure as a value for a defining
                            relationship.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Remove from all sets any concepts from the Body Structure
                            hierarchy.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>To identify content where there is an inverse concept:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Any concept with strings matching a set of keywords that would
                            indicate the inverse of another concept</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Able to vs Unable to</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Normal vs Abnormal</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Present vs Absent</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Decrease vs Increase</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Acquired vs Congenital</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Localized vs Generalized</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Does vs Does not</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Benign vs Malignant</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Complete vs Incomplete</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Accidental vs Intentional</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Active vs Inactive</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Acute vs Chronic</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Adequate vs Inadequate</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Open vs Closed</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Attends vs Does not attend</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Can vs Cannot</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>(Stable or Stability) vs (Unstable or Instability)</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Primary vs Secondary</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Positive vs Negative</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Major vs Minor</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Increased vs Decreased</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Direct vs Indirect</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Early vs Late</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Internal vs External</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Extrinsic vs Intrinsic</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>High vs Low</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Legal vs Illegal</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Appropriate vs Inappropriate</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Increasing vs Decreasing</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Effective vs Ineffective</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Insufficient vs Sufficient</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Irregular vs Regular</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Loosening vs Tightening</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Success vs (Unsuccess or not success)</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Known vs unknown</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Narrow vs Wide</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Always vs Never</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Dependent vs Nondependent</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Hodgkin vs nonhodgkin</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Smoker vs nonsmoker</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Traum vs nontraum</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Urgent vs nonurgent</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Venomous vs nonvenomous</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Old vs new</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Satisfact vs (unsatisfactory or not satisfac)</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Use vs does not use</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Lengthening vs Shortening</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Near vs Far</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Infect vs noninfect</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Inflammatory vs noninflammatory</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Obstruct vs unobstruct</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>(Loss or Lost) vs Gain</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Fit vs (unfit or not fit)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Additional keywords were identified during our review process that
                            should be added to future review efforts:</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Anteversion vs Retroversion</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Soft vs Firm</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Recessive vs Dominant</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Mature vs Immature</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Functional vs Non-functional</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>To identify content that are currently primitive concepts, but may be able to
                    be fully defined:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Select all concepts that are intermediate primitives, meaning they
                            have both ancestors and descendants that are fully defined but they are
                            primitive</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Select all concepts that are primitive leaf nodes but they have fully
                            defined ancestors</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Rules for Evaluating Membership in RefSets</title>
        <para> The following rules were used to evaluate membership in one or more of the eight
            RefSets:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Inverse vs Not Inverse</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Laterality Correct vs Laterality Incorrect vs Doesn’t Include Laterality
                    vs Ambiguous</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Primitive but should be fully defined vs. Always Primitive</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para> </para>
        <para>Scope and boundaries for RefSet membership have to be defined as clearly as
            possible to support reproducibility of concept inclusion. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Inverse</title>
            <para>The purpose of the Inverse RefSets is to identify concepts that <emphasis
                role="underline">should</emphasis> have an opposing concept due to a description
                indicating an opposite or inverse concept, regardless of whether that opposing
                concept currently exists in SNOMED CT. It is <emphasis role="underline"
                    >not</emphasis> the purpose to identify and pair opposing concepts. In many
                cases, the opposing concept does not exist in SNOMED CT and the next iteration (not
                a part of this PWS) of this RefSet should be to link the two inverse concepts
                together to identify missing content.</para>
            <para/>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Rules for Inclusion in “Inverse”
                RefSet:</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Concepts were only considered inverse if a valid opposing concept should
                        exist in SNOMED CT. For example, 56313000|Abnormal placenta affecting
                        management of mother (disorder)| was not considered to be inverse since the
                        opposing concept would be “Normal placenta affecting management of mother”
                        which would not be a valid concept.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Anatomical positions and relative locations such as lateral, medial,
                        distal, proximal, etc., were not considered to be inverse.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If there is an Open procedure and the only “closed” concept that would
                        ever need to be created would be one that uses only one specific device, we
                        would consider these two concepts as inverse. For example, 179820004 |Open
                        excision of implanted ligament (procedure)| is inverse of 179891009
                        |Arthroscopic excision of implanted ligament (procedure)| and 265071006
                        |Open bilateral clipping of fallopian tubes (procedure)| is inverse of
                        176979002 |Endoscopic bilateral clipping of fallopian tubes
                        (procedure)|.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Male and Female were not considered to be inverse.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Laterality</title>
            <para>The purpose of the Laterality RefSets is to identify concepts that are not
                currently modelled with the correct body structure that utilizes laterality. This
                only pertains to laterality as currently represented in SNOMED CT, which is used to
                designate one or both of paired bilaterally symmetrical (or near symmetrical) body
                structures. It therefore does not apply to sidedness of specific body structures.
                For example 364006 |Acute left-sided heart failure (disorder)| is not a lateralized
                disorder since the heart is not a bilaterally symmetrical body structure. For more
                information on laterality vs sidedness, please see <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2244155/?page=1"
                    ><emphasis role="italic">Choosing Sides. Assigning Laterality as an
                        Attribute in SNOMED® CT</emphasis></link><emphasis role="italic"
                            >.</emphasis></para>
            <para> </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Rules for Inclusion in “Laterality”
                RefSet:</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the concept being evaluated includes laterality in its FSN and it
                            is not modelled using a Finding Site or Procedure Site, even in cases
                            where there is no current SCT body structure concept with the correct
                            laterality, it will be marked as incorrect. For example,
                            16730001000004104 |Thrombosis of left peroneal vein (disorder)| should
                            be defined with Structure of left peroneal vein, which does not
                            currently exist in SNOMED CT.</para>
                        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_identifySolorContentRequiringSpecialHandling_00.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All bilateral concepts were evaluated against the current SNOMED CT
                            modelling guidance, which requires the use of two separate role groups
                            with one representing the right body structure and one representing the
                            left body structure. If the concept is modelled using the bilateral body
                            structure (e.g. 40638003 |Structure of both eyes (body structure)|), it
                            was added to the Laterality Incorrectly Modeled RefSet. For example,
                            12239101000119100 |Bilateral degeneration of macula (disorder)| should
                            have two different role groups, one with 721947001 |Structure of macula
                            lutea of left eye (body structure)| and the other with 721945009
                            |Structure of macula lutea of right eye (body structure)|.</para>
                        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_identifySolorContentRequiringSpecialHandling_01.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the concept being evaluated included a plural form of a potentially
                            lateralizable body structure in the FSN, we considered this concept to
                            represent bilaterality and evaluated it as such. For example, 248422003
                            |Warm hands (finding)| does not specify right, left, or bilateral in the
                            FSN but since it uses the term “hands,” we considered it to be bilateral
                            and evaluated against the current SNOMED CT modelling guidance as stated
                            above.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the concept being evaluated represented sidedness of a
                            non-bilaterally symmetrical body structure, it was added to the Does Not
                            Include Laterality RefSet. For example, 111283005 |Chronic left-sided
                            heart failure (disorder)| represents heart failure on the left side of
                            the heart. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the concept being evaluated was ambiguous as to whether it
                            represented one side vs both sides, it was placed in the Ambiguous
                            Laterality RefSet. For example, “lacrimal canaliculi” concepts were
                            considered to be ambiguous since their FSNs did not specify if it was
                            the lacrimal canaliculi of both eyes or the right or left eye.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Primitive</title>
            <para>The purpose of the Primitive RefSets is to identify concepts that could be easily
                fully defined under the current concept model of SNOMED CT. From the SNOMED CT
                Technical Implementation Guide, a fully defined concept is defined as:</para>
            <para> “A <link xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                >Concept</link> is considered to be <link
                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/fully+defined"
                    >fully defined</link> if its <link
                        xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/defining+characteristic"
                        >defining characteristics</link> are sufficient to define it relative to its
                immediate supertype(s). A <link
                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                    >Concept</link> which is not <link
                        xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/fully+defined"
                        >fully defined</link> is <link
                            xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Primitive"
                            >Primitive</link> and this is indicated by the value of the <link
                                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/definitionStatusId"
                                >definitionStatusId</link> field. </para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><link
                            xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/233604007"> 233604007 |Pneumonia|</link> is a lung
                            disease but unless <link
                                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/defining+characteristic"
                                >defining characteristics</link> are specified that effectively distinguish <link
                                    xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/233604007">233604007 |pneumonia|</link> from other
                            lung diseases then it is regarded as a <link
                                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/primitive"
                                >primitive</link><link
                                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                                    >Concept</link>. </para>
                        <para>If a <link xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                            >Concept</link> is <link
                                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/primitive"
                                >primitive</link> then the <link
                                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/defining+characteristic"
                                    >defining characteristics</link> for that <link
                                        xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                                        >Concept</link> are incomplete. It is not possible to automatically compute that a
                            <link xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                                >Concept</link> represented as a <link
                                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/postcoordinated"
                                    >postcoordinated</link> combination of several <link
                                        xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                                        >Concepts</link> is or is not a <link
                                            xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/subtype"
                                            >subtype</link> of a particular <link
                                                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/primitive"
                                                >primitive</link><link
                                                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                                                    >Concept</link>. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> The <link
                            xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                            >Concept</link> "lung disease" qualified by <link
                                xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/246075003">246075003 |causative agent|</link> =
                            <link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/41146007">41146007 |bacteria|</link> may be
                            <link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/233604007">233604007 |pneumonia|</link> but
                            could also be "bronchitis." </para>
                        <para>In contrast if a <link
                            xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                            >Concept</link> is <link
                                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/fully+defined">fully
                                defined</link> it is possible to state that any <link
                                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                                    >Concept</link> represented as a combination of the same <link
                                        xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/defining+characteristic"
                                        >defining characteristics</link> is equivalent to or a <link
                                            xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/subtype"
                                            >subtype</link> of that <link
                                                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                                                >Concept</link>. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis> Assume that the <link
                            xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/Concept"
                            >Concept</link><link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/53084003">53084003 |bacterial
                                pneumonia|</link> is <link
                                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/fully+defined">fully
                                    defined</link> as <link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/312342009">312342009
                                        |infective pneumonia|</link> with <link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/246075003"
                                            >246075003 |causative agent|</link> = <link
                                                xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/41146007">41146007 |bacteria|</link> and that
                            <link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/9861002">9861002 |pneumococcus|</link> is a
                            <link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/41146007">41146007 |bacteria|</link>. It
                            then follows that the post coordinated representation of <link
                                xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/233607000">233607000 |pneumococcal
                                pneumonia|</link> as <link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/312342009">312342009
                                    |infective pneumonia|</link> with <link xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/246075003"
                                        >246075003 |causative agent|</link> = <link
                                            xlink:href="http://snomed.info/id/9861002">9861002 |pneumococcus|</link> is
                            computably a <link
                                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/subtype"
                                >subtype</link> of <link xlink:href="http://snomed.org/fictid">|bacterial
                                    pneumonia.|</link>”</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Rules for Inclusion in “Primitive” RefSet</emphasis>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the evaluated concept can be fully defined within the current SNOMED CT
                            concept model and no changes are required, then it will be placed in the Can Be
                            Fully Defined RefSet. For example, 201558003 |Reactive arthropathy of shoulder
                            (disorder)| can be changed to fully defined today as there is nothing missing
                            from its definition.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If a concept could be fully defined by the addition of a new concept to
                            represent a single parent or by adding a single concept that could be used as a
                            value for a current concept model attribute, the concept will be placed in the
                            Can Be Fully Defined RefSet. For example, 207959006 |Closed fracture lumbar
                            vertebra, wedge (disorder)| currently cannot be considered as fully defined
                            because an Associated Morphology concept doesn’t currently exist to represent a
                            Wedge Fracture. By adding that single concept, the concept will then be able to
                            be fully defined.</para>
                        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/definitional_identifySolorContentRequiringSpecialHandling_02.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the evaluated concept requires a change to the Concept Model, for example,
                            adding a new attribute or changing the range of values an existing Concept Model
                            attribute takes, then it will be placed in the Can Not Be Fully Defined RefSet.
                            For example, 427252003 |Pain radiating to right side of chest (finding)| cannot
                            be fully defined because there is no concept model attribute to represent that
                            the pain radiated to the right side of the chest. Currently, it only indicates
                            radiating pain and doesn’t specify the body structure of chest or that it is on
                            the right side.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Reliability of Rule Sets</title>
        <para>In order to determine reliability of the identified keywords and rule sets for each
            RefSet, metrics of agreement/disagreement for the initial review were used. </para>
        <para>Two Terminologists reviewed the SNOMED CT concepts individually, applying the initial
            set of rules for each RefSet. After this first review, disagreements between the two
            Terminologists were extracted from the concept files and re-assigned for discussion and
            reconciliation. </para>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Metrics for Inter-Rater Reliability</emphasis></para>
            <para>In the course of the reconciliation discussion, the initial rules were
            re-evaluated and either confirmed, adjusted, clarified or eliminated to achieve a set of
            rules that is sufficiently expressive and reproducible. </para>
            <para>The RefSet membership status of all reconciled concepts was updated in the
                RefSets.</para>
            <para>The following metrics for agreement/disagreement percentages between the first two
                reviewers were calculated:</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Laterality RefSets Agreement = 84.12%</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inverse RefSets Agreement = 98.81%</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Fully Defined RefSets Agreement = 82.84%</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title><anchor xml:id="_Toc491441227"/>Sensitivity and Specificity</title>
        <para>Using the defined set of keywords, the sensitivity and specificity of the initial
            automated queries was tested against the final RefSets. After running the queries and
            evaluating the concepts for inclusion in their appropriate RefSet, we further
            categorized the results as either a True Positive, True Negative, False Positive, or
            False Negative. Running the queries against the original 50,000 concepts the following
            metrics were applied to the results:  </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Sensitivity = number of True Positives/number of True Positives + number of
                    False Negatives</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Specificity = number of True Negatives/ number of True Negatives + number of
                    False Positives</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para> </para>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="_Toc491441228"/>Sensitivity and Specificity of Search Criteria
                for “Laterality”</title>
            <para>
                <table frame="void">
                    <caption>Table 1. Sensitivity and Specificity of Laterality Search
                        Criteria.</caption>
                    <col width="22%"/>
                    <col width="11%"/>
                    <col width="16%"/>
                    <col width="16%"/>
                    <col width="16%"/>
                    <col width="16%"/>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Laterality Results</th>
                            <th>Query Total</th>
                            <th>Doesn't Include Laterality</th>
                            <th>Incorrect Laterality</th>
                            <th>Correct Laterality</th>
                            <th>Ambiguous</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>No Term, Attribute =side</td>
                            <td align="center">9317</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_red_white">9225</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_yellow_black">81</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_yellow_black">0</td>
                            <td align="center">11</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>No Term, Attribute = RLB</td>
                            <td align="center">94</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_orange_black">9</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_green_white">11</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_green_white">74</td>
                            <td align="center">0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Term, Attribute = RLB</td>
                            <td align="center">3899</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_orange_black">11</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_green_white">661</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_green_white">3227</td>
                            <td align="center">0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Term, No Attribute</td>
                            <td align="center">2545</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_red_white">1530</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_yellow_black">960</td>
                            <td align="center" class="cell_yellow_black">55</td>
                            <td align="center">0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Totals</td>
                            <td align="center">15855</td>
                            <td align="center">10775</td>
                            <td align="center">1713</td>
                            <td align="center">3356</td>
                            <td align="center">11</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table> 
            </para>
                     
            <para>
                <table frame="void">
                    <caption></caption>
                    <col width="125"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_green_white">True Positive</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_red_white">True Negative</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_orange_black">False Positive</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_yellow_black">False Negative</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para>Before creating assignments we categorized the concepts as either those that have
                a term that included right, left, or bilateral and those that have an attribute that
                uses a concept with a laterality of right, left or bilateral. If the concept had a
                term with right, left or bilateral and no attribute or if the attribute had a
                laterality where the value was the parent (side) of right and left we considered
                those concepts to be within the set that probably did not include laterality. If the
                concept was associated with a laterality attribute that was either right or left we
                considered it to probably include laterality whether it was correctly modelled or
                not.</para>
            <para>Sensitivity of 78.38% and Specificity of 99.81% </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="_Toc491441229"/>Sensitivity and Specificity of Keywords for
                “Inverse”</title>
            <table frame="void">
                <caption>Table 2. Sensitivity and Specificity of keywords for
                    &quot;Inverse&quot;.</caption>
                <col width="25%"/>
                <col width="25%"/>
                <col width="25%"/>
                <col width="25%"/>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Inverse Results</th>
                        <th>Query Total</th>
                        <th>Is Inverse</th>
                        <th>Is Not Inverse</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Removed Keywords </td>
                        <td align="center">5875</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_yellow_black">1773</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_red_white">4102</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Original Keywords</td>
                        <td align="center">18416</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_green_white">12155</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_orange_black">6261</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Totals</td>
                        <td align="center">24291</td>
                        <td align="center">13928</td>
                        <td align="center">10363</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
            <para> 
                <table frame="void">
                    <caption></caption>
                    <col width="125"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_green_white">True Positive</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_red_white">True Negative</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_orange_black">False Positive</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_yellow_black">False Negative</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para>After conducting a pilot certain keywords were identified a less likely to be
                inverse. We separated these concepts into separate assignments. After further
                review, 30% of these concepts contained other keywords that made them inverse. </para>
            <para>Sensitivity of 82.27% and Specificity of 39.58%</para>
            <para> </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="_Toc491441230"/>Sensitivity and Specificity of Search Criteria
                for “Can Be Fully Defined”</title>
            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                    <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Primitive Results</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Query Total</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Can Be Fully Defined</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Cannot Be Fully Defined</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Leaf Nodes</entry>
                            <entry>28394</entry>
                            <entry>7458</entry>
                            <entry>20936</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Intermediate Primitives</entry>
                            <entry>2133</entry>
                            <entry>677</entry>
                            <entry>1456</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Other</entry>
                            <entry>2154</entry>
                            <entry>573</entry>
                            <entry>1581</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Totals</entry>
                            <entry>32681</entry>
                            <entry>8708</entry>
                            <entry>23973</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
            <table frame="void">
                <caption>Table 3. Sensitivity and Specificity of Search Criteria for &quot;Can Be
                    Fully Defined&quot;.</caption>
                <col width="25%"/>
                <col width="25%"/>
                <col width="25%"/>
                <col width="25%"/>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Primitive Results</th>
                        <th>Query Total</th>
                        <th>Can Be Fully Defined</th>
                        <th>Cannot Be Fully Defined</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Leaf Nodes</td>
                        <td align="center">28394</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_green_white">7458</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_yellow_black">20936</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Intermediate Primitives</td>
                        <td align="center">2133</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_green_white">677</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_yellow_black">1456</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Other</td>
                        <td align="center">2154</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_orange_black">573</td>
                        <td align="center" class="cell_red_white">1581</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Totals</td>
                        <td align="center">32681</td>
                        <td align="center">8708</td>
                        <td align="center">23973</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
            <para>
                <table frame="void">
                    <caption/>
                    <col width="125"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_green_white">True Positive</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_red_white">True Negative</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_orange_black">False Positive</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td class="cell_yellow_black">False Negative</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para>Leaf Nodes and Intermediate Primitives were concepts that we would more likely see
                as concepts that should be Fully Defined. However, in many cases that really
                depended upon whether new Concept Model attributes could be added to SNOMED CT. The
                other Primitive concepts we reviewed were concepts that were not Leaf Nodes and
                Intermediate Primitive concepts that we reviewed and we did not expect to find many
                of them that could be fully defined.</para>
            <para>Sensitivity of 26.65% and Specificity of 73.40%</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title xml:id="title_lll_dq2_4fb">Conclusion</title>
        <para>The Inverse RefSets had good inter-rater agreement but the Fully Defined and
            Laterality RefSets had lower inter-rater agreement rates. The Fully Defined and
            Laterality RefSets both required the evaluation of the modeling of the defining
            relationships and judging their correctness. The experience of the clinical reviewing
            team with the SNOMED CT Concept Model is critical to getting a high inter-rater
            agreement rate when creating RefSets that depend on reviewing modelling. As the SNOMED
            CT Concept Model increases in complexity, the education and experience with modelling of
            SNOMED CT concepts will become even more critical in reviewing and maintaining these
            RefSets. </para>
        <para>For the 5,069 concepts that were identified as having laterality, 33.79% were deemed
            to be incorrectly modeled. While this is a rather large number, SNOMED International is
            currently modeling a large number of laterality concepts and this number should be
            decreasing with each release. </para>
        <para>The sensitivity for the Primitive RefSets is relatively low because reviewers needed
            to decide if the addition of some qualifier value or a new parent concept would make
            these concepts definable. In many cases there needed to be the addition of new concept
            model attribute to fully define concepts. The queries used to identify these concepts
            for review were not able to tell which primitive concepts could be fully defined with
            and without Concept Model changes. Overall, the exercise of reviewing primitives is very
            useful to identify more concepts that could be fully defined. </para>
        <para>Overall, this approach to identify SNOMED CT concepts that require special handling
            shows that automated queries can be very useful as a first “screening” step, but manual
            review and reconciliation still has to be performed to arrive at evaluated RefSets that
            adhere to reliable inclusion/exclusion criteria. Creating RefSets that identify modeling
            issues can present problems when the review of concepts spans multiple release dates and
            the tooling used to do the review is updated while the review is still taking place.
            This requires additional work at the end of the project to ensure that the review of the
            concepts for errors does not identify concepts that were correctly placed when they were
            initially reviewed, but are now incorrectly placed due to corrections or changes made to
            the latest release.</para>
    </section>
    
</section>
