<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article version="5.0" xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
      <info>
        <title>A Quantitative Approach to Representing and Querying the Presence or Absence of Clinical Observations</title>
        <subtitle>Supporting Domain Semantics, Flexibility, and Interoperability</subtitle>
        
        <author>
            <personname>Walter Sujansky</personname>
        </author>
        
        <date>2017-09-30</date>
      </info>
      <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>The structured representation of clinical observations in computer systems is
            challenging because representational models must support convenient entry, faithful
            storage, and accurate analysis of information in a complex and high-stakes domain.
            Existing representational models, such as SNOMED-CT<footnote xml:id="__EN1__">
                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.snomed.org/snomed-ct/what-is-snomed-ct"
                        >http://www.snomed.org/snomed-ct/what-is-snomed-ct</link>. </para>
            </footnote>, OpenEHR<footnote xml:id="__EN2__">
                <para>Demski H, Garde S, Hildebrand C. Open data models for smart health
                    interconnected applications: the example of openEHR. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak.
                    2016 Oct 22;16(1):137. (available at <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27770769"
                        >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27770769</link>).</para>
            </footnote>, and CIMI<footnote xml:id="__EN3__">
                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="https://www.opencimi.org/">https://www.opencimi.org/</link>.
                </para>
            </footnote> are sophisticated artifacts that have been developed over many years and
            meet many of the requirements of clinical information systems. </para>
        <para>Nevertheless, certain unresolved issues remain in the representation of clinical
            observations, which limit the usability and accuracy of current models. Among these
            challenges is the formal and consistent documentation of the “Presence” versus the
            “Absence” of clinical phenomena, a common and important distinction within medical
            records. This whitepaper proposes an extension to existing models to more consistently
            record and leverage observations of “presence” and “absence” in electronic health
            records.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="_Ref493868573">
        <title>The Problems Being Addressed</title>
        <para>This section describes two related problems in the representation and analysis of
            clinical observations that the model proposed in this paper attempts to address.</para>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493771252">
            <title>Representational Redundancy: “Findings” and “Observable Entities”</title>
            <para>In many representation models, such as SNOMED-CT and CIMI, a somewhat arbitrary
                distinction exists between the modeling of “Findings” and “Observable Entities.” The
                former typically document the presence or absence of some phenomenon in the patient
                (such as whether the patient has a pressure ulcer), whereas the latter characterize
                some feature of the patient or the patient’s condition (such as the number of
                pressure ulcers a patient has). <xref linkend="_Ref493845583"/> shows an example of
                the different representations for these two similar observations when modeled as
                Findings versus Observable Entity.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref493845583">
                <title>An undesirable redundancy in representing clinical observations.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image2.png"
                            contentwidth="237" contentdepth="103"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Because the observation of pressure ulcers in a patient could be correctly modeled
                as either a Finding or Observable Entity, any subsequent query to determine whether
                a patient had a pressure ulcer would need to test for the observation in two
                different ways:</para>
            <para><emphasis>IF EXISTS object WHERE object.conceptId = “3456_PressureUlcers” AND
                    (object.value = “Present” OR object.value &gt; 0)</emphasis></para>
            <para>This duality of representation complicates data querying and significantly
                increases the possibility that data analysts will not be aware of and account for
                all the ways that an observation may be represented, resulting in false-negative
                query results.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493848005">
            <title>Confusion About Negation: “Absent” and “Not Present”</title>
            <para>Negation as a logical concept is subject to many ambiguities and inconsistencies,
                in healthcare applications and general usage<footnote xml:id="__EN4__">
                    <para>Horn L. A Natural History of Negation. University of Chicago Press,
                        1989.</para>
                </footnote>. For example, the semantic distinctions between the statements “he
                didn’t say she was ill” and “he said she was not ill” are subtle and open to varying
                interpretations. When such distinctions appear in medical records and are used as
                the basis for inference or data retrieval, it’s important that a clear and formal
                semantic exists that is shared by those who record the information, those who later
                review the information and use it in medical decision making, and those who write
                software that aggregates, abstracts, infers, or performs other logical computations
                on the information.</para>
            <para>One important distinction in medical documentation is that of a clinical
                phenomenon being documented as “absent” versus the phenomenon not being documented
                as “present.” For example, does the explicit documentation of “No abdominal
                tenderness” mean the same thing as no documentation of “abdominal tenderness”? Would
                the interpretation be different if the phenomenon were instead “jaundice” or “HIV”?
                Would it matter if the presenting complaint at the time that observation were
                documented were “vomiting” versus “ankle sprain”? Depending on the clinical context,
                the specific phenomenon in question, and the assumptions of individuals using the
                medical record, the interpretation of “absent” versus “not present” could be the
                same or quite different. Today’s representation and inferencing models for
                electronic health records do not provide enough clarity and control to safely
                interpret negation in these situations.</para>
            <para>Finally, current ontology-based models for representing clinical observations
                sometimes result in gross errors when subsumption inferences are applied to negated
                clinical concepts. For example, the SNOMED-CT model incorrectly infers that the
                documentation of “No myocardial infarction” in a patient implies that the patient
                has “No heart disease” whatsoever. A model that correctly handles subsumption
                testing over negated clinical concepts is required to support correct (and safe)
                inferencing in electronic health records.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title> Components of the Solution</title>
        <para>The solution to address the problems described in Section <xref
                linkend="_Ref493868573"/> comprises a coherent and formal model made up of several
            components. Each component is described and exemplified in this section.</para>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493843805">
            <title>Phenomena and Interval Values</title>
            <para>To resolve the arbitrary distinction between “Findings” and “Observable Entities,”
                one must consolidate these redundant concepts types into the single concept type
                “Phenomenon.” Further, one must introduce a new data type to represent the values of
                Phenomena, one that can express both the “presence” (present/absent/indeterminate)
                and numeric (integer, real) values that Findings and Observable Entities can
                currently represent, respectively. This new data type is an “interval value” </para>
            <section>
                <title>The Interval Value Data Type</title>
                <para>An interval value data type (or “interval value”) formally represents a
                    numeric interval between two non-negative real numbers. The interval can be open
                    or closed. Examples of interval values are:</para>
                <para>[5,5], [0,10), (0,∞], [0,0]</para>
                <para>The formal syntax of interval values is represented by the following
                    grammar:</para>
                <para>Interval :: [ ‘[‘ | ‘(‘ ] N1 ‘,’ N2 [ ‘]’ | ‘)’ ]</para>
                <para>N1 :: Non-Negative Real Number</para>
                <para>N2 :: [ Non-Negative Real Number | ∞ ]</para>
                <para>The semantics of this grammar are as follows:</para>
                <para>‘[‘ and ‘]’ : Inclusive boundary (i.e. &gt;= and &lt;= )</para>
                <para>‘(‘ and ‘)’ : Exclusive boundary (i.e., &gt; and &lt; )</para>
                <para>∞: infinity, is &gt; every Non-Negative Real Number</para>
                <para>N1 &lt;= N2</para>
                <para>The interval value data type provides a single way to represent both
                    “presence” values and numeric values for a phenomenon. In general, the interval
                    value represents the numeric range within which the observed value of a
                    phenomenon occurs. Note that this formalism allows both exact values and ranges
                    of values to be expressed.</para>
                <para>In the special case that the beginning and end point of an interval are the
                    same number, <emphasis>n</emphasis>, the meaning is that the value of the
                    phenomenon is <emphasis>exactly n</emphasis>. </para>
                <para>[5,5] : exactly 5 ; [0,0] : exactly 0</para>
                <para>In the special case that the beginning of the interval is a number,
                        <emphasis>n</emphasis>, and the end point is ∞, the meaning is that the
                    value of the phenomenon is <emphasis>&gt; n </emphasis>or
                        <emphasis>&gt;=n</emphasis>, depending on whether the interval is open or
                    closed.</para>
                <para>(0,∞] : &gt; 0 ; [10,∞] : &gt;= 10</para>
                <para>The interval value also represents whether a phenomenon is “present”,
                    “absent”, or “indeterminate”. Specifically, any interval value that includes
                        <emphasis>only </emphasis>numbers that are &gt; 0 also denotes the value
                    “present”. Any interval value that includes only the number 0, itself, denotes
                    the value “absent”. Any interval value that includes <emphasis>both</emphasis>
                    the number 0 and at least one number &gt; 0 denotes the value “indeterminate”.
                    Lastly, there are two interval values that explicitly denote “present” and
                    “absent,” respectively. These value may be assigned to phenomena that would not
                    otherwise take on a numeric value (such as “nausea”):</para>
                <para>Nausea value = (0,∞] : present</para>
                <para>Nausea value = [0,0] : absent </para>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref493768774"/> lists a number of phenomena and how their
                    current values (as “Findings” or “Observable Entities”) would be represented
                    instead as interval values under the model proposed here.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493768774">
                    <title>The semantics of interval values assigned to phenomena, as shown through
                        examples.</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image3.png"
                                contentwidth="503" contentdepth="270"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Comparing Interval Values using IsWithin()</title>
                <para>Phenomena that represent clinical observations must be assigned interval
                    values, so the querying of such phenomena for purposes of data retrieval and
                    data analysis requires the comparison of interval values. Specifically, one must
                    be able to test whether one interval value <emphasis>is within</emphasis> (i.e.,
                    encompassed by) another interval value. For example, if one wanted to retrieve
                    only those patients who had between 1 and 5 pressure ulcers, one would test
                    whether a patient had the phenomenon “pressure ulcer” recorded with a value
                    interval that was within the interval [1,5]. Note that this test would retrieve
                    patients who had pressure-ulcer interval values, for example, of [1,1], [4,4],
                    and [3,5], but not those who had [0,0] or [1,10].</para>
                <para>Formally, the comparison of two interval values is done using the predicate
                        <emphasis>IsWithin( i</emphasis><subscript>1</subscript><emphasis>,
                        i</emphasis><subscript>2 </subscript><emphasis>), </emphasis>where
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>, i<subscript>2 </subscript>are interval values.
                    The values of the IsWithin() predicate may be TRUE, FALSE, or UNKNOWN,
                    determined as follows:</para>
                <para>TRUE =&gt; if a number is in i<subscript>1</subscript>, then it is definitely
                    in i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript> “subsumes”
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                <para>FALSE =&gt; if a number is in i<subscript>1</subscript>, then it is definitely
                    NOT in i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript>
                        “i<subscript>1</subscript>is disjoint with”
                    i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                <para>UNKNOWN =&gt; if a value is in, it may or may not be in
                        i<subscript>2</subscript> (i<subscript>2</subscript> “overlaps”
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                <para>Examples of interval-value comparisons:</para>
                <para><emphasis>IsWithin</emphasis>( [5,5], [0,10] ) =&gt; TRUE (interval
                        i<subscript>2</subscript> “subsumes” interval
                    i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                <para><emphasis>IsWithin</emphasis>( [15,20], [0,10] ) =&gt; FALSE (interval
                        i<subscript>2</subscript> “is disjoint with” interval
                        i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                <para><emphasis>IsWithin</emphasis>( [5,15], [0,10] ) =&gt; UNKNOWN (interval
                        i<subscript>2</subscript> “overlaps” interval
                    i<subscript>1</subscript>)</para>
                <para>Other useful examples:</para>
                <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [2,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                    TRUE</emphasis></para>
                <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [0,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt; UNKNOWN
                    </emphasis></para>
                <para><emphasis>IsWithin( (0,2], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                    TRUE</emphasis></para>
                <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [0,0], (0,</emphasis>∞<emphasis>] ) =&gt;
                    FALSE</emphasis></para>
                <para><emphasis>IsWithin( [0,0], [0,0] ) =&gt; TRUE</emphasis></para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Querying Phenomena Using Interval Values</title>
            <para>Based on the definition of the IsWithin() predicate, patient records may be
                queried for the presence or the numeric value of clinical observations using a
                single formalism.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Basic Querying</title>
                <para>The example query in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493771252"/> seeking to
                    determine whether a patient has a pressure ulcer may now be formulated more
                    simply and consistently (using pseudo-SQL to represent the logic):</para>
                <para>IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode =
                    “3456_PressureUlcers” AND IsWithin(ph.value, (0,∞]) = TRUE</para>
                <para>Note that, with pressure ulcers represented as Phenomena, the single predicate
                    “IsWithin(ph.value, (0,∞]) = TRUE” replaces the two expressions previously
                    required when pressure ulcers could be represented as either Findings or
                    Observable Entities (“object.value = “Present” OR object.value &gt; 0”). The
                    user formulating the query can reliably test for pressure ulcers in the
                    patient’s record without concern for how that clinical observation is
                    represented or what types of values it may have.</para>
                <para>Similarly, to determine whether a patient has any test results within a
                    specific numeric range, a similar formulation may be used, simply substituting
                    the desired numeric reference interval in the IsWithin() predicate:</para>
                <para>IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode =
                    “2468_SerumPotassium” AND IsWithin( ph.value, [0, 3.7) ) = TRUE</para>
                <para>The query above will evaluate to true if the patient 9876 has any serum
                    potassium values &lt; 3.7.</para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref493859801">
                <title>Querying with Negation</title>
                <para>Querying for the absence of a clinical phenomenon for a specific patient
                    introduces certain complications because of variations in the way that the
                    phenomenon may or may not be represented in the medical record. For example, if
                    a data-retrieval or data-analysis function needed to determine whether a patient
                    did NOT have any pressure ulcers, the query could be formulated in at least two
                    ways.</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Under the <emphasis>closed-world assumption
                                </emphasis>(CWA)<emphasis>, </emphasis>which implies that all
                            information about the state of the patient is included in the medical
                            record. In this case, the absence of any information in the medical
                            record supporting the presence of a pressure ulcer would be sufficient
                            evidence that the patient had no pressure ulcers. The specific
                            formulation of the query under this assumption would be: IF NOT (EXISTS
                            Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode =
                            “3456_PressureUlcers” AND IsWithin(ph.value, (0,∞]) = TRUE) (Note that
                            the reference value in the IsWithin() predicate is “(0,∞]” in this
                            case.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Under the <emphasis>open-world assumption </emphasis>(OWA). This
                            assumption implies that not all information about the patient’s state is
                            included in the medical record, so that the non-existence of some
                            patient state cannot be assumed based solely on a lack of data asserting
                            the presence of that state. In this case, the absence of some phenomenon
                            can only be inferred if the patient record explicitly asserts such
                            absence, or at least uncertainty about its presence. A specific
                            formulation of the query under this assumption would be: IF EXISTS
                            Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode =
                            “3456_PressureUlcers” AND IsWithin(ph.value, (0,∞]) &lt; &gt; TRUE An
                            alternative OWA formulation of the query with slightly different
                            semantics would be: IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876
                            AND ph.conceptCode = “3456_PressureUlcers” AND IsWithin(ph.value, [0,0])
                            = TRUE (Note the different formulations of the IsWithin() predicates in
                            these queries.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>The semantic distinctions among these query formulations are significant, in
                    that they will generate different query responses for the same patient data in
                    certain cases. <xref linkend="_Ref493768774"/> shows the Boolean value for each
                    query given different patient data instances in the medical record. Notably, the
                    query values are different in the last two cases. Note that in <xref
                        linkend="_Ref493768774"/>, a Boolean value of TRUE indicates that the
                    patient does NOT have pressure ulcers, whereas a Boolean value of FALSE
                    indicates that the patient DOES have pressure ulcers (since the queries are
                    testing for the absence of that phenomenon).</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Example truth table of negated querying under closed-world and open-world
                        assumptions.</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image4.png"
                                contentwidth="392" contentdepth="131"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>The potential variance in query responses depending on how a negation query is
                    formulated and how the absence of a phenomenon is represented in the medical
                    record is a problem for health-care applications that depend on clear and
                    consistent analysis of patient data. If data analysis of clinical observations
                    is subject to misinterpretation, then medical applications may reach incorrect
                    conclusions and/or provide incorrect advice, with adverse patient-safety
                    consequences.</para>
                <para>To avoid ambiguity in the representation and analysis of clinical observation
                    data, a better formalized and more intuitive model for querying is
                    required.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Normalized Querying of Phenomena</title>
            <para>This section introduces a model for normalizing the querying of clinical
                observations represented as phenomena so that the semantics of various query
                formulations are more explicit and intuitive, especially when queries include
                explicit negation. </para>
            <section xml:id="_Ref493847012">
                <title>A Tri-Valued State of Knowledge: Present, Absent, and Indeterminate</title>
                <para>The initial step involves abstracting the possible states of a clinical
                    phenomenon as reflected in the medical record to three mutually exclusive and
                    exhaustive values: Present, Absent, and Indeterminate. The informal definitions
                    of these states are as follows:</para>
                <para>Present”: The phenomenon is explicitly documented as present or can be
                    logically inferred to be present</para>
                <para>“Absent”: The phenomenon is explicitly documented as absent or can be
                    logically inferred to be absent</para>
                <para>“Indeterminate”: The phenomenon is neither “Present” nor “Absent”</para>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref493776756"/> illustrates this set of possible states and
                    their relationships to each other. </para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493776756">
                    <title>The space of value assignments in a tri-valued approach to representing
                        states of knowledge</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image5.png"
                                contentwidth="193" contentdepth="178"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>The implications of this conceptualization include the following logical
                    statements, some of which may seem counter-intuitive (note that the symbol “”
                    connotes logical equivalence, i.e. “if and only if”):</para>
                <para>Absent NOT Present AND NOT Indeterminate (Note: Absent implies NOT
                    Present)</para>
                <para>NOT Present  Absent OR Indeterminate (Note: NOT Present does not necessarily
                    imply Absent)</para>
                <para>Indeterminate  NOT Present AND NOT Absent (Note: It does not imply “Present
                    OR Absent”) </para>
                <para>It’s important to note that, in this conceptualization, Present, Absent, and
                    Indeterminate reflect the possible states<emphasis> </emphasis>of<emphasis>
                        knowledge </emphasis>about the clinical phenomenon in a particular patient,
                    not the states of the phenomenon itself. For example, Absent does not indicate
                    that the patient is necessarily free of the phenomenon, but only that the
                    medical record indicates that the patient does not have it. Similarly,
                    Indeterminate does not indicate that the patient is in some intermediate state
                    between having and not having the phenomenon or that it is impossible to
                    determine whether the patient has the phenomenon, but rather that, based on the
                    information in the medical record, it cannot be known whether the patient does
                    or does not have the phenomenon.</para>
                <para>AXIOMS:</para>
                <para>Based on this conceptualization, the three states of knowledge with respect to
                    any phenomenon, ph, are formally defined via the following axioms, which use the
                    prior definitions of “interval value” and the “IsWithin()” predicate:</para>
                <para>Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  <emphasis>ph</emphasis> where IsWithin(
                        <emphasis>ph</emphasis>.value, (0,∞] ) = TRUE</para>
                <para>Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  <emphasis>ph</emphasis> where IsWithin(
                        <emphasis>ph</emphasis>.value, [0,0] ) = TRUE</para>
                <para>Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)
                    and NOT Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)</para>
                <para>Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR
                        Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) </para>
                <para>NOT ( Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)
                    )</para>
                <para>NOT ( Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                        Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                <para>NOT ( Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                        Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref493768774"/> shows several examples of how these axioms
                    generate the appropriate value of Present, Absent, or Indeterminate for certain
                    phenomena based on how those phenomena are documented in the patient record.
                    Note that each row in the table represents a distinct state of the patient’s
                    medical record (i.e., they are not present in the record at the same time). In
                    fact, the presence of certain of the rows in the record at the same time would
                    be inconsistent with the logical model defined above.</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Example assignments of present, absent, and indeterminate based on
                        various interval values</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image6.png"
                                contentwidth="517" contentdepth="214"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref493858870">
                <title>Assigning Values to Phenomena That Include Refining Attributes</title>
                <para>In contemporary models for representing clinical observations, such as
                    SNOMED-CT, OpenEHR, and CIMI, observation instances can consist of
                    post-coordinated concept expressions, i.e., a general concept that is further
                    described and refined by a set of associated attribute/value pairs.
                    Collectively, the concept and its refining attribute/value pairs characterize
                    the distinct phenomenon that was observed. For example, <xref
                        linkend="_Ref493843663"/> shows such a post-coordinated expression
                    comprising an observed phenomenon.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493843663">
                    <title>A sample post-coordinated phenomenon. </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image7.png"
                                contentwidth="245" contentdepth="77"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>When such a phenomenon is documented in the medical record and assigned an
                    interval value, per the model specified in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493843805"
                    />, it is essential that the interval value corresponds to the conceptual
                    entirety of the phenomenon. If interval values are not clearly assigned to the
                    entirety of documented phenomena at the time the phenomena are captured and
                    stored, then inconsistent and incorrect interpretations of the data may result. </para>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref493845221"/> illustrates the correct assignment of interval
                    values to two phenomena, the first of which documents that two pressure ulcers
                    were present in the patient’s left leg on a specific date, and the second of
                    which documents that pressure ulcers were absent in the patient’s right leg on
                    the same date. The presence of both of these phenomena in the patient record at
                    the same time is intuitively possible, and is consistent with the axioms of the
                    model in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493847012"/>.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493845221">
                    <title>The correct assignment of interval values to post-coordinated phenomena. </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image8.png"
                                contentwidth="622" contentdepth="119"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref493845589"/> illustrates the problems that may occur when
                    interval values are erroneously assigned to just a subset of the
                    post-coordinated expressions used to document phenomena. In this case, the
                    interval values are assigned just to the general concept of a pressure ulcer,
                    omitting the refining attributes from the scope of the assignment. This results
                    in the representation that the patient both had and did not have pressure ulcers
                    at the same time. Because the full set of refining attributes were not included
                    in the scope of the interval-value assignment, an incorrect representation is
                    created that is intuitively non-sensical and violates the axioms of Section
                        <xref linkend="_Ref493847012"/>. Such representations can lead to incorrect
                    data-retrieval, data-analysis, and inferencing results if used by automated
                    processes later. This is underscored in the discussion of subsumption testing
                    involving phenomena in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493846313"/>.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493845589">
                    <title>The incorrect assignment of interval values to post-coordinated
                        phenomena. </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image9.png"
                                contentwidth="619" contentdepth="119"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493846313">
            <title>Normalized Querying using Subsumption Relationships Among Phenomena</title>
            <para>As mentioned in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493848005"/>, ontology-based
                representation models may produce incorrect results when performing subsumption
                testing over negated concepts. The root cause of these errors is that negation
                changes the basic rules of logical subsumption testing and must be explicitly
                handled as a special case. This section presents a formal model for handling
                subsumption over negated concepts when such concepts are represented as phenomena
                with assigned interval values.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Theoretical Foundation</title>
                <para>The semantics of logical subsumption are based on set membership. The
                    definitions of concepts (or phenomena) describe the characteristics of certain
                    sets or types of instances in the real world. We say that phenomenon A
                        <emphasis>subsumes</emphasis> phenomenon B if and only if any instance of
                    phenomenon B is <emphasis>necessarily</emphasis> an instance of phenomenon A. In
                    other words, if set A subsumes set B, the instances of set B are a subset of the
                    instances of set A. Equivalently, membership in set B <emphasis>implies
                    </emphasis>membership in set A for any instance, <emphasis>I</emphasis>, which
                    can be represented by the logical statement</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>IF Member-Set-B(<emphasis>i</emphasis>) THEN
                                Member-Set-A(<emphasis>i</emphasis>)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>These relationships can be seen graphically in <xref linkend="_Ref493852417"
                    />. Note that subsumption does not necessarily imply that Set B is a proper
                    subset of Set A – Set A and Set B could be the same.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493852417">
                    <title>Set-theoretic view of the subsumption relationship. </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image10.png"
                                contentwidth="270" contentdepth="194"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para><xref linkend="_Ref493851545"/> shows how subsumption relationships can apply
                    to clinical observations. Specifically, the figure shows a subsumption hierarchy
                    involving various types of pressure ulcer phenomena in which each parent
                    phenomenon subsumes its child phenomena, given their respective definitions. In
                    set-theoretic terms, any clinical observation that is an instance of (member-of)
                    a child phenomenon is necessarily an instance of its parent phenomenon (and,
                    indeed, any ancestors of that parent). For example, we would say that, if a
                    patient has a stage-4 pressure ulcer in the left leg, then it’s necessarily true
                    that the patient has a pressure ulcer (of some kind) in the left leg and also
                    that the patient has a pressure ulcer (somewhere on her body).</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493851545">
                    <title>An example subsumption hierarchy for post-coordinated phenomena in the
                        clinical domain. </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image11.png"
                                contentwidth="528" contentdepth="281"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>Per classical logic, statement (1) also implies the contra-positive:</para>
                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>IF NOT Member-Set-A(<emphasis>i</emphasis>) THEN NOT
                                Member-Set-B(<emphasis>i</emphasis>)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>which makes intuitive sense if one considers that an instance cannot be a
                    member of any subset of set A if it is not a member of set A to begin with. In
                    the medical context, it’s clear that a patient who does not have a pressure
                    ulcer on the right leg cannot have a stage-2 pressure ulcer on the right
                    leg.</para>
                <para>Lastly, one should note that statement (1) does <emphasis role="underline"
                        >NOT</emphasis> imply the following statements:</para>
                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>IF Member-Set-A(i) THEN Member-Set-B(i)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>IF NOT Member-Set-B(i) THEN NOT Member-Set-A(i)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>This can be seen clearly by inspection of <xref linkend="_Ref493852417"/>.
                    Note specifically that membership in Set A does not
                        <emphasis>preclude</emphasis> membership in Set B. It just does not
                    necessarily imply it, i.e., it simply provides no definitive information either
                    way. Similarly, lack of membership in Set B provides no definitive information
                    as to lack of membership in Set A.</para>
                <para>Extending this reasoning to the clinical domain, one can stipulate the
                    inferences shown in <xref linkend="_Ref493853493"/> when interval values are
                    assigned to certain of the phenomena in the subsumption hierarchy. Specifically,
                    the documented presence of a pressure ulcer in the left leg necessarily implies
                    the presence of a pressure ulcer somewhere, but it does not provide definitive
                    information about the presence of a stage-4 pressure ulcer in the left leg
                    (e.g., it could be stage 3). Similarly, the absence of a pressure ulcer in the
                    right leg necessarily implies the absence of a stage-2 pressure ulcer in the
                    right leg, but it provides no definitive information about the absence of a
                    pressure ulcer in general (e.g., there could be one in the left leg).</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493853493">
                    <title>Examples of correct subsumption inferences with respect to
                        post-coordinated phenomena.</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image12.png"
                                contentwidth="539" contentdepth="287"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="_Ref493866647">
                <title>A Formal Model of Negation with Subsumption Relationships</title>
                <para>Using these precepts of classical logic, one can generalize the set of axioms
                    introduced in <xref linkend="_Ref493847012"/> to incorporate subsumption
                    inference into the determination of whether a specified phenomenon is Present,
                    Absent, or Indeterminate, based on the state of a patient’s medical record. The
                    axioms below should replace those introduced earlier.</para>
                <para>Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  <emphasis>ph’</emphasis> where
                        Is-A(<emphasis>ph’</emphasis>, <emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                        IsWithin(<emphasis>ph’</emphasis>.value, (0,∞] ) = TRUE</para>
                <para>Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  ph’ where Is-A(<emphasis>ph’</emphasis>,
                    ph’) AND IsWithin(<emphasis>ph’</emphasis>.value, [0,0] ) = TRUE</para>
                <para>Indeterminate(ph)  NOT Present(ph) AND NOT Absent(ph)</para>
                <para>Is-A(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>, <emphasis>ph’</emphasis>)  IF an instance
                    satisfies all properties of <emphasis>ph</emphasis>, then it necessarily
                    satisfies all properties of <emphasis>ph’</emphasis>, i.e. <emphasis>ph’
                    </emphasis>subsumes <emphasis>ph</emphasis></para>
                <para>Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR
                        Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) </para>
                <para>NOT ( Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)
                    )</para>
                <para>NOT ( Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                        Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) </para>
                <para>NOT ( Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND
                        Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                <para>Again, for these axioms to hold and be mutually consistent, the scope of any
                    interval value assigned to a phenomenon must include all of its refining
                    attributes, as described in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493858870"/>.</para>
                <para>Applying standard logical operators, the axioms above also imply the following
                    logical statements:</para>
                <para>NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) NOT (  ph’ where Is-A(ph’,
                        <emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND IsWithin( ph’.value, (0,∞] ) = TRUE )</para>
                <para>NOT Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) NOT (  ph’ where
                        Is-A(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>, ph’) AND IsWithin( ph’.value, [0,0] ) = TRUE
                    )</para>
                <para>Is-A(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>, <emphasis>ph</emphasis>) (allows degenerate case
                    when present/absent are explicitly documented for a phenomenon)</para>
                <para>NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)  Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) OR
                        Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) </para>
                <para> (Note: NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) does not necessarily imply
                        Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                <para>Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) NOT Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) AND NOT
                        Indeterminate(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>)</para>
                <para> (Note: Absent(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) does imply NOT
                        Present(<emphasis>ph</emphasis>) )</para>
                <para>Returning to the original example of negation given in Section <xref
                        linkend="_Ref493859801"/>, one can now explicitly specify the closed-world
                    assumption or the open-world assumption in the manner that the query predicate
                    is formulated based on the logical definitions of “Present” and “Absent”.
                    Specifically, the query may be formulated as</para>
                <para>IF EXISTS Phenomenon ph WHERE ph.patient_Id = 9876 AND ph.conceptCode =
                    “3456_PressureUlcers” AND <emphasis> &lt;predicate&gt;</emphasis></para>
                <para>where <emphasis>&lt;predicate&gt;</emphasis> is either “NOT Present(ph)”
                    (closed-world assumption) or “Absent(ph)” (open-world assumption). The ability
                    to formulate the predicate using the higher-level abstractions “Present”, “NOT
                    Present”, “Absent”, or “NOT Absent” allows data analysts to abstract away from
                    the detailed, technical use of the IsWithin() predicate in the queries of
                    Section <xref linkend="_Ref493859801"/>. It also obviates data analysts from
                    understanding and correctly applying the logic of subsumption when negated
                    phenomenon appear in the medical record. The complete truth table for the query
                    above based on a number of potential values in the patient record are shown in
                        <xref linkend="_Ref493946553"/>.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref493946553">
                    <title>Complete truth table for querying using interval values and the
                        tri-valued model of knowledge</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="images/image13.png"
                                contentwidth="636" contentdepth="169"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Practical examples</title>
                <para>Two practical examples help to illustrate the applicability and utility of the
                    models presented above. They represent differing clinical contexts in which the
                    closed-world assumption or the open-world assumption are appropriate, and can be
                    explicitly made in the formulation of data queries.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: Medication prescription.</emphasis></para>
                <para>A decision support rule concludes that a patient meets the clinical criteria
                    to be on an antihypertensive, but must determine whether the patient is already
                    taking such a medication before recommending its prescription. The logic is best
                    formulated as</para>
                <para>IF NOT Present(prescription for antihypertensive) THEN recommend prescribing
                    an antihypertensive</para>
                <para>In this case, the closed-world assumption is appropriate in formulating the
                    query because (a) medication prescriptions are likely to be documented in the
                    medical record and (b) the explicit absence of a medication prescription is not
                    likely to be explicitly document (otherwise, all of the medications that a
                    patient were not taking would need to be documented).</para>
                <para>Note also that, were a prescription for a specific antihypertensive agent,
                    such as “Captopril” explicitly documented in the patient record, the axioms
                    presented in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> would correctly infer that
                    the predicate “NOT Present(prescription for antihypertensive)” was false,
                    because Is-A(prescription for Captopril, prescription for
                    antihypertensive).</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: Drug allergy.</emphasis></para>
                <para>A different decision support rule concludes that a patient meets the clinical
                    criteria to be prescribed penicillin, but must determine whether the patient is
                    allergic to that drug before recommending such a prescription. Here, the logic
                    is best formulated as</para>
                <para>IF Absent(allergy to penicillin) THEN recommend prescribing a
                    penicillin</para>
                <para>In this case, the open-world assumption is more appropriate because (a) it’s
                    important to be certain that no allergy exists, and (b) the presence of
                    allergies is likely to be explicitly documented in the medical record. Note also
                    the following implications of formulating the query in this way:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The explicit assignment of the interval value “[0,0]” to the
                            phenomenon “Allergy to a drug” (i.e., the documentation of “NKDA”) in
                            the medical record will result in the predicate “Absent(allergy to
                            penicillin)” evaluating to true per the axioms presented in Section
                                <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> (because Is-A(penicillin,drug) ).
                            This is the desired behavior.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The explicit assignment of the interval value “(0,∞]” to the
                            phenomenon “Allergy to Amoxicillin” (i.e., the documentation of an
                            allergy to Amoxicillin) in the medical record will result in the
                            predicate “Absent(allergy to penicillin)” evaluating to false per the
                            axioms presented in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> (because
                            Is-A(Amoxicillin, penicillin) ). Again, this is the desired
                            behavior.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If no phenomena related to drug allergies are documented in the
                            medical record at all, the phenomenon “allergy to penicillin” will be
                            indeterminate per the axioms presented in Section <xref
                                linkend="_Ref493866647"/>, which will imply that the predicate
                            “Absent(allergy to penicillin)” is false, again per the axioms. This is
                            also the desired behavior.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>These examples show that the model specified in this paper for querying with
                    negation works in a manner that is clinically appropriate in at least these two
                    important cases.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Potential Problems and Issues</title>
        <para>Although it helps to solve the problems described Section <xref
                linkend="_Ref493868573"/>, the models presented in this paper for consolidating
            “Findings” and “Observable Entities” into “Phenomena” and for normalizing the
            representation and querying of negated phenomena also entail certain challenges and
            limitations.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Negative Values for Phenomena</title>
            <para>The model does not allow interval values that include negative real numbers. In
                rare cases, clinical phenomena require such values, for example the phenomenon of
                “Max ST deflection” in an EKG, which can be either positive or negative.</para>
            <para>A potential solution in these cases is to change the modeling of certain phenomena
                so that they only take on positive numeric values. In the example above, this
                strategy would entail the specification of separate phenomena for “Max ST
                depression” and “Max ST elevation”. Further work is required to determine how often
                phenomena with negative values occur and whether the proposed strategy is effective
                is all such cases. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Values from Enumerated Value Sets that are not Numeric or not Ordinal</title>
            <para>Certain clinical phenomena have values that are simply not numeric, and to which
                the model for representing and processing interval values does not cleanly apply.
                The following phenomena and their corresponding enumerated value sets illustrate
                this point.</para>
            <para>Eye-Color: Values = (Blue, Green, Brown, Black, … )</para>
            <para>Eye-Color : Values = (1=Blue, 2=Green, 3=Brown, 4=Black, … )</para>
            <para>Dysphagia: Values = (never, rarely, sometimes, frequently, always)</para>
            <para>Patellar tendon reflex: Values = (1+, 2+, 3+, 4+)</para>
            <para>To address the reality of such observations in the medical record, the assignment
                of interval values may need to be limited to only those phenomena whose values are
                naturally numeric or can be characterized as present, absent, or indeterminate (for
                which interval values are defined). An alternative would be to always assign such
                phenomena the interval value “(0,∞]” (Present), and denote the property values using
                a different attribute (such as “color”, “frequency”, of “intensity” in the cases
                above).</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Units of Measure for Non-Quantitative Values</title>
            <para>Consolidating “Findings” and “Observable Entities” allows the use of a numeric
                interval value to denote the presence or absence of clinical observations that
                wouldn’t otherwise have numeric values, such as “nausea” or “dizziness.” Interval
                values also allow one to denote the presence and the cardinality of certain clinical
                phenomena using a single value, such as for “Daily cigarette use” or “Pressure
                ulcers”.</para>
            <para>In both situations however, there is no natural unit of measure to associate with
                the interval values. To the degree that there’s benefit in consistently assigning a
                unit of measure to all values, this void presents a problem.</para>
            <para>A possible solution is to have a “null” unit of measure, indicating that the value
                is not associated with any unit of measure. This strategy may not be unfamiliar to
                data modelers and data analysts, in that certain LOINC lab codes already include
                such a designation (such as for Urine Specific Gravity, a dimensionless
                measurement). Alternatively, one could create special-purpose units of measure to
                associate with dimensionless values. Again, this strategy has been adopted for
                certain LOINC lab codes, such as pH (which includes a special “[pH]” unit of
                measure) or manual cell count (which includes the special “per high powered field”
                unit of measure).</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Subsumption over all Refining Attributes of Phenomena</title>
            <para>As described in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493858870"/>, correct application of
                the tri-valued model for querying phenomena requires that interval values be
                assigned to the entirety of each phenomenon (including all of its refining
                attributes). Further, the correct applications of the axioms in Section <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493866647"/> also require that subsumption testing between
                phenomenon (i.e., application of the “Is-A()” predicate within these axioms) include
                all of the refining attributes to which interval values have been assigned. If
                subsumption testing is performed using only a subset of the attributes to which
                interval values are assigned, the axioms will produce incorrect results.</para>
            <para>The point is illustrated through several examples shown in <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493941874"/>. </para>
            <para>Note, for example, that if subsumption testing between phenomenon 1 and phenomenon
                3 excludes the “Observation-Date” value in phenomenon 3, and “Observation-Date” is
                within the scope of the attributes to which the interval value “[2,2]” has been
                assigned, then phenomenon 3 will be subsumed by phenomenon 1 and the axioms of
                Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> will infer that phenomenon 1 is present.
                However, upon inspection, it is clear that the presence of two pressure ulcers in
                the right leg on Oct. 4, 2017 does not necessarily imply the presence of any
                pressure ulcers on July 7, 2017. Subsumption testing that correctly included the
                “Observation-Date” attribute would have prevented this incorrect inference and
                concluded that the existence of pressure ulcers on July 7, 2017 was indeterminate
                based on the available data.</para>
            <para>Similarly, if subsumption testing between phenomenon 5 and phenomenon 2 excludes
                the “Laterality” attribute of the anatomical location of phenomenon 5 (a nested
                attribute), and “Laterality” is within the scope of the attributes to which the
                interval value “[0,0]” has been assigned, then phenomenon 5 will be subsumed by
                phenomenon 2 and the axioms of Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> will infer
                that phenomenon 5 is absent. Again, however, intuition should make clear that the
                absence of a pressure ulcer on left leg on July 18, 2017 does not necessarily imply
                the absence of a pressure on the right leg on that same date. Inclusion of the
                “Laterality” attribute in the subsumption test would have prevented this incorrect
                inference, and caused the axioms of Section <xref linkend="_Ref493866647"/> to
                conclude that the presence of a stage-2 pressure ulcer in the right leg on that date
                was indeterminate based on the data.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref493941874">
                <title>Examples of correct and incorrect application of subsumption testing
                    involving post-coordinated phenomena.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image14.png"
                            contentwidth="661" contentdepth="351"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The point of these examples is to underscore the importance of including all of
                the refining attributes to which interval values are assigned in any subsumption
                tests that are later performed. In practice, however, this may not be a trivial
                undertaking. For example, subsumption testing between date values of different
                granularities (year vs. month vs. day) is not supported by standard description
                logic reasoners, so that a phenomenon observed in July 2017 may not correctly
                subsume the same observation observed on July 12, 2017. Further, the correct
                semantics of subsumption between date values when assigned to clinical observations
                may not be straightforward. For example, assigning an Observation-Date value of
                “July 2017” to a phenomenon could mean that the phenomenon was observed at
                    <emphasis>some point</emphasis> in July 2017, or it could mean that the
                phenomenon was observed throughout the duration of July 2017. The intended meaning
                has implications for whether a phenomenon with the Observation-Date value of “July
                2017” should subsume a phenomenon with the Observation-Date value of “July 18, 2017”
                with respect to the application of the axioms in Section <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493866647"/>.</para>
            <para>Similar questions arise regarding the scope of attributes to which interval values
                should be assigned, and which ones comprise refining attributes of the phenomenon
                itself (such as laterality, observation-date, severity, etc.), and which ones
                comprise meta-attributes that do not refine the phenomenon (such as identity of the
                observer, method of observation, purpose of the observation, etc.). Strictly
                speaking, meta-attributes should be excluded from the scope of interval-value
                assignments and (therefore) from subsumption testing, but in certain cases it may
                not be clear which attributes are truly refining attributes and which are meta-data,
                and that distinction may even be context specific. For example, method of
                observation may be a significant attribute of the observed phenomenon in certain
                cases, but not others. All of these issues remain to be examined and resolved before
                one can correctly and reliably apply the models presented here.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>“Cognitive Dissonance”</title>
            <para>The final challenge in using the models described here is the unintuitive nature
                of representing the values of all clinical observations using numeric intervals, as
                formalized in Section <xref linkend="_Ref493843805"/>. The notion that entirely
                qualitative clinical observations such as “nausea” and “dizziness” have quantitative
                interval values may be difficult for those implementing and working with the
                proposed model to grasp and accept. Similarly, the model produces certain
                unintuitive characterizations of clinical observations that only have numeric
                values, such as the conclusion that a “Serum Potassium” observation is “Present” if
                it’s value is &gt; 0, and otherwise is “Absent”. It remains to be seen whether those
                using the model can overcome potential “cognitive dissonance” in encountering such
                implications.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>This whitepaper presents a formal approach to normalizing the representation of
            clinical observations currently distinguished as “Findings” and “Observable Entities” in
            medical record systems and to normalizing the retrieval and analysis of such
            observations when negation has been used in the recording or the later querying of the
            observations. The models presented have favorable properties that address certain of the
            problems in existing models. However, they also present certain theoretical problems and
            issues that remain to be analyzed and resolved. They also have not yet been implemented
            in prototype or production systems to evaluate their practical feasibility, utility, and
            correctness. Such analysis and implementation constitute the next steps in pursuing the
            proposed approach.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
</article>
