<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
    <article version="5.0" xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
        xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
        xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
        xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
        xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
        <info>
            <title>FHIR Resources and Profiles in Relation to CIMI and SOLOR</title>
            <author>
                <personname>Walter Sujansky</personname>
            </author>
            <date>2018-09-28</date>
        </info>
        
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>The HL7 FHIR standard<footnote xml:id="__EN1__">
                <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://hl7.org/implement/standards/fhir/"
                        >http://hl7.org/implement/standards/fhir/</link> (Accessed 9/28/2018)</para>
            </footnote> is a web-services API specification for accessing clinical data via RESTful
            calls and data structures. Although FHIR can provide substantial utility for the
            exchange of patient data across healthcare applications, its current form also entails
            certain limitations that compromise interoperability. A couple of independent
            data-modeling initiatives in health care (CIMI and SOLOR), however, could be leveraged
            to address certain of the existing limitations in the FHIR standard. This paper reviews
            the essential elements of FHIR, describes certain of FHIR’s limitations that may
            compromise interoperability, and proposes how the work underway in the CIMI and SOLOR
            projects could address these limitations.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Advancing the Interoperability Potential of FHIR</title>
        <para>FHIR has gained substantial attention in recent years as a modern technology to
            support interoperability, with good reason. The sound technical foundation and avid
            uptake of FHIR have made it the premier mechanism for exchanging patient data between
            applications and independent, remotely hosted data stores. However, the current FHIR
            data model and mechanisms to customize and extend it have limitations that may benefit
            from work in parallel, related data-modeling initiatives currently underway. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Review of FHIR</title>
            <para>FHIR is a RESTful<footnote xml:id="__EN2__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer"
                            >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer</link>
                        (Accessed 9/28/2018)</para>
                </footnote> standard for requesting and retrieving clinical data via HTTP
                web-services calls. <xref linkend="_Ref510779798"/> shows how FHIR data requests are
                made by sending HTTP “GET” commands over the internet, with each command encoded as
                a URL that specifies a particular kind of data resource and a set of filtering
                criteria. Responses to such queries consist of structured data objects encoded in
                standardized formalisms, usually XML or JSON. For example, <xref
                    linkend="_Ref510798078"/> shows a response to the second of the shown data
                requests in Figure, which returns the resolved conditions for a specific patient (in
                this case, a malignancy of the head and neck).</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref510779798">
                <title>The basic FHIR model for requesting and retrieving patient data.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image1.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref510798078">
                <title>An example of a JSON-encoded data instance retrieved via a FHIR
                    query.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image2.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The FHIR standard specifies the structure, contents, and coding for over 90 types
                of data resources relevant to clinical medicine. <xref linkend="_Ref510799056"/>
                lists some of the most commonly used of these resource types.</para>
            <para>For each resource type defined by FHIR, there exists a detailed specification of
                the resource’s data elements, which of the elements are required vs. optional and
                single-valued vs. multi-valued, the data type(s) that the value(s) of the elements
                must conform to, and any coding systems or value sets that code-able data values
                must be drawn from. <xref linkend="_Ref510798360"/> shows part of the specification
                for the <emphasis>Condition</emphasis> resource specified in FHIR. The inset in
                    <xref linkend="_Ref510798360"/> shows the structure for one of the complex data
                types (<emphasis>Identifier</emphasis>) that corresponds to one of the data
                elements. Note that complex data structures have their own constraints on the set of
                data elements, cardinality constraints, data types, and coding restrictions for
                related to their structures. As shown, the “type” of the Identifier must, itself, be
                structured using the <emphasis>Codeable Concept</emphasis> data type, and values for
                the type must be drawn from a specified value set (“Identifier Type Codes”).</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref510799056">
                <title>Certain of the most commonly used of the ~90 FHIR resources.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image3.jpg"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref510798360">
                <title>An example of a FHIR resource specification, including a complex data
                    type.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image4.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>FHIR Profiling</title>
            <para>As evident from a close inspection of the specification for the
                    <emphasis>Conditions</emphasis> resource, the resource definitions in FHIR
                provide relatively few constraints on the structure and coding of the clinical data
                represented using those resources. For example, the specification of the “code” data
                element does not specify any required coding system for representing patient
                conditions (it only provides one such coding system as an “example”). This
                underspecification means that different implementations of the FHIR standard (such
                as the requester and respondent for a FHIR resource query) may use entirely
                different codes to represent patient conditions, while both being fully compliant
                with the FHIR standard.</para>
            <para>The design of the FHIR standard anticipated this problem and, to address it,
                included explicit and formal mechanisms to create more constrained versions of FHIR
                resources for use by data-trading partners who want to or need to achieve a greater
                degree of standardization and plug-and-play interoperability<footnote
                    xml:id="__EN3__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/profiling.html"
                            >https://www.hl7.org/fhir/profiling.html</link> (Accessed
                        9/28/2018)</para>
                </footnote>. These mechanisms enable the definition of “profiles” with respect to
                FHIR resources, which add constraints to the resources while maintaining backward
                compatibility with them (i.e., so that any valid instance of a profile is also
                necessarily a valid instance of the resource on which the profile is based).</para>
            <para><xref linkend="_Ref525899874"/> shows an example of such a profile for the
                    <emphasis>Observation</emphasis> resource, which was designed to specifically
                represent observations that are laboratory test results. The upper portion of <xref
                    linkend="_Ref525899874"/> shows the contents of the profile, and the lower
                portion shows the content of the underlying FHIR <emphasis>Observation
                </emphasis>resource on which the profile is based. The boxed areas highlight
                specific additional constraints that have been added to certain data elements. For
                example, the <emphasis>category</emphasis> data element in the profile specifies
                that the category must be “laboratory,” the <emphasis>code</emphasis> data element
                specifies that LOINC codes must be used to encode the identity of the test that was
                performed, the <emphasis>value</emphasis> data element specifies that only the UCUM
                coding system may be used to encode units of measure (the base FHIR
                    <emphasis>Observation</emphasis> resource includes none of these
                constraints).</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref525899874">
                <title>The <emphasis>Result Observation </emphasis>profile (top) defined against the
                    core <emphasis>Observation </emphasis>resource.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image5.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The FHIR profiling mechanism includes four increasingly constrained designations
                for the use of coding systems and value sets, as shown in <xref
                    linkend="_Ref525900590"/> in decreasing order of constraint. Many of the coding
                systems and value sets specified in the base FHIR profiles include the “example”
                designation only, which indicates that implementers are not required to use values
                from those coding systems or value sets. In FHIR profiles, however, the designations
                of “required” or “extensible” are used, which indicate that the coding system or
                value set must be used, at least if they contain an appropriate code for the
                intended concept.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref525900590">
                <title>FHIR constraints on the use of designated coding systems and value
                    sets.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image6.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Lastly, but importantly, the FHIR profiling mechanism includes a construct to add
                entirely new data elements to FHIR resources – the “extension”<footnote
                    xml:id="__EN4__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/profiling.html#extensions"
                            >https://www.hl7.org/fhir/profiling.html#extensions</link> (Accessed
                        9/28/2018)</para>
                </footnote>. FHIR resources are quite general and intended to express roughly 80% of
                the necessary content across relevant instances of clinical data. However,
                expressing the complete content of certain patient data requires additional data
                elements that were not defined in FHIR. Profiles can add data elements to represent
                such content through the definition of extension elements. </para>
            <para>For example, <xref linkend="_Ref525901255"/> shows the addition of three extension
                elements to the <emphasis>Patient</emphasis> resource for representing race,
                ethnicity, and birth sex (data elements required to be captured by the U.S. EHR
                meaningful use program). Note that each extension element is uniquely identified via
                a URL value, which references the definition and required structured/content of all
                data represented using the extension. </para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref525901255">
                <title>Examples of extension data elements in the FHIR <emphasis>Patient</emphasis>
                    profile.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image7.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The definition of the extension element in the boxed area of <xref
                    linkend="_Ref525901255"/> (“us-core-ethnicity”)<footnote xml:id="__EN5__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/core/StructureDefinition-us-core-race.html"
                            >http://hl7.org/fhir/us/core/StructureDefinition-us-core-race.html</link>
                        (Accessed 9/28/2018)</para>
                </footnote> is shown in <xref linkend="_Ref525901484"/>. Note that the extension,
                itself, consists of three components (nested extensions) that are used to express
                the race category, the race code, and the text description of the race code. </para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref525901484">
                <title>Definition of the “us-core-race” data extension used in the
                        <emphasis>Patient</emphasis> profile.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image8.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Finally, <xref linkend="_Ref525901668"/> shows how a specific instance of the
                    <emphasis>Patient</emphasis> profile, as defined in <xref
                    linkend="_Ref525901255"/> and <xref linkend="_Ref525901484"/>, would use the
                extension data element to represent that a patient was of the race
                “Filipino.”</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref525901668">
                <title>An example instance patient demographic data that contains a race designation
                    encoded per the defined “us-core-race” extension. </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image9.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Note also in <xref linkend="_Ref525901668"/> that the “meta” data element near the
                top of the <emphasis>Patient</emphasis> instance specifies the profile to which the
                instance is declared to conform. This explicit denotation enables both sending and
                receiving systems to automatically validate that the data instance conforms to all
                of the constraints of the indicated profile. For example, in the case of the
                extension element “us-core-race,” one could validate that the value includes at
                least the text representation of the race, and may optionally include a race
                category and race code, both drawn from respectively specified value sets (per the
                extension definition in <xref linkend="_Ref525901484"/>).</para>
            <para>When patient data are requested, a profile may also be specified as an additional
                filter within the request URL, as shown in <xref linkend="_Ref525902358"/>. This
                capability allows data requestor to receive only those instances of data that are
                encoded per the profile(s) that they require, which ensures that required data will
                be present and appropriately structured/coded. </para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref525902358">
                <title>A FHIR query requesting only those <emphasis>Observation</emphasis> instances
                    encoded using a specific profile.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image10.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Limitations of FHIR Profiling</title>
            <para>Despite the powerful and useful features of profiling that are provided by the
                FHIR standard, there remain certain limitations in existing profiles and in the
                profiling mechanism that continue to frustrate efforts to effectively standardize
                patient data when it is exchanged between healthcare applications. These limitations
                include a lack of granularity in existing profiles and a profusion of profiles that
                sometimes overlap and are rarely mandated for use </para>
            <section>
                <title>Lack of Granularity</title>
                <para>A set of “U.S. Core” FHIR profiles have been created and assembled into an
                    “implementation guide” intended to support the specific requirements of the U.S.
                    meaningful use (M.U.) program. Although conformance to these profiles is not yet
                    a requirement of EHR certification under the M.U. program, many EHR vendors and
                    other system developers are implementing versions of these profiles in their
                    production software. However, the U.S. Core profiles still lack the degree of
                    specificity and granularity needed to represent common clinical data in a
                    standardized and near-plug-and-play manner. Such continued underspecification
                    leaves latitude for different system developers to represent the same clinical
                    data in different ways, while all being fully conformant to the U.S. Core
                    profiles.</para>
                <para>For example, the U.S. Core <emphasis>Observation</emphasis> and
                        <emphasis>Diagnostic Report</emphasis> profiles allow several different ways
                    for a multi-part clinical observation (such as a blood pressure consisting of a
                    systolic and diastolic measurement) to be represented. For example, as shown in
                        <xref linkend="_Ref525904021"/>, the available data elements within these
                    two profiles allow a blood pressure reading to be represented as (A) an
                        <emphasis>Observation </emphasis>instance that references two other
                    “related” <emphasis>Observation </emphasis>instances, each containing the
                    systolic and diastolic values, (B) a <emphasis>Diagnostic Report
                    </emphasis>instance that references two other “result” <emphasis>Observation
                    </emphasis>instances, each containing the systolic and diastolic values, or (C)
                    a single <emphasis>Observation</emphasis> instance that include two nested
                    ”component” elements, each containing the systolic and diastolic values. <xref
                        linkend="_Ref525904586"/> shows graphically how each of these alternative
                    representation decisions would result in different data structures for the same
                    blood-pressure data.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref525904021">
                    <title>Data elements within the FHIR <emphasis>Observation</emphasis> and
                            <emphasis>DiagnosticReport</emphasis> profiles that may be used to
                        represent blood-pressure measurements in different ways.</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image11.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref525904586">
                    <title>Graphical representations of alternative modeling of blood pressure using
                        existing FHIR profiles (graphic courtesy of courtesy of Claude Nanjo,
                        Cognitive Medicine, AMIA 2017).</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image12.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>“Extension Salad”</title>
                <para>The other limitation of the current approach to FHIR profiling is that a great
                    many extensions have been created to supplement the built-in data elements in
                    FHIR profiles, so as to fully represent necessary clinical data, but these
                    extensions have been developed in an <emphasis>ad hoc </emphasis>manner by
                    various organizations for various purposes without regard for duplication of
                    content or consistency with any common data model (the exception to this
                    observation is the U.S. Core profile, which developed extensions in a more
                    coordinated fashion). The result is a large set of published extensions, with no
                    requirement for any system developers to use any one or any combination of them
                    in the profiles they have created or chosen. <xref linkend="_Ref525905355"/>,
                    for example, shows a subset of the extensions that have been published just by
                        HL7<footnote xml:id="__EN6__">
                        <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/profilelist.html"
                                >https://www.hl7.org/fhir/profilelist.html</link> (Accessed
                            9/28/2018)</para>
                    </footnote>. </para>
                <para>This approach of uncoordinated extension creation provides freedom for
                    everyone, with guaranteed interoperability for no one. In particular, no
                    assurance exists that any subset of the extensions that a system developer may
                    choose to implement will be consistent with each other, or that the extensions
                    used by one clinical information system will be consistent and interoperable
                    with the extensions used by another system.</para>
                <figure xml:id="_Ref525905355">
                    <title>Examples of extension data elements published on the HL7 web
                        site.</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image13.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Role of CIMI in Addressing FHIR Profile Limitations</title>
            <para>The CIMI data-modeling initiative within HL7<footnote xml:id="__EN7__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/Special/Committees/cimi/index.cfm"
                            >http://www.hl7.org/Special/Committees/cimi/index.cfm</link> (Accessed
                        9/28/2018)</para>
                </footnote> offers a potential solution to both the issue of insufficient
                granularity and profusion of incompatible extensions. CIMI is in the process of
                creating detailed clinical data models (“DCMs”) for specific types of observations,
                which will include all of the data elements needed to represent the relevant aspects
                of the observations, as well as define the appropriate coding systems and value sets
                for these data elements. For example, as shown in <xref linkend="_Ref525905817"/>, a
                CIMI DCM will be defined for blood-pressure observations, to include the components
                for systolic and diastolic measurements, as well as additional aspects of that
                particular observation type, such as body position and BP cuff size.</para>
            <para>Based on the content of CIMI DCMs, specific FHIR profiles may be created that both
                (1) specifically indicate how the abstract data models defined in DCMs should be
                represented using the built-in data elements of FHIR resources, and (2) what
                extension data elements should be added specifically for those profiles to capture
                the full extent of relevant data for each particular type of observation. The
                right-hand side of <xref linkend="_Ref525905817"/> shows the conversion of a CIMI
                DCM for blood-pressure measurements to a corresponding FHIR profile that is also
                specific to that type of observation. By developing and adopting a large set of
                specific FHIR profiles that correspond closely to the DCMs defined by CIMI, the
                Industry will achieve highly granular data structures that are more standardized
                across implementers and that include extension elements created in a coordinated,
                model-based, and mutually consistent fashion. </para>
            <para><xref linkend="_Ref525906692"/> shows the formal specification<footnote
                    xml:id="__EN8__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://simplifier.net/fhirworkshop2/vitalsignsprofile"
                            >https://simplifier.net/fhirworkshop2/vitalsignsprofile</link> (Accessed
                        9/28/2018)</para>
                </footnote> of the FHIR profile on the right-hand side of <xref
                    linkend="_Ref525905817"/>, which can be used as the basis for constructing and
                validating conformant instances of blood-pressure observations.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref525906692">
                <title>Formal definition of a FHIR profile for blood pressure, based on a CIMI
                    DCM.</title>
                <para xml:id="_Ref525905817">A CIMI detailed clinical model and corresponding FHIR profile<inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image14.png"
                                width="5.5in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
            </figure>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image15.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Role of SOLOR in Addressing FHIR Profile Limitations</title>
            <para>The SOLOR project is an initiative to integrate coded concepts from distinct
                terminologies so as to formally reconcile semantic equivalences and other logical
                relationships across the terminologies’ content<footnote xml:id="__EN9__">
                    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://solor.io">http://solor.io</link> (Accessed
                        9/26/2018)</para>
                </footnote>. Such reconciliation enables patient data that have been encoded using
                different terminologies to be more accurately transferred between clinical
                information systems and more effectively analyzed when integrated within
                population-health data repositories. </para>
            <para>The integration of terminology resources within SOLOR can also facilitate the
                creation of value sets for CIMI DCMs and/or FHIR profiles when the contents of such
                value sets must be drawn from multiple terminologies. A notable example of this
                requirement is in the value set for encoding allergenic substances. This value set
                needs to include overlapping content from SNOMED-CT, RxNorm, and NDF-RT to fully
                capture all of the drug classes, named drugs, and drug ingredients that may be
                allergenic substances. To correctly analyze allergen codes drawn from this expansive
                value set (for example, in decision-support rules or quality measures), the
                recipients of data must have access to a resource that represents and manages the
                semantic relationships across the contents of all of these terminologies. </para>
            <para>SOLOR has the opportunity to be this resource by integrating the contents of
                SNOMED-CT, RxNorm, and NDF-RT in a semantically sound way and making the integrated
                content available as a value set that can be referenced by CIMI DCMs, FHIR profiles,
                or other clinical data models. The creation of such a SOLOR resource would,
                therefore, be an apt demonstration of SOLOR’s power and utility.</para>
            <para>Given the formal foundation of SOLOR in description logic (DL), elements of the
                SOLOR resource could also be used to help define CIMI DCMs and ensure that these
                models (or appropriate subsets of them) are mappable to equivalent DL
                representations. This feature of DCMs will enable clinical statements represented in
                FHIR or other instantiations of DCMs to be compared to each other or to reference
                concepts using DL classifiers. Such a logic based approach analyzing concepts will
                add power to queries used in decision support applications or data-analytic
                applications.</para>
            <para><xref linkend="_Ref510792220"/> illustrates these varied uses of SOLOR content in
                the development of CIMI DCMs and corresponding FHIR profiles. <xref
                    linkend="_Ref510792401"/> shows an example of the data elements within the FHIR
                    <emphasis>Observation</emphasis> resource that have no mandated value sets and
                could benefit from the consolidated terminology content of SOLOR in defining their
                coding constraints.</para>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref510792220">
                <title>Graphical depiction of the potential uses of SOLOR content in modeling CIMI
                    DCMs and FHIR profiles.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image16.jpg"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="_Ref510792401">
                <title>Examples of data elements in FHIR resources that may benefit from value sets
                    developed using SOLOR.</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/image17.png"
                            width="5.5in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>FHIR is a valuable resource for modeling clinical data that are exchanged between
            applications via web-services calls. However, the existing mechanisms for defining
            highly constrained plug-and-playable data structures within FHIR have been limited to
            date by an insufficient granularity in modeling clinical observations, by a profusion of
            uncoordinated and incompatible extension data elements, and by (in certain cases) an
            unprincipled aggregation of disparate terminologies into the same value sets. The work
            currently underway in the CIMI and SOLOR projects could be brought to bear on these
            challenges within a collaborative approach that brings the healthcare industry closer to
            truly interoperable data structures and coding systems.</para>
    </section>
</article>
