<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article version="5.1" xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <info>
         <title>Implementing an Improved Architecture to Manage CDS Knowledge Artifacts
        </title>
        <subtitle>A Three-Year Roadmap</subtitle>
        <author>
            <personname>Walter Sujansky</personname>
        </author>
        <date>2017-09-30</date>
    </info>
    
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para xml:id="_Toc486430913">A previous report<footnote xml:id="__EN1__">
                <para>An Architecture for Managing Clinical Decision Support Knowledge Artifacts
                    With Implications for Patient Safety: Principles, Tools and Processes. Veterans
                    Health Administration, Office of Informatics &amp; Analytics and Health
                    Informatics, Informatics Architecture Support Services. July 5, 2017.</para>
            </footnote> specified a desired “future state” for the tools and processes used by the
            Veterans Health Administration (VHA) to manage knowledge artifacts in its clinical
            decision support (CDS) systems. The future state was based on an earlier
                assessment<footnote xml:id="__EN2__">
                <para>Processes for the Management of Clinical Decision Support Knowledge Artifacts
                    With Implications for Patient Safety: Background, Best Practices, and Current
                    State. Veterans Health Administration, Office of Informatics &amp; Analytics and
                    Health Informatics, Informatics Architecture Support Services. March 31,
                    2017.</para>
            </footnote> of the gaps between VHA’s current processes and recognized best practices
            for managing knowledge artifacts that have implications for patient safety. This report
            lays out a three-year roadmap for actually implementing the prescribed future state. </para>
        <para>The roadmap incorporates a number of judgements and assumptions about the environment
            in which CDS knowledge artifacts will be managed, the logical sequence of implementing
            the future-state tools and processes in that environment, and the approximate time frame
            required to complete the implementation. Certain of these assumptions are subject to
            change, so that the roadmap will likely need to be adjusted over time. Notably, as VHA
            prepares to replace its bespoke EHR and CDS environments with COTS products from Cerner,
            the features of those commercial products will influence the development pace and the
            final state of the envisioned environment for managing CDS artifacts.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Overview of roadmap for the future-state architecture</title>
        <para>The future state architecture described earlier<footnote xml:id="__EN3__">
            <para>An Architecture for Managing Clinical Decision Support Knowledge Artifacts
                With Implications for Patient Safety: Principles, Tools and Processes. Veterans
                Health Administration, Office of Informatics &amp; Analytics and Health
                Informatics, Informatics Architecture Support Services. July 5, 2017.</para>
        </footnote> characterizes the <emphasis>types</emphasis>
            <emphasis>of CDS knowledge artifacts</emphasis> that need to be carefully managed, the
            appropriate <emphasis>life-cycle processes</emphasis> for managing those artifacts, and
            the applicable <emphasis>software-development tools</emphasis> needed to operationalize
            those life-cycle processes. The reader is strongly encouraged to review that report to
            best understand the roadmap described here. Several key points, however, are summarized
            below.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Types of CDS knowledge artifacts</emphasis>. Note the
                    distinction between <emphasis>high-level artifacts</emphasis> (rules, order
                    sets, documentation templates) and <emphasis>sub-artifacts </emphasis>(coded
                    concepts, value sets, data-access functions, data-manipulation functions,
                    orderable items, and external system interfaces). The roadmap sequences the
                    handling of these types of artifacts differently.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Life-cycle processes</emphasis>. The prescribed
                    processes are based on the IEC 62304 standard for developing and maintaining
                    software with implications for patient safety. Key emphases include risk
                    management, quality assurance, configuration management, and rigorous
                    documentation/validation of the life-cycle process steps.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Software-development tools</emphasis>. Appropriate
                    software tools are essential to operationalizing the life-cycle processes, and
                    the roadmap interleaves the introduction of processes and tools accordingly.
                    Many general-purpose tools already exist to manage issue tracking, version
                    control, configuration management, automated testing, and software
                    compile/validate/release steps. Integrated development environments (IDEs) also
                    exist to combine these tools into convenient and powerful work benches for
                    software developers, a model that can and should be extended to CDS knowledge
                    management.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para><xref linkend="_Ref493493823"/> summarizes the development roadmap for the future
            state, based on these concepts and other materials in the prior report. Section <xref
                linkend="_Ref493494001"/> expands on each of the steps in the roadmap, with
            references to the corresponding sections of the future-state report (in square brackets
            at the beginning of each sub-section, such as “[4.3.1]”).</para>
        <figure xml:id="_Ref493493823">
            <title>Overview of three-year roadmap.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/image2.png"
                        width="6.5in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="_Ref493494001">
        <title>Year-One Tasks</title>
        <para>Year one will be devoted to overall planning and to implementing the highest-priority
            processes and tools of the future-state architecture.</para>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493510187">
            <title>Define the envisioned knowledge artifact development/maintenance
                processes</title>
            <para>[4.2.1 and 4.3.1] The initial step is to define the specific processes that will
                be in place for developing and maintaining knowledge artifacts at the conclusion of
                the three-year implementation project. These processes will be based on the contents
                of the IEC 62304 standard, and will include the sequence of applicable
                analysis/design/implementation/testing/release steps, as well as the documentation
                and validation tasks accompanying each step. Although the complete processes will be
                implemented iteratively, to allow time for the necessary training, tooling, and
                workflow adjustments, the <emphasis>a priori</emphasis> specification of the
                processes will define the “end state” of the implementation. </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493510198">
            <title>Define in detail the required tools and envisioned tooling architecture</title>
            <para>[3.1 – 3.8, high level] Based on the characterization of the required tools in the
                “future state” report, research and plan the implementation of each type of tool and
                the interfaces among the tools to ultimately produce an integrated development
                environment for knowledge artifacts. Certain of the tools may exist already and
                simply require configuration and integration to meet the requirements for
                knowledge-artifact development. Other tools may require the significant
                modification/customization of existing software (either via internal development
                when open-source code is available or externally contracted modifications to
                proprietary products). Entirely <emphasis>de novo </emphasis>development may even be
                required in certain cases, but only as a last resort. </para>
            <para>Again, the specified tools and integrated architecture will comprise an “end
                state” of the planned tooling environment for CDS-artifact development, recognizing
                that an iterative, three-year process will be required to achieve this state.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Perform gap analysis between existing environment and envisioned
                processes/tools</title>
            <para>Using the results of the Sections <xref linkend="_Ref493510187"/> and <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493510198"/> as the planned end state, analyze the existing
                processes and tools for managing CDS artifacts within the COTS products (Cerner and
                otherwise) to be used for EHR and CDS functions in the future. The goal of this
                analysis will be to understand and document the gap between the existing
                capabilities of the COTS products and the desired future-state architecture for
                knowledge-artifact management. The gap analysis will allow fine-tuning of the
                prescribed development/maintenance processes and envisioned tooling to account for
                already existing features or notable constraints of the COTS products. The results
                of Sections <xref linkend="_Ref493510187"/> and <xref linkend="_Ref493510198"/>, and
                perhaps other details of this roadmap, may need to be adjusted subsequent to this
                gap analysis.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Define identification scheme for all configuration items</title>
            <para>[3.2, 3.4.1, and 4.4.2] An important early step in the implementation of a
                knowledge-artifact management system is to define a scheme for uniquely identifying
                and versioning each artifact. The relevant artifacts include <emphasis>source
                    objects</emphasis>, <emphasis>compiled artifacts</emphasis>, and
                    <emphasis>knowledge modules</emphasis> (as defined in Section 2.2 of the “future
                state” architecture document). </para>
            <para>A rigorous, while practical, identification scheme is critical to supporting
                version control and configuration management. The identification scheme should
                guarantee global uniqueness across potentially multiple name spaces (for example,
                each individual VHA facility, as well as the centralized national release center).
                An appropriate representation system for identifiers (GUIDs, OIDs, URIs, etc.) must
                be selected that is compatible with the envisioned version-control,
                configuration-management, and other tooling.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implement version control and configuration management system</title>
            <para>[3.2, 3.4.1, and 4.4.2] Once an identification scheme is defined, the next step is
                to implement a reliable version-control and configuration-management system to
                manage actual knowledge artifacts as they are developed, packaged, and released.
                Alternatives include separate version-control and configuration-management systems
                that may be used in tandem (such as Git for version control and Maven for
                configuration management), or a combined version-control/configuration-management
                tool (such as ClearCase). In any case, the selected tool(s) should include a
                programmatic API to enable later integration with an IDE for knowledge management.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implement Phase-1 IDE: Editing, version control, and configuration
                management</title>
            <para>[3.8] It will likely require several years to implement a comprehensive IDE for
                knowledge management, given the need to integrate a number of tools and support a
                variety of rigorous development and maintenance processes. In the meantime, certain
                tools may not be available to knowledge developers, and other tools may be available
                only in stand-alone versions that require separate access and use. </para>
            <para>The initial version of the IDE should include those features deemed most important
                to have integrated so as to prevent errors in the development and maintenance of
                knowledge artifacts. Given the importance of editing the correct versions of
                knowledge artifacts, maintaining awareness of the other software components on which
                those artifacts depend, and catching syntactic and semantic errors in the
                specifications of knowledge artifacts as early as possible, the IDE should first
                include features for version control, configuration management, and smart editing.
                The integration of these capabilities will be based on the technical architecture
                for tooling that was defined in task <xref linkend="_Ref493510198"/> above.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493595674">
            <title>Implement initial procedures and tools for knowledge-artifact “build”
                process</title>
            <para>[3.3, 4.2.4, 4.2.5] The complete build process for knowledge artifacts consists of
                the following parts:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Validating the static correctness and consistency of the knowledge
                        artifacts prior to compilation</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Compiling the artifacts into a form that can be executed directly by a
                        decision-support engine</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Performing any automated unit tests on the compiled knowledge artifacts to
                        detect logic and other runtime errors</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Packaging the knowledge artifacts into clearly identified and versioned
                        release modules that can be distributed and deployed as internally
                        consistent units</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Although implementing extensive automated validation and testing capabilities is
                critical to producing safe knowledge artifacts, doing so will require considerable
                effort and will have to be undertaken in phases.</para>
            <para>During year one, the initial implementation of the build process should focus on
                the compilation process (with basic validation checks, such as ensuring type
                compatibility for calls to other knowledge artifacts or external APIs), as well as
                the packaging process (to generate appropriately identified and versioned modules
                that can be loaded as units into runtime CDS environments). Focusing on these
                aspects will enable robust configuration management and release processes for
                knowledge artifacts, and lay the groundwork for more advanced validation and
                automated testing processes in later phases of the implementation roadmap.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implement test environments that reliably simulate production environment</title>
            <para>[4.2.5] To ensure valid testing, manual and automated testing processes must be
                performed in an environment that faithfully represents the production environment
                into which the tested software will ultimately be deployed. To this end, it must be
                possible to build and deploy such test environments as the production environment
                evolves over time. In the case of CDS knowledge artifacts, this means maintaining a
                meticulous record of the configuration of the production environment at all times
                (including the decision-support engine, other knowledge artifacts currently in
                production, and external systems that knowledge artifacts may interface to, such as
                the EHR, terminology server, or alert-notification mechanism). Based on this
                recorded information, it must be possible to reliably and efficiently clone the
                production configuration as faithfully as possible in the testing
                environment.</para>
            <para>By the end of the first year of the roadmap, processes should be in place to
                maintain a record of the production configuration at all times and reproduce it in a
                testing environment automatically. These processes will lay a critical foundation
                for the rigorous testing needed to ensure patient safety in CDS systems.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implement issue-tracking and workflow system</title>
            <para>[3.6] As a final step in the first year of the roadmap, a robust issue tracking
                system should be deployed and appropriately configured to support all aspects of the
                knowledge-artifact development and maintenance processes. Numerous open-source and
                commercial applications exist to support issue tracking and workflow for general
                software development. Although the detailed development and maintenance processes
                for knowledge artifacts differ somewhat from those for general software code, the
                existing capabilities and configurability of existing issue-tracking applications
                will likely meet the needs of knowledge engineers as well. Once such a tool is in
                place, it will enable even large teams to measurably conform to best practices in
                the development and maintenance of knowledge artifacts.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Year-Two Tasks</title>
        <para>Year two will focus on implementing robust risk-management, validation, and
            problem-resolution processes for the development and maintenance of CDS knowledge
            artifacts.</para>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493595657">
            <title>Implement automated testing for high-level knowledge artifacts</title>
            <para>[3.5] Automated testing is important to ensure adequate test coverage and
                (especially) to enable thorough regression testing of knowledge artifacts when they
                or their dependencies change. At the same time, the development and maintenance of
                automated test suites is a laborious task, as it entails software engineering
                itself. Therefore, it initially makes sense to only develop automated test suites
                for the integration testing of <emphasis>high-level</emphasis> knowledge artifacts
                (i.e., event-condition-action rules, order sets, and documentation templates). This
                prioritization is appropriate because (a) the specification of high-level artifacts
                most directly affects CDS behavior, and (b) there are fewer high-level artifacts
                than sub-artifacts to develop test suites for. In later phases of the roadmap (see
                Section <xref linkend="_Ref493531062"/>), automated test suites will also be
                developed for sub-artifacts, such as data-access functions, value sets, and
                data-entry controls.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493600958">
            <title>Operationalize risk management applied to development of new knowledge
                artifacts</title>
            <para>[4.4.1] Once the tooling infrastructure is in place for rigorous configuration
                management, software testing, issue-tracking, and workflow enforcement, it becomes
                practical to operationalize a formal risk-management process for knowledge
                artifacts. The key components of this process entail analyzing and identifying how
                knowledge artifacts could fail, potentially leading to safety hazards and patient
                harms. Issue tracking and workflow enforcement are important facets of systematizing
                and documenting those aspects of risk management. Subsequent risk-management
                processes entail controlling for the identified risks through careful artifact
                design, rigorous configuration management and thorough testing, importantly
                including regression testing.</para>
            <para>To phase in the risk-management processes, they shall initially be applied only to
                the development of new knowledge artifacts. Later, risk management processes will be
                extended to the maintenance of existing knowledge artifacts, as the
                knowledge-management team gains experience with the required workflows and
                tools.</para>
            <para>Additional components of the risk-management process will also be developed and
                incorporated during later phases of the roadmap (such as the detailed logging of CDS
                events and the automated surveillance of CDS performance – see Section <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493532506"/>).</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Operationalize architectural and design documents for high-level knowledge
                artifacts</title>
            <para>[4.2.3] During implementation of the risk-management processes, formal processes
                for documenting the architecture and the detailed design of knowledge artifacts will
                be introduced. These processes will both help to inform the risk-analysis process
                (by communicating the intended functionality and constituent components of each
                knowledge artifact) and to specify risk-mitigation steps in the implementation of
                the artifacts (such as the specification of appropriate runtime exception handling).
                The document-management capabilities of the issue-tracking system, or perhaps a
                separate document-management system, will be used to store, track, and reference the
                architectural and design documents.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Operationalize a formal problem-resolution process</title>
            <para>[4.4.3] A systematic and reliable process to correct defects found in production
                software is an important part of a safety-oriented software development life cycle
                for knowledge artifacts. An appropriate process, based on the IEC 62304 process
                standards and applicable issue-tracking tools, should be implemented by this point
                of the roadmap. The key components of the process will include the formal reporting
                of failures in knowledge artifacts, root-cause analyses of the reported failures,
                communication of identified defects to affected parties, implementation and testing
                of appropriate fixes, and tracking and verification of the problems’
                resolution.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implement advanced validation of knowledge artifacts during build process</title>
            <para>[3.3.2] Building on the foundation implemented in phase <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493595674"/> of the roadmap, additional automated validation steps
                should be added to the build process for knowledge artifacts. At this point,
                rigorous compile-time consistency checking with respect to sub-artifact dependencies
                and external system APIs should be incorporated into the build process for
                high-level artifacts, as well as the execution of automated test suites. The
                consistency checks and automated tests will be specific to the types of high-level
                artifacts being built (i.e., rules vs. order sets vs. documentation
                templates).</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implement Phase-2 IDE: Integration with build, release, and issue-tracking
                tools</title>
            <para>[3.8] At this point, the IDE should be extended to enable seamless execution of
                the build process and convenient review of build-time error reports. Integration of
                these capabilities will make the knowledge-artifact development and maintenance
                processes more efficient and more responsive to automatically detected errors. The
                IDE should also directly enable the release of knowledge artifacts to the QA team or
                to production, with automated recording of these transitions in the issue-tracking
                and workflow tool.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Year-Three Tasks</title>
        <para>In year three, the knowledge-management environment will be extended to include
            greater automated testing, more advanced dependency management, and the automated
            surveillance of knowledge artifacts that have been released to production.</para>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493532506">
            <title>Implement detailed logging and automated surveillance of CDS events</title>
            <para>[3.7] The EHR and clinical decision support engine should be modified to
                automatically log detailed information about the invocation and behavior of
                knowledge artifacts in production. These data should be collected in a structured
                format and at a granular level, perhaps in relational database tables, to enable
                convenient tracking and analysis of CDS events. These logging functions should be
                implemented after careful analysis of the required information and design of the
                appropriate data structures. </para>
            <para>The logged data should include instances in which clinical alert and reminder
                rules fired, instances in which order sets were invoked, and instances in which
                documentation templates were used. Sufficient data should be collected to enable
                calculating the rates at which these various knowledge artifacts were applied, and
                the rates at which decision-support recommendations were accepted versus overridden.
                In addition, background processes should be implemented to automatically track these
                rates over time, identify statistically significant variances, and notify knowledge
                engineers of trends and outliers that may indicate knowledge artifacts are not
                functioning as intended.</para>
            <para>Lastly, a mechanism should be incorporated into the EHR and clinical decision
                support user interface to enable end users to conveniently report perceived problems
                in the functioning of the CDS system. The mechanism should ensure that submitted
                reports are readily visible in the issue-tracking system, such that they can be
                reliably investigated and addressed.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_Ref493531062">
            <title>Implement automated testing for lower-level knowledge artifacts
                (sub-artifacts)</title>
            <para>[3.5] Building on the foundation implemented in phase <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493595657"/> of the roadmap, test suites should be added to enable
                automated unit testing of sub-artifacts, such as data-access functions, value sets,
                and data-entry controls. These artifacts have dependencies on other artifacts, such
                as terminology concepts and database structures, which are subject to change.
                Automated test suites allow for regression testing of sub-artifacts as
                terminologies, database structures, and other sub-components evolve over
                time.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implement detailed dependency management system for all knowledge
                artifacts</title>
            <para>[3.4.2] Configuration-management tools typically represent dependencies among
                software libraries and other high-level aggregations of software components. Such
                dependencies are valuable when determining which software assets are compatible with
                each other, but do not represent the granularity of dependencies needed to determine
                which specific knowledge artifacts are affected by detailed changes to other
                knowledge artifacts and in which specific ways they are affected. Good
                dependency-management systems identify and track all such dependencies by analyzing
                the source code of knowledge artifacts and building dependency networks that can be
                manually or automatically analyzed. These dependency networks, along with
                appropriate visualization and querying tools, enable knowledge engineers to
                anticipate the effects of changes to existing knowledge artifacts and to address
                those changes without introducing regression errors.</para>
            <para>The next phase in the roadmap is to develop or procure a dependency-management
                system for high-level and low-level knowledge artifacts. Initially, existing
                commercial systems specifically designed for knowledge artifacts should be assessed
                (such as Semedy). If necessary, commercial or open-source tools that provide
                dependency-management for general-purpose programming languages could be customized
                to handle the programming languages and APIs used by knowledge artifacts. As a last
                resort, an entirely new tool could be developed to provide bespoke
                dependency-management services in the context of the COTS system that VHA will be
                using.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Operationalize risk management applied to maintenance of knowledge
                artifacts</title>
            <para>[4.4.1] Building on the foundation implemented in phase <xref
                    linkend="_Ref493600958"/> of the roadmap, the risk-management process should now
                be extended to the maintenance of existing knowledge artifacts, not just the
                development of new ones. The enhanced process will require analyzing the risks
                inherent in making changes to existing knowledge artifacts, both high-level and
                low-level. Dependency management will play a larger role in this risk analysis, and
                configuration management and regression testing a greater role in controlling for
                unintended consequences of updates to knowledge artifacts.</para>
            <para>As with risk-management processes applied to the development of knowledge
                artifacts, careful documentation of requirements, designs, and test plans will also
                be required to manage risks during the maintenance of knowledge artifacts, and the
                appropriate issue-tracking and workflow tools will be equally important. Finally,
                the release of modified knowledge artifacts will have to be carefully coordinated,
                to ensure that mutually dependent and collectively updated artifacts are correctly
                released together. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implement Phase-3 IDE: Integration with testing tools and dependency
                management</title>
            <para>[3.8] The final development phase for the IDE will entail its integration with
                automated testing tools and the detailed dependency-management system. The resulting
                development environment will comprise a comprehensive set of tools that knowledge
                engineers can use to develop and maintain knowledge artifacts safely and
                efficiently. The primary goal of the IDE is to make it as easy as possible for
                knowledge engineers to adhere to the prescribed lifecycle processes, which provide
                the rigorous framework to ensure high quality and reliability in clinical decision
                support software.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>This roadmap document, combined with the detailed components of the “future state”
            architecture report delivered earlier, provide a clear initial plan for implementing the
            envisioned architecture for managing knowledge artifacts. However, it’s not unlikely
            that information will emerge in the course of implementing the processes and tools,
            particularly in the context of pre-existing COTS software, that will necessitate
            adjustments to both the roadmap and the ultimate future state. These adjustments, while
            inevitable, should not be so great as to alter the overriding objective and approach of
            this initiative, which are based on sound and proven principles of risk management in
            the development of software that impacts patient safety.</para>
    </section>
 </article>
