<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Concrete Domains</title>

    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Concrete domains can be used in SNOMED CT to represent and reason over values like
            integers in Description Logic. Our initial work focused on medications and evaluating
            the use of concrete domains to represent not only the product strength, but also the
            unit of use size. To fully test the feasibility of concrete domains, additional
            attributes were also added, in order to fully represent all information regarding
            medications, which will then allow concepts to be fully defined. Thus, this will enable
            testing the equivalence and subsumption of concepts by the Description Logic classifiers
            within the tooling.</para>
        <para>At the beginning of the project there was no ability to represent numeric attributes
            of concepts in SNOMED CT, which made machine readability of numeric attributes
            difficult, prone to error, and left a large portion of Products as primitive concepts.
            Without the ability to fully represent the numeric properties, equivalence checking and
            subsumption using the Description Logic classifier is not possible. With the
            introduction of the new Drug Concept Model in the July 2017 International Release the
            representation of product strength and units will begin to be modelled over the next few
            releases. However, this new Drug Concept Model does not utilize concrete domains but
            instead creates the strength numbers as concepts themselves to be used as values for the
            product strength attributes. </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Approach</title>
        <para>By using a lexical search for string containing integers and textual representation of
            integers, 10,114 potential Pharmaceutical / Biologic Product concepts were identified,
            which were modeled with the proposed attributes including one attribute to represent
            product strength. To properly represent the numeric information contained in these
            products, the Australian Medicines Terminology Approach that applied to its Australian
            extension content and not to the International SNOMED CT content was utilized.</para>
        <para>To speed up the modeling process, already available data around strength and units
            from NDF-RT through RxNorm RXNSAT relationships that was linked to the SNOMED CT
            concepts through the RXCUI was used. Technical validation was performed on these values
            and any incorrect strength or units we identified were corrected before using these
            values to populate the relationships. After loading the new relationships into the
            terminology editor, further manual review was conducted to verify the relationships and
            add any missing information.</para>
        <para>Using the findings from the drug modeling, the team evaluated other hierarchies that
            were identified as having potential for modeling concrete domains.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Attributes for Representing Medications</title>
        <para>Below are attributes that have been added to the medications model to represent
            concrete domains: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Has Basis of Strength Substance (BoSS)</emphasis> –
                        The substance(s) that correspond to the strength. If strength is not stated
                        then this attribute is not used. The Has Active Ingredient attribute is
                        still used and grouped together with this attribute</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Range: &lt;&lt; Substance (substance)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Has Product Strength</emphasis> – The strength of
                        the Has Basis of Strength Substance and is always grouped together</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Range: Float 0 to 1000000000</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Units</emphasis> – Unit of Measure is always
                        associated with the Strength</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Range: &lt;&lt;Unit (qualifier value)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Has Unit of Use </emphasis>– Describes a discrete
                        unit that a product presents in, for example a vial, bag, etc.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Range: (&lt;&lt;)Type of drug preparation (qualifier value) and
                                (&lt;&lt;) Unit of drug administration (qualifier value)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Unit of Use Size</emphasis> – Represents the size of
                        the unit of use</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Range: Float 0 to 1000000000</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Unit of Use Quantity</emphasis> – Represents the
                        pack quantity</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Range: Float 0 to 1000000000</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        
        
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Findings</title>
        <para>Under the new SNOMED CT International Drug Concept Model, existing concepts will be
            updated to meet the new modelling guidelines and terming updated to conform to the
            terming guidelines in the editorial guide. One of the most frequent issues we found
            while modelling the medication attributes was that the Fully Specified Names (FSN) were
            not completely fully specified or that the values needed to fully define a concept were
            not available. For example, the common issues we saw around FSN’s were due to the salt
            or dose form not present or not fully defined in the FSN, but modelled with the more
            specific value in the current Has active ingredient and Has dose form attributes. With
            the SNOMED CT International review and application of the new modelling guidelines these
            FSN’s should be corrected and fix the issues we found with FSN’s.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></para>
                    <para>(FSN does not explicitly state that it is an Oral suspension):</para>
                    <para>370762006 |Azithromycin 1g/packet oral (product)| </para>
                    <para>&lt;&lt;&lt; 392327001 |Oral form azithromycin (product)| :</para>
                    <para>127489000 |Has active ingredient (attribute)| = 391805000 |Azithromycin
                        dihydrate (substance)|, 411116001 |Has dose form (attribute)| = 385024007
                        |Oral suspension (qualifier value)|</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Another common issue with fully defining concepts using our proposed model was
            associated with sugar free, gluten free, preservative free, etc. dose forms. This issue
            is currently out of scope for the new SNOMED CT International Drug Concept Model and
            will prevent the concepts that currently exist in SNOMED CT from being fully defined. A
            potential solution for representing these dose forms and fully defining the drug
            concepts would be to create concepts in the qualifier value hierarchy for sugar free
            dose form, gluten free dose form, etc and use a nested relationship to combine it with
            the other appropriate dose form. This would eliminate the need to create all the
            possible combinations of dose forms required to support the Drug Concept Model.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></para>
                <para>320108004 |Salbutamol 2mg/5mL sugar free syrup (product)| </para>
                <para>&lt;&lt;&lt; 135639005 |Oral form albuterol (product)| :</para>
                <para> 127489000 |Has active ingredient (attribute)| = 48474002 |Albuterol sulfate
                    (substance)|, 411116001 |Has dose form (attribute)| = (385032004 |Syrup
                    (qualifier value)| + XXXXXX|Sugar free dose form(qualifier value)|)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The sections of the SNOMED CT International Drug Concept Model dealing with Grouper,
            Virtual Medicinal Product (VMP), and Virtual Medicinal Product Form (VMPF) concepts in
            the Pharmaceutical / biological product hierarchy did not affect our concrete domain
            work as these concepts do not include product strength as a part of their FSN. However,
            correcting issues with these concepts will have downstream effects on the modelling of
            the concepts we made modified. </para>
        <para>The section that was most relevant to the concrete domain work was the Virtual
            Clinical Drug model. The main differences between our approaches are:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Strength is not represented as a number in the SNOMED CT International
                        model, but as a conceptid that is a representation of that number.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The SNOMED CT International model currently has no way to represent ranges
                        of strength (for example radiopharmaceuticals).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The SNOMED CT International model separates out numerator and denominator
                        for both strength and units whereas we chose to normalize the
                        strength.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>After the testing of concrete domains using the pharmacy model we reviewed concepts in
            findings, procedures and observables to determine the feasibility of applying concrete
            domains to concepts in those hierarchies as well. We identified 3668 concepts that may
            potentially benefit from the use of concrete domains in these hierarchies. </para>
        <para>These concepts mainly fall into 4 categories:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Grades/Stages/Scales</emphasis></para>
                    <para>This category of concepts is least likely to benefit from concrete domains
                        as some grades/stages/scales are alpha-numeric and would more likely fall
                        into a similar model as the SNOMED International Drug Concept Model.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>Examples:</emphasis></para>
                            <para>109970006 |Follicular lymphoma, grade 1|</para>
                            <para>112110007 |Glasgow coma scale, 4|</para>
                            <para>112241002 |Lymphoma stage III 1|</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Measurements/Percentiles</emphasis></para>
                    <para>This category of concepts mirrors the requirements of the Drug Concept
                        Model most closely and would be very similar in that it would require both
                        an attribute for recording the numeric value and another attribute to record
                        the unit. This would also require the ability to capture less than, greater
                        than and equal to which is not currently something supported in the SNOMED
                        CT International Drug Concept Model. Therefore using concrete domains would
                        be a much more suitable solution as it allows for that capture of that
                        information but would require a change to the SNOMED CT Release Format to
                        accommodate these relationships.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>Examples:</emphasis></para>
                            <para>314643009 |Child head circumference &lt; 0.4th centile|</para>
                            <para>385303005 |pT3: Tumor more than 5 cm in greatest dimension (anal
                                canal)|</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Timing/Frequency</emphasis></para>
                    <para>While these concepts contain numeric values, they may not lend themselves
                        to being captured by concrete domains due to the fact that there are some
                        expressions like “every 12 months”, “once a week”, “five times a week”,
                        etc.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>Examples:</emphasis></para>
                            <para>34259007 |Measurement of glucose 5 hours after glucose challenge
                                for glucose tolerance test|</para>
                            <para>416755008 |Cervical smear every 12 months for life|</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Dosing Number/Episode</emphasis></para>
                    <para>This would be a small subset of concepts that would be affected but would
                        be a good target for a set of relationships to use for post-coordination
                        instead of adding pre-coordinated concepts to the standard. Making these
                        relationships strictly available through post-coordination and using
                        concrete domains would not require a change to the release format. It would
                        however require existing concepts (less than 100) to be retired in order for
                        all concepts to be aggregated appropriately.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis>Examples:</emphasis></para>
                            <para>170425007 |Typhoid and Paratyphoid first dose|</para>
                            <para>231499006 |Endogenous depression first episode|</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    
    
</chapter>
