<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Examples of SOLOR Application</title>
    <para>Below are examples of where SOLOR content can be applied.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Maintaining Terminology Standards Update</title>
        <para>While the use of Standard terminology is a critical step toward interoperability, it
            is not a trivial process especially if an institution needs to stay current and use
            up-to-date content. Standard bodies typically releases their developed content in
            asynchronous release cycles (SNOMED - twice/year, LOINC - once/year, RxNorm - monthly),
            and are distributed in different formats (SNOMED - 3-6 text files, LOINC - Excel
            workbook or CSV, RxNorm - 9 Rich Release Files). As a result, users of Standard
            Terminologies are often times required to budget time and money for resources to monitor
            and obtain the latest release files. When obtained, due to its disparate model and
            source file format, users will also maintain separate databases to store the data within
            the release files. Without a robust versioning control mechanism, latest version of
            content is typically the only version available to users as history is often lost or
            will require significant effort to query into historical content. As a result, it
            creates a barrier for users or institutions to create and maintain content that are
            dependent on these standard content. </para>
        <para>SOLOR avoids this unnecessary complexity with its Versioning Model. By utilizing a
            common set of building blocks (Concepts and Semantics), content from disparate sources
            are transformed into the same model, which allows for a single place for storage and a
            single set of retrieval mechanism. In addition, with STAMP coordinates, history of a
            particular set of content could be maintained by allowing historical versions of the
            same content to exist. Utilizing an automated and repeatable process, SOLOR's back-end
            processes will retrieve the content as they are released by the Authoring Bodies,
            transform the disparate files into SOLOR, and apply STAMP coordinates to the created
            objects within SOLOR. Once a SOLOR user provides licensing information to the content
            within, the user is able to freely access the most current and historical content within
            SOLOR. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Locally Created Content</title>
        <para>Other than handling asynchronous content update cycles, SOLOR will support the ongoing
            maintenance of locally created content. By using STAMP coordinates, locally created
            content are stored together with, and at the same time, segregated from standard
            content. This is achieved by marking these locally created content with a different
            STAMP coordinates such as Author and/or Module, where the set of locally created content
            are organized by the same Author and/or Module. Furthermore, with dependency
            information, SOLOR allows for quick identification of the impacted locally created
            content when the underlying dependent content is updated. During updates, these locally
            created content can be treated as a set of potentially impacted content that will need
            to be reviewed. </para>
        <para>For example, if a set of concepts requires locally created descriptions, then that set
            of locally created terms could be retrieved by indicating the desired Author and/or
            Module. Similarly, a set of concepts that requires these locally created terms can be
            queried upon to determine which concepts are now inactive and will therefore need to
            have the locally created term inactivated as well. The result is a clean separation of
            content while maintaining dependency information. This results in a quicker turnaround
            time for knowledge worker to address locally created content affected by a standard
            content update without the need to query across multiple disparate databases. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Data Retrieval</title>
        <para>Because all content are stored in the same repository, using the same SOLOR Versioning
            Model, only a single set of retrieval mechanism is required to obtain data. By utilizing
            the STAMP coordinates, one could locate the desired set of content. Moreover, by
            querying for certain values of a semantic, one could easily retrieve data from SOLOR.
            For example, "set of locally created Descriptions created on SNOMED concepts that have
            been placed into the 'diagnosis' module where SNOMED concepts were active from 2
            releases prior" is easily retrieved by entering the appropriate values of the STAMP
            coordinates, which is in contrast with the current mechanism of querying across multiple
            disparate databases that may or may not contain the up-to-date version and/or historical
            versions. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Use Case</title>
        <para>Current state of utilizing disparate siloed terminologies and/or with information
            models has many implications that could impact patient safety. One of the main goals of
            SOLOR is to provide the ability to transmit information without information loss.
            Following examples highlights potential points of failure and how SOLOR could address
            the underlying issue.</para>
        <section>
            <info>
        <title>Inability to express clinically important concept</title>
            </info>
        <para>Medicine is an ever-evolving field with new discoveries occurring at a rapid pace.
            Although Standard Development Organizations work tirelessly to bring content up-to-date,
            there will inevitably be a lag if content is released at scheduled intervals. SOLOR
            addresses this gap by providing the capability for organizations to create local
            content. While the desired content is under evaluation by Standard Development
            Organizations, localized content could be utilized and even shared by the SOLOR
            community.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <info>
                <title>Equivalence</title>
            </info>
            <para>Currently, it is left to users to determine which concept from which terminology
                must be used. For example, for diagnosis, users will typically choose a SNOMED
                concept from the Clinical Finding / Disorder hierarchy, while a LOINC concept is
                typically chosen for laboratory related patient data. This requires the user to have
                a significant terminology training or experience. Many systems will also require
                developers to either have the same knowledge or rely heavily on terminologists to
                expose required content (e.g. RxNorm concepts in medication related area) to the
                users. SOLOR addresses this issue by shielding users from needing to know which
                terminology to use. In order to accomplish this, SOLOR will address equivalency
                during the transformation step from native source file into SOLOR. By utilizing
                various techniques, concepts that are equivalent will have a single representation
                in SOLOR, while having linkages to the source contributor. Therefore, a user could
                simply search for the desired content (e.g. Measurement of Gentamycin peak and
                trough for a laboratory test) rather than searching for a specific concept within a
                desired terminology.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <info>
                <title>Separation of Concerns</title>
            </info>
            <para>In order to exchange information, numerous efforts have been taken to develop an information models to transmit patient data. Unfortunately, many models will often have a tight binding to a terminology component, which in turn will cause ambiguity over time and will force users to know the intricacies of the model to properly utilize it.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 1</emphasis>: Laterality is a notion that is present
                in SNOMED and HL7 FHIR profile. Having a lack of separation of concerns would allow
                data entry of both a SNOMED concept that explicitly states a laterality as well as a
                SNOMED concept without laterality and utilizing FHIR profile to enter the
                laterality. While this is convenient, it would allow an user to enter the same data
                in different ways. A user could potentially select a precordinated concept of "Pain
                in the left arm" or a user could select "Pain of the arm" and use the laterality
                segment to enter "Left". This would now require one to account for both cases when
                querying for data - an user is required to know that the pre-coordinated concept of
                "Pain in the left arm" speaks to laterality of left, and will also need to know to
                look for "Left" in the laterality segment.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 2</emphasis>: Another example is seen in the
                specimen attribute of the HL7 OBR segment. HL7 OBR segment transmits information
                about an exam, diagnostic study/observation, or assessment that is specific to an
                order or result (<link
                    xlink:href="https://corepointhealth.com/resource-center/hl7-resources/hl7-obr-segment"
                    >https://corepointhealth.com/resource-center/hl7-resources/hl7-obr-segment</link>).
                Prior to HL7 version 2.5, sequence 15 of the OBR segment allows one to capture
                specimen source information. This is a composite field that requires combination of
                different data fields (<link
                    xlink:href="http://hl7-definition.caristix.com:9010/HL7%20v2.3.1/segment/OBR?version=HL7%20v2.3.1&amp;dataType=SPS"
                    >http://hl7-definition.caristix.com:9010/HL7%20v2.3.1/segment/OBR?version=HL7%20v2.3.1&amp;dataType=SPS</link>),
                which in turn requires use of HL7 codes from tables 0070 and 0163 to capture the
                specimen source and body site, respectively. This structure is complex and difficult
                to use and does not allow an user to capture information such as specimen did not
                originate for the patient. As a result, many users leveraged the z-segments (<link
                    xlink:href="http://healthstandards.com/blog/2006/10/05/what-are-z-segments/"
                    >http://healthstandards.com/blog/2006/10/05/what-are-z-segments/</link>), which
                is a "catch all" to provide additional information. This echoes the issues raised in
                the previous example where an user will need to know to look for sequence 15 as well
                as segment 15 AND z-segment to capture all of the variations of specimen source.
                Moreover, z-segment is a String type which would allow any free text entry, which
                results in variability. </para>
            <para>To address this issue, OBR15 has been deprecated and SPM segment was introduced in
                HL7 version 2.5 (<link
                    xlink:href="http://hl7-definition.caristix.com:9010/Default.aspx?version=HL7%20v2.5.1&amp;segment=SPM"
                    >http://hl7-definition.caristix.com:9010/Default.aspx?version=HL7%20v2.5.1&amp;segment=SPM</link>),
                which describes the characteristics of a specimen. Although more robust, it now
                require users to have the knowledge to look for specimen source in three different
                manners. Furthermore, codes that were once used to support sequence 15 are no longer
                necessary as the model evolve over time.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion </title>
        <para>It is therefore a goal of SOLOR to work toward a solution by following the principle
            of separation of concerns. This is accomplished with current development work to create
            an information model implemented as Clinical Input Form and Analysis Normal Form, and
            relevant fields from the information model would call on terminology and allow
            terminology to capture and represent the appropriate information. As the information
            model or terminology evolve over time, one would not impact the other. Using examples
            from above, laterality could be modeled as a precoordinated concept within SOLOR or
            could be represented as a post-coordinated concept—either approach would leverage
            terminology to handle the expression without requiring the information model to handle
            the laterality component. In the second example, terminology could be leveraged to
            express specimen source. Furthermore, a fully defined concept could express additional
            information regarding the specimen, similar to the attempt of SPM segment. The
            differentiating factor is that it is isolated in the terminology layer, thus leaving the
            information model untouched. Lastly, SOLOR's Module of the STAMP coordinates would allow
            an aggregation of concepts, such as specimens, such that a set of relevant concepts
            could be utilized by appropriate segment of fields of the information model. </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
