<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>What is SOLOR?</title>
    <para>As alluded to above, content is currently delivered by various organizations in which the
        content is often times created in silos, stored in different formats, represented by
        different models, and released with different cycles and mechanisms. As a result, end users
        are taxed heavily to monitor, retrieve, implement, and analyze the ramifications of an
        update. This burden is compounded even further when a new set of content is required for
        use. While designed to provide the content within the ISAAC architecture, SOLOR was created
        as an open-source terminology platform that is intended to shield users from the burden and
        complexities of content management. This is achieved by representing disparate content via
        two SOLOR components: Concepts and Semantics, which are controlled by a versioning mechanism
        known as STAMP (Status, Time, Module, Path).</para>
    <section>
        <title>SOLOR Building Blocks: Concepts and Semantics</title>
        <para>Concept is defined as an idea or a general notion. When abstracted out, it can be used
            to represent any idea, whether that is a medically related idea (e.g., heart attack) or
            an idea to represent a metadata (e.g., a synonym or a fully specified name).</para>
        <para>When semantics or context is given to a concept, it allows for further refinement or
            definition of the concept or idea. For example, there may be a string. When given
            semantics, that string could be defined as a 'Description Type'. When further semantics
            are given that 'Description Type' may be further defined as a 'Synonym'. A concept of
            'Synonym' with sufficient semantics associated with is now understood as a "Description
            Type', which is a piece of string. This concept of 'Synonym' could now be used to define
            any idea (e.g., heart attack) to provide a string representation for human
            comprehension—the idea of 'heart attack', devoid of any semantic meaning, could now have
            a semantic identity with the string value of "Heart attack" to give semantic meaning to
            the concept. </para>
        <para>These abstract semantic identities are generic and reusable to represent content
            provided by disparate organizations. For example, the semantic identity of 'Synonym'
            could be used to represent a description that originiated from SNOMED or LOINC. This
            notion of semantics can be used to create various semantic identities such as
            Descriptions (e.g., Fully Specified Name, Synonym, Abbreviation), Relationships (e.g.,
            Is-A, Broader-than, Narrower-than), Attributes (e.g., SNOMED Concept ID, LOINC ID) or
            even identities to capture EL++ description logic. As a result, SOLOR component is used
            to represent any and all content regardless of where it originated or how it is
            conceptually represented in its native form (polyhierarchy representation of SNOMED vs.
            'flat' representation of LOINC). In essence, SOLOR has two fundamental building blocks:
            a concept and semantics that can be attached to a concept to provide contexual meaning
            to the concept.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>STAMP Versioning</title>
        <para>While aggregating content from different sources using similar SOLOR building blocks,
            there is also a need to be able to separate these disparate content as well as its
            history. This is accomplished in SOLOR by a consistent version managment system using a
            set of attributes known as STAMP coordinates. Components of STAMP and its defniitions
            are:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">S</emphasis>tatus - indicates whether the object is
                        active or inactive</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">T</emphasis>ime - indicates the effetive time/date
                        of the object's status</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>uthor - captures the origin of the
                        object</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis>odule - associates the object with an
                        applicable set</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">P</emphasis>ath - stores the branch in which the
                        object resides in (see: <link
                            xlink:href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Branching-What-a-Branch-Is"
                            >https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Branching-What-a-Branch-Is</link>)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>From a combination of these coordinates, SOLOR would allow one to associate the
            'where' and 'when' aspects with an object. Below are few examples of STAMP coodrinates
            in action.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: </emphasis>Versioning of a Concept</para>
        <para>In this example, let's assume that NLM released a concept named "X" during the SNOMED
            US Extension January 2017 release. In the source file, X has an effective date of
            1/31/2017. During the processing of SNOMED source file into SOLOR, concept X would have
            the following coordinates:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Status = Active</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Time = 1/31/2017</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Author = NLM</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Module = SNOMED US Extension</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Path = [enter info here]</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Fast forwarding to the second release, NLM retires "X" and is effective as of
            7/31/2017. After processing, "X" would have the following coordinates:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Status = Inactive</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Time = 7/31/2017</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Author = NLM</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Module = SNOMED US Extension</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Path = [enter info here]</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para> </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 2:</emphasis> Creation of Local Concept</para>
        <para>In this example, let's assume that organization "ABC" requires the representation of
            disease "Y" along with SNOMED US Extension content, and requires immediate use. If a
            knowledge worker creates this concept in SOLOR, it would have the following
            coordinates:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Status = Active</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Time = [some effective date]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Author = ABC</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Module = SNOMED US Extension</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Path = [enter info here]</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para> </para>
        <para/>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 3:</emphasis> Concept Belonging to Multiple
            Modules</para>
        <para>In this example, let's assume that concept "X" (same concept as NLM example above) is
            a concept representing a particular diagnosis, and on 5/1/2017, an organization requires
            concept "X" to be present along with other diagnosis for the purpose of allowing users
            to populate a particular section of a form. This concept X would have an additional
            coordinate of:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="soychoi" timestamp="20171111T184920-0500" comment="Not sure, but are there more coordinates to use here?"?>
                    <para>Status = Active</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Time = 5/1/2017</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Module = 'name of module that aggregates desired set of concepts'</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Path = [enter info here]<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Chronology Identity</title>
        <para>As alluded to by the examples, an object is allowed to have more than one set of STAMP
            coordinates. Therefore, continuing with the example of concept "X" from above, it would
            have a set of STAMP coordinates:</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Version Status Time Author Module Path</emphasis></para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>V1 Active 1/31/2017 NLM SNOMED US Extension []</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>V2 Active 5/1/2017 N/A 'name of module that aggregates desired set of
                    concepts' []</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>V3 Inactive 7/31/2017 NLM SNOMED US Extension []</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>This collection of STAMP coordinates is known in SOLOR as Chronology Identity.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Language Coordinate</title>
        <para>While the initial audience is expected to be users of English content, SOLOR supports
            foreign language content by its language coordinate. This allows representation of data
            in different languages and allows one to specify desired language for usage when using
            SOLOR.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Putting It All Together</title>
        <para>After an Authoring Body releases its content, a process will need to occur to
            transform data from its native format into SOLOR components. This programmatic process
            is tailored to each incoming data stream, where it will account for data represented in
            its original format. Other than transformation and applying STAMP coordinates, the
            underlying process will also address the notion of dependency. For example, SNOMED US
            Extension will have a dependency on SNOMED International, and relationships from the
            LOINC-SNOMED collaboration effort will have a dependency on SNOMED and LOINC. </para>
        <para>Once the content is in SOLOR, there is a step where equivalency is determined through
            various methods where concepts of same idea are aggregated. For example, Gentamycin from
            SNOMED is the same as Gentamycin from LOINC, and is also the same Gentamycin from
            RxNorm. End result from this process is the creation of a SOLOR concept that is devoid
            of any source information (but will have traceability). This end result is what will be
            exposed to the user to view and use. In the Gentamycin example, a user will find this
            concept that is devoid of any source information and will not need to know if this is
            the SNOMED/LOINC/RxNorm Gentamycin that needs to be selected.</para>
        <para>To complete the example walkthrough, if the Gentamycin was used in the context of
            identifying what medication the patient is currently taking, then the underlying process
            will be able to transmit the RxNorm code if the receiving system is expecting RxNorm
            codes. Conversely, when SOLOR is adopted more globally, the transmitted information
            could be isolated to the SOLOR Gentamycin rather than a specific code from a specific
            terminology.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
